Practice Directions

(1.) The practice directions to the Civil Procedure Rules apply to civil litigation in the Queen's Bench Division and the Chancery Division of the High Court and to litigation in the county courts other than family proceedings. Where relevant they also apply to appeals to the Civil Division of the Court of Appeal.

(2.) Since the coming into force of the Constitutional Reform Act 2005 in April 2006, the power to make practice directions for the civil courts falls to the Lord Chief Justice (with the approval of the Lord Chancellor in most instances). This power is governed by Section 5 of the Civil Procedure Act (as amended).

(3.) The Lord Chief Justice has power under the Part 1 of Schedule 2 of the Constitutional Reform Act to nominate a judicial office holder to perform his functions with regards making designated directions. He has therefore nominated the Master of the Rolls to make practice directions for the civil courts.

Historical Making Powers

(4.) Until the inception of the Constitutional Reform Act, practice directions were made –

(1) for the Queen’s Bench Division by the Lord Chief Justice as president of that Division;

(2) for the Civil Division of the Court of Appeal by the Master of the Rolls as president of that Division;

(3) for the Chancery Division by the Vice-Chancellor as vice-president of that Division; and

(4) for the county courts by the Lord Chancellor or a person authorised to act on his behalf under section 74A of the County Courts Act 1984.

(5.) From April 1999 to July 2000 the Lord Chancellor authorised the Vice-Chancellor, Sir Richard Scott (as he then was) under section 74A of the 1984 Act. The Vice-Chancellor made all practice directions for county courts during that time.

(6.) From July 2000 to September 2003, the Lord Chancellor authorised Lord Justice May to make these practice directions. Lord Justice May made all practice directions for county courts during that time.

(7.) From September 2003 until April 2006 the Lord Chancellor authorised Lord Justice Dyson to make practice directions for the county courts.

PART 2 - APPLICATION AND INTERPRETATION OF THE RULES

Contents of this Part

Title | Number
Application of the Rules | Rule 2.1
The glossary | Rule 2.2
Interpretation | Rule 2.3
Power of judge, Master or district judge to perform functions of the court | Rule 2.4
Court staff
| Rule 2.5
Court documents to be sealed | Rule 2.6
Court’s discretion as to where it deals with cases | Rule 2.7
Time | Rule 2.8
Dates for compliance to be calendar dates and to include time of day | Rule 2.9
Meaning of ‘month’ in judgments, etc. | Rule 2.10
Time limits may be varied by parties | Rule 2.11

Application of the Rules

2.1

(1) Subject to paragraph (2), these Rules apply to all proceedings in –

(a) county courts;

(b) the High Court; and

(c) the Civil Division of the Court of Appeal.

(2) These Rules do not apply to proceedings of the kinds specified in the first column of the following table (proceedings for which rules may be made under the enactments specified in the second column) except to the extent that they are applied to those proceedings by another enactment –

Proceedings | Enactments
1. | Insolvency proceedings | Insolvency Act 1986[1], ss.411 and 412
2. | Non-contentious or common form probate proceedings | Supreme Court Act 1981^2, s.127
3. | Proceedings in the High Court when acting as a Prize Court | Prize Courts Act 1894^3, s.3
4. | Proceedings before the Court of Protection | Mental Capacity Act 2005^4, s.51
5. | Family proceedings | Matrimonial and Family Proceedings Act 1984^5, s.40
6. | Adoption proceedings | Adoption Act 1976^6, s.66 or Adoption and Children Act 2002, s.141(c)^7.
7. | Election petitions in the High Court | Representation of the People Act 1983^8, s.182

The glossary

2.2

(1) The glossary at the end of these Rules is a guide to the meaning of certain legal expressions used in the Rules, but is not to be taken as giving those expressions any meaning in the Rules which they do not have in the law generally.

(2) Subject to paragraph (3), words in these Rules which are included in the glossary are followed by‘(GL)’.

(3) The words ‘counterclaim’, ‘damages’, ‘practice form’ and ‘service’, which appear frequently in the Rules, are included in the glossary but are not followed by[‘(GL)’].

Interpretation

2.3

(1) In these Rules –

‘child’ has the meaning given by rule 21.1(2);

‘civil restraint order’ means an order restraining a party –

(a) from making any further applications in current proceedings (a limited civil restraint order);

(b) from issuing certain claims or making certain applications in specified courts (an extended civil restraint order); or

(c) from issuing any claim or making any application in specified courts (a general civil restraint order).

‘claim for personal injuries’ means proceedings in which there is a claim for damages in respect of personal injuries to the claimant or any other person or in respect of a person’s death, and ‘personal injuries’ includes any disease and any impairment of a person’s physical or mental condition;

‘claimant’ means a person who makes a claim;

‘CCR’ is to be interpreted in accordance with Part 50;

‘court officer’ means a member of the court staff;

‘defendant’ means a person against whom a claim is made;

‘defendant's home court’ means –

(a) if the claim is proceeding in a county court, the county court for the district in which the defendant resides or carries on business; and

(b) if the claim is proceeding in the High Court, the district registry for the district in which the defendant resides or carries on business or, where there is no such district registry, the Royal Courts of Justice;

(Rule 6.23 provides for a party to give an address for service)

‘designated money claim’ means any claim which –

(a) is started in a county court under Part 7;

(b) is only a claim for either or both a specified amount of money or an unspecified amount of money; and

(c) is not a claim for which special procedures are provided in these rules;

‘filing’, in relation to a document, means delivering it, by post or otherwise, to the court office;

‘judge’ means, unless the context otherwise requires, a judge, Master or district judge or a person authorised to act as such;

‘jurisdiction’ means, unless the context requires otherwise, England and Wales and any part of the territorial waters of the United Kingdom adjoining England and Wales;

‘legal representative’ means a –

(a) barrister;

(b) solicitor;

(c) solicitor’s employee;

(d) manager of a body recognised under section 9 of the Administration of Justice Act 1985^9; or

(e) person who, for the purposes of the Legal Services Act 2007^10, is an authorised person in relation to an activity which constitutes the conduct of litigation (within the meaning of that Act),

who has been instructed to act for a party in relation to proceedings;

‘litigation friend’ has the meaning given by Part 21;

‘preferred court’ means, if the claim is proceeding in a county court, the county court the claimant has specified in practice form N1 as the court to which the proceedings should be transferred if necessary;

‘protected party’ has the meaning given by rule 21.1(2);

‘RSC’ is to be interpreted in accordance with Part 50;

‘statement of case’ –

(a) means a claim form, particulars of claim where these are not included in a claim form, defence, Part 20 claim, or reply to defence; and

(b) includes any further information given in relation to them voluntarily or by court order under rule 18.1;

‘statement of value’ is to be interpreted in accordance with rule 16.3;

‘summary judgment’ is to be interpreted in accordance with Part 24.

(2) A reference to a ‘specialist list’ is a reference to a list(GL) that has been designated as such by a rule or practice direction.

(3) Where the context requires, a reference to ‘the court’ means a reference to a particular county court, a district registry, or the Royal Courts of Justice.

Power of judge, Master or district judge to perform functions of the court

2.4

Where these Rules provide for the court to perform any act then, except where an enactment, rule or practice direction provides otherwise, that act may be performed –

(a) in relation to proceedings in the High Court, by any judge, Master or district judge of that Court; and

(b) in relation to proceedings in a county court, by any judge or district judge.

Court staff

2.5

(1) Where these Rules require or permit the court to perform an act of a formal or administrative character, that act may be performed by a court officer.

(2) A requirement that a court officer carry out any act at the request of a party is subject to the payment of any fee required by a fees order for the carrying out of that act.

(Rule 3.2 allows a court officer to refer to a judge before taking any step)

Court documents to be sealed

2.6

(1) The court must seal(GL) the following documents on issue –

(a) the claim form; and

(b) any other document which a rule or practice direction requires it to seal.

(2) The court may place the seal(GL) on the document –

(a) by hand; or

(b) by printing a facsimile of the seal on the document whether electronically or otherwise.

(3) A document purporting to bear the court’s seal(GL) shall be admissible in evidence without further proof.

Court’s discretion as to where it deals with cases

2.7

The court may deal with a case at any place that it considers appropriate.

Time

2.8

(1) This rule shows how to calculate any period of time for doing any act which is specified –

(a) by these Rules;

(b) by a practice direction; or

(c) by a judgment or order of the court.

(2) A period of time expressed as a number of days shall be computed as clear days.

(3) In this rule ‘clear days’ means that in computing the number of days –

(a) the day on which the period begins; and

(b) if the end of the period is defined by reference to an event, the day on which that event occurs

are not included.

Examples

(i) Notice of an application must be served at least 3 days before the hearing.

An application is to be heard on Friday 20 October.

The last date for service is Monday 16 October.

(ii) The court is to fix a date for a hearing.

The hearing must be at least 28 days after the date of notice.

If the court gives notice of the date of the hearing on 1 October, the earliest date for the hearing is 30 October.

(iii) Particulars of claim must be served within 14 days of service of the claim form.

The claim form is served on 2 October.

The last day for service of the particulars of claim is 16 October.

(4) Where the specified period –

(a) is 5 days or less; and

(b) includes –

(i) a Saturday or Sunday; or

(ii) a Bank Holiday, Christmas Day or Good Friday,

that day does not count.

Example

Notice of an application must be served at least 3 days before the hearing.

An application is to be heard on Monday 20 October.

The last date for service is Tuesday 14 October.

(5) Subject to the provisions of Practice Direction 5C, when the period specified –

(a) by these Rules or a practice direction; or

(b) by any judgment or court order,

for doing any act at the court office ends on a day on which the office is closed, that act shall be in time if done on the next day on which the court office is open.

Dates for compliance to be calendar dates and to include time of day

2.9

(1) Where the court gives a judgment, order or direction which imposes a time limit for doing any act, the last date for compliance must, wherever practicable –

(a) be expressed as a calendar date; and

(b) include the time of day by which the act must be done.

(2) Where the date by which an act must be done is inserted in any document, the date must, wherever practicable, be expressed as a calendar date.

Meaning of ‘month’ in judgments, etc.

2.10

Where ‘month’ occurs in any judgment, order, direction or other document, it means a calendar month.

Time limits may be varied by parties

2.11

Unless these Rules or a practice direction provide otherwise or the court orders otherwise, the time specified by a rule or by the court for a person to do any act may be varied by the written agreement of the parties.

(Rules 3.8 (sanctions have effect unless defaulting party obtains relief), 28.4 (variation of case management timetable – fast track) and 29.5 (variation of case management timetable – multi-track), provide for time limits that cannot be varied by agreement between the parties)

Footnotes

1986 c.45. Back to text
1981 c.54. Back to text
1894 c.39. Back to text
2005 c. 9. Back to text
1984 c.42. Section 40 was amended by the Courts and Legal Services Act 1990 (c.41), Schedule 18, paragraph 50. Back to text
1976 c.36. Back to text
2002 c.38. Back to text
1983 c.2. Back to text
1985 c. 61. Back to text
2007 c. 29. Back to text

Back to top

PRACTICE DIRECTION 2B – ALLOCATION OF CASES TO LEVELS OF JUDICIARY

Contents of this Practice Direction

1.1

Rule 2.4 provides that Judges, Masters and District Judges may exercise any function of the court except where an enactment, rule or practice direction provides otherwise. This Practice Direction sets out the matters over which Masters and District Judges do not have jurisdiction or which they may deal with only on certain conditions. It does not affect jurisdiction conferred by other enactments. Reference should also be made to other relevant Practice Directions (e.g. Part 24, paragraph 3 and Part 26, paragraphs 12.1-10). References to Circuit Judges include Recorders and Assistant Recorders and references to Masters and District Judges include Deputies.

1.2

Wherever a Master or District Judge has jurisdiction, he may refer the matter to a Judge instead of dealing with it himself.

THE HIGH COURT

Injunctions

2.1

Search orders (rule 25.1(1)(h)), freezing orders (rule 25.1(1)(f)), an ancillary order under rule 25.1(1)(g) and orders authorising a person to enter land to recover, inspect or sample property (rule 25.1(1)(d)) may only be made by a Judge.

2.2

Except where paragraphs 2.3 and 2.4 apply, injunctions and orders relating to injunctions, including orders for specific performance where these involve an injunction, must be made by a Judge.

2.3

A Master or a District Judge may only make an injunction:

(a) in terms agreed by the parties;

(b) in connection with or ancillary to a charging order;

(c) in connection with or ancillary to an order appointing a receiver by way of equitable execution; or

(d) in proceedings under rule 66.7 (order restraining person from receiving sum due from the Crown).

2.4

A Master or District Judge may make an order varying or discharging an injunction or undertaking given to the court if all parties to the proceedings have consented to the variation or discharge.

Other pre-trial Orders and Interim Remedies

3.1

A Master or District Judge may not make orders or grant interim remedies:

(a) relating to the liberty of the subject;

(b) relating to criminal proceedings or matters except procedural applications in appeals to the High Court (including appeals by case stated) under any enactment;

(c) relating to a claim for judicial review, except that interim applications in claims for judicial review may be made to Masters of the Queen’s Bench Division.

(d) relating to appeals from Masters or District Judges;

(e) in appeals against costs assessment under Parts 44 to 47, except on an appeal under rule 47.21 against the decision of an authorised court officer.

(f) in applications under section 42 of the Senior Courts Act 1981 by a person subject to a Civil or a Criminal or an All Proceedings Order (vexatious litigant) for permission to start or continue proceedings.

(g) in applications under section 139 of the Mental Health Act 1983 for permission to bring proceedings against a person.

3.1A

Notwithstanding the provisions of paragraph 3.1 a Master of the Crown Office or a Master of the Administrative Court may–

(a) make orders and grant interim remedies relating to claims for judicial review (including claims for judicial review relating to criminal causes, appeals under the Extradition Act 2003 and applications to vary bail conditions, provided the prosecutor does not oppose the variation);

(b) determine liability for costs and make summary assessments of costs in relation to claims for judicial review; and

(c) make orders and grant interim remedies relating to applications under section 42 of the Senior Courts Act 1981 for permission to start or continue claims for judicial review.

3.2

This Practice Direction is not concerned with family proceedings. It is also not concerned with proceedings in the Family Division except to the extent that such proceedings can be dealt with in the Chancery Division or the Family Division, e.g. proceedings under the Inheritance (Provision for Family and Dependants) Act 1975 or under section 14 of the Trusts of Land and Appointment of Trustees Act 1996. District Judges (including District Judges of the Principal Registry of the Family Division) have jurisdiction to hear such proceedings, subject to any Direction given by the President of the Family Division.

Trials and Assessments of damages

4.1

A Master or District Judge may, subject to any Practice Direction, try a case which is treated as being allocated to the multi-track because it is proceeding under Part 8 (see rule 8.9(c)). He may try a case which has been allocated to the multi-track under Part 26 only with the consent of the parties. Restrictions on the trial jurisdiction of Masters and District Judges do not prevent them from hearing applications for summary judgment or, if the parties consent, for the determination of a preliminary issue.

4.2

A Master or a District Judge may assess the damages or sum due to a party under a judgment without limit as to the amount.

Chancery Proceedings

5.1

In proceedings in the Chancery Division, a Master or a district judge may not deal with the following without the consent of the Chancellor of the High Court –

(a) approving compromises (other than applications under the Inheritance (Provision for Family and Dependants) Act 1975) (i) on behalf of a person under disability where that person’s interest in a fund, or if there is no fund, the maximum amount of the claim, exceeds£100,000 and (ii) on behalf of absent, unborn and unascertained persons;

(b) making declarations, except in plain cases;

(c) making final orders under section 1(1) of the Variation of Trusts Act 1958, except for the removal of protective trusts where the interest of the principal beneficiary has not failed or determined;

(d) where the proceedings are brought by a Part 8 claim form, seeking determination of any question of law or as to the construction of a document which is raised by the claim form;

(e) giving permission to executors, administrators and trustees to bring or defend proceedings or to continue the prosecution or defence of proceedings, and granting an indemnity for costs out of the trust estate, except in plain cases;

(f) granting an indemnity for costs out of the assets of a company on the application of minority shareholders bringing a derivative action, except in plain cases;

(g) making an order for rectification, except for –

(i) rectification of the register under the Land Registration Act 1925; or

(ii) alteration or rectification of the register under the Land Registration Act 2002,

in plain cases;

(h) making orders to vacate entries in the register under the Land Charges Act 1972, except in plain cases;

(i) making final orders on applications under section 19 of the Leasehold Reform Act 1967, section 48 of the Administration of Justice Act 1985 and sections 21 and 25 of the Law of Property Act 1969;

(j) making final orders under the Landlord and Tenant Acts 1927 and 1954, except (i) by consent, and (ii) orders for interim rents under sections 24A to 24D of the 1954 Act;

(k) making orders in proceedings in the Patents Court except –

(i) orders by way of settlement, except settlement of procedural disputes;

(ii) applications for extension of time;

(iii) applications for permission to serve out of the jurisdiction;

(iv) applications for security for costs;

(v) other matters as directed by a judge of the court; and

(vi) enforcement of money judgments.

5.2

A Master or District Judge may only give directions for early trial after consulting the Judge in charge of the relevant list.

5.3

Where a winding-up order has been made against a company, any proceedings against the company by or on behalf of debenture holders may be dealt with, at the Royal Courts of Justice, by a Registrar and, in a District Registry with insolvency jurisdiction, by a District Judge.

Assignment of Claims to Masters and Transfer between Masters

6.1

The Senior Master, and the Chief Master will make arrangements for proceedings to be assigned to individual Masters. They may vary such arrangements generally or in particular cases, for example, by transferring a case from a Master to whom it had been assigned to another Master.

6.2

The fact that a case has been assigned to a particular Master does not prevent another Master from dealing with that case if circumstances require, whether at the request of the assigned Master or otherwise.

Freezing Orders: Cross Examination of Deponents about Assets

7

Where the court has made a freezing order under rule 25.1(f) and has ordered a person to make a witness statement or affidavit about his assets and to be cross-examined on its contents, unless the Judge directs otherwise, the cross-examination will take place before a Master or a District Judge, or if the Master or District Judge directs, before an examiner of the Court.

Human Rights

7A

A deputy High Court Judge, a Master or District Judge may not try –

(1) a case in a claim made in respect of a judicial act under the Human Rights Act 1998, or

(2) a claim for a declaration of incompatibility in accordance with section 4 of the Human Rights Act 1998.

COUNTY COURTS

Injunctions, Anti-social Behaviour Orders and Committal

8.1

Injunctions which a county court has jurisdiction to make may only be made by a Circuit Judge, except:

(a) where the injunction is to be made in proceedings which a District Judge otherwise has jurisdiction to hear (see paragraph 11.1 below);

(b) where the injunction is sought in a money claim which has not yet been allocated to a track and the amount claimed does not exceed the fast track financial limit;

(c) in the circumstances provided by paragraph 2.3;

(d) where the injunction is to be made under any of the following provisions –

(i) section 153A, 153B or 153D of the Housing Act 1996;

(ii) section 3 of the Protection from Harassment Act 1997; or

(iii) sections 34, 40 or 41 of the Policing and Crime Act 2009.

8.1A

A District Judge has jurisdiction to make an order under –

(1) section 1B or 1D of the Crime and Disorder Act 1998 (anti-social behaviour);

(2) section 26A, 26B or 26C of the Anti-social Behaviour Act 2003 (parenting orders); and

(3) section 4 or 9 of the Violent Crime Reduction Act 2006 (drinking banning orders).

8.2

A District Judge may make orders varying or discharging injunctions in the circumstances provided by paragraph 2.4.

8.3

A District Judge may only make an order committing a person to prison or attach a power of arrest to an injunction or remand a person where an enactment authorises this: see section 23 of the Attachment of Earnings Act 1971, sections 14 and 118 of the County Courts Act 1984, sections 153C,153D and 154-158 of and Schedule 15 to the Housing Act 1996, sections 36,40-45 and 48 of and Schedule 5 to the Policing and Crime Act 2009, and the relevant rules.

Homelessness Appeals

9

A District Judge may not hear appeals under section 204 or section 204A of the Housing Act 1996.

Other pre-trial Orders and Interim Remedies

10.1

In addition to the restrictions on jurisdiction mentioned at paragraphs 8.1–3, paragraph 3.1(d) and (e) above applies.

Trials and Assessments of Damages

11.1

A District Judge has jurisdiction to hear the following:

(a) any claim which has been allocated to the small claims track or fast track or which is treated as being allocated to the multi-track under rule 8.9(c) and the table at Section B of Practice Direction 8A, except claims:

(i) under Part I of the Landlord and Tenant Act 1927;

(ii) for a new tenancy under section 24 or for the termination of a tenancy under section 29(2) of the Landlord and Tenant Act 1954;

(iii) for an order under section 38 or 40 of the Landlord and Tenant Act 1987;

(iv) under paragraph 26 or 27 of Schedule 11 to or section 27 of the Agricultural Holdings Act 1986;

(v) under section 45(2) of the Matrimonial Causes Act 1973 for a declaration of legitimation by virtue of the Legitimacy Act 1976;

(vi) under section 35, 38 or 40 of the Fair Trading Act 1973; or

(vii) under Part II of the Mental Health Act 1983.

(b) proceedings for the recovery of land, proceedings under section 82A(2) of the Housing Act 1985 or section 6A(2) of the Housing Act 1988 (demotion claims) or proceedings in a county court under Chapter 1A of the Housing Act 1996 (demoted tenancies);

(c) the assessment of damages or other sum due to a party under a judgment without any financial limit;

(d) with the permission of the Designated Civil Judge in respect of that case, any other proceedings.

11.2

A case allocated to the small claims track may only be assigned to a Circuit Judge to hear with his consent.

Freezing Orders: Cross Examination of Deponents about Assets

12

To the extent that a county court has power to make a freezing order, paragraph 7 applies as appropriate.

Distribution of Business between Circuit Judge and District Judge

13

Where both the Circuit Judge and the District Judge have jurisdiction in respect of any proceedings, the exercise of jurisdiction by the District Judge is subject to any arrangements made by the Designated Civil Judge for the proper distribution of business between Circuit Judges and District Judges.

14.1

In district registries of the High Court and in the county court, the Designated Civil Judge may make arrangements for proceedings to be assigned to individual District Judges. He may vary such arrangements generally or in particular cases.

14.2

The fact that a case has been assigned to a particular District Judge does not prevent another District Judge from dealing with the case if the circumstances require.

Human Rights

15

A district judge may not try a case in which an allegation of indirect discrimination is made against a public authority that would, if the court finds that it occurred, be unlawful under section 19B of the Race Relations Act 1976.

PRACTICE DIRECTION 3A – STRIKING OUT A STATEMENT OF CASE

This Practice Direction supplements CPR Rule 3.4

Contents of this Practice Direction

Title
Introductory
Claims which appear to fall within rule 3.4(2)(a) or (b)
Defences which appear to fall within rule 3.4(2)(a) or (b)
General provisions
Applications for orders under rule 3.4(2)
Applications for summary judgment
Vexatious litigants

Introductory

1.1 Rule 1.4(2)(c) includes as an example of active case management the summary disposal of issues which do not need full investigation at trial.

1.2 The rules give the court two distinct powers which may be used to achieve this. Rule 3.4 enables the court to strike out the whole or part of a statement of case which discloses no reasonable grounds for bringing or defending a claim (rule 3.4(2)(a)), or which is an abuse of the process of the court or otherwise likely to obstruct the just disposal of the proceedings (rule 3.4(2)(b)) Rule 24.2 enables the court to give summary judgment against a claimant or defendant where that party has no real prospect of succeeding on his claim or defence. Both those powers may be exercised on an application by a party or on the court’s own initiative.

1.3 This practice direction sets out the procedure a party should follow if he wishes to make an application for an order under rule 3.4.

1.4 The following are examples of cases where the court may conclude that particulars of claim (whether contained in a claim form or filed separately) fall within rule 3.4(2)(a):

(1) those which set out no facts indicating what the claim is about, for example ‘Money owed £5000’,

(2) those which are incoherent and make no sense,

(3) those which contain a coherent set of facts but those facts, even if true, do not disclose any legally recognisable claim against the defendant.

1.5 A claim may fall within rule 3.4(2)(b) where it is vexatious, scurrilous or obviously ill-founded.

1.6 A defence may fall within rule 3.4(2)(a) where:

(1) it consists of a bare denial or otherwise sets out no coherent statement of facts, or

(2) the facts it sets out, while coherent, would not even if true amount in law to a defence to the claim.

1.7 A party may believe he can show without a trial that an opponent’s case has no real prospect of success on the facts, or that the case is bound to succeed or fail, as the case may be, because of a point of law (including the construction of a document). In such a case the party concerned may make an application under rule 3.4 or Part 24 (or both) as he thinks appropriate.

1.8 The examples set out above are intended only as illustrations.

1.9 Where a rule, practice direction or order states ‘shall be struck out or dismissed’ or ‘will be struck out or dismissed’ this means that the striking out or dismissal will be automatic and that no further order of the court is required.

Claims which appear to fall within rule 3.4(2)(a) or (b)

2.1 If a court officer is asked to issue a claim form which he believes may fall within rule 3.4(2)(a) or (b) he should issue it, but may then consult a judge (under rule 3.2) before returning the claim form to the claimant or taking any other step to serve the defendant. The judge may on his own initiative make an immediate order designed to ensure that the claim is disposed of or (as the case may be) proceeds in a way that accords with the rules.

2.3 The judge may allow the claimant a hearing before deciding whether to make such an order.

2.4 Orders the judge may make include:

(1) an order that the claim be stayed until further order,

(2) an order that the claim form be retained by the court and not served until the stay is lifted,

(3) an order that no application by the claimant to lift the stay be heard unless he files such further documents (for example a witness statement or an amended claim form or particulars of claim) as may be specified in the order.

2.5 Where the judge makes any such order or, subsequently, an order lifting the stay he may give directions about the service on the defendant of the order and any other documents on the court file.

2.6 The fact that a judge allows a claim referred to him by a court officer to proceed does not prejudice the right of any party to apply for any order against the claimant.

Defences which appear to fall within rule 3.4(2)(a) or (b)

3.1 A court officer may similarly consult a judge about any document filed which purports to be a defence and which he believes may fall within rule 3.4(2)(a) or (b).

3.2 If the judge decides that the document falls within rule 3.4(2)(a) or (b) he may on his own initiative make an order striking it out. Where he does so he may extend the time for the defendant to file a proper defence.

3.3 The judge may allow the defendant a hearing before deciding whether to make such an order.

3.4 Alternatively the judge may make an order under rule 18.1 requiring the defendant within a stated time to clarify his defence or to give additional information about it. The order may provide that the defence will be struck out if the defendant does not comply.

3.5 The fact that a judge does not strike out a defence on his own initiative does not prejudice the right of the claimant to apply for any order against the defendant.

General provisions

4.1 The court may exercise its powers under rule 3.4(2)(a) or (b) on application or on its own initiative at any time.

4.2 Where a judge at a hearing strikes out all or part of a party’s statement of case he may enter such judgment for the other party as that party appears entitled to.

Applications for orders under rule 3.4(2)

5.1 Attention is drawn to Part 23 (General Rules about Applications) and to Practice Direction 23A. The practice direction requires all applications to be made as soon as possible and before allocation if possible.

5.2 While many applications under rule 3.4(2) can be made without evidence in support, the applicant should consider whether facts need to be proved and, if so, whether evidence in support should be filed and served.

Applications for summary judgment

6.1 Applications for summary judgment may be made under Part 24. Attention is drawn to that Part and to Practice Direction 24.

Vexatious litigants

7.1 This Practice Direction applies where a ‘civil proceedings order’ or an ‘all proceedings order’ (as respectively defined under section 42(1A) of the Senior Courts Act 1981) is in force against a person (‘the litigant’).

7.2 An application by the litigant for permission to begin or continue, or to make any application in, any civil proceedings shall be made by application notice issued in the High Court and signed by the litigant.

7.3 The application notice must state:

(1) the title and reference number of the proceedings in which the civil proceedings order or the all proceedings order, as the case may be, was made,

(2) the full name of the litigant and his address,

(3) the order the applicant is seeking, and

(4) briefly, why the applicant is seeking the order.

7.4 The application notice must be filed together with any written evidence on which the litigant relies in support of his application.

7.5 Either in the application notice or in written evidence filed in support of the application, the previous occasions on which the litigant made an application for permission under section 42(1A) of the said Act must be listed.

7.6 The application notice, together with any written evidence, will be placed before a High Court judge who may:

(1) without the attendance of the applicant make an order giving the permission sought;

(2) give directions for further written evidence to be supplied by the litigant before an order is made on the application;

(3) make an order dismissing the application without a hearing; or

(4) give directions for the hearing of the application.

7.7 Directions given under paragraph 7.6(4) may include an order that the application notice be served on the Attorney General and on any person against whom the litigant desires to bring the proceedings for which permission is being sought.

7.8 Any order made under paragraphs 6 or 7 will be served on the litigant at the address given in the application notice. CPR Part 6 will apply.

7.9 A person may apply to set aside the grant of permission if:

(1) the permission allowed the litigant to bring or continue proceedings against that person or to make any application against him, and

(2) the permission was granted other than at a hearing of which that person was given notice under paragraph 7.

7.10 Any application under paragraph 7.9 must be made in accordance with CPR Part 23.

PRACTICE DIRECTION 3E - COSTS MANAGEMENT

This Practice Direction supplements Section II of CPR Part 3

Contents of this Practice Direction

Budget format

1 Unless the court otherwise orders, a budget must be in the form of Precedent H annexed to this Practice Direction. It must be in landscape format with an easily legible typeface. In substantial cases, the court may direct that budgets be limited initially to part only of the proceedings and subsequently extended to cover the whole proceedings. A budget must be dated and verified by a statement of truth signed by a senior legal representative of the party. In cases where a party's budgeted costs do not exceed £25,000, there is no obligation on that party to complete more than the first page of Precedent H.

(The wording for a statement of truth verifying a budget is set out in Practice Direction 22.)

Costs management orders

2.1 If the court makes a costs management order under rule 3.15, the following paragraphs apply.

2.2 Save in exceptional circumstances –

(1) the recoverable costs of initially completing Precedent H shall not exceed the higher of £1,000 or 1% of the approved budget;

(2) All other recoverable costs of the budgeting and costs management process shall not exceed 2% of the approved budget.

2.3 If the budgets or parts of the budgets are agreed between all parties, the court will record the extent of such agreement. In so far as the budgets are not agreed, the court will review them and, after making any appropriate revisions, record its approval of those budgets. The court's approval will relate only to the total figures for each phase of the proceedings, although in the course of its review the court may have regard to the constituent elements of each total figure. When reviewing budgets, the court will not undertake a detailed assessment in advance, but rather will consider whether the budgeted costs fall within the range of reasonable and proportionate costs.

2.4 As part of the costs management process the court may not approve costs incurred before the date of any budget. The court may, however, record its comments on those costs and should take those costs into account when considering the reasonableness and proportionality of all subsequent costs.

2.5 The court may set a timetable or give other directions for future reviews of budgets.

2.6 Each party shall revise its budget in respect of future costs upwards or downwards, if significant developments in the litigation warrant such revisions.

Such amended budgets shall be submitted to the other parties for agreement. In default of agreement, the amended budgets shall be submitted to the court, together with a note of (a) the changes made and the reasons for those changes and (b) the objections of any other party. The court may approve, vary or disapprove the revisions, having regard to any significant developments which have occurred since the date when the previous budget was approved or agreed.

2.7 After its budget has been approved, each party shall re-file and re-serve the budget in the form approved with re-cast figures, annexed to the order approving it.

2.8 A litigant in person, even though not required to prepare a budget, shall nevertheless be provided with a copy of the budget of any other party.

2.9 If interim applications are made which, reasonably, were not included in a budget, then the costs of such interim applications shall be treated as additional to the approved budgets.

Annex

Precedent H (xls file - opens in new window)

Guidance Notes for Precedent H (PDF - opens in new window)

PRACTICE DIRECTION 5A – COURT DOCUMENTS

This Practice Direction supplements CPR Part 5

Contents of this Practice Direction

Signature of documents by mechanical means

1 Where, under rule 5.3, a replica signature is printed electronically or by other mechanical means on any document, the name of the person whose signature is printed must also be printed so that the person may be identified. This paragraph does not apply to claim forms issued through the Claims Production Centre.

Form of documents

2.1 Statements of case and other documents drafted by a legal representative should bear his/her signature and if they are drafted by a legal representative as a member or employee of a firm they should be signed in the name of the firm.

2.2 Every document prepared by a party for filing or use at the Court must –

(1) Unless the nature of the document renders it impracticable, be on A4 paper of durable quality having a margin, not less than 3.5 centimetres wide,

(2) be fully legible and should normally be typed,

(3) where possible be bound securely in a manner which would not hamper filing or otherwise each page should be endorsed with the case number,

(4) have the pages numbered consecutively,

(5) be divided into numbered paragraphs,

(6) have all numbers, including dates, expressed as figures, and

(7) give in the margin the reference of every document mentioned that has already been filed.

2.3 A document which is a copy produced by a colour photostat machine or other similar device may be filed at the court office provided that the coloured date seal of the Court is not reproduced on the copy.

Supply of documents to new parties

3.1 Where a party is joined to existing proceedings, the party joined shall be entitled to require the party joining him to supply, without charge, copies of all statements of case, written evidence and any documents appended or exhibited to them which have been served in the proceedings by or upon the joining party which relate to any issues between the joining party and the party joined, and copies of all orders made in those proceedings. The documents must be supplied within 48 hours after a written request for them is received.

3.2 If the party joined is not supplied with copies of the documents requested under paragraph 3.1 within 48 hours, he may apply under Part 23 for an order that they be supplied.

3.3 The party by whom a copy is supplied under paragraph 3.1 or, if he is acting by a solicitor, his solicitor, shall be responsible for it being a true copy.

Supply of documents from court records

4.1 Registers of claims which have been issued are available for inspection at the following offices of the High Court at the Royal Courts of Justice:

(1) the Central Office of the Queen’s Bench Division;

(2) Chancery Chambers;

(3) the Admiralty and Commercial Court Registry.

4.2 No registers of claims are at present available for inspection in county courts or in district registries or other offices of the High Court.

4.2A A party to proceedings may, unless the court orders otherwise, obtain from the records of the court a copy of –

(a) a certificate of suitability of a litigation friend;

(b) a notice of funding;

(c) a claim form or other statement of case together with any documents filed with or attached to or intended by the claimant to be served with such claim form;

(d) an acknowledgment of service together with any documents filed with or attached to or intended by the party acknowledging service to be served with such acknowledgement of service;

(e) a certificate of service, other than a certificate of service of an application notice or order in relation to a type of application mentioned in sub-paragraph (h)(i) or (ii);

(f) a notice of non-service;

(g) a directions questionnaire;

(h) an application notice, other than in relation to –

(i) an application by a solicitor for an order declaring that he has ceased to be the solicitor acting for a party; or

(ii) an application for an order that the identity of a party or witness should not be disclosed;

(i) any written evidence filed in relation to an application, other than a type of application mentioned in sub-paragraph (h)(i) or (ii);

(j) a judgment or order given or made in public (whether made at a hearing or without a hearing);

(k) a statement of costs;

(l) a list of documents;

(m) a notice of payment into court;

(n) a notice of discontinuance;

(o) a notice of change; or

(p) an appellant's or respondent's notice of appeal.

4.3 An application under rule 5.4B(2), 5.4C(1B), 5.4C(2) or 5.4C(3)(b)(ii) for permission to obtain a copy of a document, even if made without notice, must be made under CPR Part 23 and the application notice must identify the document or class of document in respect of which permission is sought and the grounds relied upon.

4.4 An application under rule 5.4C(4) by a party or a person identified in a claim form must be made –

(1) under CPR Part 23; and

(2) to a Master or district judge, unless the court directs otherwise.

4.5

Rule 5.4B allows a person who is a party to proceedings to obtain copies of documents from court records. A person is a party to proceedings who has been named as a party on a statement of case irrespective of whether they have been served with that statement of case.

Supply of documents from court records – statements of case filed before 2nd October 2006

4A.1 Rule 5.4C(1A) provides that the rules of court relating to access by a non-party to statements of case in force immediately before 2nd October 2006 apply to statements of case filed before that date as if they had not been revoked. For ease of reference, those rules are set out in the following paragraphs as they applied to statements of case, along with the relevant supplementary provisions previously contained in this practice direction.

4A.2 A person who is not a party to proceedings may –

(1) unless the court orders otherwise, obtain from the records of the court a copy of a claim form, but not any documents filed with or attached to or intended by the claimant to be served with such claim form, subject to paragraph 4A.3 and to any order of the court under paragraph 4A.4; and

(2) if the court gives permission, obtain from the records of the court a copy of any other statement of case.

4A.3 A person may obtain a copy of a claim form under paragraph 4A.2(1) only if –

(1) where there is one defendant, the defendant has filed an acknowledgment of service or a defence;

(2) where there is more than one defendant, either –

(a) all the defendants have filed an acknowledgment of service or a defence;

(b) at least one defendant has filed an acknowledgment of service or a defence, and the court gives permission;

(3) the claim has been listed for a hearing; or

(4) judgment has been entered in the claim.

4A.4 The court may, on the application of a party or any person identified in the claim form –

(1) restrict the persons or classes of persons who may obtain a copy of the claim form;

(2) order that persons or classes of persons may only obtain a copy of the claim form if it is edited in accordance with the directions of the court; or

(3) make such other order as it thinks fit.

4A.5 A person wishing to obtain a copy of a document under paragraph 4A.2 must pay any prescribed fee and –

(a) if the court’s permission is required, file an application notice in accordance with Part 23; or

(b) if permission is not required, file a written request for the document.

4A.6 An application for permission to obtain a copy of a statement of case, or for an order under paragraph 4A.4, may be made without notice, but the court may direct notice to be given to any person who would be affected by its decision.

4A.7 An application under paragraph 4A.3(2)(b) for permission to obtain a copy of a claim form must be made under Part 23.

4A.8 An application notice under paragraph 4A.2(2) or paragraph 4A.3(2)(b) must identify the document or class of document in respect of which permission is sought and the grounds relied upon.

4A.9 An application under paragraph 4A.4 by a party or a person identified in a claim form must be made –

(a) under Part 23; and

(b) to a Master or district judge, unless the court directs otherwise.

Documents for filing at court

5.1 The date on which a document was filed at court must be recorded on the document. This may be done by a seal or a receipt stamp.

5.2 Particulars of the date of delivery at a court office of any document for filing and the title of the proceedings in which the document is filed shall be entered in court records, on the court file or on a computer kept in the court office for the purpose. Except where a document has been delivered at the court office through the post, the time of delivery should also be recorded.

5.3 Filing by Facsimile

(1) Subject to paragraph (6) below, a party may file a document at court by sending it by facsimile (‘fax’).

(2) Where a party files a document by fax, he must not send a hard copy in addition.

(3) A party filing a document by fax should be aware that the document is not filed at court until it is delivered by the court’s fax machine, whatever time it is shown to have been transmitted from the party’s machine.

(4) The time of delivery of the faxed document will be recorded on it in accordance with paragraph 5.2.

(5) It remains the responsibility of the party to ensure that the document is delivered to the court in time.

(6) If a fax is delivered after 4 p.m. it will be treated as filed on the next day the court office is open.

(7) If a fax relates to a hearing, the date and time of the hearing should be prominently displayed.

(8) Fax should not be used to send letters or documents of a routine or non-urgent nature.

(9) Fax should not be used, except in an unavoidable emergency, to deliver:

(a) a document which attracts a fee

(b) omitted

(c) a document relating to a hearing less than two hours ahead

(d) trial bundles or skeleton arguments

(10) Where (9)(a) or (b) applies, the fax should give an explanation for the emergency and include an undertaking that the fee or money has been dispatched that day by post or will be paid at the court office counter the following business day.

(11) Where courts have several fax machines, each allocated to an individual section, fax messages should only be sent to the machine of the section for which the message is intended.

5.4 Where the Court orders any document to be lodged in Court, the document must, unless otherwise directed, be deposited in the office of that Court.

5.5 A document filed, lodged or held in any court office shall not be taken out of that office without the permission of the Court unless the document is to be sent to the office of another court (for example under CPR Part 30 (Transfer)), except in accordance with CPR rule 39.7 (impounded documents) or in accordance with paragraph 5.6 below.

5.6

(1) Where a document filed, lodged or held in a court office is required to be produced to any Court, Tribunal or arbitrator, the document may be produced by sending it by registered post (together with a Certificate as in paragraph 5.6(8)(b)) to the Court, Tribunal or arbitrator in accordance with the provisions of this paragraph.

(2) Any Court, Tribunal or arbitrator or any party requiring any document filed, lodged or held in any court office to be produced must apply to that court office by sending a completed request (as in paragraph 5.6 (8)(a)), stamped with the prescribed fee.

(3) On receipt of the request the court officer will submit the same to a Master in the Royal Courts of Justice or to a District Judge elsewhere, who may direct that the request be complied with. Before giving a direction the Master or District Judge may require to be satisfied that the request is made in good faith and that the document is required to be produced for the reasons stated. The Master or District Judge giving the direction may also direct that, before the document is sent, an official copy of it is made and filed in the court office at the expense of the party requiring the document to be produced.

(4) On the direction of the Master or District Judge the court officer shall send the document by registered post addressed to the Court, Tribunal or arbitrator, with:

(a) an envelope stamped and addressed for use in returning the document to the court office from which it was sent;

(b) a Certificate as in paragraph 5.6(8)(b);

(c) a covering letter describing the document, stating at whose request and for what purpose it is sent, referring to this paragraph of the Practice Direction and containing a request that the document be returned to the court office from which it was sent in the enclosed envelope as soon as the Court or Tribunal no longer requires it.

(5) It shall be the duty of the Court, Tribunal or arbitrator to whom the document was sent to keep it in safe custody, and to return it by registered post to the court office from which it was sent, as soon as the Court, Tribunal or arbitrator no longer requires it.

(6) In each court office a record shall be kept of each document sent and the date on which it was sent and the Court, Tribunal or arbitrator to whom it was sent and the date of its return. It shall be the duty of the court officer who has signed the certificate referred to in para 5.6(8)(b) below to ensure that the document is returned within a reasonable time and to make inquiries and report to the Master or District Judge who has given the direction under paragraph (3) above if the document is not returned, so that steps may be taken to secure its return.

(7) Notwithstanding the preceding paragraphs, the Master or District Judge may direct a court officer to attend the Court, Tribunal or arbitrator for the purpose of producing the document.

(8)

(a) I,      of      , an officer of the      Court/Tribunal at      /an arbitrator of      /the Claimant /Defendant /Solicitor for the Claimant/ Defendant [describing the Applicant so as to show that he is a proper person to make the request] in the case of       v.      [19 No. ]

(REQUEST that the following document [or documents] be produced to the Court /Tribunal/arbitrator on the day of 19 [and following days] and I request that the said document [or documents] be sent by registered post to the proper officer of the Court/Tribunal/arbitrator for production to that Court/ Tribunal/arbitrator on that day.

(Signed).

Dated the day of 1999/2

(b) I, A.B., an officer of the            Court            of      certify that the document sent herewith for production to the Court/Tribunal/arbitrator on the      day of          1999/2      in the case of v. and marked ‘A.B.’ is the document requested on the day of 1999/2 and I FURTHER CERTIFY that the said document has been filed in and is produced from the custody of the Court.

(Signed)

Dated the day of 1999/2 .

Enrolment of deeds and other documents

6.1

(1) Any deed or document which by virtue of any enactment is required or authorised to be enrolled in the Senior Courts may be enrolled in the Central Office of the High Court.

(2) Attention is drawn to the Enrolment of Deeds (Change of Name) Regulations 1994 which are reproduced in the Appendix to this Practice Direction.

6.2 The following paragraph of the Practice Direction describes the practice to be followed in any case in which a child’s name is to be changed and to which the 1994 Regulations apply.

6.3

(1) Where a person has by any order of the High Court, County Court or Family Proceedings Court been given parental responsibility for a child and applies to the Central Office, Filing Department, for the enrolment of a Deed Poll to change the surname (family name) of a child who is under the age of 18 years (unless a child who is or has been married or has formed a civil partnership), the application must be supported by the production of the consent in writing of every other person having parental responsibility.

(2) In the absence of that consent, the application will be adjourned generally unless and until permission is given in the proceedings, in which the said order was made, to change the surname of the child and the permission is produced to the Central Office.

(3) Where an application is made to the Central Office by a person who has not been given parental responsibility for a child by any order of the High Court, County Court or Family Proceedings Court for the enrolment of a Deed Poll to change the surname of the child who is under the age of 18 years (unless the child is or has been married or has formed a civil partnership), permission of the Court to enrol the Deed will be granted if the consent in writing of every person having parental responsibility is produced or if the person (or, if more than one, persons) having parental responsibility is dead or overseas or despite the exercise of reasonable diligence it has not been possible to find him or her for other good reason.

(4) In cases of doubt the Senior Master or, in his absence, the Practice Master will refer the matter to the Master of the Rolls.

(5) In the absence of any of the conditions specified above the Senior Master or the Master of the Rolls, as the case may be, may refer the matter to the Official Solicitor for investigation and report.

Appendix

Regulations made by the Master of the Rolls, Sir Thomas Bingham M.R. on March 3, 1994 (S.I. 1994 No.604) under s.133(1) of the Supreme Court Act 1981.

1

(1) These regulations may be cited as the Enrolment of Deeds (Change of Name) Regulations 1994 and shall come into force on April 1, 1994.

(2) These Regulations shall govern the enrolment in the Central Office of the Supreme Court of deeds evidencing change of name (referred to in these Regulations as ‘deeds poll’).

2

(1) A person seeking to enrol a deed poll (’the applicant’) must be a Commonwealth citizen as defined by section 37(1) of the British Nationality Act 1981.

(2) If the applicant is a British citizen, a British Dependent Territories citizen or a British Overseas citizen, he must be described as such in the deed poll, which must also specify the section of the British Nationality Act under which the relevant citizenship was acquired.

(3) In any other case, the applicant must be described as a Commonwealth citizen.

(4) The applicant must be described in the deed poll as single, married, widowed, divorced, a civil partner or former civil partner and, if a former civil partner, whether the civil partnership ended on death or dissolution.

3

(1) As proof of the citizenship named in the deed poll, the applicant must produce:

(a) a certificate of birth; or

(b) a certificate of citizenship by registration or naturalisation or otherwise; or

(c) some other document evidencing such citizenship.

(2) In addition to the documents set out in paragraph (1), an applicant who is married or a civil partner must:

(a) produce his certificate of marriage or civil partnership certificate; and

(b) show that the notice of his intention to apply for the enrolment of the deed poll had been given to his spouse or civil partner by delivery or by post to his spouse's or civil partner's last known address; and

(c) show that he has obtained the consent of his spouse or civil partner to the proposed change of name or that there is good reason why such consent should be dispensed with.

4

(1) The deed poll and the documents referred to in regulation 3 must be exhibited to a statutory declaration by a Commonwealth citizen who is a householder in the United Kingdom and who must declare that he is such in the statutory declaration.

(2) The statutory declaration must state the period, which should ordinarily not be less than 10 years, during which the householder has known the applicant and must identify the applicant as the person referred to in the documents exhibited to the statutory declaration.

(3) Where the period mentioned in paragraph (2) is stated to be less than 10 years, the Master of the Rolls may in his absolute discretion decide whether to permit the deed poll to be enrolled and may require the applicant to provide more information before so deciding.

5 If the applicant is resident outside the United Kingdom, he must provide evidence that such residence is not intended to be permanent and the applicant may be required to produce a certificate by a solicitor as to the nature and probable duration of such residence.

6 The applicant must sign the deed poll in both his old and new names.

7 Upon enrolment the deed poll shall be advertised in the London Gazette by the clerk in charge for the time being of the Filing and Record Department at the Central Office of the Supreme Court.

8

(1) Subject to the following provisions of this regulation, these Regulations shall apply in relation to a deed poll evidencing the change of name of a child as if the child were the applicant.

(2) Paragraphs (3) to (8) shall not apply to a child who has attained the age of 16 and is or has been married or a civil partner.

(3) If the child is under the age of 16, the deed poll must be executed by a person having parental responsibility for him.

(4) If the child has attained the age of 16, the deed poll must, except in the case of a person mentioned in paragraph (2), be executed by a person having parental responsibility for the child and be endorsed with the child’s consent signed in both his old and new names and duly witnessed.

(5) The application for enrolment must be supported:

(a) by a witness statement showing that the change of name is for the benefit of the child; and –

(i) that the application is submitted by all persons having parental responsibility for the child; or

(ii) that it is submitted by one person having parental responsibility for the child with the consent of every other person; or

(iii) that it is submitted by one person having parental responsibility for the child without the consent of every other such person, or by some other person whose name and capacity are given, for reasons set out in the affidavit; and

(b) by such other evidence, if any, as the Master of the Rolls may require in the particular circumstances of the case.

(6) Regulation 4(2) shall not apply but the statutory declaration mentioned in regulation 4(1) shall state how long the householder has known the deponent under paragraph (5)(a) and the child respectively.

(7) Regulation 6 shall not apply to a child who has not attained the age of 16.

(8) In this regulation ‘parental responsibility’ has the meaning given in section 3 of the Children Act 1989.

9 The Enrolment of Deeds (Change of Name) Regulations 1983 and the Enrolment of Deeds (Change of Name) (Amendment) Regulations 1990 are hereby revoked.

PRACTICE DIRECTION 5B – ELECTRONIC COMMUNICATION AND FILING OF DOCUMENTS

This Practice Direction supplements rule 5.5

Contents of this Practice Direction

Title | Number
General | Para. 1.1
SECTION I – COMMUNICATION AND FILING OF DOCUMENTS BY E-MAIL |

Interpretation | Para. 2.1
Communications and documents which may be sent by e-mail | Para. 3.1
Technical specifications of e-mail | Para. 4.1
SECTION II – ONLINE FORMS SERVICE
|

Scope and interpretation | Para. 5.1
Filing of documents online | Para. 6.1
SECTION III – GENERAL PROVISIONS
|

Interpretation | Para. 7
Provisions relating to the filing of documents electronically | Para. 8.1
Statement of truth in documents filed electronically | Para. 9

General

1.1 Section I of this practice direction provides for parties to claims in specified courts to –

(1) communicate with the court by e-mail; and

(2) file specified documents by e-mail.

1.2 Section II of this practice direction provides for parties to claims in specified courts to file specified documents electronically via an online forms service.

1.3 Section III of this practice direction contains general provisions which apply to both Section I and Section II.

1.4 This practice direction does not allow –

(1) communication with the court or the filing of documents by email; or

(2) use of the online forms service,

in proceedings to which the Civil Procedure Rules do not apply.

SECTION I – COMMUNICATION AND FILING OF DOCUMENTS BY E-MAIL

Interpretation

2.1 For the purposes of this Section –

(1) a specified court is a court or court office which has published an e-mail address for the filing of documents on Her Majest’s Courts and Tribunals Service website; and

(2) a specified document is a document listed on Her Majesty’s Courts and Tribunals Service website as a document that may be sent to or filed in that court by e-mail.

Communications and documents which may be sent by e-mail

3.1 Subject to paragraph 3.2, a party to a claim in a specified court may send a specified document to the court by e-mail.

3.2 Subject to paragraph 3.2A, a party must not use e-mail to take any step in a claim for which a fee is payable.

3.2A A party may make an application using e-mail in the Preston Combined Court, where he is permitted to do so by PREMA (Preston E-mail Application Service) User Guide and Protocols.

3.3 Subject to paragraph 3.3A and paragraph 15.1A of Practice Direction 52, if –

(a) a fee is payable on the filing of a particular document; and

(b) a party purports to file that document by e-mail,

the court shall treat the document as not having been filed.

3.3A A party may file by email an application notice in the Preston Combined Court where permitted to do so by PREMA (Preston E-mail Application Service) User Guide and Protocols.

(Paragraph 15.1A of Practice Direction 52 provides for filing by email an appeal notice or application notice in proceedings in the Court of Appeal, Civil Division.)

(Rules 6.3(1)(d) and 6.20(1)(d) permit service by e-mail in accordance with the relevant practice direction. Rule 6.23(6) and paragraph 4 of Practice Direction 6A set out the circumstances in which a party may serve a document by e-mail.)

Technical specifications of e-mail

4.1 The e-mail message must contain the name, telephone number and e-mail address of the sender and should be in plain text or rich text format rather than HTML.

4.2 Correspondence and documents may be sent as either text in the body of the e-mail, or as attachments, except as mentioned in paragraph 4.3.

4.3 Documents required to be in a practice form must be sent in that form as attachments.

4.4 Court forms may be downloaded from Her Majesty’s Courts and Tribunals Service website.

4.5 Attachments must be sent in a format supported by the software used by the specified court to which it is sent. The format or formats which may be used in sending attachments to a particular specified court are listed on Her Majesty’s Courts and Tribunals Service website.

4.6 An attachment which is sent to a specified court in a format not listed on Her Majesty’s Courts and Tribunals Service website as appropriate for that court will be treated as not having been received by the court.

4.7 The length of attachments and total size of e-mail must not exceed the maximum which a particular specified court has indicated that it can accept. This information is listed on the email guidance page.

4.8 Where proceedings have been commenced, the subject line of the e-mail must contain the following information –

(1) the case number;

(2) the parties' names (abbreviated if necessary); and

(3) the date and time of any hearing to which the e-mail relates.

SECTION II – ONLINE FORMS SERVICE

Scope and interpretation

5.1 Reference to an online forms service is reference to a service available on Her Majesty’s Courts and Tribunals Service website. The website contains certain documents which a user may complete online and then submit electronically to a specified court.

5.2 For the purposes of this Section –

(1) a specified court is a court or court office listed on Her Majesty’s Courts and Tribunals Service website as able to receive documents filed electronically via the online forms service; and

(2) a specified document is a document which is available for completion on the website.

(Paragraph 15.1B of Practice Direction 52 provides for certain notices to be filed electronically at the Court of Appeal, Civil Division using the online forms service on the Court of Appeal, Civil Division website)

Filing of documents online

6.1 A party to a claim in a specified court may send a specified document to the court using the online forms service.

6.2 A party may use the online forms service to take a step in a claim for which a fee is payable. The fee must be paid, using the facilities available at the online forms service, before the application, or other document attracting a fee, is forwarded to the specified court.

6.3 The online forms service will assist the user in completing a document accurately but the user is responsible for ensuring that the rules and practice directions relating to the document have been complied with. Transmission by the service does not guarantee that the document will be accepted by the specified court.

SECTION III – GENERAL PROVISIONS

Interpretation

7 In this Section –

(1) filing or sending a document‘electronically’, means filing or sending it in accordance with Section I or Section II; and

(2) a reference to 'transmission' means, unless the context otherwise requires –

(a) in relation to Section I, the e-mail sent by the party to the court; and

(b) in relation to Section II, the electronic transmission of the form by the online forms service to the court.

Provisions relating to the filing of documents electronically

8.1 Where a party files a document electronically, he must not send a hard copy of that document to the court.

8.2 A document is not filed until the transmission is received by the court, whatever time it is shown to have been sent.

8.3 The time of receipt of a transmission will be recorded electronically on the transmission as it is received.

8.4 If a transmission is received after 4pm –

(1) the transmission will be treated as received; and

(2) any document attached to the transmission will be treated as filed,

on the next day the court office is open.

8.5 A party –

(1) sending an e-mail in accordance with Section I; or

(2) using the online forms service in accordance with Section II,

is responsible for ensuring that the transmission or any document attached to it is filed within any relevant time limits.

8.6 The court will normally reply by e-mail where–

(1) the response is to a message transmitted electronically; and

(2) the sender has provided an e-mail address.

8.7 Parties are advised not to transmit electronically any correspondence or documents of a confidential or sensitive nature, as security cannot be guaranteed.

8.8 If a document transmitted electronically requires urgent attention, the sender should contact the court by telephone.

8.9 A document that is required by a rule or practice direction to be filed at court is not filed when it is sent to the judge by e-mail.

Statement of truth in documents filed electronically

9 Where a party wishes to file a document containing a statement of truth electronically, that party should retain the document containing the original signature and file with the court a version of the document satisfying one of the following requirements

(1) the name of the person who has signed the statement of truth is typed underneath the statement;

(2) the person who has signed the statement of truth has applied a facsimile of his signature to the statement in the document by mechanical means; or

(3) the document that is filed is a scanned version of the document containing the original signature to the statement of truth.

PRACTICE DIRECTION 5C – ELECTRONIC WORKING SCHEME

This Practice Direction supplements CPR rules 5.5 and 7.12

Contents of this Practice Direction

Title | Number
General | Para. 1.1
Security | Para. 2.1
Fees
| Para. 3.1
Forms | Para. 4.1
Scope of electronic working | Para. 5
Starting a claim | Para. 6.1
Electronic working response | Para. 7.1
Statement of truth | Para. 8.1
Signature | Para. 9
Request for judgment or issue of warrant | Para. 10.1
Inspecting the case record | Para. 11.1
Applications in proceedings | Para. 12
Allocation and case management | Para. 13.1
Trial bundles | Para. 14.1
Transfer of proceedings | Para. 15.1
Public kiosk service | Para. 16.1
Scanning documents filed in paper format | Para. 17.1
Annex |

General

1.1

(1) This Practice Direction is made under rules 5.5 and 7.12 of the Civil Procedure Rules (‘CPR’). It provides for a scheme (‘Electronic Working’) to –

(a) operate from 1st April 2010;

(b) operate in the Admiralty, Commercial and London Mercantile Courts, the Technology and Construction Court, and the Chancery Division of the High Court at the Royal Courts of Justice, including in the case of the Chancery Division the Patents Court and the Bankruptcy and Companies courts. It is intended that this Practice Direction should continue to apply to those jurisdictions when they transfer to the Rolls Building, and to the Bankruptcy jurisdiction of the Central London County Court (the Rolls Building jurisdictions); and

(c)

(i) apply to claims started on or after 1st April 2010; and

(ii) apply to claims started or continued electronically under the Electronic Working Pilot Scheme between 1st April 2009 and 31st March 2010.

(2) Where the provisions of this Practice Direction conflict with the provisions of Practice Direction 5B this Practice Direction shall take precedence.

(3) In this Practice Direction‘document key’ means the unique alpha-numeric identifier set out on the court form to obtain the relevant document where there is no electronic link.

1.2

(1) This Practice Direction provides for a scheme of electronic working by which –

(a) proceedings may be started and all subsequent steps may be taken electronically; and

(b) proceedings which have not been started electronically, may be continued electronically after documents in paper format in those proceedings have been converted to an electronic format by means of a scanning procedure by the Court and the proceedings shall then continue under the scheme as if they had been started electronically.

(2) As an electronic system, the Electronic Working scheme will operate 24 hours a day all year round, including weekends and bank holidays. This will enable claim forms to be issued and documents to be filed in electronic format out of normal court office opening hours. However, there will be two exceptions to this –

(a) planned ‘down-time’: as with all electronic systems, there will be some planned periods for system maintenance and upgrades when Electronic Working will not be available; and

(b) unplanned ‘down-time’: in the event of unplanned periods during which Electronic Working will not be available due, for example, to a system failure or power outage.

1.3 The Electronic Working scheme will be subject to the following provisions of the CPR, unless specifically excluded or revised by this Practice Direction:

Part 57 (Probate Actions)

Part 58 (Commercial Court claims)

Part 59 (Mercantile Court claims)

Part 60 (Technology and Construction Court claims)

Part 61 (Admiralty claims)

Part 62 (Arbitration claims)

Part 63 (Patent claims)

(Litigants will need to give careful consideration to:

The Chancery Guide

The Queen’s Bench Division Guide

The Admiralty and Commercial Courts Guide

The Technology and Construction Court Guide

and The Patents Court Guide)

1.4

(1) This Practice Direction enables claimants to start or continue electronically claims in the Rolls Building jurisdictions.

(2) Where a claim has been started or is continuing electronically any party may file electronically all forms and documents, using where necessary, the multi purpose form.

1.5 Any form or document which is filed electronically –

(a) must not be filed in paper format unless this is required by a court order, rule, or practice direction;

(b) must consist of one copy only with no further copies unless required by a court order, rule or practice direction; and

(c) will receive an automated response to acknowledge receipt.

1.6

(1) Persons wishing to use the Electronic Working scheme are required, wherever possible, to communicate with the court by means of e-mail. For the purposes of e-mail communications a person using the Electronic Working scheme must –

(a) provide the court with at least one and not more than three e-mail address(es) at which that person can be contacted;

(b) use the e-mail address provided by the court to file documents at the court; and

(c) use the document keys where provided by the court, to populate the subject line of the e-mail or use the electronic link to obtain the relevant document.

(2) Where persons using the Electronic Working scheme include their e-mail address on any court form, document or statement of case this is not confirmation or agreement that they are prepared to accept service by e-mail of documents between the parties to the proceedings unless they expressly agree to do so. Paragraph 4.1(2)(c) of Practice Direction 6A does not apply.

1.7

(1) A claim filed electronically under the Electronic Working scheme will be issued by the Admiralty Court, the Commercial Court, the London Mercantile Court, the Technology and Construction Court, or the Chancery Division of the High Court as appropriate and the claim will proceed in that court unless it is transferred to another court.

(2) If the claim is transferred to another court which is not operating the Electronic Working scheme it will come out of the scheme and this Practice Direction shall not apply to the proceedings in relation to any step taken after the date of transfer.

(Paragraph 15 contains further provisions about the transfer of proceedings.)

1.8 Unless the court orders otherwise, any form, statement of case, document or order issued or filed by any party under the Rolls Building jurisdiction whether in electronic or paper format, which is required to be served shall be served by the party who requested it.

Security

2.1 Her Majesty’s Courts and Tribunals Service will take such measures as it thinks fit to ensure the security of steps taken or information communicated or stored electronically. These may include requiring persons using Electronic Working to –

(1) enter a customer identification and/or password;

(2) provide personal information for identification purposes; and

(3) comply with any other security measures, as may from time to time be required before taking any of the steps mentioned in paragraph 1. 4 or 1.5.

2.2 Her Majesty’s Courts and Tribunals Service may provide such method of encryption to promote security of e-mail communications as may be deemed appropriate.

(Paragraph 8.7 of Practice Direction 5B (Electronic communications and filing of documents) contains provisions concerning the transmission of documents or correspondence electronically.)

Fees

3.1 Where this Practice Direction provides for a fee to be paid, it may be paid by any method which Her Majesty’s Courts and Tribunals Service may permit including any online or offline payment facility.

3.2 In certain circumstances, a party may be entitled to a remission or part remission of fees. Her Majesty’s Courts and Tribunals Service website contains guidance as to when this entitlement might arise. A party, who wishes to apply for remission or part remission of fees, must do so prior to taking any step which requires a fee to be paid.

3.3

(1) On issuing or filing electronically any form or document which requires the payment of a fee, the person issuing or filing that document shall –

(a) pay the appropriate fee; or

(b) apply for fee remission in accordance with paragraph 3.2.

(2) The form or document will be subject to an initial automated validation to ensure all mandatory fields have been completed.

(3) Once validated the form or document will be issued, sealed where appropriate, and returned to the person filing or requesting the issue of the same.

(Paragraph 7 contains provisions about the filing of counterclaims and other Part 20 claims)

Forms

4.1 Persons using the Electronic Working scheme must ensure that all forms, documents, schedules and other attachments filed at court are in PDF format.

4.2 Persons using the Electronic Working scheme must, where they are available, use the PDF forms which have been created by Her Majesty’s Courts and Tribunals Service specifically for Electronic Working.

4.3 Persons using the Electronic Working scheme and wishing to file any document which has not been created specifically for Electronic Working must before filing that document –

(1) convert the document to PDF format if it is already in an electronic form or if it is only available in paper copy scan the document into PDF format; and

(2) attach the document to the multi purpose form for that case which has been created specifically for Electronic Working.

Scope of electronic working

5 The Electronic Working scheme may be used to start claims pursuant to Part 7, Part 8 and Part 20 and also Arbitration claims and Admiralty proceedings as appropriate in the Admiralty and Commercial Court, the London Mercantile Court, the Technology and Construction Court, and in the Chancery Division of the High Court.

Starting a claim

6.1 A claimant may request the issue of a claim form by –

(a) obtaining the electronic claim form from Her Majesty's Courts and Tribunals Service in the following manner –

(i) typing in the form number the claimant requires in the subject line of an e-mail; and

(ii) sending the e-mail to getform@justice.gsi.gov.uk;

(b) completing and sending the electronic claim form and such other forms or documents as may be required to start the claim by e-mail to submit@justice.gsi.gov.uk; and

(c) paying the appropriate issue fee.

(The Annex to this Practice Direction lists and contains relevant forms)

6.2 The particulars of claim may be included in or attached to the electronic claim form, or may be filed separately in accordance with rules 58.5, 59.4, 61.3 or 7.4, where applicable, by attaching the particulars of claim to the electronic multi purpose form.

6.3 When a claim form is received electronically at the address provided by the court –

(1) subject to the automated validation referred to in paragraph 3.3, the claim form will be issued, sealed and returned to the claimant for service; but

(2) if the form fails the automated validation it will be returned to the claimant together with notice of the reasons for failure.

6.4

(1) The court will accept receipt of claim forms filed through Electronic Working out of normal court office opening hours. Claim forms received by the court up to midnight will bear the date they are received as the issue date.

(2) When the court issues a claim form through Electronic Working following a validated request under paragraphs 6.1 and 6.3 –

(a) the court will seal the claim form with the date on which the claim form was received by the court through Electronic Working and this shall be the issue date; and

(b) the court will keep a record of when claim forms filed through Electronic Working are received.

(Paragraph 1.2(2) contains provisions about system ‘down-time’ which may prevent immediate issue of claim forms.)

6.5

(1) When the court issues a claim form through Electronic Working the court will –

(a) return an electronic sealed version in PDF format for service by the claimant; and

(b) return a further electronic version in PDF format which must be retained by the claimant in case the form needs to be amended.

(2) It is a party’s responsibility to print and serve any form requiring service by that party unless the party or parties to be served have agreed to accept service by email or other electronic means.

(Paragraph 1.6(2) contains provisions for service by email and paragraph 1.8 contains provisions about the service of forms and documents.)

6.6 A document key or electronic link will be printed on the sealed claim form and this will allow the party by whom it is served to obtain and file the acknowledgment of service through Electronic Working, together with other document keys or electronic links which will then allow the parties to obtain other forms required for the purposes of the proceedings.

Electronic working response

7.1 A party wishing to file –

(a) an acknowledgment of service under Part 10;

(b) an admission or part admission;

(c) a defence or defence and counterclaim under Part 15;

(d) a Part 20 claim; or

(e) any other document,

may obtain the Electronic Working version of the following documents or forms –

(i) requests for judgment on acceptance of an admission of the whole of the amount claimed;

(ii) statements of case and any amended statements of case;

(iii) requests for further information and any replies;

(iv) applications for an order, whether before or after the start of proceedings;

(v) witness statements or affidavits and exhibits;

(vi) draft orders and orders for sealing;

(vii) case summaries, lists of issues, chronologies, skeleton arguments, case management information sheets, progress monitoring information sheets, directions questionnaires where appropriate and pre-trial checklists;

(viii) statements of costs;

by using the document keys referred to in paragraph 6.6 and file the same electronically.

7.2 Where a party files a form or document through Electronic Working –

(a) the form or document is not filed until it is acknowledged as received by the court, notwithstanding when it may have been sent;

(b) the defendant may file forms and documents electronically through Electronic Working out of normal court office opening hours; and

(c) a form acknowledged as received electronically out of normal court office opening hours but before midnight will be treated as having been filed the same day.

7.3 When a document is issued or filed electronically by a party an automated response will be sent to acknowledge receipt.

7.4

(1) The electronic copy must –

(a) be filed electronically by email;

(b) be formatted as one PDF document with bookmarks for each document and where appropriate with section headings within the document;

(c) not exceed such size in megabytes as Her Majesty’s Courts and Tribunals Service may from time to time specify.

(2) In the event that the bundle exceeds the maximum limit in 1(c) it shall be filed on CD Rom, DVD, or such other removable storage media as may be acceptable to Her Majesty’s Courts and Tribunals Service.

Statement of truth

8.1 Part 22 and Practice Direction 22 which requires certain documents and forms to be verified by a statement of truth shall apply to any Electronic Working forms filed electronically.

8.2 The statement of truth for documents and forms in Electronic Working must be in the form –

“[I believe][The claimant believes] that the facts stated in this claim form (or as the case may be) are true.”; or

“[I believe][The defendant believes] that the facts stated in this defence (or as the case may be) are true.”, as appropriate.

8.3 Rule 32.14, which sets out the consequences of making, or causing to be made, a false statement in a document verified by a statement of truth without an honest belief in its truth, applies to any false statement in a statement of truth in a document filed electronically.

Signature

9 Any provision of the CPR which requires a document (other than an affidavit) to be signed by any person is satisfied by that person or an authorised person typing his or her name on an electronic version of the form.

Request for judgment or issue of warrant

10.1 If, in proceedings under the Electronic Working scheme –

(1) the claimant wishes to apply for judgment in default in accordance with Part 12; or

(2) the defendant has filed or served an admission of the whole of the claim in accordance with rule 14.4,

the claimant may request judgment to be entered in default or on the admission (as the case may be) by completing and sending the electronic version of the appropriate form to the e-mail address which will be provided to the parties.

10.2 When judgment has been entered following a request under paragraph 10.1 and the claimant is entitled to the issue of a warrant of execution without requiring the permission of the court, the claimant may request the issue of a warrant of execution by –

(1) completing and sending an Electronic Working request form to the e-mail address which will be provided by the court to the parties; and

(2) paying the appropriate fee in accordance with paragraph 3.1.

10.3 A request under paragraph 10.1 or 10.2 will be treated as being filed –

(1) on the day the court acknowledges receipt of the request, if it receives it before 10 a.m. on a working day (which is any day on which the court office is open);

(2) otherwise, on the next working day after the court receives the request.

Inspecting the case record

11.1 The parties shall be entitled to inspect an electronic record of the proceedings and obtain documents in the electronic court file.

(Rule 5.4B contains provisions about the supply to a party to the proceedings of documents from the court record.)

11.2 The record of proceedings will be automatically updated.

11.3 Information concerning the availability of this facility under the Electronic Working scheme will be communicated by Her Majesty’s Courts and Tribunals Service in such manner as is deemed appropriate including the Her Majesty’s Courts and Tribunals Service website.

Applications in proceedings

12

(1) Where prior to the commencement of, or in the course of proceedings under, the Electronic Working scheme a party to those proceedings issues an application for an order electronically, whether a hearing is required or not, the party issuing the application shall lodge an application bundle with the court.

(2) The application bundle must –

(a) be filed in both paper copy and electronic format;

(b) contain the application notice and the evidence in support, including exhibits together with such other documents as may be required by any rule, practice direction, order of the court or court guide; and

(c) be filed in accordance with the time limits required by any applicable rule, practice direction, or order of the court.

(3) The electronic copy must –

(a) be filed electronically by e-mail using the multi purpose form available to the parties;

(b) be formatted as one PDF document with bookmarks as appropriate for each document and with section headings within the document;

(c) not exceed such size in megabytes as Her Majesty’s Courts and Tribunals Service may from time to time specify; and

(d) be updated as required and filed in compliance with sub-paragraphs (a) to (c).

(4) In the event that the bundle exceeds the maximum limit in 3(c) it shall be filed on CD Rom, DVD, or such other removable storage media as may be acceptable to Her Majesty’s Courts and Tribunals Service.

(5) The copy in paper format should be indexed and should correspond exactly to the electronic version of the bundle including sequential pagination.

(6) Unless the judge otherwise directs the paper copy shall be returned to the parties at the conclusion of the hearing.

Allocation and case management

13.1 Where a rule, practice direction or order of the court requires a directions questionnaire to be filed with the court and a party wishes to file the directions questionnaire electronically –

(1) the directions questionnaire together with any other forms required by a rule, practice direction, or order of the court must be filed in both paper and electronic format; and

(2) the paper copy of the directions questionnaire should be accompanied by other relevant documents including all statements of case, draft directions or case summaries and costs schedules in paper format.

13.2

(1) Where –

(a) a rule, practice direction, or order of the court requires:

(i) the court to give case management or other directions; or

(ii) a bundle to be filed with the court in connection with case management or other directions; and

(b) a party wishes to file the bundle electronically,

the bundle must contain –

(i) such documents as are required; and

(ii) in all Part 8 claims, the statements of case and evidence in support.

(2) The bundle must be filed in both paper copy and electronic format.

(3) The electronic copy must –

(a) be filed electronically by e-mail, using the multi purpose form available to the parties;

(b) be formatted as one PDF document with bookmarks for each document and where appropriate with section headings within the document;

(c) not exceed such size in megabytes as Her Majesty’s Courts and Tribunals Service may from time to time specify; and

(d) be updated as required and filed in compliance with sub-paragraphs (a) to (c).

(4) In the event that the bundle exceeds the maximum limit in 3(c) the electronic copy must be filed on CD Rom, DVD, or such other removable storage media as may be acceptable to Her Majesty’s Courts and Tribunals Service.

(5) The paper copy should be indexed and should correspond exactly with the electronic version of the bundle with sequential pagination.

(6) Unless the judge otherwise directs, the paper copy shall be returned to the parties at the conclusion of the hearing.

Trial bundles

14.1 The trial bundle must be filed with the court in paper format.

14.2 An electronic version of the trial bundle must also be filed if the court so orders, in which case it must comply with the requirements of paragraph 13.2(3) and the paper copy must comply with paragraph 13.2(5).

14.3 The court will retain any electronic copy of the trial bundle for a period of two months after judgment has been delivered, after which it may be deleted.

14.4 The time in paragraph 14.3 may be extended by order of the court at the request of a party or on the court's own initiative.

Transfer of proceedings

15.1 If proceedings under the Electronic Working scheme are subsequently transferred to a court not operating under the scheme the parties must ensure that a version of the court file in paper format is made available to that court.

15.2 If proceedings which have not been started under the Electronic Working scheme are transferred to a court operating under the scheme all subsequent steps may be taken electronically after documents in paper format in those proceedings have been converted to an electronic format pursuant to paragraph 1.2(1)(b).

Public kiosk Service

16.1 A version of the electronic court file allowing access only to those documents which are available to non-parties pursuant to rule 5.4C(1) or 5.4C(1A) and subject to rule 5.4C(4) will be made available through a public kiosk service.

(Part 5 contains provisions about access to court documents by non-parties.)

16.2 Persons wishing to obtain copies of documents available to non-parties –

(1) may select the documents they require using the computer facilities provided by the public kiosk service; and

(2) must pay the appropriate fee.

16.3 Electronic copies of the documents will be sent by e-mail to an address supplied by the person applying for copies.

Scanning documents filed in paper format

17.1 Proceedings issued after 1st April 2010 in the Admiralty and Commercial Court, the London Mercantile Court, the Technology and Construction Court, and the Chancery Division of the High Court will be stored by the court in electronic format. Any claims which are not started by issuing a claim form electronically will be converted to an electronic format by means of a scanning procedure by the court and the provisions of paragraph 1.2(1)(b) shall apply to those proceedings.

17.2 Documents which the parties wish to file with the court may be lodged either by using the Electronic Working scheme or by lodging copies in paper format.

17.3 In the event that a party lodges a document in paper format the court will –

(1) where appropriate seal the paper copy of the document;

(2) obtain payment of any fee due;

(3) enter the relevant information for the document onto an electronic equivalent to create or update an electronic working case file;

(4) convert the document to an electronic format and automatically attach this scanned copy to the electronic working case file;

(5) where the party filing has given an e-mail address, send by email to that address –

(a) a scanned image of the original document; and

(b) an electronic version of the document submitted on paper as entered onto the system by the Court; and

(6) return the sealed copy of the document originally lodged.

Annex: Electronic Working Scheme Forms

Claim forms and a Multi Purpose Form are attached for information.

All the electronic forms available for use under the scheme can be obtained from Her Majesty's Courts and Tribunals Service by:

(1) Typing in the form number required in the subject line of an email; and

(2) Sending the e-mail to getform@justice.gsi.gov.uk

Once the form has been completed it should be e-mailed to submit@justice.gsi.gov.uk

Claim Form (Chancery) (PDF - opens in new window)

Claim form (Admiralty and Commercial) (PDF - opens in new window)

Claim form (Technology and Construction) (PDF - opens in new window)

Non-Monetary Claim (PDF - opens in new window)

Multi Purpose Form (PDF - opens in new window)

The claim forms have references to the other relevant forms which are not listed here and these can also be obtained electronically.

PRACTICE DIRECTION 6B – SERVICE OUT OF THE JURISDICTION

This Practice Direction supplements Section IV of CPR Part 6

Contents of this Practice Direction

Title | Number
Scope of this Practice Direction | Para. 1.1
Service out of the jurisdiction where permission of the court is not required | Para. 2.1
Service out of the jurisdiction where permission is required | Para. 3.1
Documents to be filed under rule 6.43(2)(c) | Para. 4.1
Service in a Commonwealth State or British overseas territory | Para. 5.1
Period for responding to a claim form | Para. 6.1
Period for responding to an application notice | Para. 7.1
Annex |

Scope of this Practice Direction

1.1  This Practice Direction supplements Section IV (service of the claim form and other documents out of the jurisdiction) of Part 6.

(Practice Direction 6A contains relevant provisions supplementing rule 6.40 in relation to the method of service on a party in Scotland or Northern Ireland.)

Service out of the jurisdiction where permission of the court is not required

2.1  Where rule 6.34 applies, the claimant must file practice form N510 when filing the claim form.

Service out of the jurisdiction where permission is required

3.1  The claimant may serve a claim form out of the jurisdiction with the permission of the court under rule 6.36 where –

General Grounds

(1) A claim is made for a remedy against a person domiciled within the jurisdiction.

(2) A claim is made for an injunction(GL) ordering the defendant to do or refrain from doing an act within the jurisdiction.

(3) A claim is made against a person (‘the defendant’) on whom the claim form has been or will be served (otherwise than in reliance on this paragraph) and –

(a) there is between the claimant and the defendant a real issue which it is reasonable for the court to try; and

(b) the claimant wishes to serve the claim form on another person who is a necessary or proper party to that claim.

(4) A claim is an additional claim under Part 20 and the person to be served is a necessary or proper party to the claim or additional claim.

Claims for interim remedies

(5) A claim is made for an interim remedy under section 25(1) of the Civil Jurisdiction and Judgments Act 1982.
Claims in relation to contracts

(6) A claim is made in respect of a contract where the contract –

(a) was made within the jurisdiction;

(b) was made by or through an agent trading or residing within the jurisdiction;

(c) is governed by English law; or

(d) contains a term to the effect that the court shall have jurisdiction to determine any claim in respect of the contract.

(7) A claim is made in respect of a breach of contract committed within the jurisdiction.

(8) A claim is made for a declaration that no contract exists where, if the contract was found to exist, it would comply with the conditions set out in paragraph (6).

Claims in tort

(9) A claim is made in tort where

(a) damage was sustained within the jurisdiction; or

(b) the damage sustained resulted from an act committed within the jurisdiction.

Enforcement

(10) A claim is made to enforce any judgment or arbitral award.

Claims about property within the jurisdiction

(11) The whole subject matter of a claim relates to property located within the jurisdiction.

Claims about trusts etc.

(12) A claim is made for any remedy which might be obtained in proceedings to execute the trusts of a written instrument where –

(a) the trusts ought to be executed according to English law; and

(b) the person on whom the claim form is to be served is a trustee of the trusts.

(13) A claim is made for any remedy which might be obtained in proceedings for the administration of the estate of a person who died domiciled within the jurisdiction.

(14) A probate claim or a claim for the rectification of a will.

(15) A claim is made for a remedy against the defendant as constructive trustee where the defendant's alleged liability arises out of acts committed within the jurisdiction.

(16) A claim is made for restitution where the defendant’s alleged liability arises out of acts committed within the jurisdiction.

Claims by HM Revenue and Customs

(17) A claim is made by the Commissioners for H.M. Revenue and Customs relating to duties or taxes against a defendant not domiciled in Scotland or Northern Ireland.

Claim for costs order in favour of or against third parties

(18) A claim is made by a party to proceedings for an order that the court exercise its power under section 51 of the Senior Courts Act 1981 to make a costs order in favour of or against a person who is not a party to those proceedings.

(Rule 46.2 sets out the procedure where the court is considering whether to exercise its discretion to make a costs order in favour of or against a non-party.)

Admiralty claims

(19) A claim is –

(a) in the nature of salvage and any part of the services took place within the jurisdiction; or

(b) to enforce a claim under section 153, 154,175 or 176A of the Merchant Shipping Act 1995.

Claims under various enactments

(20) A claim is made –

(a) under an enactment which allows proceedings to be brought and those proceedings are not covered by any of the other grounds referred to in this paragraph; or

(b) under the Directive of the Council of the European Communities dated 15 March 1976 No. 76/308/EEC, where service is to be effected in a Member State of the European Union.

Documents to be filed under rule 6.43(2)(c)

4.1  A party must provide the following documents for each party to be served out of the jurisdiction –

(1) a copy of the particulars of claim if not already contained in or served with the claim form and any other relevant documents;

(2) a duplicate of the claim form, a duplicate of the particulars of claim (if not already contained in or served with the claim form), copies of any documents accompanying the claim form and copies of any other relevant documents;

(3) forms for responding to the claim; and

(4) any translation required under rule 6.45 in duplicate.

4.2  Some countries require legalisation of the document to be served and some require a formal letter of request which must be signed by the Senior Master. Any queries on this should be addressed to the Foreign Process Section (Room E02) at the Royal Courts of Justice.

Service in a Commonwealth State or British overseas territory

5.1  The judicial authorities of certain Commonwealth States which are not a party to the Hague Convention require service to be in accordance with rule 6.42(1)(b)(i) and not 6.42(3). A list of such countries can be obtained from the Foreign Process Section (Room E02) at the Royal Courts of Justice.

5.2  The list of British overseas territories is contained in Schedule 6 to the British Nationality Act 1981. For ease of reference, these are –

(a) Anguilla;

(b) Bermuda;

(c) British Antarctic Territory;

(d) British Indian Ocean Territory;

(e) British Virgin Islands;

(f) Cayman Islands;

(g) Falkland Islands;

(h) Gibraltar;

(i) Montserrat;

(j) Pitcairn, Henderson, Ducie and Oeno;

(k) St. Helena and Dependencies;

(l) South Georgia and the South Sandwich Islands;

(m) Sovereign Base Areas of Akrotiri and Dhekelia; and

(n) Turks and Caicos Islands.

Period for responding to a claim form

6.1  Where rule 6.35(5) applies, the periods within which the defendant must –

(1) file an acknowledgment of service;

(2) file or serve an admission; or

(3) file a defence,

will be calculated in accordance with paragraph 6.3, 6.4 or 6.5.

6.2  Where the court grants permission to serve a claim form out of the jurisdiction the court will determine in accordance with paragraph 6.3, 6.4 or 6.5 the periods within which the defendant must –

(1) file an acknowledgment of service;

(2) file or serve an admission; or

(3) file a defence.

(Rule 6.37(5)(a) provides that when giving permission to serve a claim form out of the jurisdiction the court will specify the period within which the defendant may respond to the claim form.)

6.3  The period for filing an acknowledgment of service under Part 10 or for filing or serving an admission under Part 14 is the number of days listed in the Table after service of the particulars of claim.

6.4  The period for filing a defence under Part 15 is –

(1) the number of days listed in the Table after service of the particulars of claim; or

(2) where the defendant has filed an acknowledgment of service, the number of days listed in the Table plus an additional 14 days after the service of the particulars of claim.

6.5  Under the State Immunity Act 1978, where a State is served, the period permitted under paragraphs 6.3 and 6.4 for filing an acknowledgment of service or defence or for filing or serving an admission does not begin to run until 2 months after the date on which the State is served.

6.6  Where particulars of claim are served out of the jurisdiction any statement as to the period for responding to the claim contained in any of the forms required by rule 7.8 to accompany the particulars of claim must specify the period prescribed under rule 6.35 or by the order permitting service out of the jurisdiction under rule 6.37(5).

Period for responding to an application notice

7.1  Where an application notice is served out of the jurisdiction, the period for responding is 7 days less than the number of days listed in the Table.

Further information

7.2  Further information concerning service out of the jurisdiction can be obtained from the Foreign Process Section, Room E02, Royal Courts of Justice, Strand, London WC2A 2LL (telephone 020 7947 6691).

TABLE

Place or country | number of days
Afghanistan | 23
Albania | 25
Algeria | 22
Andorra | 21
Angola | 22
Anguilla | 31
Antigua and Barbuda | 23
Antilles (Netherlands) | 31
Argentina | 22
Armenia | 21
Ascension Island | 31
Australia | 25
Austria | 21
Azerbaijan | 22
Azores | 23
Bahamas | 22
Bahrain | 22
Balearic Islands | 21
Bangladesh | 23
Barbados | 23
Belarus | 21
Belgium | 21
Belize | 23
Benin | 25
Bermuda | 31
Bhutan | 28
Bolivia | 23
Bosnia and Herzegovina | 21
Botswana | 23
Brazil | 22
British Virgin Islands | 31
Brunei | 25
Bulgaria | 23
Burkina Faso | 23
Burma | 23
Burundi | 22
Cambodia | 28
Cameroon | 22
Canada | 22
Canary Islands | 22
Cape Verde | 25
Caroline Islands | 31
Cayman Islands | 31
Central African Republic | 25
Chad | 25
Chile | 22
China | 24
China (Hong Kong) | 31
China (Macau) | 31
China (Taiwan) | 23
China (Tibet) | 34
Christmas Island | 27
Cocos (Keeling) Islands | 41
Colombia | 22
Comoros | 23
Congo (formerly Congo Brazzaville or French Congo) | 25
Congo (Democratic Republic) | 25
Corsica | 21
Costa Rica | 23
Croatia | 21
Cuba | 24
Cyprus | 31
Czech Republic | 21
Denmark | 21
Djibouti | 22
Dominica | 23
Dominican Republic | 23
East Timor | 25
Ecuador | 22
Egypt | 22
El Salvador | 25
Equatorial Guinea | 23
Eritrea | 22
Estonia | 21
Ethiopia | 22
Falkland Islands and Dependencies | 31
Faroe Islands | 31
Fiji | 23
Finland | 24
France | 21
French Guyana | 31
French Polynesia | 31
French West Indies | 31
Gabon | 25
Gambia | 22
Georgia | 21
Germany | 21
Ghana | 22
Gibraltar | 31
Greece | 21
Greenland | 31
Grenada | 24
Guatemala | 24
Guernsey | 21
Guinea | 22
Guinea-Bissau | 22
Guyana | 22
Haiti | 23
Holland (Netherlands) | 21
Honduras | 24
Hungary | 22
Iceland | 22
India | 23
Indonesia | 22
Iran | 22
Iraq | 22
Ireland (Republic of) | 21
Ireland (Northern) | 21
Isle of Man | 21
Israel | 22
Italy | 21
Ivory Coast | 22
Jamaica | 22
Japan | 23
Jersey | 21
Jordan | 23
Kazakhstan | 21
Kenya | 22
Kiribati | 23
Korea (North) | 28
Korea (South) | 24
Kosovo | 21
Kuwait | 22
Kyrgyzstan | 21
Laos | 30
Latvia | 21
Lebanon | 22
Lesotho | 23
Liberia | 22
Libya | 21
Liechtenstein | 21
Lithuania | 21
Luxembourg | 21
Macedonia | 21
Madagascar | 23
Madeira | 31
Malawi | 23
Malaysia | 24
Maldives | 26
Mali | 25
Malta | 21
Mariana Islands | 26
Marshall Islands | 32
Mauritania | 23
Mauritius | 22
Mexico | 23
Micronesia | 23
Moldova | 21
Monaco | 21
Mongolia | 24
Montenegro | 21
Montserrat | 31
Morocco | 22
Mozambique | 23
Namibia | 23
Nauru | 36
Nepal | 23
Netherlands | 21
Nevis | 24
New Caledonia | 31
New Zealand | 26
New Zealand Island Territories | 50
Nicaragua | 24
Niger (Republic of) | 25
Nigeria | 22
Norfolk Island | 31
Norway | 21
Oman (Sultanate of) | 22
Pakistan | 23
Palau | 23
Panama | 26
Papua New Guinea | 26
Paraguay | 22
Peru | 22
Philippines | 23
Pitcairn, Henderson, Ducie and Oeno Islands | 31
Poland | 21
Portugal | 21
Portuguese Timor | 31
Puerto Rico | 23
Qatar | 23
Reunion | 31
Romania | 22
Russia | 21
Rwanda | 23
Sabah | 23
St. Helena | 31
St. Kitts and Nevis | 24
St. Lucia | 24
St. Pierre and Miquelon | 31
St. Vincent and the Grenadines | 24
Samoa (U.S.A. Territory) (See also Western Samoa) | 30
San Marino | 21
Sao Tome and Principe | 25
Sarawak | 28
Saudi Arabia | 24
Scotland | 21
Senegal | 22
Serbia | 21
Seychelles | 22
Sierra Leone | 22
Singapore | 22
Slovakia | 21
Slovenia | 21
Society Islands (French Polynesia) | 31
Solomon Islands | 29
Somalia | 22
South Africa | 22
South Georgia (Falkland Island Dependencies) | 31
South Orkneys | 21
South Shetlands | 21
Spain | 21
Spanish Territories of North Africa | 31
Sri Lanka | 23
Sudan | 22
Surinam | 22
Swaziland | 22
Sweden | 21
Switzerland | 21
Syria | 23
Tajikistan | 21
Tanzania | 22
Thailand | 23
Togo | 22
Tonga | 30
Trinidad and Tobago | 23
Tristan Da Cunha | 31
Tunisia | 22
Turkey | 21
Turkmenistan | 21
Turks & Caicos Islands | 31
Tuvalu | 23
Uganda | 22
Ukraine | 21
United Arab Emirates | 22
United States of America | 22
Uruguay | 22
Uzbekistan | 21
Vanuatu | 29
Vatican City State | 21
Venezuela | 22
Vietnam | 28
Virgin Islands – U.S.A | 24
Wake Island | 25
Western Samoa | 34
Yemen (Republic of) | 30
Zaire | 25
Zambia | 23
Zimbabwe | 22

Annex

Service Regulation (Rule 6.41) (PDF - opens in new window)

PART 7 - HOW TO START PROCEEDINGS – THE CLAIM FORM

Contents of this Part

Where to start proceedings

7.1  Restrictions on where proceedings may be started are set out in the relevant practice directions supplementing this Part.

How to start proceedings

7.2

(1) Proceedings are started when the court issues a claim form at the request of the claimant.

(2) A claim form is issued on the date entered on the form by the court.

(A person who seeks a remedy from the court before proceedings are started or in relation to proceedings which are taking place, or will take place, in another jurisdiction must make an application under Part 23)

(Part 16 sets out what the claim form must include)

(Omitted)

(Omitted)

7.2A  Practice Direction 7A makes provision for procedures to be followed when claims are brought by or against a partnership within the jurisdiction.

Right to use one claim form to start two or more claims

7.3  A claimant may use a single claim form to start all claims which can be conveniently disposed of in the same proceedings.

Particulars of claim

7.4

(1) Particulars of claim must –

(a) be contained in or served with the claim form; or

(b) subject to paragraph (2) be served on the defendant by the claimant within 14 days after service of the claim form.

(2) Particulars of claim must be served on the defendant no later than the latest time for serving a claim form.

(Rule 7.5 sets out the latest time for serving a claim form)

(3) Where the claimant serves particulars of claim separately from the claim form in accordance with paragraph (1)(b), the claimant must, within 7 days of service on the defendant, file a copy of the particulars except where –

(a) paragraph 5.2(4) of Practice Direction 7C applies; or

(b) paragraph 6.4 of Practice Direction 7E applies.

(Part 16 sets out what the particulars of claim must include)

(Part 22 requires particulars of claim to be verified by a statement of truth)

Service of a claim form

7.5

(1) Where the claim form is served within the jurisdiction, the claimant must complete the step required by the following table in relation to the particular method of service chosen, before 12.00 midnight on the calendar day four months after the date of issue of the claim form.

(2) Where the claim form is to be served out of the jurisdiction, the claim form must be served in accordance with Section IV of Part 6 within 6 months of the date of issue.

Extension of time for serving a claim form

7.6

(1) The claimant may apply for an order extending the period for compliance with rule 7.5.

(2) The general rule is that an application to extend the time for compliance with rule 7.5 must be made –

(a) within the period specified by rule 7.5; or

(b) where an order has been made under this rule, within the period for service specified by that order.

(3) If the claimant applies for an order to extend the time for compliance after the end of the period specified by rule 7.5 or by an order made under this rule, the court may make such an order only if –

(a) the court has failed to serve the claim form; or

(b) the claimant has taken all reasonable steps to comply with rule 7.5 but has been unable to do so; and

(c) in either case, the claimant has acted promptly in making the application.

(4) An application for an order extending the time for compliance with rule 7.5 –

(a) must be supported by evidence; and

(b) may be made without notice.

Application by defendant for service of claim form

7.7

(1) Where a claim form has been issued against a defendant, but has not yet been served on him, the defendant may serve a notice on the claimant requiring him to serve the claim form or discontinue the claim within a period specified in the notice.

(2) The period specified in a notice served under paragraph (1) must be at least 14 days after service of the notice.

(3) If the claimant fails to comply with the notice, the court may, on the application of the defendant –

(a) dismiss the claim; or

(b) make any other order it thinks just.

Form for defence etc. must be served with particulars of claim

7.8

(1) When particulars of claim are served on a defendant, whether they are contained in the claim form, served with it or served subsequently, they must be accompanied by –

(a) a form for defending the claim;

(b) a form for admitting the claim; and

(c) a form for acknowledging service.

(2) Where the claimant is using the procedure set out in Part 8 (alternative procedure for claims) –

(a) paragraph (1) does not apply; and

(b) a form for acknowledging service must accompany the claim form.

Fixed date and other claims

7.9  A practice direction –

(a) may set out the circumstances in which the court may give a fixed date for a hearing when it issues a claim;

(b) may list claims in respect of which there is a specific claim form for use and set out the claim form in question; and

(c) may disapply or modify these Rules as appropriate in relation to the claims referred to in paragraphs (a) and (b).

Production Centre for claims

7.10

(1) There shall be a Production Centre for the issue of claim forms and other related matters.

(2) Practice Direction 7C makes provision for–

(a) which claimants may use the Production Centre;

(b) the type of claims which the Production Centre may issue;

(c) the functions which are to be discharged by the Production Centre;

(d) the place where the Production Centre is to be located; and

(e) other related matters.

(3) Practice Direction 7C may disapply or modify these Rules as appropriate in relation to claims issued by the Production Centre.

Human Rights

7.11

(1) A claim under section 7(1)(a) of the Human Rights Act 1998^1 in respect of a judicial act may be brought only in the High Court.

(2) Any other claim under section 7(1)(a) of that Act may be brought in any court.

Electronic issue of claims

7.12

(1) A practice direction may make provision for a claimant to start a claim by requesting the issue of a claim form electronically.

(2) The practice direction may, in particular –

(a) specify –

(i) the types of claim which may be issued electronically; and

(ii) the conditions which a claim must meet before it may be issued electronically;

(b) specify –

(i) the court where the claim will be issued; and

(ii) the circumstances in which the claim will be transferred to another court;

(c) provide for the filing of other documents electronically where a claim has been started electronically;

(d) specify the requirements that must be fulfilled for any document filed electronically; and

(e) provide how a fee payable on the filing of any document is to be paid where that document is filed electronically.

(3) The practice direction may disapply or modify these Rules as appropriate in relation to claims started electronically.

(Practice Direction 5C deals with electronic issue of claims started or continued under the Electronic Working scheme.)

Footnotes

1998 c.42. Back to text

PRACTICE DIRECTION 7A – HOW TO START PROCEEDINGS – THE CLAIM FORM

This Practice Direction supplements CPR Part 7

Contents of this Practice Direction

Title
General
Where to start proceedings
The claim form
Title of proceedings
Starting a designated money claim
Start of proceedings
Claims by and against partnerships within the jurisdiction
Partnership membership statements
Persons carrying on business in another name
Particulars of claim
Statement of Truth
Extension of time

General

1  Subject to the following provisions of this practice direction, proceedings which both the High Court and the county courts have jurisdiction to deal with may be started in the High Court or in a county court.

Where to start proceedings

2.1  Proceedings (whether for damages or for a specified sum) may not be started in the High Court unless the value of the claim is more than £25,000.

2.2  Proceedings which include a claim for damages in respect of personal injuries must not be started in the High Court unless the value of the claim is £50,000 or more (paragraph 9 of the High Court and County Courts Jurisdiction Order 1991 (S.I. 1991/724 as amended) describes how the value of a claim is to be determined).

2.3  A claim must be issued in the High Court or a county court if an enactment so requires.

2.4  Subject to paragraphs 2.1 and 2.2 above, a claim should be started in the High Court if by reason of:

(1) the financial value of the claim and the amount in dispute, and/or

(2) the complexity of the facts, legal issues, remedies or procedures involved, and/or

(3) the importance of the outcome of the claim to the public in general,

the claimant believes that the claim ought to be dealt with by a High Court judge.

(CPR Part 30 and Practice Direction 30 contain provisions relating to the transfer to the county court of proceedings started in the High Court and vice-versa.)

2.5  A claim relating to Chancery business (which includes any of the matters specified in paragraph 1 of Schedule 1 to the Senior Courts Act 1981) may, subject to any enactment, rule or practice direction, be dealt with in the High Court or in a county court. The claim form should, if issued in the High Court, be marked in the top right hand corner ‘Chancery Division’ and, if issued in the county court, be marked ‘Chancery Business’.

(For the equity jurisdiction of county courts, see section 23 of the County Courts Act 1984.)

2.6  A claim relating to any of the matters specified in sub-paragraphs (a) and (b) of paragraph 2 of Schedule 1 to the Senior Courts Act 1981 must be dealt with in the High Court and will be assigned to the Queen’s Bench Division.

2.7  Practice directions applying to particular types of proceedings, or to proceedings in particular courts, will contain provisions relating to the commencement and conduct of those proceedings.

2.8  A claim in the High Court for which a jury trial is directed will, if not already being dealt with in the Queen’s Bench Division, be transferred to that Division.

2.9  The following proceedings may not be started in a county court unless the parties have agreed otherwise in writing:

(1) a claim for damages or other remedy for libel or slander, and

(2) a claim in which the title to any toll, fair, market or franchise is in question.

2.10

(1) The normal rules apply in deciding in which court and specialist list a claim that includes issues under the Human Rights Act 1998 should be started. They also apply in deciding which procedure to use to start the claim; this Part or CPR Part 8 or CPR Part 54 (judicial review).

(2) The exception is a claim for damages in respect of a judicial act, which should be commenced in the High Court. If the claim is made in a notice of appeal then it will be dealt with according to the normal rules governing where that appeal is heard.

(A county court cannot make a declaration of incompatibility in accordance with section 4 of the Human Rights Act 1998. Legislation may direct that such a claim is to be brought before a specified tribunal)

The claim form

3.1  A claimant must use practice form N1 or practice form N208 (the Part 8 claim form) to start a claim (but see paragraphs 3.2 and 3.4 below).

3.2  Rule 7.9 deals with fixed date claims and rule 7.10 deals with the Production Centre for the issue of claims; there are separate practice directions supplementing rules 7.9 and 7.10.

3.3  If a claimant wishes the claim to proceed under Part 8, or if the claim is required to proceed under Part 8, the claim form should so state. Otherwise the claim will proceed under Part 7. But note that in respect of claims in specialist proceedings (listed in CPR Part 49) and claims brought under the RSC or CCR set out in the Schedule to the CPR (see CPR Part 50) the CPR will apply only to the extent that they are not inconsistent with the rules and practice directions that expressly apply to those claims.

3.4  Other practice directions may require special practice forms to be used to commence particular types of proceedings, or proceedings in particular courts.

3.5  Where a claim form to be served out of the jurisdiction is one which the court has power to deal with –

(a) under the Civil Jurisdiction and Judgments Act 1982; and

(b) the Judgments Regulation (which has the same meaning as in rule 6.31(d)),

the claim form must, pursuant to rule 6.34, be filed and served with the notice referred to in that rule and paragraph 2.1 of Practice Direction 6B.

3.6  If a claim for damages or for an unspecified sum is started in the High Court, the claim form must:

(1) state that the claimant expects to recover more than £25,000 (or £50,000 or more if the claim is for personal injuries) or

(2) state that some enactment provides that the claim may only be commenced in the High Court and specify that enactment or

(3) state that the claim is to be in one of the specialist High Court lists (see CPR Parts 49 and 58–62) and specify that list.

3.7  If the contents of a claim form commencing specialist proceedings comply with the requirements of the specialist list in question the claim form will also satisfy paragraph 3.6 above.

3.8  If a claim for damages for personal injuries is started in the county court, the claim form must state whether or not the claimant expects to recover more than £1000 in respect of pain, suffering and loss of amenity.

3.9  If a claim for housing disrepair which includes a claim for an order requiring repairs or other work to be carried out by the landlord is started in the county court, the claim form must state:

(1) whether or not the cost of the repairs or other work is estimated to be more than £1000, and

(2) whether or not the claimant expects to recover more than £1000 in respect of any claim for damages[1].

If either of the amounts mentioned in (1) and (2) is more than £1000, the small claims track will not be the normal track for that claim.

Title of proceedings

4.1  The claim form and every other statement of case, must be headed with the title of the proceedings. The title should state:

(1) the number of proceedings,

(2) the court or Division in which they are proceeding,

(3) the full name of each party,

(4) each party’s status in the proceedings (i.e. claimant/defendant).

(Paragraph 2.6 of Practice Direction 16 sets out what is meant by a full name in respect of each type of claimant.)

4.2  Where there is more than one claimant and/or more than one defendant, the parties should be described in the title as follows:

AB
CD
EF         Claimants

          and

GH
IJ
KL          Defendants

Starting a designated money claim

4A.1  In all designated money claims, practice form N1 must be sent to: County Court Money Claims Centre, PO Box 527. M5 0BY. The claims will then be issued in Northampton County Court.

4A.2  In proceedings referred to in paragraph 4A.1, the claimant must specify the preferred court on practice form N1.

Start of proceedings

5.1  Proceedings are started when the court issues a claim form at the request of the claimant (see rule 7.2) but where the claim form as issued was received in the court office on a date earlier than the date on which it was issued by the court, the claim is ‘brought’ for the purposes of the Limitation Act 1980 and any other relevant statute on that earlier date.

5.2  The date on which the claim form was received by the court will be recorded by a date stamp either on the claim form held on the court file or on the letter that accompanied the claim form when it was received by the court.

5.3  An enquiry as to the date on which the claim form was received by the court should be directed to a court officer.

5.4  Parties proposing to start a claim which is approaching the expiry of the limitation period should recognise the potential importance of establishing the date the claim form was received by the court and should themselves make arrangements to record the date.

5.5  Where it is sought to start proceedings against the estate of a deceased defendant where probate or letters of administration have not been granted, the claimant should issue the claim against ‘the personal representatives of A.B. deceased’. The claimant should then, before the expiry of the period for service of the claim form, apply to the court for the appointment of a person to represent the estate of the deceased.

Claims by and against partnerships within the jurisdiction

5A.1  Paragraphs 5A and 5B apply to claims that are brought by or against two or more persons who –

(1) were partners; and

(2) carried on that partnership business within the jurisdiction, at the time when the cause of action accrued.

5A.2  For the purposes of this paragraph, ‘partners’includes persons claiming to be entitled as partners and persons alleged to be partners.

5A.3  Where that partnership has a name, unless it is inappropriate to do so, claims must be brought in or against the name under which that partnership carried on business at the time the cause of action accrued.

Partnership membership statements

5B.1  In this paragraph a ‘partnership membership statement’ is a written statement of the names and last known places of residence of all the persons who were partners in the partnership at the time when the cause of action accrued, being the date specified for this purpose in accordance with paragraph 5B.3.

5B.2  If the partners are requested to provide a copy of a partnership membership statement by any party to a claim, the partners must do so within 14 days of receipt of the request.

5B.3  In that request the party seeking a copy of a partnership membership statement must specify the date when the relevant cause of action accrued.

(Signing of the acknowledgment of service in the case of a partnership is dealt with in paragraph 4.4 of Practice Direction 10)

Persons carrying on business in another name

5C.1  This paragraph applies where –

(1) a claim is brought against an individual;

(2) that individual carries on a business within the jurisdiction (even if not personally within the jurisdiction); and

(3) that business is carried on in a name other than that individual’s own name (‘the business name’).

5C.2  The claim may be brought against the business name as if it were the name of a partnership.

Particulars of claim

6.1  Where the claimant does not include the particulars of claim in the claim form, they may be served separately:

(1) either at the same time as the claim form, or

(2) within 14 days after service of the claim form provided that the service of the particulars of claim is within 4 months after the date of issue of the claim form[2] (or 6 months where the claim form is to be served out of the jurisdiction[3]).

6.2  If the particulars of claim are not included in or have not been served with the claim form, the claim form must contain a statement that particulars of claim will follow^4.

(These paragraphs do not apply where the Part 8 procedure is being used. For information on matters to be included in the claim form or the particulars of claim, see Part 16 (statements of case) and Practice Direction 16.)

Statement of Truth

7.1  Part 22 requires the claim form and, where they are not included in the claim form, the particulars of claim, to be verified by a statement of truth.

7.2  The form of the statement of truth is as follows:

‘[I believe][the claimant believes] that the facts stated in [this claim form] [these particulars of claim] are true.’

7.3  Attention is drawn to rule 32.14 which sets out the consequences of verifying a statement of case containing a false statement without an honest belief in its truth.

Extension of time

8.1  An application under rule 7.6 (for an extension of time for serving a claim form under rule 7.6(1)) must be made in accordance with Part 23 and supported by evidence.

8.2  The evidence should state:

(1) all the circumstances relied on,

(2) the date of issue of the claim,

(3) the expiry date of any rule 7.6 extension, and

(4) a full explanation as to why the claim has not been served.

(For information regarding (1) written evidence see Part 32 and Practice Direction 32 and (2) service of the claim form see Part 6 and Practice Directions 6A and 6B.)

Footnotes

See rules 16.3(4) and 26.6. Back to text
See rules 7.4(2) and 7.5(1). Back to text
See rule 7.5(2). Back to text
See rule 16.2(2). Back to text

PRACTICE DIRECTION 7B – CONSUMER CREDIT ACT 2006 – UNFAIR RELATIONSHIPS

This Practice Direction supplements CPR rule 7.9

Contents of this Practice Direction

Title
When to use the Consumer Credit Act procedure
The provisions of the Act
Restrictions on where to start some Consumer Credit Act claims
The Consumer Credit Act procedure
Powers of the court at the hearing
Matters which must be included in the particulars of claim
Admission of certain claims for recovery of goods under regulated agreements
Additional requirements about parties to the proceedings
Notice to be given to re-open a consumer credit agreement

1.1  In this practice direction ‘the Act’ means the Consumer Credit Act 1974, a section referred to by number means the section with that number in the Act, and expressions which are defined in the Act have the same meaning in this practice direction as they have in the Act.

1.2  ‘Consumer Credit Act procedure’ means the procedure set out in this practice direction.

When to use the Consumer Credit Act procedure

2.1  A claimant must use the Consumer Credit Act procedure where he makes a claim under a provision of the Act to which paragraph 3 of this practice direction applies.

2.2  Where a claimant is using the Consumer Credit Act procedure the CPR are modified to the extent that they are inconsistent with the procedure set out in this practice direction.

2.3  The court may at any stage order the claim to continue as if the claimant had not used the Consumer Credit Act procedure, and if it does so the court may give any directions it considers appropriate.

2.4  This practice direction also sets out matters which must be included in the particulars of claim in certain types of claim, and restrictions on where certain types of claim may be started.

The provisions of the Act

3.1  Subject to paragraph 3.2 and 3.3 this practice direction applies to claims made under the following provisions of the Act:

(1) section 141 (claim by the creditor to enforce regulated agreement relating to goods etc),

(2) section 129 (claim by debtor or hirer for a time order),

(3) section 90 (creditor’s claim for an order for recovery of protected goods),

(4) section 92(1) (creditor’s or owner’s claim to enter premises to take possession of goods),

(5) section 140B(2)(a) (debtor’s or surety’s application for an order relating to an unfair relationship);

(6) creditor’s or owner’s claim for a court order to enforce a regulated agreement relating to goods or money where the court order is required by –

(a) section 65(1) (improperly executed agreement),

(b) section 86(2) (death of debtor or hirer where agreement is partly secured or unsecured),

(c) section 111(2) (default notice etc not served on surety),

(d) section 124(1) or (2) (taking of a negotiable instrument in breach of terms of section 123), or

(e) section 105(7)(a) or (b) (security not expressed in writing, or improperly executed).

3.2  This practice direction does not apply to any claim made under the provisions listed in paragraph 3.1 above if that claim relates to the recovery of land.

3.3  This practice direction also does not apply to a claim made by the creditor under section 141 of the Act to enforce a regulated agreement where the agreement relates only to money. Such a claim must be started by the issue of a Part 7 claim form.

Restrictions on where to start some Consumer Credit Act claims

4.1  Where the claim includes a claim to recover goods to which a regulated hire purchase agreement or conditional sale agreement relates, it may only be started in the county court for the district in which the debtor, or one of the debtors:

(1) resides or carries on business, or

(2) resided or carried on business at the date when the defendant last made a payment under the agreement.

4.2  In any other claim to recover goods, the claim may only be started in the court for the district:

(1) in which the defendant, or one of the defendants, resides or carries on business, or

(2) in which the goods are situated.

4.3  A claim of a debtor or hirer for an order under section 129(1)(b) or 129(1)(ba) of the Act (a time order) may only be started in the court where the claimant resides or carries on business.

(Costs rule 45.1(2)(b) allows the claimant to recover fixed costs in certain circumstances where such a claim is made.)

(Paragraph 7 sets out the matters the claimant must include in his particulars of claim where he is using the Consumer Credit Act procedure.)

The Consumer Credit Act procedure

5.1  In the types of claim to which paragraph 3 applies the court will fix a hearing date on the issue of the claim form.

5.2  The particulars of claim must be served with the claim form.

5.3  Where a claimant is using the Consumer Credit Act procedure, the defendant to the claim is not required to:

(1) serve an acknowledgment of service, or

(2) file a defence, although he may choose to do so.

5.4  Where a defendant intends to defend a claim, his defence should be filed within 14 days of service of the particulars of claim. If the defendant fails to file a defence within this period, but later relies on it, the court may take such a failure into account as a factor when deciding what order to make about costs.

5.5  Part 12 (default judgment) does not apply where the claimant is using the Consumer Credit Act procedure.

5.6  Each party must be given at least 28 days’ notice of the hearing date.

5.7  Where the claimant serves the claim form, he must serve notice of the hearing date at the same time, unless the hearing date is specified in the claim form.

Powers of the court at the hearing

6.1  On the hearing date the court may dispose of the claim.

6.2  If the court does not dispose of the claim on the hearing date:

(1) if the defendant has filed a defence, the court will:

(a) allocate the claim to a track and give directions about the management of the case, or

(b) give directions to enable it to allocate the claim to a track,

(2) if the defendant has not filed a defence, the court may make any order or give any direction it considers appropriate.

6.3  Rule 26.5 (3) and (4) and rules 26.6 to 26.10 apply to the allocation of a claim under paragraph 6.2.

Matters which must be included in the particulars of claim

7.1  Where the Consumer Credit Act procedure is used, the claimant must state in his particulars of claim that the claim is a Consumer Credit Act claim.

7.2  A claimant making a claim for the delivery of goods to enforce a hire purchase agreement or conditional sale agreement which is:

(1) a regulated agreement for the recovery of goods, and

(2) let to a person other than a company or other corporation, must also state (in this order) in his particulars of claim:

(a) the date of the agreement,

(b) the parties to the agreement,

(c) the number or other identification of the agreement (with enough information to allow the debtor to identify the agreement),

(d) where the claimant was not one of the original parties to the agreement, the means by which the rights and duties of the creditor passed to him,

(e) the place where the agreement was signed by the defendant (if known),

(f) the goods claimed,

(g) the total price of the goods,

(h) the paid up sum,

(i) the unpaid balance of the total price,

(j) whether a default notice or a notice under section 76(1) or section 88(1) of the Act has been served on the defendant, and, if it has, the date and the method of service,

(k) the date on which the right to demand delivery of the goods accrued,

(l) the amount (if any) claimed as an alternative to the delivery of goods, and

(m) the amount (if any) claimed in addition to –

(i) the delivery of the goods, or

(ii) any claim under sub paragraph (l) above with the grounds of each such claim.

7.3  A claimant who is a debtor or hirer making a claim for an order under section 129(1)(b) or 129(1)(ba) of the Act (a time order) must state (in the following order) in the particulars of claim:

(1) the date of the agreement,

(2) the parties to the agreement,

(3) the number or other means of identifying the agreement,

(4) details of any sureties,

(5) if the defendant is not one of the original parties to the agreement then the name of the original party to the agreement,

(6) the names and addresses of the persons intended to be served with the claim form,

(7) the place where the claimant signed the agreement,

(8) details of the notice served by the creditor or owner giving rise to the claim for the time order,

(9) the total unpaid balance the claimant admits is due under the agreement, and –

(a) the amount of any arrears (if known), and

(b) the amount and frequency of the payments specified in the agreement,

(10) the claimant’s proposals for payments of any arrears and of future instalments together with details of his means;

(11) where the claim relates to a breach of the agreement other than for the payment of money the claimant’s proposals for remedying it.

7.3A  A claimant who is a debtor or hirer making a claim for an order under section 129(1)(ba) of the Act must attach to the particulars of claim a copy of the notice served on the creditor or owner under section 129A(1)(a) of the Act.

7.4

(1) This paragraph applies where a claimant is required to obtain a court order to enforce a regulated agreement by:

(a) section 65(1) (improperly executed agreement),

(b) section 105(7)(a) or (b) (security not expressed in writing, or improperly executed),

(c) section 111(2) (default notice etc. not served on surety),

(d) section 124(1) or (2) (taking of a negotiable instrument in breach of terms of section 123), or

(e) section 86(2) of the Act (death of debtor or hirer where agreement is partly secured or unsecured).

(2) The claimant must state in his particulars of claim what the circumstances are that require him to obtain a court order for enforcement.

Admission of certain claims for recovery of goods under regulated agreements

8.1  In a claim to recover goods to which section 90(1)^1 applies:

(1) the defendant may admit the claim, and

(2) offer terms on which a return order should be suspended under section 135(1)(b).

8.2  He may do so by filing a request in practice form N9C.

8.3  He should do so within the period for making an admission specified in rule 14.2(b). If the defendant fails to file his request within this period, and later makes such a request, the court may take the failure into account as a factor when deciding what order to make about costs.

8.4  On receipt of the admission, the court will serve a copy on the claimant.

8.5  The claimant may obtain judgment by filing a request in practice form N228.

8.6  On receipt of the request for judgment, the court will enter judgment in the terms of the defendant’s admission and offer and for costs.

8.7  If:

(1) the claimant does not accept the defendant’s admission and offer, and

(2) the defendant does not appear on the hearing date fixed when the claim form was issued,

the court may treat the defendant’s admission and offer as evidence of the facts stated in it for the purposes of sections 129(2)(a)[2] and 135(2)^3.

Additional requirements about parties to the proceedings

9.1  The court may dispense with the requirement in section 141(5) (all parties to a regulated agreement and any surety to be parties to any proceedings) in any claim relating to the regulated agreement, if:

(1) the claim form has not been served on the debtor or the surety, and

(2) the claimant either before or at the hearing makes an application (which may be made without notice) for the court to make such an order.

9.2  In a claim relating to a regulated agreement where –

(1) the claimant was not one of the original parties to the agreement, and

(2) the former creditor’s rights and duties under the agreement have passed to him by –

(a) operation of law, or

(b) assignment,

the requirement of section 141(5) (all parties to a regulated agreement and any surety to be parties to any proceedings) does not apply to the former creditor, unless the court otherwise orders.

9.3  Where a claimant who is a creditor or owner makes a claim for a court order under section 86(2) (death of debtor or hirer where agreement is partly secured or unsecured) the personal representatives of the deceased debtor or hirer must be parties to the proceedings in which the order is sought, unless no grant of representation has been made to the estate.

9.4  Where no grant of representation has been made to the estate of the deceased debtor or hirer, the claimant must make an application in accordance with Part 23 for directions about which persons (if any) are to be made parties to the claim as being affected or likely to be affected by the enforcement of the agreement.

9.5  The claimant’s application under paragraph 9.4:

(a) may be made without notice, and

(b) should be made before the claim form is issued.

Notice to be given to re-open a consumer credit agreement

10.1  Paragraph 10.2 applies where –

(1) a debtor or any surety intends to seek an order relating to an unfair relationship between a creditor and that debtor, arising out of a credit agreement (taken together with any related agreement);

(2) a claim relating to that agreement or any related agreement has already begun; and

(3) section 140B(2)(b) or section 140B(2)(c) applies.

10.2  The debtor or surety must serve written notice of intention on the court and every other party to the claim within 14 days of service of the claim form.

10.3  A debtor or surety (as the case may be) who serves a notice under paragraph 10.2 will be treated as having filed a defence for the purposes of the Consumer Credit Act procedure.

Footnotes

1. Section 90(1) provides that:

At any time when -

(a) the debtor is in breach of a regulated hire-purchase or a regulated conditional sale agreement relating to goods, and

(b) the debtor has paid to the creditor one-third or more of the total price of the goods, and

(c) the property in the goods remains in the creditor, the creditor is not entitled to recover possession of the goods from the debtor except on an order of the court.

Back to text

2. Section 129(2) provides that –

A time order shall provide for one or both of the following, as the court considers just –

(a) the payment by the debtor or hirer or any surety of any sum owed under a regulated agreement or a security by such instalments, payable at such times, as the court, having regard to the means of the debtor or hirer and any surety, considers reasonable;

(b) the remedying by the debtor or hirer of any breach of a regulated agreement (other than non-payment of money) within such period as the court may specify.

Back to text

3. Section 135(2) provides that –

The court shall not suspend the operation of a term [in an order relating to a regulated agreement] requiring the delivery up of goods by any person unless satisfied that the goods are in his possession or control.

Back to text

PRACTICE DIRECTION 8A – ALTERNATIVE PROCEDURE FOR CLAIMS

This Practice Direction supplements CPR Part 8 and Schedule 1 & Schedule 2 to the CPR

Contents of this Practice Direction

Terminology

1.1  In this Practice Direction, ‘Schedule rules’ means provisions contained in the Schedules to the CPR, which were previously contained in the Rules of the Supreme Court (1965) or the County Court Rules (1981).

Application of this Practice Direction

2.1  Section A contains general provisions about claims and applications to which Part 8 applies. Section B comprises a table listing claims, petitions and applications under various enactments which must be made under Part 8. Section C contains certain additions and modifications to the Part 8 procedure that apply to the particular claims and applications identified.

2.2  Some of the claims and applications listed in the table in Section B are dealt with in the Schedule Rules in the CPR. The table in Section B contains cross-reference to the relevant Schedule Rules.

SECTION A

GENERAL PROVISIONS APPLICABLE TO PART 8 CLAIMS

Types of claim in which the Part 8 procedure may be used

3.1  The types of claim for which the Part 8 procedure may be used include –

(1) a claim by or against a child or protected party, as defined in rule 21.1(2), which has been settled before the commencement of proceedings and the sole purpose of the claim is to obtain the approval of the court to the settlement; or

(2) a claim for provisional damages which has been settled before the commencement of proceedings and the sole purpose of the claim is to obtain a consent judgment.

3.2

(1) The Part 8 procedure must be used for those claims, petitions and applications listed in the table in Section B.

(2) Where a claim is listed in the table in Section B and is identified as a claim to which particular provisions of Section C apply, the Part 8 procedure shall apply subject to the additions and modifications set out in the relevant paragraphs in Section C.

3.3  The Part 8 procedure must also be used for any claim or application in relation to which an Act, rule or practice direction provides that the claim or application is brought by originating summons, originating motion or originating application.

3.4  Where it appears to a court officer that a claimant is using the Part 8 procedure inappropriately, he may refer the claim to a judge for the judge to consider the point.

3.5  The court may at any stage order the claim to continue as if the claimant had not used the Part 8 procedure and, if it does so, the court will allocate the claim to a track and give such directions as it considers appropriate.

Issuing the claim

4.1  Part 7 and Practice Direction 7A contain a number of rules and directions applicable to all claims, including those to which Part 8 applies. Those rules and directions should be applied where appropriate.

4.2  Where a claimant uses the Part 8 procedure, the claim form (practice form N208) should be used and must state the matters set out in rule 8.2 and, if rule 8.1(6) applies, must comply with the requirements of the rule or practice direction in question. In particular, the claim form must state that Part 8 applies; a Part 8 claim form means a claim form which so states.

Responding to the claim

5.1  The provisions of Part 15 (defence and reply) do not apply where the claim form is a Part 8 claim form.

5.2  Where a defendant who wishes to respond to a Part 8 claim form is required to file an acknowledgment of service, that acknowledgment of service should be in practice form N210.

5.3  Where a defendant objects to the use of the Part 8 procedure, and his statement of reasons includes matters of evidence, the acknowledgment of service must be verified by a statement of truth.

Managing the claim

6.1  The court may give directions immediately a Part 8 claim form is issued either on the application of a party or on its own initiative. The directions may include fixing a hearing date where –

(1) there is no dispute, such as in child and protected party settlements; or

(2) where there may be a dispute, but a hearing date could conveniently be given.

6.2  Where the court does not fix a hearing date when the claim form is issued, it will give directions for the disposal of the claim as soon as practicable after the defendant has acknowledged service of the claim form or, as the case may be, after the period for acknowledging service has expired.

6.3  Certain applications may not require a hearing.

6.4  The court may convene a directions hearing before giving directions.

Evidence

7.1  A claimant must file the written evidence on which he relies when his Part 8 claim form is issued (unless the evidence is contained in the claim form itself).

7.2  Evidence will normally be in the form of a witness statement or an affidavit but a claimant may rely on the matters set out in his claim form provided that it has been verified by a statement of truth.

(For information about (1) statements of truth see Part 22 and Practice Direction 22, and (2) written evidence see Part 32 and Practice Direction 32.)

7.3  A defendant wishing to rely on written evidence, must file it with his acknowledgment of service.

7.4  A party may apply to the court for an extension of time to serve and file evidence under rule 8.5 or for permission to serve and file additional evidence under rule 8.6(1).

(For information about applications see Part 23 and Practice Direction 23A.)

7.5

(1) The parties may, subject to the following provisions, agree in writing on an extension of time for serving and filing evidence under rule 8.5(3) or rule 8.5(5).

(2) An agreement extending time for a defendant to file evidence under rule 8.5(3)-

(a) must be filed by the defendant at the same time as he files his acknowledgement of service; and

(b) must not extend time by more than 14 days after the defendant files his acknowledgement of service.

(3) An agreement extending time for a claimant to file evidence in reply under rule 8.5(5) must not extend time to more than 28 days after service of the defendant's evidence on the claimant.

Hearing

8.1  The court may on the hearing date –

(1) proceed to hear the case and dispose of the claim;

(2) give case management directions.

8.2  Case management directions may include the specific allocation of a case to a track.

8.3  CPR rules 26.5(3) and (4) and rules 26.6 to 26.10 apply to the allocation of a claim under paragraph 8.2.

SECTION B

CLAIMS AND APPLICATIONS THAT MUST BE MADE UNDER PART 8

9.1  The claimant must use the Part 8 procedure if the claim is listed in the table below.

9.2  Section C of this Practice Direction contains special provisions modifying the Part 8 procedure, and where it does so, those provisions should be followed. The table below refers to the relevant paragraph of Section C where it applies.

9.3  Some of the claims and applications listed in the table below are dealt with in the Schedule Rules, and those rules modify the Part 8 procedure. A cross-reference to the relevant Schedule Rule is contained in the table below.

9.4  For applications that may or must be brought in the High Court, where no other rule or practice direction assigns the application to a Division of the court, the table specifies the Division to which the application is assigned.

SECTION C

SPECIAL PROVISIONS

10.1  The following special provisions apply to the applications indicated.

Applications under section 14 of the Bills of Sale Act 1878

10A.1  This paragraph applies to an application under section 14 of the Bills of Sale Act 1878 for an order to rectify an omission or mis-statement in relation to the registration, or renewal of the registration, of a bill of sale –

(1) by inserting in the register the true name, residence or occupation of a person; or

(2) by extending the time for registration of the bill of sale or an affidavit of its renewal.

10A.2  The application must be made –

(1) by claim form under Part 8; or

(2) by witness statement.

10A.3  Where the application is made by witness statement –

(1) Part 23 applies to the application;

(2) the witness statement constitutes the application notice under that Part;

(3) the witness statement does not need to be served on any other person; and

(4) the application will normally be dealt with without a hearing.

10A.4  The application must set out –

(1) the particulars of the bill of sale and of the omission or mis-statement; and

(2) the grounds on which the application is made.

10A.5  The application must be made to a Master of the Queen's Bench Division and accompanied by payment of the prescribed fee.

Applications under Section 15 of the Bills of Sale Act 1878

11.1  This paragraph applies where an application is made under section 15 of the Bills of Sale Act 1878 for an order that a memorandum of satisfaction be written on a registered copy of a bill of sale.

11.2  If the person entitled to the benefit of the bill of sale has not consented to the satisfaction, the claim form –

(1) must be served on that person; and

(2) must be supported by evidence that the debt (if any) for which the bill of sale was made has been satisfied or discharged.

11.3  If the person entitled to the benefit of the bill of sale has consented to the satisfaction, the application may be made by –

(1) claim form under Part 8; or

(2) witness statement.

11.4  Where paragraph 11.3 applies and the application is made by Part 8 claim form, the claim form –

(1) must contain details of the consent;

(2) must be supported by a witness statement by a person who witnessed the consent verifying the signature on it; and

(3) must not be served on any person other than the person entitled to the benefit of the bill of sale.

11.5  Where paragraph 11.3 applies and the application is made by witness statement –

(1) Part 23 will apply to the application;

(2) the witness statement will constitute the application notice under that Part;

(3) the witness statement does not need to be served on any other person; and

(4) the application will normally be dealt with without a hearing.

Applications under section 16 of the Bills of Sale Act 1878

11A.1  This paragraph applies to an application under section 16 of the Bills of Sale Act 1878 for a search of the bills of sale register and for a certificate of the results of the search.

11A.2  The application must be made –

(1) by claim form under Part 8; or

(2) by written request.

11A.3  The application must give sufficient information to enable the relevant bill of sale to be identified.

11A.4  The application must be made to a Master of the Queen's Bench Division and accompanied by payment of the prescribed fee.

Application under the Public Trustee Act 1906

12.1  An application under the Public Trustee Act 1906 must be made –

(1) where no proceedings have been issued, by a Part 8 claim;

(2) in existing proceedings, by a Part 23 application.

12.2  Without prejudice to sections 10(2) and 13(7) of the Public Trustee Act 1906, the jurisdiction of the High Court under the Act is exercised by a single judge of the Chancery Division sitting in private.

Applications under section 7 of the Deeds of Arrangement Act 1914

12A.1  This paragraph applies to an application under section 7 of the Deeds of Arrangement Act 1914 for an order to rectify an omission or mis-statement in relation to the registration of a deed of arrangement –

(1) by inserting in the register the true name, residence or description of a person; or

(2) by extending the time for registration.

12A.2  The application must be made –

(1) by claim form under Part 8; or

(2) by witness statement.

12A.3  Where the application is made by witness statement –

(1) Part 23 applies to the application;

(2) the witness statement constitutes the application notice under that Part;

(3) the witness statement does not need to be served on any other person; and

(4) the application will normally be dealt with without a hearing.

12A.4  The application must set out –

(1) the particulars of the deed of arrangement and of the omission or mis-statement; and

(2) the grounds on which the application is made.

12A.5  The application must be made to a Master of the Queen's Bench Division and accompanied by payment of the prescribed fee.

Application under section 2(3) of the Public Order Act 1936

13.1  The Attorney General may determine the persons who should be made defendants to an application under section 2(3) of the Public Order Act 1936.

13.2  If the court directs an inquiry under section 2(3), it may appoint the Official Solicitor to represent any interests it considers are not sufficiently represented and ought to be represented.

Proceedings under section 1 of the Railway and Canal Commission (Abolition) Act 1949

14.1  Paragraphs 15.3 to 15.14 apply, with appropriate modifications, to proceedings in which jurisdiction has been conferred on the High Court by section 1 of the Railway and Canal Commission (Abolition) Act 1949, except to the extent that –

(1) an Act;

(2) a rule;

(3) a practice direction,

provides otherwise.

Application under the Mines (Working Facilities and Support) Act 1966

15.1  In this paragraph –

(1) ‘the Act’ means the Mines (Working Facilities and Support) Act 1966;

(2) ‘the applicant’ means the person who has applied for the grant of a right under the Act.

15.2  This paragraph applies where the Secretary of State refers an application to the High Court under any provision of the Act.

15.3  The Secretary of State must –

(1) file a reference signed by him or a person authorised to sign on his behalf in the Chancery Division of the High Court;

(2) file, along with the reference, any documents and plans deposited with him by the applicant in support of his application; and

(3) within 3 days of filing the reference, give notice to the applicant that the reference has been filed.

15.4  Within 10 days of receiving the notice referred to in paragraph 15.3(3), the applicant must issue a claim form.

15.5  The claim form –

(1) must identify the application under the Act and the remedy sought; and

(2) need not be served on any other party.

15.6  Within 7 days of the claim form being issued, the applicant must –

(1) apply for the claim to be listed for a hearing before a Master; and

(2) give notice of the hearing date to the Secretary of State.

15.7  The applicant must, not less than 2 days before the date fixed for a hearing, file at court –

(1) a witness statement in support of the claim, giving details of all persons known to the applicant to be interested in, or affected by, the application; and

(2) a draft of any proposed advertisement or notice of the application.

15.8  At the hearing, the Master will –

(1) fix a date by which any notice of objection under paragraph 15.9 must be filed;

(2) fix a date for a further hearing of the claim; and

(3) give directions about –

(a) any advertisement that is to be inserted or notice of the application and hearing date that is to be given; and

(b) what persons are to be served with a copy of the application or any other document in the proceedings.

15.9  Any person who wishes to oppose the application must, within the time fixed by the court under paragraph 15.8, serve notice of objection on the applicant, stating –

(a) his name and address;

(b) the name and address of his solicitor, if any;

(c) the grounds of his objection;

(d) any alternative method for effecting the objects of the application that he alleges may be used; and

(e) the facts on which he relies.

15.10  Any document that is required to be served on the person who has given notice of objection ('the objector') may be served by posting it to the following address –

(1) where the notice of objection gives the name and address of a solicitor, to the solicitor;

(2) in any other case, to the objector at the address stated in the notice of objection.

15.11  The objector may appear, or be represented at any further hearing, and may take such part in the proceedings as the court allows.

15.12  The applicant must, not less than two days before the date set for the further hearing, file at court –

(1) any notices of objection served on him;

(2) a list of objectors, together with –

(a) their names and addresses;

(b) the names and addresses of their solicitors, if any; and

(c) a summary of their respective grounds of objection.

15.13  If the objector does not appear, or is not represented, at the further hearing –

(1) his notice of objection will have no effect; and

(2) he will not be entitled to take any further part in the proceedings unless the court orders otherwise.

15.14  At the further hearing, the court will –

(1) give directions about the future conduct of the claim, including –

(a) any further information the applicant is required to give in relation to any of the grounds or facts relied on in support of the application;

(b) any further information the objector is required to give in relation to any of the grounds or facts relied on in opposition to the application;

(c) whether the applicant may serve a reply to any notice of objection;

(d) whether any particular fact should be proved by a witness statement;

(e) whether any statements of case or points of claim or defence are to be served; and

(2) adjourn the claim for hearing before a judge.

Applications under article 10 of the Mortgaging of Aircraft Order 1972

15A.1  This paragraph applies to an application under article 10 of the Mortgaging of Aircraft Order 1972 for an order to amend the Register of Aircraft Mortgages.

15A.2  The application must be made by claim form under Part 8.

15A.3  Every person (other than the claimant) who appears in the register as mortgagor or mortgagee of the aircraft concerned must be made a defendant to the claim.

15A.4  A copy of the claim form must be sent to the Civil Aviation Authority.

15A.5  The application will be assigned to the Chancery Division.

15A.6  The Civil Aviation Authority is entitled to be heard in the proceedings.

Applications under section 344 of the Insolvency Act 1986 for registration of assignments of book debts

15B.1  This paragraph applies to an application under section 344 of the Insolvency Act 1986 to register an assignment of book debts.

15B.2  The application must be made –

(1) by claim form under Part 8; or

(2) by witness statement.

15B.3  The application must be made to a Master of the Queen’s Bench Division and accompanied by payment of the prescribed fee.

15B.4  Where the application is made by witness statement –

(1) Part 23 applies to the application;

(2) the witness statement constitutes the application notice under that Part;

(3) the witness statement does not need to be served on any other person; and

(4) the application will normally be dealt with without a hearing.

15B.5  The application –

(1) must have exhibited to it a true copy of the assignment and of every schedule to it;

(2) must set out the particulars of the assignment and the parties to it; and

(3) must verify the date and time of the execution of the assignment, and its execution in the presence of a witness.

15B.6  Upon the court being satisfied, the documents so exhibited will be filed and the particulars of the assignment and of the parties to it entered in the register.

Application under section 42 of the Senior Courts Act 1981

16.1  An application under section 42 of the Senior Courts Act 1981 is heard and determined by a Divisional Court.

16.2  The claim form must be filed at the Administrative Court and –

(1) be accompanied by a witness statement in support; and

(2) be served on the person against whom the order is sought.

Application for detailed assessment of a returning officer’s account

17.1  An application by the Secretary of State under section 30 of the Representation of the People Act 1983 for the detailed assessment of a returning officer's account must be made by claim form.

17.2  When it issues the claim form, the court will fix a date for the hearing of the detailed assessment to be dealt with if the application is granted.

17.3  The returning officer may, on the application, apply to the court to examine any claim made against him in respect of matters charged in the account.

17.4  To make an application under paragraph 17.3, the returning officer must file an application within 7 days of being served with a copy of the application for detailed assessment.

17.5  When an application is filed under paragraph 17.3, the court will –

(a) fix a date for the hearing;

(b) give notice of the hearing date to the returning officer; and

(c) serve a copy of the application and notice of hearing on the claimant.

17.6  The examination and detailed assessment may take place on the same day, provided that the examination is determined before the detailed assessment is concluded.

17.7  The district judge may hear and determine –

(a) an application for detailed assessment;

(b) any application under paragraph 17.3.

17.8  The court will serve a copy of the order made in the application on –

(a) the Secretary of State;

(b) the returning officer; and

(c) in an application under paragraph 17.3, the claimant.

Other proceedings under the Representation of the People Acts

17A.1

(1) This paragraph applies to proceedings under the Representation of the People Acts (other than proceedings under section 30 of the Representation of the People Act 1983).

(2) The jurisdiction of the High Court under those Acts in matters relating to Parliamentary and local government elections will be exercised by a Divisional Court except that –

(a) any jurisdiction, under a provision of any of those Acts, exercisable by a single judge will be exercised by a single judge;

(b) any jurisdiction, under any such provision, exercisable by a Master will be exercised by a Master; and

(c) where the court’s jurisdiction in matters relating to Parliamentary elections is exercisable by a single judge, that jurisdiction in matters relating to local government elections is also exercisable by a single judge.

Application under Mental Health Act 1983

18.1  In this paragraph –

(1) a section referred to by a number refers to the section so numbered in the Mental Health Act 1983 and ‘Part II’ means Part II of that Act;

(2) ‘hospital manager’ means the manager of a hospital as defined in section 145(1) of the Act; and

(3) ‘place of residence’ means, in relation to a patient who is receiving treatment as an in-patient in a hospital or other institution, that hospital or institution.

18.2  The claim form must be filed –

(1) in the court for the district in which the patient's place of residence is situated; or

(2) in the case of an application under section 30, in the court that made the order under section 29 which the application seeks to discharge or vary.

18.3  Where an application is made under section 29 for an order that the functions of the nearest relative of the patient are to be exercisable by some other person –

(1) the nearest relative must be made a respondent, unless –

(a) the application is made on the grounds that the patient has no nearest relative or that it is not reasonably practicable to ascertain whether he has a nearest relative; or

(b) the court orders otherwise; and

(2) the court may order that any other person shall be made a respondent.

18.4  Subject to paragraph 18.5, the court may accept as evidence of the facts relied upon in support of the application, any report made –

(1) by a medical practitioner; or

(2) by any of the following acting in the course of their official duties –

(a) a probation officer;

(b) an officer of a local authority;

(c) an officer of a voluntary body exercising statutory functions on behalf of a local authority; or

(d) an officer of a hospital manager.

18.5  The respondent must be informed of the substance of any part of the report dealing with his fitness or conduct that the court considers to be material to the determination of the claim.

18.6  An application under Part II shall be heard in private unless the court orders otherwise.

18.7  The judge may, for the purpose of determining the application, interview the patient. The interview may take place in the presence of, or separately from, the parties. The interview may be conducted elsewhere than at the court. Alternatively, the judge may direct the district judge to interview the patient and report to the judge in writing.

Applications under section 13 of the Coroners Act 1988

19.1  An application under section 13 of the Coroners Act 1988 is heard and determined by a Divisional Court.

19.2  The application must, unless made by the Attorney General, be accompanied by the Attorney General’s fiat.

19.3  The claim form must –

(1) state the grounds for the application;

(2) be filed at the Administrative Court; and

(3) be served upon all persons directly affected by the application within six weeks of the grant of the Attorney General’s fiat.

Application for injunction to prevent environmental harm or unlicensed activities

20.1  This paragraph relates to applications under –

(1) section 187B or 214A of the Town and Country Planning Act 1990;

(2) section 44A of the Planning (Listed Buildings and Conservation Areas) Act 1990;

(3) section 26AA of the Planning (Hazardous Substances) Act 1990; or

(4) section 12 or 26 of the Energy Act 2008.

20.2  An injunction may be granted under those sections against a person whose identity is unknown to the applicant.

20.3  In this paragraph, an injunction refers to an injunction under one of those sections and 'the defendant’ is the person against whom the injunction is sought.

20.4  In the claim form, the applicant must describe the defendant by reference to –

(1) a photograph;

(2) a thing belonging to or in the possession of the defendant; or

(3) any other evidence.

20.5  The description of the defendant under paragraph 20.4 must be sufficiently clear to enable the defendant to be served with the proceedings.

(The court has power under Part 6 to dispense with service or make an order permitting service by an alternative method or at an alternative place).

20.6  The application must be accompanied by a witness statement. The witness statement must state –

(1) that the applicant was unable to ascertain the defendant's identity within the time reasonably available to him;

(2) the steps taken by him to ascertain the defendant’s identity;

(3) the means by which the defendant has been described in the claim form; and

(4) that the description is the best the applicant is able to provide.

20.7  When the court issues the claim form it will –

(1) fix a date for the hearing; and

(2) prepare a notice of the hearing date for each party.

20.8  The claim form must be served not less than 21 days before the hearing date.

20.9  Where the claimant serves the claim form, he must serve notice of the hearing date at the same time, unless the hearing date is specified in the claim form.

(CPR rules 3.1(2) (a) and (b) provide for the court to extend or shorten the time for compliance with any rule or practice direction, and to adjourn or bring forward a hearing)

20.10  The court may on the hearing date –

(1) proceed to hear the case and dispose of the claim; or

(2) give case management directions.

Proceedings under the Financial Services and Markets Act 2000

21.1  This paragraph applies to proceedings in the High Court under the Financial Services and Markets Act 2000.

21.2  Proceedings in the High Court under the Act (other than applications for a mandatory order) and actions for damages for breach of a statutory duty imposed by the Act shall be assigned to the Chancery Division.

21.3  Such proceedings and actions must be begun by claim form (except for applications by petition by the Financial Conduct Authority or the Prudential Regulation Authority under section 367 of the Act).

21.4  The Financial Conduct Authority or the Prudential Regulation Authority may make representations to the court where there is a question about the meaning of any rule or other instrument made by, or with the approval or consent of, the Financial Conduct Authority or the Prudential Regulation Authority.

Application to quash certain orders, schemes, etc

22.1  This paragraph applies where the High Court has jurisdiction under any enactment, on the application of any person to quash or prohibit any –

(1) order, scheme, certificate or plan of;

(2) amendment or approval of a plan of;

(3) decision of;

(4) action on the part of,

a Minister or government department.

22.2  The jurisdiction shall be exercisable by a single judge of the Queen's Bench Division.

22.3  The claim form must be filed at the Administrative Court and served within the time limited by the relevant enactment for making the application. Practice Direction 54D applies to applications under this paragraph.

22.4  Subject to paragraph 22.6, the claim form must be served on the appropriate Minister or government department and on the person indicated in the following table.

22.5  In paragraph 22.4, ‘the appropriate Minister or government department’ means the Minister of the Crown or government department –

(1) by whom the order, scheme, certificate, plan, amendment, approval or decision in question was or may be made, authorised, confirmed, approved or given;

(2) on whose part the action in question was or may be taken.

22.6  Where the application relates to an order made under the Road Traffic Regulation Act 1984, the claim form must be served –

(1) if the order was made by a Minister of the Crown, on that Minister;

(2) if the order was made by a local authority with the consent, or following a direction, of a Minister of the Crown, on that authority and also on that Minister;

(3) in any other case, on the local authority by whom the order was made.

22.7  Evidence at the hearing of an application under this paragraph is by witness statement.

22.8  The applicant must –

(1) file a witness statement in support of the application in the Administrative Court within 14 days after service of the claim form; and

(2) serve a copy of the witness statement and of any exhibit on the respondent at the time of filing.

22.9  The respondent must –

(1) file any witness statement in opposition to the application in the Administrative Court within 21 days after service on him of the applicant's witness statement; and

(2) serve a copy of his witness statement and of any exhibit on the applicant at the time of filing.

22.10  A party must, when filing a witness statement, file a further copy of the witness statement, including exhibits, for the use of the court.

22.11  Unless the court otherwise orders, the application will not be heard earlier than 14 days after the time for filing a witness statement by the respondent has expired.

PRACTICE DIRECTION 8B – PRE-ACTION PROTOCOL FOR LOW VALUE PERSONAL INJURY CLAIMS IN ROAD TRAFFIC ACCIDENTS AND LOW VALUE PERSONAL INJURY (EMPLOYERS’ LIABILITY AND PUBLIC LIABILITY) CLAIMS – STAGE 3 PROCEDURE

This Practice Direction supplements rule 8.1(6)

Contents of this Practice Direction

Title | Number
General | Para. 1.1
Modification of Part 8 | Para. 2.1
Definitions | Para. 3.1
Types of claim in which this modified Part 8 procedure may be followed | Para. 4.1
An application to the court to determine the amount of damages | Para. 5.1
Filing and serving written evidence | Para. 6.1
Evidence – general | Para. 7.1
Acknowledgment of Service | Para. 8.1
Dismissal of the claim | Para. 9.1
Withdrawal of the protocol offer | Para. 10.1
Consideration of the claim | Para. 11.1
Settlement at Stage 2 where the claimant is a child | Para. 12.1
Settlement at Stage 3 where the claimant is a child | Para. 13.1
Adjournment | Para. 14.1
Appeals – determination on the papers | Para. 15.1
Limitation | Para. 16.1
Modification to the general rules | Para. 17.1

General

1.1  This Practice Direction sets out the procedure (‘the Stage 3 Procedure’) for a claim where –

(1) the parties –

(a) have followed the Pre-Action Protocol for Low Value Personal Injury Claims in Road Traffic Accidents (‘the RTA Protocol’) or the Pre-Action Protocol for Low Value Personal Injury (Employers’ Liability and Public Liability) Claims (“the EL/PL Protocol”); but

(b) are unable to agree the amount of damages payable at the end of Stage 2 of the relevant Protocol;

(2)

(a) the claimant is a child;

(b) a settlement has been agreed by the parties at the end of Stage 2 of the relevant Protocol; and

(c) the approval of the court is required in relation to the settlement in accordance with rule 21.10(2); or

(3) compliance with the relevant Protocol is not possible before the expiry of a limitation period and proceedings are started in accordance with paragraph 16 of this Practice Direction.

1.2  A claim under this Practice Direction must be started in a county court and will normally be heard by a district judge.

Modification of Part 8

2.1  The claim is made under the Part 8 procedure as modified by this Practice Direction and subject to paragraph 2.2.

2.2  The claim will be determined by the court on the contents of the Court Proceedings Pack. The following rules do not apply to a claim under this Practice Direction –

(1) rule 8.2A (issue of claim form without naming defendants);

(2) rule 8.3 (acknowledgment of service);

(3) rule 8.5 (filing and serving written evidence);

(4) rule 8.6 (evidence – general);

(5) rule 8.7 (part 20 claims);

(6) rule 8.8 (procedure where defendant objects to use of the Part 8 procedure); and

(7) rule 8.9(c).

Definitions

3.1  References to ‘the Court Proceedings Pack (Part A) Form’, ‘the Court Proceedings Pack (Part B) Form’ and ‘the CNF Response Form’ are references to the forms used in the Protocols.

3.2  ‘Protocol offer’ has the meaning given by rule 36.17.

3.3  ‘Settlement hearing’ means a hearing where the court considers a settlement agreed between the parties (whether before or after proceedings have started) and the claimant is a child.

3.4  ‘Stage 3 hearing’ means a final hearing to determine the amount of damages that remain in dispute between the parties.

Types of claim in which this modified Part 8 procedure may be followed

4.1  The court may at any stage order a claim that has been started under Part 7 to continue under the Part 8 procedure as modified by this Practice Direction.

An application to the court to determine the amount of damages

5.1  An application to the court to determine the amount of damages must be started by a claim form.

5.2  The claim form must state –

(1) that the claimant has followed the procedure set out in the relevant Protocol;

(2) the date when the Court Proceedings Pack (Part A and Part B) Form was sent to the defendant. (This provision does not apply where the claimant is a child and the application is for a settlement hearing);

(3) whether the claimant wants the claim to be determined by the court on the papers (except where a party is a child) or at a Stage 3 hearing;

(4) where the claimant seeks a settlement hearing or a Stage 3 hearing, the dates which the claimant requests should be avoided; and

(5) the value of the claim.

Filing and serving written evidence

6.1  The claimant must file with the claim form –

(1) the Court Proceedings Pack (Part A) Form;

(2) the Court Proceedings Pack (Part B) Form (the claimant and defendant’s final offers) in a sealed envelope. (This provision does not apply where the claimant is a child and the application is for a settlement hearing);

(3) copies of medical reports;

(4) evidence of special damages; and

(5) evidence of disbursements (for example the cost of any medical report) in accordance with rule 45.19(2).

6.2  The filing of the claim form and documents set out in paragraph 6.1 represent the start of Stage 3 for the purposes of fixed costs.

6.3  Subject to paragraph 6.5 the claimant must only file those documents in paragraph 6.1 where they have already been sent to the defendant under the relevant Protocol.

6.4  The claimant’s evidence as set out in paragraph 6.1 must be served on the defendant with the claim form.

6.5  Where the claimant is a child the claimant must also provide to the court the following in relation to a settlement made before or after the start of proceedings –

(1) the draft consent order;

(2) the advice by counsel, solicitor or other legal representative on the amount of damages; and

(3) a statement verified by a statement of truth signed by the litigation friend which confirms whether the child has recovered in accordance with the prognosis and whether there are any continuing symptoms. This statement will enable the court to decide whether to order the child to attend the settlement hearing.

6.6  Where the defendant is uninsured and the Motor Insurers’ Bureau (‘MIB’) or its agents have consented in the CNF Response Form to the MIB being joined as a defendant, the claimant must name the MIB as the second defendant and must also provide to the court a copy of the CNF Response Form completed by or on behalf of the MIB.

6.7  Where this Practice Direction requires a step to be taken by the defendant, it will be sufficient for this step to be taken by the MIB.

Evidence – general

7.1  The parties may not rely upon evidence unless –

(1) it has been served in accordance with paragraph 6.4;

(2) it has been filed in accordance with paragraph 8.2 and 11.3: or

(3) (where the court considers that it cannot properly determine the claim without it), the court orders otherwise and gives directions.

7.2  Where the court considers that –

(1) further evidence must be provided by any party; and

(2) the claim is not suitable to continue under the Stage 3 Procedure,

the court will order that the claim will continue under Part 7, allocate the claim to a track and give directions.

7.3  Where paragraph 7.2 applies the court will not allow the Stage 3 fixed costs.

Acknowledgment of Service

8.1  The defendant must file and serve an acknowledgment of service in Form N210B not more than 14 days after service of the claim form.

8.2  The defendant must file and serve with the acknowledgment of service, or as soon as possible thereafter, a certificate that is in force.

('Certificate' is defined in rule 36.15(1)(e)(i).)

8.3  The acknowledgment of service must state whether the defendant –

(1)

(a) contests the amount of damages claimed;

(b) contests the making of an order for damages;

(c) disputes the court’s jurisdiction; or

(d) objects to the use of the Stage 3 Procedure;

(2) wants the claim to be determined by the court on the papers or at a Stage 3 hearing.

8.4  Where the defendant objects to the use of the Stage 3 Procedure reasons must be given in the acknowledgment of service.

8.5  The acknowledgment of service may be signed and filed by the defendant’s insurer who may give their address as the address for service.

Dismissal of the claim

9.1  Where the defendant opposes the claim because the claimant has –

(1) not followed the procedure set out in the relevant Protocol; or

(2) filed and served additional or new evidence with the claim form that had not been provided under the relevant Protocol,

the court will dismiss the claim and the claimant may start proceedings under Part 7.

(Rule 45.24 sets out the costs consequences of failing to comply with the relevant Protocol.)

Withdrawal of the Protocol offer

10.1  A party may only withdraw a Protocol offer after proceedings have started with the court’s permission. Where the court gives permission the claim will no longer continue under the Stage 3 Procedure and the court will give directions. The court will only give permission where there is good reason for the claim not to continue under the Stage 3 Procedure.

Consideration of the claim

11.1  The court will order that damages are to be assessed –

(1) on the papers; or

(2) at a Stage 3 hearing where –

(a) the claimant so requests on the claim form;

(b) the defendant so requests in the acknowledgment of service (Form N210B); or

(c) the court so orders,

and on a date determined by the court.

11.2  The court will give the parties at least 21 days notice of the date of the determination on the papers or the date of the Stage 3 hearing.

11.3  Where further deductible amounts have accrued since the final offer was made by both parties in the Court Proceedings Pack (Part B) Form, the defendant must file an up to date certificate at least 5 days before the date of a determination on the papers.

11.4  Where the claim is determined on the papers the court will give reasons for its decision in the judgment.

(‘Deductible amount’ is defined in rule 36.15(1)(d).)

Settlement at Stage 2 where the claimant is a child

12.1  Paragraphs 12.2 to 12.5 apply where –

(1) the claimant is a child;

(2) there is a settlement at Stage 2 of the Protocol; and

(3) an application is made to the court to approve the settlement.

12.2  Where the settlement is approved at the settlement hearing the court will order the costs to be paid in accordance with rule 45.21(2).

12.3  Where the settlement is not approved at the first settlement hearing and the court orders a second settlement hearing at which the settlement is approved, the court will order the costs to be paid in accordance with rule 45.21(4) to (6).

12.4  Where the settlement is not approved at the first settlement hearing and the court orders that the claim is not suitable to be determined under the Stage 3 Procedure, the court will order costs to be paid in accordance with rule 45.23 and will give directions.

12.5  Where the settlement is not approved at the second settlement hearing the claim will no longer continue under the Stage 3 Procedure and the court will give directions.

Settlement at Stage 3 where the claimant is a child

13.1  Paragraphs 13.2 and 13.3 apply where –

(1) the claimant is a child;

(2) there is a settlement after proceedings have started under the Stage 3 Procedure; and

(3) an application is made to the court to approve the settlement.

13.2  Where the settlement is approved at the settlement hearing the court will order the costs to be paid in accordance with rule 45.22(2).

13.3  Where the settlement is not approved at the settlement hearing the court will order the claim to proceed to a Stage 3 hearing.

Adjournment

14.1  Where the court adjourns a settlement hearing or a Stage 3 hearing it may, in its discretion, order the costs to be paid in accordance with rule 45.27.

Appeals – determination on the papers

15.1  The court will not consider an application to set aside a judgment made after a determination on the papers. The judgment will state the appeal court to which an appeal lies.

Limitation

16.1  Where compliance with the relevant Protocol is not possible before the expiry of a limitation period the claimant may start proceedings in accordance with paragraph 16.2.

16.2  The claimant must –

(1) start proceedings under this Practice Direction; and

(2) state on the claim form that –

(a) the claim is for damages; and

(b) a stay of proceedings is sought in order to comply with the relevant Protocol.

16.3  The claimant must send to the defendant the claim form together with the order imposing the stay.

16.4  Where a claim is made under paragraph 16.1 the provisions in this Practice Direction, except paragraphs 1.2, 2.1, 2.2 and 16.1 to 16.6, are disapplied.

16.5  Where –

(1) a stay is granted by the court;

(2) the parties have complied with the relevant Protocol; and

(3) the claimant wishes to start the Stage 3 Procedure,

the claimant must make an application to the court to lift the stay and request directions.

16.6  Where the court orders that the stay be lifted –

(1) the provisions of this Practice Direction will apply; and

(2) the claimant must –

(a) amend the claim form in accordance with paragraph 5.2; and

(b) file the documents in paragraph 6.1.

16.7  Where, during Stage 1 or Stage 2 of the relevant Protocol –

(1) the claim no longer continues under that Protocol; and

(2) the claimant wishes to start proceedings under Part 7,

the claimant must make an application to the court to lift the stay and request directions.

Modification to the general rules

17.1  The claim will not be allocated to a track. Parts 26 to 29 do not apply.

PART 11 - DISPUTING THE COURT’S JURISDICTION

Contents of this Part

Title | Number
Procedure for disputing the court’s jurisdiction | Rule 11

Procedure for disputing the court’s jurisdiction

11

(1) A defendant who wishes to –

(a) dispute the court’s jurisdiction to try the claim; or

(b) argue that the court should not exercise its jurisdiction

may apply to the court for an order declaring that it has no such jurisdiction or should not exercise any jurisdiction which it may have.

(2) A defendant who wishes to make such an application must first file an acknowledgment of service in accordance with Part 10.

(3) A defendant who files an acknowledgment of service does not, by doing so, lose any right that he may have to dispute the court’s jurisdiction.

(4) An application under this rule must –

(a) be made within 14 days after filing an acknowledgment of service; and

(b) be supported by evidence.

(5) If the defendant –

(a) files an acknowledgment of service; and

(b) does not make such an application within the period specified in paragraph (4),

he is to be treated as having accepted that the court has jurisdiction to try the claim.

(6) An order containing a declaration that the court has no jurisdiction or will not exercise its jurisdiction may also make further provision including –

(a) setting aside the claim form;

(b) setting aside service of the claim form;

(c) discharging any order made before the claim was commenced or before the claim form was served; and

(d) staying[GL] the proceedings.

(7) If on an application under this rule the court does not make a declaration –

(a) the acknowledgment of service shall cease to have effect;

(b) the defendant may file a further acknowledgment of service within 14 days or such other period as the court may direct; and

(c) the court shall give directions as to the filing and service of the defence in a claim under Part 7 or the filing of evidence in a claim under Part 8 in the event that a further acknowledgment of service is filed.

(8) If the defendant files a further acknowledgment of service in accordance with paragraph (7)(b) he shall be treated as having accepted that the court has jurisdiction to try the claim.

(9) If a defendant makes an application under this rule, he must file and serve his written evidence in support with the application notice, but he need not before the hearing of the application file –

(a) in a Part 7 claim, a defence; or

(b) in a Part 8 claim, any other written evidence.

(10) Omitted

PRACTICE DIRECTION 12 – DEFAULT JUDGMENT

This Practice Direction supplements CPR Part 12

Contents of this Practice Direction

Title | Number
Default judgment |
Obtaining default judgment |
Default judgment by request | Para. 3.1
Evidence | Para. 4.1
General | Para. 5.1

Default judgment

1.1  A default judgment is judgment without a trial where a defendant has failed to file either:

(1) an acknowledgment of service, or

(2) a defence.

For this purpose a defence includes any document purporting to be a defence.

(See Part 10 and Practice Direction 10 for information about the acknowledgment of service, and Parts 15 and 16 and Practice Directions 15 and 16 for information about the defence and what it should contain.)

1.2  A claimant may not obtain a default judgment under Part 12 (notwithstanding that no acknowledgment of service or defence has been filed) if:

(1) the procedure set out in Part 8 (Alternative Procedure for Claims) is being used, or

(2) the claim is for delivery of goods subject to an agreement regulated by the Consumer Credit Act 1974, or

1.3  Other rules and practice directions provide that default judgment under Part 12 cannot be obtained in particular types of proceedings. Examples are:

(1) admiralty proceedings;

(2) arbitration proceedings;

(3) contentious probate proceedings;

(4) claims for provisional damages;

(5) possession claims.

Obtaining default judgment

2.1  Rules 12.4(1) and 12.9(1) describe the claims in respect of which a default judgment may be obtained by filing a request in the appropriate practice form.

2.2  A default judgment on:

(1) the claims referred to in rules 12.9(1)(b) and 12.10, and

(2) claims other than those described in rule 12.4(1),

can only be obtained if an application for default judgment is made and cannot be obtained by filing a request.

2.3  The following are some of the types of claim which require an application for a default judgment:

(1) against children and protected parties^1,

(2) for costs (other than fixed costs) only[2],

(3) by one spouse or civil partner against the other[3] on a claim in tort^4,

(4) for delivery up of goods where the defendant will not be allowed the alternative of paying their value; and

(5) Omitted.

(6) against persons or organisations who enjoy immunity from civil jurisdiction under the provisions of the International Organisations Acts 1968 and 1981.

Default judgment by request

3.1  Requests for default judgment;

(1) in respect of a claim for a specified amount of money or for the delivery of goods where the defendant will be given the alternative of paying a specified sum representing their value, or for fixed costs only, must be in Form N205A or N225, and

(2) in respect of a claim where an amount of money (including an amount representing the value of goods) is to be decided by the court, must be in Form N205B or N227.

3.2  The forms require the claimant to provide the date of birth (if known) of the defendant where the defendant is an individual.

Evidence

4.1  Both on a request and on an application for default judgment the court must be satisfied that:

(1) the particulars of claim have been served on the defendant (a certificate of service on the court file will be sufficient evidence),

(2) either the defendant has not filed an acknowledgment of service or has not filed a defence and that in either case the relevant period for doing so has expired,

(3) the defendant has not satisfied the claim, and

(4) the defendant has not returned an admission to the claimant under rule 14.4 or filed an admission with the court under rule 14.6.

4.2  On an application against a child or protected party[5]:

(1) a litigation friend^6 to act on behalf of the child or protected party must be appointed by the court before judgment can be obtained, and

(2) the claimant must satisfy the court by evidence that he is entitled to the judgment claimed.

4.3  On an application where the defendant was served with the claim either:

(1) outside the jurisdiction^7 without leave under the Civil Jurisdiction and Judgments Act 1982, or the Lugano Convention or the Judgments Regulation, or

(2) within the jurisdiction but when domiciled[8] in Scotland or Northern Ireland or in any other Convention territory^9 or Member State,

and the defendant has not acknowledged service, the evidence must establish that:

(a) the claim is one that the court has power to hear and decide,

(b) no other court has exclusive jurisdiction under the Act or the Lugano Convention or Judgments Regulation to hear and decide the claim, and

(c) the claim has been properly served in accordance with Article 20 of Schedule 1 to the Act, Article 26 of the Lugano Convention, paragraph 15 of Schedule 4 to the Act, or Article 26 of the Judgments Regulation.

4.4  On an application against a State[10] the evidence must:

(1) set out the grounds of the application,

(2) establish the facts proving that the State is excepted from the immunity conferred by section 1 of the State Immunity Act 1978,

(3) establish that the claim was sent through the Foreign and Commonwealth Office to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the State or, where the State has agreed to another form of service, that the claim was served in the manner agreed; and

(4) establish that the time for acknowledging service (which is extended to two months by section 12(2) of the Act when the claim is sent through the Foreign and Commonwealth Office to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the State) has expired.

(See rule 40.8 for when default judgment against a State takes effect.)

4.5  Evidence in support of an application referred to in paragraphs 4.3 and 4.4 above must be by affidavit.

4.6  On an application for judgment for delivery up of goods where the defendant will not be given the alternative of paying their value, the evidence must identify the goods and state where the claimant believes the goods to be situated and why their specific delivery up is sought.

General

5.1  On all applications to which this practice direction applies, other than those referred to in paragraphs 4.3 and 4.4 above[11], notice should be given in accordance with Part 23.

5.2  Where default judgment is given on a claim for a sum of money expressed in a foreign currency, the judgment should be for the amount of the foreign currency with the addition of ‘or the Sterling equivalent at the time of payment’.

Footnotes

See rule 12.10(a)(i). Back to text
See rule 12.9(b). Back to text
See rule 12.10(a)(ii). Back to text
Tort may be defined as an act or a failure to do an act which causes harm or damage to another person and which gives the other person a right to claim compensation without having to rely on a contract with the person who caused the harm or damage. Back to text
As defined in rule 21.1(2). Back to text
As defined in Practice Direction 21. Back to text
As defined in rule 2.3. Back to text
As determined in accordance with the provisions of ss.41 to 46 of the Civil Jurisdictions and Judgments Act 1982. Back to text
Means the territory of a Contracting State as defined in s.1(3) of the Civil Jurisdiction and Judgments Act 1982. Back to text
As defined in s.14 of the State Immunity Act 1978. Back to text 11. See rule 12.11(4) and (5). Back to text

PRACTICE DIRECTION 14 – ADMISSIONS

This Practice Direction supplements CPR Part 14

Contents of this Practice Direction

Admissions generally

1.1

(1) Rules 14.1, 14.1A and 14.2 deal with the manner in which a defendant may make an admission of a claim or part of a claim.

(2) Rule 14.1A makes provision about admissions made before commencement of a claim. It applies only to admissions made after 6th April 2007, and only in proceedings to which one of the following pre-action protocols apply –

(a) the pre-action protocol for personal injury claims;

(b) the pre-action protocol for the resolution of clinical disputes; or

(c) the pre-action protocol for disease and illness claims.

(The pre-action protocol for personal injury claims states that it is primarily designed for certain types of personal injury claim with a value of less than the fast track limit. But, paragraph 2.2 of the protocol indicates that it generally applies to all claims which include a claim for personal injury.)

1.2  Rules 14.3, 14.4, 14.5, 14.6 and 14.7 set out how judgment may be obtained on a written admission.

Forms

2.1  When particulars of claim are served on a defendant the forms for responding to the claim that will accompany them will include a form^1 for making an admission.

2.2  If the defendant is requesting time to pay he should complete as fully as possible the statement of means contained in the admission form, or otherwise give in writing the same details of his means as could have been given in the admission form.

Returning or filing the admission

3.1  If the defendant wishes to make an admission in respect of the whole of a claim for a specified amount of money, the admission form or other written notice of the admission should be completed and returned to the claimant within 14 days of service of the particulars of claim^2.

3.2  If the defendant wishes to make an admission in respect of a part of a claim for a specified amount of money, or in respect of a claim for an unspecified amount of money, the admission form or other written notice of admission should be completed and filed with the court within 14 days of service of the particulars of claim^3.

3.3  The defendant may also file a defence under rule 15.2.

Request for time to pay

4.1  A defendant who makes an admission in respect of a claim for a specified sum of money or offers to pay a sum of money in respect of a claim for an unspecified sum may, in the admission form, make a request for time to pay[4].

4.2  If the claimant accepts the defendant’s request, he may obtain judgment by filing a request for judgment contained in Form N225A^5; the court will then enter judgment for payment at the time and rate specified in the defendant’s request^6.

4.3  If the claimant does not accept the request for time to pay, he should file notice to that effect by completing Form N225A; the court will then enter judgment for the amount of the admission (less any payments made) at a time and rate of payment decided by the court (see rule 14.10).

Determining the rate of payment

5.1  In deciding the time and rate of payment the court will take into account:

(1) the defendant’s statement of means set out in the admission form or in any other written notice of the admission filed,

(2) the claimant’s objections to the defendant’s request set out in the claimant’s notice[7], and

(3) any other relevant factors.

5.2  The time and rate of payment may be decided:

(1) by a judge with or without a hearing, or

(2) by a court officer without a hearing provided that –

(a) the only claim is for a specified sum of money, and

(b) the amount outstanding is not more than £50,000 (including costs).

5.3  Where a decision has been made without a hearing whether by a court officer or by a judge, either party may apply for the decision to be re-determined by a judge[8].

5.4  If the decision was made by a court officer the re-determination may take place without a hearing, unless a hearing is requested in the application notice.

5.5  If the decision was made by a judge the re-determination must be made at a hearing unless the parties otherwise agree.

5.6  Rule 14.13(2) describes how to apply for a re-determination.

Varying the rate of payment

6.1  Either party may, on account of a change in circumstances since the date of the decision (or re-determination as the case may be) apply to vary the time and rate of payment of instalments still remaining unpaid.

6.2  An application to vary under paragraph 6.1 above should be made in accordance with Part 23.

Withdrawing an admission

7.1  An admission made under Part 14 may be withdrawn with the court’s permission.

7.2  In deciding whether to give permission for an admission to be withdrawn, the court will have regard to all the circumstances of the case, including –

(a) the grounds upon which the applicant seeks to withdraw the admission including whether or not new evidence has come to light which was not available at the time the admission was made;

(b) the conduct of the parties, including any conduct which led the party making the admission to do so;

(c) the prejudice that may be caused to any person if the admission is withdrawn;

(d) the prejudice that may be caused to any person if the application is refused;

(e) the stage in the proceedings at which the application to withdraw is made, in particular in relation to the date or period fixed for trial;

(f) the prospects of success (if the admission is withdrawn) of the claim or part of the claim in relation to which the offer was made; and

(g) the interests of the administration of justice.

Footnotes

Practice forms N9A (specified amount) or N9C (unspecified amount). Back to text
Rules 14.2 and 14.4. Back to text
Rules 14.2, 14.5, 14.6 and 14.7. Back to text
Rule 14.9. Back to text
Rule 14.9(4). Back to text
Rule 14.9(5) and (6). Back to text
Practice form N225A. Back to text
Rule 14.13(1). Back to text

PART 15 - DEFENCE AND REPLY

Contents of this Part

Title | Number
Part not to apply where claimant uses Part 8 procedure | Rule 15.1
Filing a defence | Rule 15.2
Consequence of not filing a defence | Rule 15.3
The period for filing a defence | Rule 15.4
Agreement extending the period for filing a defence | Rule 15.5
Service of copy of defence | Rule 15.6
Making a counterclaim | Rule 15.7
Reply to defence | Rule 15.8
No statement of case after a reply to be filed without court’s permission | Rule 15.9
Claimant’s notice where defence is that money claimed has been paid | Rule 15.10
Claim stayed if it is not defended or admitted | Rule 15.11

Part not to apply where claimant uses Part 8 procedure

15.1  This Part does not apply where the claimant uses the procedure set out in Part 8 (alternative procedure for claims).

Filing a defence

15.2  A defendant who wishes to defend all or part of a claim must file a defence.

(Part 14 contains further provisions which apply where the defendant admits a claim)

Consequence of not filing a defence

15.3  If a defendant fails to file a defence, the claimant may obtain default judgment if Part 12 allows it.

The period for filing a defence

15.4

(1) The general rule is that the period for filing a defence is –

(a) 14 days after service of the particulars of claim; or

(b) if the defendant files an acknowledgment of service under Part 10, 28 days after service of the particulars of claim.

(Rule 7.4 provides for the particulars of claim to be contained in or served with the claim form or served within 14 days of service of the claim form)

(2) The general rule is subject to the following rules –

(a) rule 6.35 (which specifies how the period for filing a defence is calculated where the claim form is served out of the jurisdiction under rule 6.32 or 6.33);

(b) rule 11 (which provides that, where the defendant makes an application disputing the court’s jurisdiction, the defendant need not file a defence before the hearing);

(c) rule 24.4(2) (which provides that, if the claimant applies for summary judgment before the defendant has filed a defence, the defendant need not file a defence before the summary judgment hearing); and

(d) rule 6.12(3) (which requires the court to specify the period for responding to the particulars of claim when it makes an order under that rule).

Agreement extending the period for filing a defence

15.5

(1) The defendant and the claimant may agree that the period for filing a defence specified in rule 15.4 shall be extended by up to 28 days.

(2) Where the defendant and the claimant agree to extend the period for filing a defence, the defendant must notify the court in writing.

Service of copy of defence

15.6  A copy of the defence must be served on every other party.

(Part 16 sets out what a defence must contain)

Making a counterclaim

15.7  Part 20 applies to a defendant who wishes to make a counterclaim.

Reply to defence

15.8  If a claimant files a reply to the defence, the claimant must

(a) file the reply with a directions questionnaire; and

(b) serve the reply on the other parties at the same time as it is filed.

(Rule 26.3(1) and (6) requires the parties to file directions questionnaires and specifies the period for doing so).

(Part 22 requires a reply to be verified by a statement of truth)

No statement of case after a reply to be filed without court’s permission

15.9  A party may not file or serve any statement of case after a reply without the permission of the court.

Claimant’s notice where defence is that money claimed has been paid

15.10

(1) Where –

(a) the only claim (apart from a claim for costs and interest) is for a specified amount of money; and

(b) the defendant states in his defence that he has paid to the claimant the amount claimed,

the court will send notice to the claimant requiring him to state in writing whether he wishes the proceedings to continue.

(2) When the claimant responds, he must serve a copy of his response on the defendant.

(3) If the claimant fails to respond under this rule within 28 days after service of the court’s notice on him the claim shall be stayed(GL).

(4) Where a claim is stayed under this rule any party may apply for the stay(GL) to be lifted.

(If the claimant files notice under this rule that he wishes the proceedings to continue, the procedure which then follows is set out in Part 26)

Claim stayed if it is not defended or admitted

15.11

(1) Where –

(a) at least 6 months have expired since the end of the period for filing a defence specified in rule 15.4;

(b) no defendant has served or filed an admission or filed a defence or counterclaim; and

(c) the claimant has not entered or applied for judgment under Part 12 (default judgment), or Part 24 (summary judgment),

the claim shall be stayed[GL].

(2) Where a claim is stayed(GL) under this rule any party may apply for the stay to be lifted.

PRACTICE DIRECTION 15 – DEFENCE AND REPLY

This Practice Direction supplements CPR Part 15

Contents of this Practice Direction

Title
Defending the claim
Statement of truth
General

Defending the claim

1.1  The provisions of Part 15 do not apply to claims in respect of which the Part 8 procedure is being used.

1.2  In relation to specialist proceedings (see CPR Part 49) in respect of which special provisions for defence and reply are made by the rules and practice directions applicable to those claims, the provisions of Part 15 apply only to the extent that they are not inconsistent with those rules and practice directions.

1.3  Form N9B (specified amount) or N9D (unspecified amount or non-money claims) may be used for the purpose of defence and is included in the response pack served on the defendant with the particulars of claim.

1.4  Attention is drawn to rule 15.3 which sets out a possible consequence of not filing a defence.

(Part 16 (statements of case) and Practice Direction 16 contain rules and directions about the contents of a defence.)

Statement of truth

2.1  Part 22 requires a defence to be verified by a statement of truth.

2.2  The form of the statement of truth is as follows:

‘[I believe][the defendant believes] that the facts stated in this defence are true.’

2.3  Attention is drawn to rule 32.14 which sets out the consequences of verifying a statement of case containing a false statement without an honest belief in its truth.

(For information about statements of truth see Part 22 and Practice Direction 22.)

General

3.1  Where a defendant to a claim serves a counterclaim under Part 20, the defence and counterclaim should normally form one document with the counterclaim following on from the defence.

3.2  Where a claimant serves a reply and a defence to counterclaim, the reply and defence to counterclaim should normally form one document with the defence to counterclaim following on from the reply.

3.2A  Rule 15.8(a) provides that a claimant must file any reply with his directions questionnaire. Where the date by which he must file his directions questionnaire is later than the date by which he must file his defence to counterclaim (because the time for filing the directions questionnaire under rule 26.3(6) is more than 14 days (small claims track) or more than 28 days (fast track and multi-track) after the date on which it is deemed to be served), the court will normally order that the defence to counterclaim must be filed by the same date as the reply. Where the court does not make such an order the reply and defence to counterclaim may form separate documents.

3.3  Where a claim has been stayed under rules 15.10(3) or 15.11(1) any party may apply for the stay to be lifted[1].

3.4  The application should be made in accordance with Part 23 and should give the reason for the applicant’s delay in proceeding with or responding to the claim.

Footnotes

Rules 15.10(4) and 15.11(2). Back to text

PART 16 - STATEMENTS OF CASE

Contents of this Part

Title | Number
Part not to apply where claimant uses Part 8 procedure | Rule 16.1
Contents of the claim form | Rule 16.2
Statement of value to be included in the claim form | Rule 16.3
Contents of the particulars of claim | Rule 16.4
Content of defence | Rule 16.5
Defence of set-off | Rule 16.6
Reply to defence | Rule 16.7
Court’s power to dispense with statements of case | Rule 16.8

Part not to apply where claimant uses Part 8 procedure

16.1  This Part does not apply where the claimant uses the procedure set out in Part 8 (alternative procedure for claims).

Contents of the claim form

16.2

(1) The claim form must –

(a) contain a concise statement of the nature of the claim;

(b) specify the remedy which the claimant seeks;

(c) where the claimant is making a claim for money, contain a statement of value in accordance with rule 16.3;

(cc) where the claimant’s only claim is for a specified sum, contain a statement of the interest accrued on that sum; and

(d) contain such other matters as may be set out in a practice direction.

(1A) In civil proceedings against the Crown, as defined in rule 66.1(2), the claim form must also contain –

(a) the names of the government departments and officers of the Crown concerned; and

(b) brief details of the circumstances in which it is alleged that the liability of the Crown arose.

(2) If the particulars of claim specified in rule 16.4 are not contained in, or are not served with the claim form, the claimant must state on the claim form that the particulars of claim will follow.

(3) If the claimant is claiming in a representative capacity, the claim form must state what that capacity is.

(4) If the defendant is sued in a representative capacity, the claim form must state what that capacity is.

(5) The court may grant any remedy to which the claimant is entitled even if that remedy is not specified in the claim form.

(Part 22 requires a claim form to be verified by a statement of truth)

Statement of value to be included in the claim form

16.3

(1) This rule applies where the claimant is making a claim for money.

(2) The claimant must, in the claim form, state –

(a) the amount of money claimed;

(b) that the claimant expects to recover –

(i) not more than £10,000;

(ii) more than £10,000 but not more than £25,000; or

(iii) more than £25,000; or

(c) that the claimant cannot say how much is likely to be recovered.

(3) In a claim for personal injuries, the claimant must also state in the claim form whether the amount which the claimant expects to recover as general damages for pain, suffering and loss of amenity is –

(a) not more than £1,000; or

(b) more than £1,000.

(4) In a claim which includes a claim by a tenant of residential premises against a landlord where the tenant is seeking an order requiring the landlord to carry out repairs or other work to the premises, the claimant must also state in the claim form –

(a) whether the estimated costs of those repairs or other work is –

(i) not more than £1,000; or

(ii) more than £1,000; and

(b) whether the value of any other claim for damages is –

(i) not more than £1,000; or

(ii) more than £1,000.

(5) If the claim form is to be issued in the High Court it must, where this rule applies –

(a) state that the claimant expects to recover more than £25,000;

(b) state that some other enactment provides that the claim may be commenced only in the High Court and specify that enactment;

(c) if the claim is a claim for personal injuries state that the claimant expects to recover £50,000 or more; or

(d) state that the claim is to be in one of the specialist High Court lists and state which list.

(6) When calculating how much the claimant expects to recover, the claimant must disregard any possibility –

(a) that the court may make an award of –

(i) interest;

(ii) costs;

(b) that the court may make a finding of contributory negligence;

(c) that the defendant may make a counterclaim or that the defence may include a set-off; or

(d) that the defendant may be liable to pay an amount of money which the court awards to the claimant to the Secretary of State for Social Security under section 6 of the Social Security (Recovery of Benefits) Act 1997 ^1.

(7) The statement of value in the claim form does not limit the power of the court to give judgment for the amount which it finds the claimant is entitled to.

Contents of the particulars of claim

16.4

(1) Particulars of claim must include –

(a) a concise statement of the facts on which the claimant relies;

(b) if the claimant is seeking interest, a statement to that effect and the details set out in paragraph (2);

(c) if the claimant is seeking aggravated damages[GL] or exemplary damages(GL), a statement to that effect and his grounds for claiming them;

(d) if the claimant is seeking provisional damages, a statement to that effect and his grounds for claiming them; and

(e) such other matters as may be set out in a practice direction.

(2) If the claimant is seeking interest he must –

(a) state whether he is doing so –

(i) under the terms of a contract;

(ii) under an enactment and if so which; or

(iii) on some other basis and if so what that basis is; and

(b) if the claim is for a specified amount of money, state –

(i) the percentage rate at which interest is claimed;

(ii) the date from which it is claimed;

(iii) the date to which it is calculated, which must not be later than the date on which the claim form is issued;

(iv) the total amount of interest claimed to the date of calculation; and

(v) the daily rate at which interest accrues after that date.

(Part 22 requires particulars of claim to be verified by a statement of truth)

Content of defence

16.5

(1) In his defence, the defendant must state –

(a) which of the allegations in the particulars of claim he denies;

(b) which allegations he is unable to admit or deny, but which he requires the claimant to prove; and

(c) which allegations he admits.

(2) Where the defendant denies an allegation –

(a) he must state his reasons for doing so; and

(b) if he intends to put forward a different version of events from that given by the claimant, he must state his own version.

(3) A defendant who –

(a) fails to deal with an allegation; but

(b) has set out in his defence the nature of his case in relation to the issue to which that allegation is relevant,

shall be taken to require that allegation to be proved.

(4) Where the claim includes a money claim, a defendant shall be taken to require that any allegation relating to the amount of money claimed be proved unless he expressly admits the allegation.

(5) Subject to paragraphs (3) and (4), a defendant who fails to deal with an allegation shall be taken to admit that allegation.

(6) If the defendant disputes the claimant’s statement of value under rule 16.3 he must –

(a) state why he disputes it; and

(b) if he is able, give his own statement of the value of the claim.

(7) If the defendant is defending in a representative capacity, he must state what that capacity is.

(8) If the defendant has not filed an acknowledgment of service under Part 10, the defendant must give an address for service.

(Part 22 requires a defence to be verified by a statement of truth)

(Rule 6.23 makes provision in relation to addresses for service.)

Defence of set-off

16.6  Where a defendant –

(a) contends he is entitled to money from the claimant; and

(b) relies on this as a defence to the whole or part of the claim,

the contention may be included in the defence and set off against the claim, whether or not it is also a Part 20 claim.

Reply to defence

16.7

(1) A claimant who does not file a reply to the defence shall not be taken to admit the matters raised in the defence.

(2) A claimant who –

(a) files a reply to a defence; but

(b) fails to deal with a matter raised in the defence, shall be taken to require that matter to be proved.

(Part 22 requires a reply to be verified by a statement of truth)

Court’s power to dispense with statements of case

16.8  If a claim form has been –

(a) issued in accordance with rule 7.2; and

(b) served in accordance with rule 7.5,

the court may make an order that the claim will continue without any other statement of case.

Footnotes

1. 1997 c.27. Back to text

PART 17 - AMENDMENTS TO STATEMENTS OF CASE

Contents of this Part

Amendments to statements of case

17.1

(1) A party may amend his statement of case at any time before it has been served on any other party.

(2) If his statement of case has been served, a party may amend it only –

(a) with the written consent of all the other parties; or

(b) with the permission of the court.

(3) If a statement of case has been served, an application to amend it by removing, adding or substituting a party must be made in accordance with rule 19.4.

(Part 22 requires amendments to a statement of case to be verified by a statement of truth unless the court orders otherwise)

Power of court to disallow amendments made without permission

17.2

(1) If a party has amended his statement of case where permission of the court was not required, the court may disallow the amendment.

(2) A party may apply to the court for an order under paragraph (1) within 14 days of service of a copy of the amended statement of case on him.

Amendments to statements of case with the permission of the court

17.3

(1) Where the court gives permission for a party to amend his statement of case, it may give directions as to –

(a) amendments to be made to any other statement of case; and

(b) service of any amended statement of case.

(2) The power of the court to give permission under this rule is subject to –

(a) rule 19.1 (change of parties – general);

(b) rule 19.4 (special provisions about adding or substituting parties after the end of a relevant limitation period(GL)); and

(c) rule 17.4 (amendments of statement of case after the end of a relevant limitation period).

Amendments to statements of case after the end of a relevant limitation period

17.4

(1) This rule applies where –

(a) a party applies to amend his statement of case in one of the ways mentioned in this rule; and

(b) a period of limitation has expired under –

(i) the Limitation Act 1980^1;

(ii) the Foreign Limitation Periods Act 1984[2]; or

(iii) any other enactment which allows such an amendment, or under which such an amendment is allowed.

(2) The court may allow an amendment whose effect will be to add or substitute a new claim, but only if the new claim arises out of the same facts or substantially the same facts as a claim in respect of which the party applying for permission has already claimed a remedy in the proceedings.

(3) The court may allow an amendment to correct a mistake as to the name of a party, but only where the mistake was genuine and not one which would cause reasonable doubt as to the identity of the party in question.

(4) The court may allow an amendment to alter the capacity in which a party claims if the new capacity is one which that party had when the proceedings started or has since acquired.

(Rule 19.5 specifies the circumstances in which the court may allow a new party to be added or substituted after the end of a relevant limitation period[GL])

Footnotes

1980 c.58. Back to text
1984 c.16. Back to text

PRACTICE DIRECTION 18 – FURTHER INFORMATION

This Practice Direction supplements CPR Part 18

Contents of this Practice Direction

Title
Preliminary Request for further information or clarification
Responding to a Request
Statements of truth
General matters
Applications for Orders under Part 18

Attention is also drawn to Part 22 (Statements of Truth).

Preliminary Request for further information or clarification

1.1  Before making an application to the court for an order under Part 18, the party seeking clarification or information (the first party) should first serve on the party from whom it is sought (the second party) a written request for that clarification or information (a Request) stating a date by which the response to the Request should be served. The date must allow the second party a reasonable time to respond.

1.2  A Request should be concise and strictly confined to matters which are reasonably necessary and proportionate to enable the first party to prepare his own case or to understand the case he has to meet.

1.3  Requests must be made as far as possible in a single comprehensive document and not piecemeal.

1.4  A Request may be made by letter if the text of the Request is brief and the reply is likely to be brief; otherwise the Request should be made in a separate document.

1.5  If a Request is made in a letter, the letter should, in order to distinguish it from any other that might routinely be written in the course of a case,

(1) state that it contains a Request made under Part 18, and

(2) deal with no matters other than the Request.

1.6

(1) A Request (whether made by letter or in a separate document) must –

(a) be headed with the name of the court and the title and number of the claim,

(b) in its heading state that it is a Request made under Part 18, identify the first party and the second party and state the date on which it is made,

(c) set out in a separate numbered paragraph each request for information or clarification,

(d) where a Request relates to a document, identify that document and (if relevant) the paragraph or words to which it relates,

(e) state the date by which the first party expects a response to the Request.

(2)

(a) A Request which is not in the form of a letter may, if convenient, be prepared in such a way that the response may be given on the same document.

(b) To do this the numbered paragraphs of the Request should appear on the left hand half of each sheet so that the paragraphs of the response may then appear on the right.

(c) Where a Request is prepared in this form an extra copy should be served for the use of the second party.

1.7  Subject to the provisions of rule 6.23(5) and (6) and paragraphs 4.1 to 4.3 of Practice Direction 6A, a request should be served by e-mail if reasonably practicable.

Responding to a Request

2.1  A response to a Request must be in writing, dated and signed by the second party or his legal representative.

2.2

(1) Where the Request is made in a letter the second party may give his response in a letter or in a formal reply.

(2) Such a letter should identify itself as a response to the Request and deal with no other matters than the response.

2.3

(1) Unless the Request is in the format described in paragraph 1.6(2) and the second party uses the document supplied for the purpose, a response must:

(a) be headed with the name of the court and the title and number of the claim,

(b) in its heading identify itself as a response to that Request,

(c) repeat the text of each separate paragraph of the Request and set out under each paragraph the response to it,

(d) refer to and have attached to it a copy of any document not already in the possession of the first party which forms part of the response.

(2) A second or supplementary response to a Request must identify itself as such in its heading.

2.4

The second party must when he serves his response on the first party serve on every other party and file with the court a copy of the Request and of his response.

Statements of Truth

3  Attention is drawn to Part 22 and to the definition of a statement of case in Part 2 of the rules; a response should be verified by a statement of truth.

General matters

4.1

(1) If the second party objects to complying with the Request or part of it or is unable to do so at all or within the time stated in the Request he must inform the first party promptly and in any event within that time.

(2) He may do so in a letter or in a separate document (a formal response), but in either case he must give reasons and, where relevant, give a date by which he expects to be able to comply.

4.2

(1) There is no need for a second party to apply to the court if he objects to a Request or is unable to comply with it at all or within the stated time. He need only comply with paragraph 4.1(1) above.

(2) Where a second party considers that a Request can only be complied with at disproportionate expense and objects to comply for that reason he should say so in his reply and explain briefly why he has taken that view.

Applications for Orders under Part 18

5.1  Attention is drawn to Part 23 (Applications) and to Practice Direction 23A.

5.2  An application notice for an order under Part 18 should set out or have attached to it the text of the order sought and in particular should specify the matter or matters in respect of which the clarification or information is sought.

5.3

(1) If a Request under paragraph 1 for the information or clarification has not been made, the application notice should, in addition, explain why not.

(2) If a Request for clarification or information has been made, the application notice or the evidence in support should describe the response, if any.

5.4  Both the first party and the second party should consider whether evidence in support of or in opposition to the application is required.

5.5

(1) Where the second party has made no response to a Request served on him, the first party need not serve the application notice on the second party, and the court may deal with the application without a hearing.

(2) Sub-paragraph (1) above only applies if at least 14 days have passed since the Request was served and the time stated in it for a response has expired.

5.6

Unless paragraph 5.5 applies the application notice must be served on the second party and on all other parties to the claim.

5.7  An order made under Part 18 must be served on all parties to the claim.

5.8  Costs:

(1) Attention is drawn to the Practice Directions 44 to 48 on costs and, in particular, Subsections 8 and 9 of Practice Direction 44, which relate to the court’s power to make a summary assessment of costs.

(2) Attention is also drawn to rule 44.10(1) which provides that the general rule is that if an order does not mention costs no party is entitled to costs relating to that order.

PART 19 - PARTIES AND GROUP LITIGATION

Contents of this Part

Title | Number
Parties – general | Rule 19.1
I ADDITION AND SUBSTITUTION OF PARTIES |
Change of parties – general | Rule 19.2
Provisions applicable where two or more persons are jointly entitled to a remedy | Rule 19.3
Procedure for adding and substituting parties | Rule 19.4
Human Rights | Rule 19.4A
Special provisions about adding or substituting parties after the end of a relevant limitation period | Rule 19.5
Special rules about parties in claims for wrongful interference with goods | Rule 19.5A
II REPRESENTATIVE PARTIES |
Representative parties with same interest | Rule 19.6
Representation of interested persons who cannot be ascertained etc. | Rule 19.7
Representation of beneficiaries by trustees etc. | Rule 19.7A
Postal Services Act 2000 (c.26) | Rule 19.7B
Death | Rule 19.8
Power to make judgements binding on non-parties | Rule 19.8A
Derivative claims – how started | Rule 19.9
Derivative claims under Chapter 1 of Part 11 of the Companies Act 2006 – application for permission | Rule 19.9A
Derivative claims under Chapter 1 of Part 11 of the Companies Act 2006 – members of companies taking over claims by companies or other members | Rule 19.9B
Derivative claims – other bodies corporate and trade unions | Rule 19.9C
Derivative claims arising in the course of other proceedings | Rule 19.9D
Derivative claims – costs | Rule 19.9E
Derivative claims – discontinuance and settlement | Rule 19.9F
III GROUP LITIGATION |
Definition | Rule 19.10
Group Litigation Order | Rule 19.11
Effect of the GLO | Rule 19.12
Case management | Rule 19.13
Removal from the register | Rule 19.14
Test claims | Rule 19.15

Parties – general

19.1  Any number of claimants or defendants may be joined as parties to a claim.

I ADDITION AND SUBSTITUTION OF PARTIES

Change of parties – general

19.2

(1) This rule applies where a party is to be added or substituted except where the case falls within rule 19.5 (special provisions about changing parties after the end of a relevant limitation period[GL]).

(2) The court may order a person to be added as a new party if –

(a) it is desirable to add the new party so that the court can resolve all the matters in dispute in the proceedings; or

(b) there is an issue involving the new party and an existing party which is connected to the matters in dispute in the proceedings, and it is desirable to add the new party so that the court can resolve that issue.

(3) The court may order any person to cease to be a party if it is not desirable for that person to be a party to the proceedings.

(4) The court may order a new party to be substituted for an existing one if –

(a) the existing party’s interest or liability has passed to the new party; and

(b) it is desirable to substitute the new party so that the court can resolve the matters in dispute in the proceedings.

Provisions applicable where two or more persons are jointly entitled to a remedy

19.3

(1) Where a claimant claims a remedy to which some other person is jointly entitled with him, all persons jointly entitled to the remedy must be parties unless the court orders otherwise.

(2) If any person does not agree to be a claimant, he must be made a defendant, unless the court orders otherwise.

(3) This rule does not apply in probate proceedings.

Procedure for adding and substituting parties

19.4

(1) The court’s permission is required to remove, add or substitute a party, unless the claim form has not been served.

(2) An application for permission under paragraph (1) may be made by –

(a) an existing party; or

(b) a person who wishes to become a party.

(3) An application for an order under rule 19.2(4) (substitution of a new party where existing party’s interest or liability has passed) –

(a) may be made without notice; and

(b) must be supported by evidence.

(4) Nobody may be added or substituted as a claimant unless –

(a) he has given his consent in writing; and

(b) that consent has been filed with the court.

(4A) The Commissioners for HM Revenue and Customs may be added as a party to proceedings only if they consent in writing.

(5) An order for the removal, addition or substitution of a party must be served on –

(a) all parties to the proceedings; and

(b) any other person affected by the order.

(6) When the court makes an order for the removal, addition or substitution of a party, it may give consequential directions about –

(a) filing and serving the claim form on any new defendant;

(b) serving relevant documents on the new party; and

(c) the management of the proceedings.

Human Rights

19.4A  Section 4 of the Human Rights Act 1998

(1) The court may not make a declaration of incompatibility in accordance with section 4 of the Human Rights Act 1998 unless 21 days’ notice, or such other period of notice as the court directs, has been given to the Crown.

(2) Where notice has been given to the Crown a Minister, or other person permitted by that Act, shall be joined as a party on giving notice to the court.

(Only courts specified in section 4 of the Human Rights Act 1998 can make a declaration of incompatibility)

Section 9 of the Human Rights Act 1998

(3) Where a claim is made under that Act for damages in respect of a judicial act –

(a) that claim must be set out in the statement of case or the appeal notice; and

(b) notice must be given to the Crown.

(4) Where paragraph (3) applies and the appropriate person has not applied to be joined as a party within 21 days, or such other period as the court directs, after the notice is served, the court may join the appropriate person as a party.

(Practice Direction 19A makes provision for these notices)

Special provisions about adding or substituting parties after the end of a relevant limitation period

19.5

(1) This rule applies to a change of parties after the end of a period of limitation under –

(a) the Limitation Act 1980^1;

(b) the Foreign Limitation Periods Act 1984[2]; or

(c) any other enactment which allows such a change, or under which such a change is allowed.

(2) The court may add or substitute a party only if –

(a) the relevant limitation period[GL] was current when the proceedings were started; and

(b) the addition or substitution is necessary.

(3) The addition or substitution of a party is necessary only if the court is satisfied that –

(a) the new party is to be substituted for a party who was named in the claim form in mistake for the new party;

(b) the claim cannot properly be carried on by or against the original party unless the new party is added or substituted as claimant or defendant; or

(c) the original party has died or had a bankruptcy order made against him and his interest or liability has passed to the new party.

(4) In addition, in a claim for personal injuries the court may add or substitute a party where it directs that –

(a)

(i) section 11 (special time limit for claims for personal injuries); or

(ii) section 12 (special time limit for claims under fatal accidents legislation), of the Limitation Act 1980 shall not apply to the claim by or against the new party; or

(b) the issue of whether those sections apply shall be determined at trial.

(Rule 17.4 deals with other changes after the end of a relevant limitation period[GL])

Special rules about parties in claims for wrongful interference with goods

19.5A

(1) A claimant in a claim for wrongful interference with goods must, in the particulars of claim, state the name and address of every person who, to his knowledge, has or claims an interest in the goods and who is not a party to the claim.

(2) A defendant to a claim for wrongful interference with goods may apply for a direction that another person be made a party to the claim to establish whether the other person –

(a) has a better right to the goods than the claimant; or

(b) has a claim which might render the defendant doubly liable under section 7 of the Torts (Interference with Goods) Act 1977(a).

(3) Where the person referred to in paragraph (2) fails to attend the hearing of the application, or comply with any directions, the court may order that he is deprived of any claim against the defendant in respect of the goods.

(Rule 3.1(3) provides that the court may make an order subject to conditions)

(4) The application notice must be served on all parties and on the person referred to in paragraph (2).

II REPRESENTATIVE PARTIES

Representative parties with same interest

19.6

(1) Where more than one person has the same interest in a claim –

(a) the claim may be begun; or

(b) the court may order that the claim be continued,

by or against one or more of the persons who have the same interest as representatives of any other persons who have that interest.

(2) The court may direct that a person may not act as a representative.

(3) Any party may apply to the court for an order under paragraph (2).

(4) Unless the court otherwise directs any judgment or order given in a claim in which a party is acting as a representative under this rule –

(a) is binding on all persons represented in the claim; but

(b) may only be enforced by or against a person who is not a party to the claim with the permission of the court.

(5) This rule does not apply to a claim to which rule 19.7 applies.

Representation of interested persons who cannot be ascertained etc.

19.7

(1) This rule applies to claims about –

(a) the estate of a deceased person;

(b) property subject to a trust; or

(c) the meaning of a document, including a statute.

(2) The court may make an order appointing a person to represent any other person or persons in the claim where the person or persons to be represented –

(a) are unborn;

(b) cannot be found;

(c) cannot easily be ascertained; or

(d) are a class of persons who have the same interest in a claim and –

(i) one or more members of that class are within sub-paragraphs (a), (b) or (c); or

(ii) to appoint a representative would further the overriding objective.

(3) An application for an order under paragraph (2) –

(a) may be made by –

(i) any person who seeks to be appointed under the order; or

(ii) any party to the claim; and

(b) may be made at any time before or after the claim has started.

(4) An application notice for an order under paragraph (2) must be served on –

(a) all parties to the claim, if the claim has started;

(b) the person sought to be appointed, if that person is not the applicant or a party to the claim; and

(c) any other person as directed by the court.

(5) The court’s approval is required to settle a claim in which a party is acting as a representative under this rule.

(6) The court may approve a settlement where it is satisfied that the settlement is for the benefit of all the represented persons.

(7) Unless the court otherwise directs, any judgment or order given in a claim in which a party is acting as a representative under this rule –

(a) is binding on all persons represented in the claim; but

(b) may only be enforced by or against a person who is not a party to the claim with the permission of the court.

Representation of beneficiaries by trustees etc.

19.7A

(1) A claim may be brought by or against trustees, executors or administrators in that capacity without adding as parties any persons who have a beneficial interest in the trust or estate (‘the beneficiaries’).

(2) Any judgment or order given or made in the claim is binding on the beneficiaries unless the court orders otherwise in the same or other proceedings.

Postal Services Act 2000 (c.26)

19.7B

(1) An application under section 92 of the Postal Services Act 2000 for permission to bring proceedings in the name of the sender or addressee of a postal packet or his personal representative is made in accordance with Part 8.

(2) A copy of the application notice must be served on the universal service provider and on the person in whose name the applicant seeks to bring the proceedings.

Death

19.8

(1) Where a person who had an interest in a claim has died and that person has no personal representative the court may order –

(a) the claim to proceed in the absence of a person representing the estate of the deceased; or

(b) a person to be appointed to represent the estate of the deceased.

(2) Where a defendant against whom a claim could have been brought has died and –

(a) a grant of probate or administration has been made, the claim must be brought against the persons who are the personal representatives of the deceased;

(b) a grant of probate or administration has not been made –

(i) the claim must be brought against ‘the estate of’ the deceased; and

(ii) the claimant must apply to the court for an order appointing a person to represent the estate of the deceased in the claim.

(3) A claim shall be treated as having been brought against ‘the estate of’ the deceased in accordance with paragraph (2)(b)(i) where –

(a) the claim is brought against the ‘personal representatives’ of the deceased but a grant of probate or administration has not been made; or

(b) the person against whom the claim was brought was dead when the claim was started.

(4) Before making an order under this rule, the court may direct notice of the application to be given to any other person with an interest in the claim.

(5) Where an order has been made under paragraphs (1) or (2)(b)(ii) any judgment or order made or given in the claim is binding on the estate of the deceased.

Power to make judgements binding on non-parties

19.8A

(1) This rule applies to any claim relating to –

(a) the estate of a deceased person;

(b) property subject to a trust; or

(c) the sale of any property.

(2) The court may at any time direct that notice of –

(a) the claim; or

(b) any judgment or order given in the claim,

be served on any person who is not a party but who is or may be affected by it.

(3) An application under this rule –

(a) may be made without notice; and

(b) must be supported by written evidence which includes the reasons why the person to be served should be bound by the judgment in the claim.

(4) Unless the court orders otherwise –

(a) a notice of a claim or of a judgment or order under this rule must be –

(i) in the form required by the practice direction;

(ii) issued by the court; and

(iii) accompanied by a form of acknowledgment of service with any necessary modifications;

(b) a notice of a claim must also be accompanied by –

(i) a copy of the claim form; and

(ii) such other statements of case, witness statements or affidavits as the court may direct; and

(c) a notice of a judgment or order must also be accompanied by a copy of the judgment or order.

(5) If a person served with notice of a claim files an acknowledgment of service of the notice within 14 days he will become a party to the claim.

(6) If a person served with notice of a claim does not acknowledge service of the notice he will be bound by any judgment given in the claim as if he were a party.

(7) If, after service of a notice of a claim on a person, the claim form is amended so as substantially to alter the relief claimed, the court may direct that a judgment shall not bind that person unless a further notice, together with a copy of the amended claim form, is served on him.

(8) Any person served with a notice of a judgment or order under this rule –

(a) shall be bound by the judgment or order as if he had been a party to the claim; but

(b) may, provided he acknowledges service –

(i) within 28 days after the notice is served on him, apply to the court to set aside or vary the judgment or order; and

(ii) take part in any proceedings relating to the judgment or order.

(9) The following rules of Part 10 (acknowledgment of service) apply –

(b) rule 10.5, subject to the modification that references to the defendant are to be read as references to the person served with the notice.

(10) A notice under this rule is issued on the date entered on the notice by the court.

Derivative claims – how started

19.9

(1) This rule –

(a) applies to a derivative claim (where a company, other body corporate or trade union is alleged to be entitled to claim a remedy, and a claim is made by a member of it for it to be given that remedy), whether under Chapter 1 of Part 11 of the Companies Act 2006^3 or otherwise; but

(b) does not apply to a claim made pursuant to an order under section 996 of that Act.

(2) A derivative claim must be started by a claim form.

(3) The company, body corporate or trade union for the benefit of which a remedy is sought must be made a defendant to the claim.

(4) After the issue of the claim form, the claimant must not take any further step in the proceedings without the permission of the court, other than –

(a) a step permitted or required by rule 19.9A or 19.9C; or

(b) making an urgent application for interim relief.

Derivative claims under Chapter 1 of Part 11 of the Companies Act 2006 – application for permission

19.9A

(1) In this rule –

‘the Act’ means the Companies Act 2006;

‘derivative claim’ means a derivative claim under Chapter 1 of Part 11 of the Act;

‘permission application’ means an application referred to in section 261(1), 262(2) or 264(2) of the Act;

‘the company’ means the company for the benefit of which the derivative claim is brought.

(2) When the claim form for a derivative claim is issued, the claimant must file –

(a) an application notice under Part 23 for permission to continue the claim; and

(b) the written evidence on which the claimant relies in support of the permission application.

(3) The claimant must not make the company a respondent to the permission application.

(4) Subject to paragraph (7), the claimant must notify the company of the claim and permission application by sending to the company as soon as reasonably practicable after the claim form is issued –

(a) a notice in the form set out in Practice Direction 19C, and to which is attached a copy of the provisions of the Act required by that form;

(b) copies of the claim form and the particulars of claim;

(c) the application notice; and

(d) a copy of the evidence filed by the claimant in support of the permission application.

(5) The claimant may send the notice and documents required by paragraph (4) to the company by any method permitted by Part 6 as if the notice and documents were being served on the company.

(6) The claimant must file a witness statement confirming that the claimant has notified the company in accordance with paragraph (4).

(7) Where notifying the company of the permission application would be likely to frustrate some party of the remedy sought, the court may, on application by the claimant, order that the company need not be notified for such period after the issue of the claim form as the court directs.

(8) An application under paragraph (7) may be made without notice.

(9) Where the court dismisses the claimant’s permission application without a hearing, the court will notify the claimant and (unless the court orders otherwise) the company of that decision.

(10) The claimant may ask for an oral hearing to reconsider the decision to dismiss the permission application, but the claimant –

(a) must make the request to the court in writing within seven days of being notified of the decision; and

(b) must notify the company in writing, as soon as reasonably practicable, of that request unless the court orders otherwise.

(11) Where the court dismisses the permission application at a hearing pursuant to paragraph (10), it will notify the claimant and the company of its decision.

(12) Where the court does not dismiss the application under section 261(2) of the Act, the court will –

(a) order that the company and any other appropriate party must be made respondents to the permission application; and

(b) give directions for the service on the company and any other appropriate party of the application notice and the claim form.

Derivative claims under Chapter 1 of Part 11 of the Companies Act 2006 – members of companies taking over claims by companies or other members

19.9B

(1) This rule applies to proceedings under section 262(1) or 264(1) of the Companies Act 2006.

(2) The application for permission must be made by an application notice in accordance with Part 23.

(3) Rule 19.9A (except for paragraphs (1), (2) and (4)(b) of that rule, and paragraph (12)(b) so far as it applies to the claim form) applies to an application under this rule and references to the claimant in rule 19.9A are to be read as references to the person who seeks to take over the claim.

Derivative claims – other bodies corporate and trade unions

19.9C

(1) This rule sets out the procedure where –

(a) either –

(i) a body corporate to which Chapter 1 of Part 11 of the Companies Act 2006 does not apply; or

(ii) a trade union,

is alleged to be entitled to a remedy; and

(b) either –

(i) a claim is made by a member for it to be given that remedy; or

(ii) a member of the body corporate or trade union seeks to take over a claim already started, by the body corporate or trade union or one or more of its members, for it to be given that remedy.

(2) The member who starts, or seeks to take over, the claim must apply to the court for permission to continue the claim.

(3) The application for permission must be made by an application notice in accordance with Part 23.

(4) The procedure for applications in relation to companies under section 261, 262 or 264 (as the case requires) of the Companies Act 2006 applies to the permission application as if the body corporate or trade union were a company.

(5) Rules 19.9A (except for paragraph (1) of that rule) and 19.9B apply to the permission application as if the body corporate or trade union were a company.

Derivative claims arising in the course of other proceedings

19.9D

If a derivative claim (except such a claim in pursuance of an order under section 996 of the Companies Act 2006) arises in the course of other proceedings –

(a) in the case of a derivative claim under Chapter 1 of Part 11 of that Act, rule 19.9A or 19.9B applies, as the case requires; and

(b) in any other case, rule 19.9C applies.

Derivative claims – costs

19.9E

The court may order the company, body corporate or trade union for the benefit of which a derivative claim is brought to indemnify the claimant against liability for costs incurred in the permission application or in the derivative claim or both.

Derivative claims – discontinuance and settlement

19.9F  Where the court has given permission to continue a derivative claim, the court may order that the claim may not be discontinued, settled or compromised without the permission of the court.

III GROUP LITIGATION

Definition

19.10  A Group Litigation Order (‘GLO’) means an order made under rule 19.11 to provide for the case management of claims which give rise to common or related issues of fact or law (the ‘GLO issues’).

Group Litigation Order

19.11

(1) The court may make a GLO where there are or are likely to be a number of claims giving rise to the GLO issues.

(Practice Direction 19B provides the procedure for applying for a GLO)

(2) A GLO must –

(a) contain directions about the establishment of a register (the ‘group register’) on which the claims managed under the GLO will be entered;

(b) specify the GLO issues which will identify the claims to be managed as a group under the GLO; and

(c) specify the court (the ‘management court’) which will manage the claims on the group register.

(3) A GLO may –

(a) in relation to claims which raise one or more of the GLO issues –

(i) direct their transfer to the management court;

(ii) order their stay[GL] until further order; and

(iii) direct their entry on the group register;

(b) direct that from a specified date claims which raise one or more of the GLO issues should be started in the management court and entered on the group register; and

(c) give directions for publicising the GLO.

Effect of the GLO

19.12

(1) Where a judgment or order is given or made in a claim on the group register in relation to one or more GLO issues –

(a) that judgment or order is binding on the parties to all other claims that are on the group register at the time the judgment is given or the order is made unless the court orders otherwise; and

(b) the court may give directions as to the extent to which that judgment or order is binding on the parties to any claim which is subsequently entered on the group register.

(2) Unless paragraph (3) applies, any party who is adversely affected by a judgment or order which is binding on him may seek permission to appeal the order.

(3) A party to a claim which was entered on the group register after a judgment or order which is binding on him was given or made may not –

(a) apply for the judgment or order to be set aside[GL], varied or stayed[GL]; or

(b) appeal the judgment or order,

but may apply to the court for an order that the judgment or order is not binding on him.

(4) Unless the court orders otherwise, disclosure of any document relating to the GLO issues by a party to a claim on the group register is disclosure of that document to all parties to claims –

(a) on the group register; and

(b) which are subsequently entered on the group register.

Case management

19.13  Directions given by the management court may include directions –

(a) varying the GLO issues;

(b) providing for one or more claims on the group register to proceed as test claims;

(c) appointing the solicitor of one or more parties to be the lead solicitor for the claimants or defendants;

(d) specifying the details to be included in a statement of case in order to show that the criteria for entry of the claim on the group register have been met;

(e) specifying a date after which no claim may be added to the group register unless the court gives permission; and

(f) for the entry of any particular claim which meets one or more of the GLO issues on the group register.

(Part 3 contains general provisions about the case management powers of the court)

Removal from the register

19.14

(1) A party to a claim entered on the group register may apply to the management court for the claim to be removed from the register.

(2) If the management court orders the claim to be removed from the register it may give directions about the future management of the claim.

Test claims

19.15

(1) Where a direction has been given for a claim on the group register to proceed as a test claim and that claim is settled, the management court may order that another claim on the group register be substituted as the test claim.

(2) Where an order is made under paragraph (1), any order made in the test claim before the date of substitution is binding on the substituted claim unless the court orders otherwise.

Footnotes

1980 c.58. Back to text
1984 c.16. Back to text
2006 c. 46. Back to text

PART 20 - COUNTERCLAIMS AND OTHER ADDITIONAL CLAIMS

Contents of this Part

Title | Number
Purpose of this Part | Rule 20.1
Scope and interpretation | Rule 20.2
Application of these Rules to additional claims | Rule 20.3
Defendant’s counterclaim against the claimant | Rule 20.4
Counterclaim against a person other than the claimant | Rule 20.5
Defendant’s additional claim for contribution or indemnity from another party | Rule 20.6
Procedure for making any other additional claim | Rule 20.7
Service of claim form | Rule 20.8
Matters relevant to question of whether an additional claim should be separate from the claim | Rule 20.9
Effect of service of an additional claim | Rule 20.10
Special provisions relating to default judgment on an additional claim other than a counterclaim or a contribution or indemnity notice | Rule 20.11
Procedural steps on service of an additional claim form on a non-party | Rule 20.12
Case management where a defence to an additional claim is filed | Rule 20.13

Purpose of this Part

20.1  The purpose of this Part is to enable counterclaims and other additional claims to be managed in the most convenient and effective manner.

Scope and interpretation

20.2

(1) This Part applies to –

(a) a counterclaim by a defendant against the claimant or against the claimant and some other person;

(b) an additional claim by a defendant against any person (whether or not already a party) for contribution or indemnity or some other remedy; and

(c) where an additional claim has been made against a person who is not already a party, any additional claim made by that person against any other person (whether or not already a party).

(2) In these Rules –

(a) ‘additional claim’ means any claim other than the claim by the claimant against the defendant; and

(b) unless the context requires otherwise, references to a claimant or defendant include a party bringing or defending an additional claim.

Application of these Rules to additional claims

20.3

(1) An additional claim shall be treated as if it were a claim for the purposes of these Rules, except as provided by this Part.

(2) The following rules do not apply to additional claims –

(a) rules 7.5 and 7.6 (time within which a claim form may be served);

(b) rule 16.3(5) (statement of value where claim to be issued in the High Court); and

(c) Part 26 (case management – preliminary stage).

(3) Part 12 (default judgment) applies to a counterclaim but not to other additional claims.

(4) Part 14 (admissions) applies to a counterclaim, but only –

(a) rules 14.1(1) and 14.1(2) (which provide that a party may admit the truth of another party's case in writing); and

(b) rule 14.3 (admission by notice in writing – application for judgment),

apply to other additional claims.

(Rule 12.3(2) sets out how to obtain judgment in default of defence for a counterclaim against the claimant, and rule 20.11 makes special provision for default judgment for some additional claims).

Defendant’s counterclaim against the claimant

20.4

(1) A defendant may make a counterclaim against a claimant by filing particulars of the counterclaim.

(2) A defendant may make a counterclaim against a claimant –

(a) without the court’s permission if he files it with his defence; or

(b) at any other time with the court’s permission.

(Part 15 makes provision for a defence to a claim and applies to a defence to a counterclaim by virtue of rule 20.3).

(3) Part 10 (acknowledgment of service) does not apply to a claimant who wishes to defend a counterclaim.

Counterclaim against a person other than the claimant

20.5

(1) A defendant who wishes to counterclaim against a person other than the claimant must apply to the court for an order that that person be added as an additional party.

(2) An application for an order under paragraph (1) may be made without notice unless the court directs otherwise.

(3) Where the court makes an order under paragraph (1), it will give directions as to the management of the case.

Defendant’s additional claim for contribution or indemnity from another party

20.6

(1) A defendant who has filed an acknowledgment of service or a defence may make an additional claim for contribution or indemnity against a person who is already a party to the proceedings by –

(a) filing a notice containing a statement of the nature and grounds of his additional claim; and

(b) serving the notice on that party.

(2) A defendant may file and serve a notice under this rule –

(a) without the court’s permission, if he files and serves it –

(i) with his defence; or

(ii) if his additional claim for contribution or indemnity is against a party added to the claim later, within 28 days after that party files his defence; or

(b) at any other time with the court’s permission.

Procedure for making any other additional claim

20.7

(1) This rule applies to any additional claim except –

(a) a counterclaim only against an existing party; and

(b) a claim for contribution or indemnity made in accordance with rule 20.6.

(2) An additional claim is made when the court issues the appropriate claim form.

(Rule 7.2(2) provides that a claim form is issued on the date entered on the form by the court)

(3) A defendant may make an additional claim –

(a) without the court’s permission if the additional claim is issued before or at the same time as he files his defence;

(b) at any other time with the court’s permission.

(Rule 15.4 sets out the period for filing a defence).

(4) Particulars of an additional claim must be contained in or served with the additional claim.

(5) An application for permission to make an additional claim may be made without notice, unless the court directs otherwise.

Service of claim form

20.8

(1) Where an additional claim may be made without the court’s permission, any claim form must –

(a) in the case of a counterclaim against an additional party only, be served on every other party when a copy of the defence is served;

(b) in the case of any other additional claim, be served on the person against whom it is made within 14 days after the date on which the additional claim is issued by the court.

(2) Paragraph (1) does not apply to a claim for contribution or indemnity made in accordance with rule 20.6.

(3) Where the court gives permission to make an additional claim it will at the same time give directions as to its service.

Matters relevant to question of whether an additional claim should be separate from the claim

20.9

(1) This rule applies where the court is considering whether to –

(a) permit an additional claim to be made;

(b) dismiss an additional claim; or

(c) require an additional claim to be dealt with separately from the claim by the claimant against the defendant.

(Rule 3.1(2)(e) and (j) deal respectively with the court's power to order that part of proceedings be dealt with as separate proceedings and to decide the order in which issues are to be tried).

(2) The matters to which the court may have regard include –

(a) the connection between the additional claim and the claim made by the claimant against the defendant;

(b) whether the additional claimant is seeking substantially the same remedy which some other party is claiming from him; and

(c) whether the additional claimant wants the court to decide any question connected with the subject matter of the proceedings –

(i) not only between existing parties but also between existing parties and a person not already a party; or

(ii) against an existing party not only in a capacity in which he is already a party but also in some further capacity.

Effect of service of an additional claim

20.10

(1) A person on whom an additional claim is served becomes a party to the proceedings if he is not a party already.

(2) When an additional claim is served on an existing party for the purpose of requiring the court to decide a question against that party in a further capacity, that party also becomes a party in the further capacity specified in the additional claim.

Special provisions relating to default judgment on an additional claim other than a counterclaim or a contribution or indemnity notice

20.11

(1) This rule applies if –

(a) the additional claim is not –

(i) a counterclaim; or

(ii) a claim by a defendant for contribution or indemnity against another defendant under rule 20.6; and

(b) the party against whom an additional claim is made fails to file an acknowledgment of service or defence in respect of the additional claim.

(2) The party against whom the additional claim is made –

(a) is deemed to admit the additional claim, and is bound by any judgment or decision in the proceedings in so far as it is relevant to any matter arising in the additional claim;

(b) subject to paragraph (3), if default judgment under Part 12 is given against the additional claimant, the additional claimant may obtain judgment in respect of the additional claim by filing a request in the relevant practice form.

(3) An additional claimant may not enter judgment under paragraph (2)(b) without the court’s permission if –

(a) he has not satisfied the default judgment which has been given against him; or

(b) he wishes to obtain judgment for any remedy other than a contribution or indemnity.

(4) An application for the court’s permission under paragraph (3) may be made without notice unless the court directs otherwise.

(5) The court may at any time set aside or vary a judgment entered under paragraph (2)(b).

Procedural steps on service of an additional claim form on a non-party

20.12

(1) Where an additional claim form is served on a person who is not already a party it must be accompanied by –

(a) a form for defending the claim;

(b) a form for admitting the claim;

(c) a form for acknowledging service; and

(d) a copy of –

(i) every statement of case which has already been served in the proceedings; and

(ii) such other documents as the court may direct.

(2) A copy of the additional claim form must be served on every existing party.

Case management where a defence to an additional claim is filed

20.13

(1) Where a defence is filed to an additional claim the court must consider the future conduct of the proceedings and give appropriate directions.

(2) In giving directions under paragraph (1) the court must ensure that, so far as practicable, the original claim and all additional claims are managed together.

(Part 66 contains provisions about counterclaims and other Part 20 claims in relation to proceedings by or against the Crown.)

PRACTICE DIRECTION 20 – COUNTERCLAIMS AND OTHER ADDITIONAL CLAIMS

This Practice Direction supplements CPR Part 20

Contents of this Practice Direction

An additional claim is any claim other than the claim by the claimant against the defendant.

Claims under this Part were formerly known as ‘Part 20 claims’. As a result of the amendments to Part 20, introduced by Civil Procedure (Amendment No.4) Rules 2005, they are now called ‘additional claims’.

However, they are described as ‘Part 20 claims’ on a number of court forms. For the present, some of those forms will continue to refer to Part 20 claims. These references should be construed as being additional claims under this Part. Any reference to a Part 20 claimant or a Part 20 defendant means a claimant or defendant in an additional claim under this Part.

Cases where court’s permission to make an additional claim is required

1.1  Rules 20.4(2)(b), 20.5(1) and 20.7(3)(b) set out the circumstances in which the court's permission will be needed for making an additional claim.

1.2  Where an application is made for permission to make an additional claim the application notice should be filed together with a copy of the proposed additional claim.

Applications for permission to issue an additional claim

2.1  An application for permission to make an additional claim must be supported by evidence stating:

(1) the stage which the proceedings have reached,

(2) the nature of the additional claim to be made or details of the question or issue which needs to be decided,

(3) a summary of the facts on which the additional claim is based, and

(4) the name and address of any proposed additional party.

(For further information regarding evidence see Practice Direction 32).

2.2  Where delay has been a factor contributing to the need to apply for permission to make an additional claim an explanation of the delay should be given in evidence.

2.3  Where possible the applicant should provide a timetable of the proceedings to date.

2.4  Rules 20.5(2) and 20.7(5) allow applications to be made to the court without notice unless the court directs otherwise.

General

3  The Civil Procedure Rules apply generally to additional claims as if they were claims. Parties should be aware that the provisions relating to failure to respond to a claim will apply.

Statement of truth

4.1  The contents of an additional claim should be verified by a statement of truth. Part 22 requires a statement of case to be verified by a statement of truth.

4.2  The form of the statement of truth should be as required by paragraph 2.1 of Practice Direction 22.

4.3  Attention is drawn to rule 32.14 which sets out the consequences of verifying a statement of case containing a false statement without an honest belief in its truth.

Case management where there is a defence to an additional claim

5.1  Where the defendant to an additional claim files a defence, other than to a counterclaim, the court will arrange a hearing to consider case management of the additional claim. This will normally be at the same time as a case management hearing for the original claim and any other additional claims.

5.2  The court will give notice of the hearing to each party likely to be affected by any order made at the hearing.

5.3  At the hearing the court may:

(1) treat the hearing as a summary judgment hearing,

(2) order that the additional claim be dismissed,

(3) give directions about the way any claim, question or issue set out in or arising from the additional claim should be dealt with,

(4) give directions as to the part, if any, the additional defendant will take at the trial of the claim,

(5) give directions about the extent to which the additional defendant is to be bound by any judgment or decision to be made in the claim.

5.4  The court may make any of the orders in 5.3(1) to (5) either before or after any judgment in the claim has been entered by the claimant against the defendant.

Form of counterclaim

6.1  Where a defendant to a claim serves a counterclaim, the defence and counterclaim should normally form one document with the counterclaim following on from the defence.

6.2  Where a claimant serves a reply and a defence to counterclaim, the reply and the defence to counterclaim should normally form one document with the defence to counterclaim following on from the reply.

Titles of proceedings where there are additional claims

7.1  Paragraph 4 of Practice Direction 7A contains directions regarding the title to proceedings.

7.2  Where there are additional claims which add parties, the title to the proceedings should comprise a list of all parties describing each by giving them a single identification. Subject to paragraph 7.11, this identification should be used throughout.

7.3  Claimants and defendants in the original claim should always be referred to as such in the title to the proceedings, even if they subsequently acquire an additional procedural status.

7.4  Additional parties should be referred to in the title to the proceedings in accordance with the order in which they are joined to the proceedings, for example ‘Third Party’ or ‘Fourth Party’, whatever their actual procedural status.

Examples:

(a) If the defendant makes an additional claim against a single additional party, the additional party should be referred to in the title as ‘Third Party’.

(b) If the defendant makes separate additional claims against two additional parties, the additional parties should be referred to in the title as ‘Third Party’ and ‘Fourth Party’.

(c) If the defendant makes a counterclaim against the claimant and an additional party, the claimant should remain as ‘Claimant’ and the additional party should be referred to in the title as ‘Third Party’.

(d) If the Third Party in example (b) makes an additional claim against a further additional party, that additional party should be referred to in the title as ‘Fifth Party’.

7.5  If an additional claim is brought against more than one party jointly, they should be referred to in the title to the proceedings as, for example, ‘First Named Third Party’ and ‘Second Named Third Party’.

7.6  In group litigation, the court should give directions about the designation of parties.

7.7  All parties should co-operate to ensure that two parties each making additional claims do not attribute the same nominal status to more than one party.

7.8  In proceedings with numerous parties, the court will if necessary give directions as to the preparation and updating of a list of parties giving their roles in the claim and each additional claim.

7.9  If an additional party ceases to be a party to the proceedings, for example because the claim against that party is discontinued or dismissed, all other additional parties should retain their existing nominal status.

7.10  In proceedings where there are additional parties, the description of all statements of case or other similar documents should clearly identify the nature of the document with reference to each relevant party.

Examples:

(e) In example (a), the defendant’s additional claim should be headed ‘Defendant’s Additional Claim against Third Party’ and the Third Party’s defence to it should be headed ‘Third Party’s Defence to Defendant’s Additional Claim’.

(f) In example (c), the defendant’s counterclaim should be headed ‘Defendant’s Counterclaim against Claimant and Third Party’ and the Third Party’s defence to it should be headed ‘Third Party’s defence to Defendant’s Counterclaim’.

7.11  In proceedings where there are Fourth or subsequent parties, additional parties should be referred to in the text of statements of case or other similar documents by name, suitably abbreviated if appropriate. If parties have similar names, suitable distinguishing abbreviations should be used.

PRACTICE DIRECTION 22 – STATEMENTS OF TRUTH

This Practice Direction supplements CPR Part 22

Contents of this Practice Direction

Title
Documents to be verified by a statement of truth
Form of the statement of truth
Who may sign the statement of truth
Inability to persons to read or sign documents to be verified by a statement of truth
Consequences of failure to verify
Penalty
Annex

Documents to be verified by a statement of truth

1.1  Rule 22.1(1) sets out the documents which must be verified by a statement of truth. The documents include:

(1) a statement of case,

(2) a response complying with an order under rule 18.1 to provide further information,

(3) a witness statement,

(4) an acknowledgment of service in a claim begun by the Part 8 procedure,

(5) a certificate stating the reasons for bringing a possession claim or a landlord and tenant claim in the High Court in accordance with rules 55.3(2) and 56.2(2),

(6) a certificate of service.

1.2  If an applicant wishes to rely on matters set out in his application notice as evidence, the application notice must be verified by a statement of truth[1].

1.3  An expert’s report should also be verified by a statement of truth. For the form of the statement of truth verifying an expert’s report (which differs from that set out below) see Practice Direction 35.

1.4  In addition, the following documents must be verified by a statement of truth:

(1) an application notice for –

(a) a third party debt order (rule 72.3),

(b) a hardship payment order (rule 72.7), or

(c) a charging order (rule 73.3);

(2) a notice of objections to an account being taken by the court, unless verified by an affidavit or witness statement;

(3) a schedule or counter-schedule of expenses and losses in a personal injury claim, and any amendments to such a schedule or counter-schedule, whether or not they are contained in a statement of case.

1.5  The statement of truth may be contained in the document it verifies or it may be in a separate document served subsequently, in which case it must identify the document to which it relates.

1.6  Where the form to be used includes a jurat for the content to be verified by an affidavit then a statement of truth is not required in addition.

Form of the statement of truth

2.1  The form of the statement of truth verifying a statement of case, a response, an application notice or a notice of objections should be as follows:

‘[I believe][the (claimant or as may be) believes] that the facts stated in this [name document being verified] are true.’

2.2  The form of the statement of truth verifying a witness statement should be as follows:

‘I believe that the facts stated in this witness statement are true.’

2.2A  The form of the statement of truth verifying a costs budget should be as follows:

‘The costs stated to have been incurred do not exceed the costs which my client is liable to pay in respect of such work. The future costs stated in this budget are a proper estimate of the reasonable and proportionate costs which my client will incur in this litigation.’

2.3  Where the statement of truth is contained in a separate document, the document containing the statement of truth must be headed with the title of the proceedings and the claim number. The document being verified should be identified in the statement of truth as follows:

(1) claim form: ‘the claim form issued on [date]’,

(2) particulars of claim: ‘the particulars of claim issued on [date]’,

(3) statement of case: ‘the [defence or as may be] served on the [name of party] on [date]’,

(4) application notice: ‘the application notice issued on [date] for [set out the remedy sought]’,

(5) witness statement: ‘the witness statement filed on [date] or served on [party] on [date]’.

Who may sign the statement of truth

3.1  In a statement of case, a response or an application notice, the statement of truth must be signed by:

(1) the party or his litigation friend^2, or

(2) the legal representative[3] of the party or litigation friend.

3.2  A statement of truth verifying a witness statement must be signed by the witness.

3.3  A statement of truth verifying a notice of objections to an account must be signed by the objecting party or his legal representative.

3.4  Where a document is to be verified on behalf of a company or other corporation, subject to paragraph 3.7 below, the statement of truth must be signed by a person holding a senior position^4 in the company or corporation. That person must state the office or position held.

3.5  Each of the following persons is a person holding a senior position:

(1) in respect of a registered company or corporation, a director, the treasurer, secretary, chief executive, manager or other officer of the company or corporation, and

(2) in respect of a corporation which is not a registered company, in addition to those persons set out in (1), the mayor, chairman, president or town clerk or other similar officer of the corporation.

3.6  Where the document is to be verified on behalf of a partnership, those who may sign the statement of truth are:

(1) any of the partners, or

(2) a person having the control or management of the partnership business.

3.6A  An insurer or the Motor Insurers’ Bureau may sign a statement of truth in a statement of case on behalf of a party where the insurer or the Motor Insurers’ Bureau has a financial interest in the result of proceedings brought wholly or partially by or against that party.

3.6B  If insurers are conducting proceedings on behalf of many claimants or defendants a statement of truth in a statement of case may be signed by a senior person responsible for the case at a lead insurer, but–

(1) the person signing must specify the capacity in which he signs;

(2) the statement of truth must be a statement that the lead insurer believes that the facts stated in the document are true; and

(3) the court may order that a statement of truth also be signed by one or more of the parties.

3.7  Where a party is legally represented, the legal representative may sign the statement of truth on his behalf. The statement signed by the legal representative will refer to the client’s belief, not his own. In signing he must state the capacity in which he signs and the name of his firm where appropriate.

3.8  Where a legal representative has signed a statement of truth, his signature will be taken by the court as his statement:

(1) that the client on whose behalf he has signed had authorised him to do so,

(2) that before signing he had explained to the client that in signing the statement of truth he would be confirming the client’s belief that the facts stated in the document were true, and

(3) that before signing he had informed the client of the possible consequences to the client if it should subsequently appear that the client did not have an honest belief in the truth of those facts (see rule 32.14).

3.9  The individual who signs a statement of truth must print his full name clearly beneath his signature.

3.10  A legal representative who signs a statement of truth must sign in his own name and not that of his firm or employer.

3.11  The following are examples of the possible application of this practice direction describing who may sign a statement of truth verifying statements in documents other than a witness statement. These are only examples and not an indication of how a court might apply the practice direction to a specific situation.

Managing Agent

|

An agent who manages property or investments for the party cannot sign a statement of truth. It must be signed by the party or by the legal representative of the party.

Trusts

|

Where some or all of the trustees comprise a single party one, some or all of the trustees comprising the party may sign a statement of truth. The legal representative of the trustees may sign it.

Insurers and the Motor Insurers’ Bureau

|

If an insurer has a financial interest in a claim involving its insured then, if the insured is the party, the insurer may sign a statement of truth in a statement of case for the insured party. Paragraphs 3.4 and 3.5 apply to the insurer if it is a company. The claims manager employed by the insurer responsible for handling the insurance claim or managing the staff handling the claim may sign the statement of truth for the insurer (see next example). The position for the Motor Insurers’ Bureau is similar.

Companies

|

Paragraphs 3.4 and 3.5 apply. The word manager will be construed in the context of the phrase ‘a person holding a senior position’ which it is used to define. The court will consider the size of the company and the size and nature of the claim. It would expect the manager signing the statement of truth to have personal knowledge of the content of the document or to be responsible for managing those who have that knowledge of the content. A small company may not have a manager, apart from the directors, who holds a senior position. A large company will have many such managers. In a larger company with specialist claims, insurance or legal departments the statement may be signed by the manager of such a department if he or she is responsible for handling the claim or managing the staff handling it.

In-house legal representatives

|

Legal representative is defined in rule 2.3(1). A legal representative employed by a party may sign a statement of truth. However a person who is not a solicitor, barrister or other authorised litigator, but who is employed by the company and is managed by such a person, is not employed by that person and so cannot sign a statement of truth. (This is unlike the employee of a solicitor in private practice who would come within the definition of legal representative.) However such a person may be a manager and able to sign the statement on behalf of the company in that capacity.

Inability to persons to read or sign documents to be verified by a statement of truth

3A.1  Where a document containing a statement of truth is to be signed by a person who is unable to read or sign the document, it must contain a certificate made by an authorised person.

3A.2  An authorised person is a person able to administer oaths and take affidavits but need not be independent of the parties or their representatives.

3A.3  The authorised person must certify:

(1) that the document has been read to the person signing it;

(2) that that person appeared to understand it and approved its content as accurate;

(3) that the declaration of truth has been read to that person;

(4) that that person appeared to understand the declaration and the consequences of making a false declaration; and

(5) that that person signed or made his mark in the presence of the authorised person.

3A.4  The form of the certificate is set out at Annex 1 to this Practice Direction.

Consequences of failure to verify

4.1  If a statement of case is not verified by a statement of truth, the statement of case will remain effective unless it is struck out[5], but a party may not rely on the contents of a statement of case as evidence until it has been verified by a statement of truth.

4.2  Any party may apply to the court for an order that unless within such period as the court may specify the statement of case is verified by the service of a statement of truth, the statement of case will be struck out.

4.3  The usual order for the costs of an application referred to in paragraph 4.2 will be that the costs be paid by the party who had failed to verify in any event and forthwith.

Penalty

5  Attention is drawn to rule 32.14 which sets out the consequences of verifying a statement of case containing a false statement without an honest belief in its truth, and to the procedures set out in rule 81.18 and paragraphs 5.1 to 5.7 of Practice Direction 81 – Applications and proceedings in relation to contempt of court.

Annex

Certificate to be used where a person is unable to read or sign a document to be verified by a statement of truth

I certify that I [name and address of authorised person] have read over the contents of this document and the declaration of truth to the person signing the document [if there are exhibits, add ‘and explained the nature and effect of the exhibits referred to in it’] who appeared to understand (a) the document and approved its content as accurate and (b) the declaration of truth and the consequences of making a false declaration, and made his mark in my presence.

Footnotes

See rule 22.1(3). Back to text
See Part 21 (Children and Protected Parties). Back to text
See rule 2.3 for the definition of legal representative. Back to text
Paragraph 6.2 of Practice Direction 6A sets out the meaning of ‘senior position’. Back to text
See rule 22.2(1). Back to text

PART 23 - GENERAL RULES ABOUT APPLICATIONS FOR COURT ORDERS

Contents of this Part

<tdrule 23.2< td=""> </tdrule 23.2<>

Title | Number
Meaning of ‘application notice’ and‘respondent’ | Rule 23.1
Where to make an application | Rule 23.2
Application notice to be filed | Rule 23.3
Notice of an application | Rule 23.4
Time when an application is made | Rule 23.5
What an application notice must include | Rule 23.6
Service of a copy of an application notice | Rule 23.7
Applications which may be dealt with without a hearing | Rule 23.8
Service of application where application made without notice | Rule 23.9
Application to set aside or vary order made without notice | Rule 23.10
Power of the court to proceed in the absence of a party | Rule 23.11
Dismissal of totally without merit applications | Rule 23.12

Meaning of ‘application notice’ and‘respondent’

23.1  In this Part –

‘application notice’ means a document in which the applicant states his intention to seek a court order; and

‘respondent’ means –

(a) the person against whom the order is sought; and

(b) such other person as the court may direct.

Where to make an application

23.2

(1) The general rule is that an application must be made to the court where the claim was started.

(2) If a claim has been transferred to another court since it was started, an application must be made to the court to which the claim has been transferred.

(3) If the parties have been notified of a fixed date for the trial, an application must be made to the court where the trial is to take place.

(4) Subject to paragraph (4A), if an application is made before a claim has been started, it must be made to the court where it is likely that the claim to which the application relates will be started unless there is good reason to make the application to a different court.

(4A) If –

(a) an application is made before a claim has been started; and

(b) the claim is a designated money claim,

the application may be made in any county court.

(5) If an application is made after proceedings to enforce judgment have begun, it must be made to any court which is dealing with the enforcement of the judgment unless any rule or practice direction provides otherwise.

Application notice to be filed

23.3

(1) The general rule is that an applicant must file an application notice.

(2) An applicant may make an application without filing an application notice if –

(a) this is permitted by a rule or practice direction; or

(b) the court dispenses with the requirement for an application notice.

Notice of an application

23.4

(1) The general rule is that a copy of the application notice must be served on each respondent.

(2) An application may be made without serving a copy of the application notice if this is permitted by –

(a) a rule;

(b) a practice direction; or

(c) a court order.

(Rule 23.7 deals with service of a copy of the application notice)

Time when an application is made

23.5  Where an application must be made within a specified time, it is so made if the application notice is received by the court within that time.

What an application notice must include

23.6  An application notice must state –

(a) what order the applicant is seeking; and

(b) briefly, why the applicant is seeking the order.

(Part 22 requires an application notice to be verified by a statement of truth if the applicant wishes to rely on matters set out in his application notice as evidence)

Service of a copy of an application notice

23.7

(1) A copy of the application notice –

(a) must be served as soon as practicable after it is filed; and

(b) except where another time limit is specified in these Rules or a practice direction, must in any event be served at least 3 days before the court is to deal with the application.

(2) If a copy of the application notice is to be served by the court, the applicant must, when he files the application notice, file a copy of any written evidence in support.

(3) When a copy of an application notice is served it must be accompanied by –

(a) a copy of any written evidence in support; and

(b) a copy of any draft order which the applicant has attached to his application.

(4) If –

(a) an application notice is served; but

(b) the period of notice is shorter than the period required by these Rules or a practice direction,

the court may direct that, in the circumstances of the case, sufficient notice has been given and hear the application.

(5) This rule does not require written evidence –

(a) to be filed if it has already been filed; or

(b) to be served on a party on whom it has already been served.

(Part 6 contains the general rules about service of documents including who must serve a copy of the application notice)

Applications which may be dealt with without a hearing

23.8  The court may deal with an application without a hearing if –

(a) the parties agree as to the terms of the order sought;

(b) the parties agree that the court should dispose of the application without a hearing, or

(c) the court does not consider that a hearing would be appropriate.

Service of application where application made without notice

23.9

(1) This rule applies where the court has disposed of an application which it permitted to be made without service of a copy of the application notice.

(2) Where the court makes an order, whether granting or dismissing the application, a copy of the application notice and any evidence in support must, unless the court orders otherwise, be served with the order on any party or other person –

(a) against whom the order was made; and

(b) against whom the order was sought.

(3) The order must contain a statement of the right to make an application to set aside(GL) or vary the order under rule 23.10.

Application to set aside or vary order made without notice

23.10

(1) A person who was not served with a copy of the application notice before an order was made under rule 23.9, may apply to have the order set aside(GL) or varied.

(2) An application under this rule must be made within 7 days after the date on which the order was served on the person making the application.

Power of the court to proceed in the absence of a party

23.11

(1) Where the applicant or any respondent fails to attend the hearing of an application, the court may proceed in his absence.

(2) Where –

(a) the applicant or any respondent fails to attend the hearing of an application; and

(b) the court makes an order at the hearing,

the court may, on application or of its own initiative, re-list the application.

(Part 40 deals with service of orders)

Dismissal of totally without merit applications

23.12  If the court dismisses an application (including an application for permission to appeal or for permission to apply for judicial review) and it considers that the application is totally without merit –

(a) the court’s order must record that fact; and

(b) the court must at the same time consider whether it is appropriate to make a civil restraint order.

PART 24 - SUMMARY JUDGMENT

Contents of this Part

Title | Number
Scope of this Part | Rule 24.1
Grounds for summary judgment | Rule 24.2
Types of proceedings in which summary judgment is available | Rule 24.3
Procedure | Rule 24.4
Evidence for the purposes of a summary judgment hearing | Rule 24.5
Court’s powers when it determines a summary judgment application | Rule 24.6

Scope of this Part

24.1  This Part sets out a procedure by which the court may decide a claim or a particular issue without a trial.

(Part 53 makes special provision about summary disposal of defamation claims in accordance with the Defamation Act 1996)^1

Grounds for summary judgment

24.2  The court may give summary judgment against a claimant or defendant on the whole of a claim or on a particular issue if –

(a) it considers that –

(i) that claimant has no real prospect of succeeding on the claim or issue; or

(ii) that defendant has no real prospect of successfully defending the claim or issue; and

(b) there is no other compelling reason why the case or issue should be disposed of at a trial.

(Rule 3.4 makes provision for the court to strike out(GL) a statement of case or part of a statement of case if it appears that it discloses no reasonable grounds for bringing or defending a claim)

Types of proceedings in which summary judgment is available

24.3

(1) The court may give summary judgment against a claimant in any type of proceedings.

(2) The court may give summary judgment against a defendant in any type of proceedings except –

(a) proceedings for possession of residential premises against –

(i) a mortgagor; or

(ii) a tenant or a person holding over after the end of his tenancy whose occupancy is protected within the meaning of the Rent Act 1977[2] or the Housing Act 1988^3 and;

(b) proceedings for an admiralty claim in rem.

(c) Omitted

Procedure

24.4

(1) A claimant may not apply for summary judgment until the defendant against whom the application is made has filed –

(a) an acknowledgement of service; or

(b) a defence,

unless –

(i) the court gives permission; or

(ii) a practice direction provides otherwise.

(Rule 10.3 sets out the period for filing an acknowledgment of service and rule 15.4 the period for filing a defence)

(1A) In civil proceedings against the Crown, as defined in rule 66.1(2), a claimant may not apply for summary judgment until after expiry of the period for filing a defence specified in rule 15.4.

(2) If a claimant applies for summary judgment before a defendant against whom the application is made has filed a defence, that defendant need not file a defence before the hearing.

(3) Where a summary judgment hearing is fixed, the respondent (or the parties where the hearing is fixed of the court’s own initiative) must be given at least 14 days’ notice of –

(a) the date fixed for the hearing; and

(b) the issues which it is proposed that the court will decide at the hearing.

(4) A practice direction may provide for a different period of notice to be given.

(Part 23 contains the general rules about how to make an application)

(Rule 3.3 applies where the court exercises its powers of its own initiative)

Evidence for the purposes of a summary judgment hearing

24.5

(1) If the respondent to an application for summary judgment wishes to rely on written evidence at the hearing, he must –

(a) file the written evidence; and

(b) serve copies on every other party to the application,

at least 7 days before the summary judgment hearing.

(2) If the applicant wishes to rely on written evidence in reply, he must –

(a) file the written evidence; and

(b) serve a copy on the respondent,

at least 3 days before the summary judgment hearing.

(3) Where a summary judgment hearing is fixed by the court of its own initiative –

(a) any party who wishes to rely on written evidence at the hearing must –

(i) file the written evidence; and

(ii) unless the court orders otherwise, serve copies on every other party to the proceedings,

at least 7 days before the date of the hearing;

(b) any party who wishes to rely on written evidence at the hearing in reply to any other party’s written evidence must –

(i) file the written evidence in reply; and

(ii) unless the court orders otherwise serve copies on every other party to the proceedings,

at least 3 days before the date of the hearing.

(4) This rule does not require written evidence –

(a) to be filed if it has already been filed; or

(b) to be served on a party on whom it has already been served.

Court’s powers when it determines a summary judgment application

24.6  When the court determines a summary judgment application it may –

(a) give directions as to the filing and service of a defence;

(b) give further directions about the management of the case.

(Rule 3.1(3) provides that the court may attach conditions when it makes an order)

Footnotes

1196c.31. Back to text
1977 c.42. Back to text
1988 c.50. Back to text

PRACTICE DIRECTION 24 – THE SUMMARY DISPOSAL OF CLAIMS

This Practice Direction supplements CPR Part 24

Contents of this Practice Direction

Title
Applications for Summary Judgment under Part 24
Procedure for making an application
The hearing
The Court’s approach
Orders the Court may make
Accounts and inquiries
Specific performance
Setting aside order for summary judgment
Costs
Case management

Applications for Summary Judgment under Part 24

1.1  Attention is drawn to Part 24 itself and to:

Part 3, in particular rule 3.1(3)and (5),

Part 22, Part 23, in particular rule 23.6,

Part 32, in particular rule 32.6(2).

1.2  In this paragraph, where the context so admits, the word ‘claim’ includes:

(1) a part of a claim, and

(2) an issue on which the claim in whole or part depends.

1.3  An application for summary judgment under rule 24.2 may be based on:

(1) a point of law (including a question of construction of a document),

(2) the evidence which can reasonably be expected to be available at trial or the lack of it, or

(3) a combination of these.

1.4  Rule 24.4(1) deals with the stage in the proceedings at which an application under Part 24 can be made (but see paragraph 7.1 below).

Procedure for making an application

2

(1) Attention is drawn to rules 24.4(3) and 23.6.

(2) The application notice must include a statement that it is an application for summary judgment made under Part 24.

(3) The application notice or the evidence contained or referred to in it or served with it must –

(a) identify concisely any point of law or provision in a document on which the applicant relies, and/or

(b) state that it is made because the applicant believes that on the evidence the respondent has no real prospect of succeeding on the claim or issue or (as the case may be) of successfully defending the claim or issue to which the application relates,

and in either case state that the applicant knows of no other reason why the disposal of the claim or issue should await trial.

(4) Unless the application notice itself contains all the evidence (if any) on which the applicant relies, the application notice should identify the written evidence on which the applicant relies. This does not affect the applicant’s right to file further evidence under rule 24.5(2).

(5) The application notice should draw the attention of the respondent to rule 24.5(1).

(6) Where the claimant has failed to comply with Practice Direction (Pre-Action Conduct) or any relevant pre-action protocol, an action for summary judgment will not normally be entertained before the defence has been filed or, alternatively, the time for doing so has expired.

The hearing

3

(1) The hearing of the application will normally take place before a Master or a district judge.

(2) The Master or district judge may direct that the application be heard by a High Court Judge (if the case is in the High Court) or a circuit judge (if the case is in a county court).

The Court’s approach

4  Where it appears to the court possible that a claim or defence may succeed but improbable that it will do so, the court may make a conditional order, as described below.

Orders the Court may make

5.1  The orders the court may make on an application under Part 24 include:

(1) judgment on the claim,

(2) the striking out or dismissal of the claim,

(3) the dismissal of the application,

(4) a conditional order.

5.2  A conditional order is an order which requires a party:

(1) to pay a sum of money into court, or

(2) to take a specified step in relation to his claim or defence, as the case may be, and provides that that party’s claim will be dismissed or his statement of case will be struck out if he does not comply.

(Note – the court will not follow its former practice of granting leave to a defendant to defend a claim, whether conditionally or unconditionally.)

Accounts and inquiries

6  If a remedy sought by a claimant in his claim form includes, or necessarily involves, taking an account or making an inquiry, an application can be made under Part 24 by any party to the proceedings for an order directing any necessary accounts or inquiries to be taken or made.

(Practice Direction 40A contains further provisions as to orders for accounts and inquiries.)

Specific performance

7.1

(1) If a remedy sought by a claimant in his claim form includes a claim –

(a) for specific performance of an agreement (whether in writing or not) for the sale, purchase, exchange, mortgage or charge of any property, or for the grant or assignment of a lease or tenancy of any property, with or without an alternative claim for damages, or

(b) for rescission of such an agreement, or

(c) for the forfeiture or return of any deposit made under such an agreement,

the claimant may apply under Part 24 for judgment.

(2) The claimant may do so at any time after the claim form has been served, whether or not the defendant has acknowledged service of the claim form, whether or not the time for acknowledging service has expired and whether or not any particulars of claim have been served.

7.2  The application notice by which an application under paragraph 7.1 is made must have attached to it the text of the order sought by the claimant.

7.3  The application notice and a copy of every affidavit or witness statement in support and of any exhibit referred to therein must be served on the defendant not less than 4 days before the hearing of the application. (Note – the 4 days replaces for these applications the 14 days specified in rule 24.4(3). Rule 24.5 cannot, therefore apply.)

(This paragraph replaces RSC Order 86, rules 1 and 2 but applies to county court proceedings as well as to High Court proceedings.)

Setting aside order for summary judgment

8.1  If an order for summary judgment is made against a respondent who does not appear at the hearing of the application, the respondent may apply for the order to be set aside or varied (see also rule 23.11).

8.2  On the hearing of an application under paragraph 8.1 the court may make such order as it thinks just.

Costs

9.1  Attention is drawn to Part 45 (fixed costs).

9.2  Attention is drawn to Practice Directions 44 to 48 on costs and in particular to Subsections 8 and 9 of Practice Direction 44, which relate to the court’s power to make a summary assessment of costs.

9.3  Attention is also drawn to rule 44.10(1) which provides that if an order does not mention costs no party is entitled to costs relating to that order.

Case management

10

Where the court dismisses the application or makes an order that does not completely dispose of the claim, the court will give case management directions as to the future conduct of the case.

PRACTICE DIRECTION 25A – INTERIM INJUNCTIONS

This Practice Direction supplements CPR Part 25

Contents of this Practice Direction

Jurisdiction

1.1  High Court Judges and any other Judge duly authorised may grant ‘search orders’[1] and ‘freezing injunctions’^2.

1.2  In a case in the High Court, Masters and district judges have the power to grant injunctions:

(1) by consent,

(2) in connection with charging orders and appointments of receivers,

(3) in aid of execution of judgments.

1.3  In any other case any judge who has jurisdiction to conduct the trial of the action has the power to grant an injunction in that action.

1.4  A Master or district judge has the power to vary or discharge an injunction granted by any Judge with the consent of all the parties.

Making an application

2.1  The application notice must state:

(1) the order sought, and

(2) the date, time and place of the hearing.

2.2  The application notice and evidence in support must be served as soon as practicable after issue and in any event not less than 3 days before the court is due to hear the application^3.

2.3  Where the court is to serve, sufficient copies of the application notice and evidence in support for the court and for each respondent should be filed for issue and service.

2.4  Whenever possible a draft of the order sought should be filed with the application notice and a disk containing the draft should also be available to the court in a format compatible with the word processing software used by the court. This will enable the court officer to arrange for any amendments to be incorporated and for the speedy preparation and sealing of the order.

Evidence

3.1  Applications for search orders and freezing injunctions must be supported by affidavit evidence.

3.2  Applications for other interim injunctions must be supported by evidence set out in either:

(1) a witness statement, or

(2) a statement of case provided that it is verified by a statement of truth,^4 or

(3) the application provided that it is verified by a statement of truth,

unless the court, an Act, a rule or a practice direction requires evidence by affidavit.

3.3  The evidence must set out the facts on which the applicant relies for the claim being made against the respondent, including all material facts of which the court should be made aware.

3.4  Where an application is made without notice to the respondent, the evidence must also set out why notice was not given.

(See Part 32 and Practice Direction 32 for information about evidence.)

Urgent applications and applications without notice

4.1  These fall into two categories:

(1) applications where a claim form has already been issued, and

(2) applications where a claim form has not yet been issued,

and, in both cases, where notice of the application has not been given to the respondent.

4.2  These applications are normally dealt with at a court hearing but cases of extreme urgency may be dealt with by telephone.

4.3  Applications dealt with at a court hearing after issue of a claim form:

(1) the application notice, evidence in support and a draft order (as in 2.4 above) should be filed with the court two hours before the hearing wherever possible,

(2) if an application is made before the application notice has been issued, a draft order (as in 2.4 above) should be provided at the hearing, and the application notice and evidence in support must be filed with the court on the same or next working day or as ordered by the court, and

(3) except in cases where secrecy is essential, the applicant should take steps to notify the respondent informally of the application.

4.4  Applications made before the issue of a claim form:

(1) in addition to the provisions set out at 4.3 above, unless the court orders otherwise, either the applicant must undertake to the court to issue a claim form immediately or the court will give directions for the commencement of the claim[5],

(2) where possible the claim form should be served with the order for the injunction,

(3) an order made before the issue of a claim form should state in the title after the names of the applicant and respondent ‘the Claimant and Defendant in an Intended Action’.

4.5  Applications made by telephone:

(1) where it is not possible to arrange a hearing, application can be made between 10.00 a.m. and 5.00 p.m. weekdays by telephoning the Royal Courts of Justice on 020 7947 6000 and asking to be put in contact with a High Court Judge of the appropriate Division available to deal with an emergency application in a High Court matter. The appropriate district registry may also be contacted by telephone. In county court proceedings, the appropriate county court should be contacted,

(2) where an application is made outside those hours the applicant should either –

(a) telephone the Royal Courts of Justice on 020 7947 6000 where he will be put in contact with the clerk to the appropriate duty judge in the High Court (or the appropriate area Circuit Judge where known), or

(b) the Urgent Court Business Officer of the appropriate Circuit who will contact the local duty judge,

(3) where the facility is available it is likely that the judge will require a draft order to be faxed to him,

(4) the application notice and evidence in support must be filed with the court on the same or next working day or as ordered, together with two copies of the order for sealing,

(5) injunctions will be heard by telephone only where the applicant is acting by counsel or solicitors.

Orders for injunctions

5.1  Any order for an injunction, unless the court orders otherwise, must contain:

(1) subject to paragraph 5.1B, an undertaking by the applicant to the court to pay any damages which the respondent sustains which the court considers the applicant should pay.

(2) if made without notice to any other party, an undertaking by the applicant to the court to serve on the respondent the application notice, evidence in support and any order made as soon as practicable,

(3) if made without notice to any other party, a return date for a further hearing at which the other party can be present,

(4) if made before filing the application notice, an undertaking to file and pay the appropriate fee on the same or next working day, and

(5) if made before issue of a claim form –

(a) an undertaking to issue and pay the appropriate fee on the same or next working day, or

(b) directions for the commencement of the claim.

5.1A  Subject to paragraph 5.1B, when the court makes an order for an injunction, it should consider whether to require an undertaking by the applicant to pay any damages sustained by a person other than the respondent, including another party to the proceedings or any other person who may suffer loss as a consequence of the order.

5.1B

(1) If in an Aarhus Convention claim the court is satisfied that an injunction is necessary to prevent significant environmental damage and to preserve the factual basis of the proceedings, the court will, in considering whether to require an undertaking by the applicant to pay any damages which the respondent or any other person may sustain as a result and the terms of any such undertaking –

(a) have particular regard to the need for the terms of the order overall not to be such as would make continuing with the claim prohibitively expensive for the applicant; and

(b) make such directions as are necessary to ensure that the case is heard promptly.

(2) ‘Aarhus Convention claim’ has the same meaning as in rule 45.41(2).

5.2  An order for an injunction made in the presence of all parties to be bound by it or made at a hearing of which they have had notice, may state that it is effective until trial or further order.

5.3  Any order for an injunction must set out clearly what the respondent must do or not do.

Freezing injunctions

Orders to restrain disposal of assets worldwide and within England and Wales

6.1  An example of a freezing injunction is annexed to this practice direction.

6.2  This example may be modified as appropriate in any particular case. In particular, the court may, if it considers it appropriate, require the applicant’s solicitors, as well as the applicant, to give undertakings.

Search orders

7.1  The following provisions apply to search orders in addition to those listed above.

The Supervising Solicitor

7.2  The Supervising Solicitor must be experienced in the operation of search orders. A Supervising Solicitor may be contacted either through the Law Society or, for the London area, through the London Solicitors Litigation Association.

Evidence

7.3

(1) the affidavit must state the name, firm and its address, and experience of the Supervising Solicitor, also the address of the premises and whether it is a private or business address, and

(2) the affidavit must disclose very fully the reason the order is sought, including the probability that relevant material would disappear if the order were not made.

Service

7.4

(1) the order must be served personally by the Supervising Solicitor, unless the court otherwise orders, and must be accompanied by the evidence in support and any documents capable of being copied,

(2) confidential exhibits need not be served but they must be made available for inspection by the respondent in the presence of the applicant’s solicitors while the order is carried out and afterwards be retained by the respondent’s solicitors on their undertaking not to permit the respondent –

(a) to see them or copies of them except in their presence, and

(b) to make or take away any note or record of them,

(3) the Supervising Solicitor may be accompanied only by the persons mentioned in the order,

(4) the Supervising Solicitor must explain the terms and effect of the order to the respondent in everyday language and advise him –

(a) of his right to take legal advice and to apply to vary or discharge the order; and

(b) that he may be entitled to avail himself of –

(i) legal professional privilege; and

(ii) the privilege against self-incrimination.

(5) where the Supervising Solicitor is a man and the respondent is likely to be an unaccompanied woman, at least one other person named in the order must be a woman and must accompany the Supervising Solicitor, and

(6) the order may only be served between 9.30 a.m. and 5.30 p.m. Monday to Friday unless the court otherwise orders.

Search and custody of materials

7.5

(1) no material shall be removed unless clearly covered by the terms of the order,

(2) the premises must not be searched and no items shall be removed from them except in the presence of the respondent or a person who appears to be a responsible employee of the respondent,

(3) where copies of documents are sought, the documents should be retained for no more than 2 days before return to the owner,

(4) where material in dispute is removed pending trial, the applicant’s solicitors should place it in the custody of the respondent’s solicitors on their undertaking to retain it in safekeeping and to produce it to the court when required,

(5) in appropriate cases the applicant should insure the material retained in the respondent’s solicitors’ custody,

(6) the Supervising Solicitor must make a list of all material removed from the premises and supply a copy of the list to the respondent,

(7) no material shall be removed from the premises until the respondent has had reasonable time to check the list,

(8) if any of the listed items exists only in computer readable form, the respondent must immediately give the applicant’s solicitors effective access to the computers, with all necessary passwords, to enable them to be searched, and cause the listed items to be printed out,

(9) the applicant must take all reasonable steps to ensure that no damage is done to any computer or data,

(10) the applicant and his representatives may not themselves search the respondent’s computers unless they have sufficient expertise to do so without damaging the respondent’s system,

(11) the Supervising Solicitor shall provide a report on the carrying out of the order to the applicant’s solicitors,

(12) as soon as the report is received the applicant’s solicitors shall –

(a) serve a copy of it on the respondent, and

(b) file a copy of it with the court, and

(13) where the Supervising Solicitor is satisfied that full compliance with paragraph 7.5(7) and (8) above is impracticable, he may permit the search to proceed and items to be removed without compliance with the impracticable requirements.

General

7.6  The Supervising Solicitor must not be an employee or member of the applicant’s firm of solicitors.

7.7  If the court orders that the order need not be served by the Supervising Solicitor, the reason for so ordering must be set out in the order.

7.8  The search order must not be carried out at the same time as a police search warrant.

7.9  There is no privilege against self incrimination in –

(1) Intellectual Property cases in respect of a ‘related offence’ or for the recovery of a ‘related penalty’ as defined in section 72 Senior Courts Act 1981;

(2) proceedings for the recovery or administration of any property, for the execution of a trust or for an account of any property or dealings with property, in relation to –

(a) an offence under the Theft Act 1968 (see section 31 of the Theft Act 1968[6]); or

(b) an offence under the Fraud Act 2006 (see section 13 of the Fraud Act 2006^7) or a related offence within the meaning given by section 13(4) of that Act – that is, conspiracy to defraud or any other offence involving any form of fraudulent conduct or purpose; or

(3) proceedings in which a court is hearing an application for an order under Part IV or Part V of the Children Act 1989 (see section 98 Children Act 1989).

However, the privilege may still be claimed in relation to material or information required to be disclosed by an order, as regards potential criminal proceedings outside those statutory provisions.

7.10  Applications in intellectual property cases should be made in the Chancery Division.

7.11  An example of a Search Order is annexed to this Practice Direction. This example may be modified as appropriate in any particular case.

Delivery-up orders

8.1  The following provisions apply to orders, other than search orders, for delivery up or preservation of evidence or property where it is likely that such an order will be executed at the premises of the respondent or a third party.

8.2  In such cases the court shall consider whether to include in the order for the benefit or protection of the parties similar provisions to those specified above in relation to injunctions and search orders.

Injunctions against third parties

9.1  The following provisions apply to orders which will affect a person other than the applicant or respondent, who:

(1) did not attend the hearing at which the order was made; and

(2) is served with the order.

9.2  Where such a person served with the order requests –

(1) a copy of any materials read by the judge, including material prepared after the hearing at the direction of the judge or in compliance with the order; or

(2) a note of the hearing,

the applicant, or his legal representative, must comply promptly with the request, unless the court orders otherwise.

Annex

THIS ORDER

1.  This is a Freezing Injunction made against [ ] (‘the Respondent’) on [ ] by Mr Justice [ ] on the application of [ ] (‘the Applicant’). The Judge read the Affidavits listed in Schedule A and accepted the undertakings set out in Schedule B at the end of this Order.

2.  This order was made at a hearing without notice to the Respondent. The Respondent has a right to apply to the court to vary or discharge the order – see paragraph 13 below.

3.  There will be a further hearing in respect of this order on [ ] (‘the return date’).

4.  If there is more than one Respondent –

(a) unless otherwise stated, references in this order to ‘the Respondent’ mean both or all of them; and

(b) this order is effective against any Respondent on whom it is served or who is given notice of it.

FREEZING INJUNCTION

[For injunction limited to assets in England and Wales]

5.  Until the return date or further order of the court, the Respondent must not remove from England and Wales or in any way dispose of, deal with or diminish the value of any of his assets which are in England and Wales up to the value of £ .

[For worldwide injunction]

5.  Until the return date or further order of the court, the Respondent must not –

(1) remove from England and Wales any of his assets which are in England and Wales up to the value of £ ; or

(2) in any way dispose of, deal with or diminish the value of any of his assets whether they are in or outside England and Wales up to the same value.

[For either form of injunction]

6.  Paragraph 5 applies to all the Respondent’s assets whether or not they are in his own name and whether they are solely or jointly owned. For the purpose of this order the Respondent’s assets include any asset which he has the power, directly or indirectly, to dispose of or deal with as if it were his own. The Respondent is to be regarded as having such power if a third party holds or controls the asset in accordance with his direct or indirect instructions.

7.  This prohibition includes the following assets in particular –

(a) the property known as [title/address] or the net sale money after payment of any mortgages if it has been sold;

(b) the property and assets of the Respondent’s business [known as [name]] [carried on at [address]] or the sale money if any of them have been sold; and

(c) any money standing to the credit of any bank account including the amount of any cheque drawn on such account which has not been cleared.

[For injunction limited to assets in England and Wales]

8.  If the total value free of charges or other securities (‘unencumbered value’) of the Respondent’s assets in England and Wales exceeds £ , the Respondent may remove any of those assets from England and Wales or may dispose of or deal with them so long as the total unencumbered value of his assets still in England and Wales remains above £ .

[For worldwide injunction]

8.

(1) If the total value free of charges or other securities (‘unencumbered value’) of the Respondent’s assets in England and Wales exceeds £ , the Respondent may remove any of those assets from England and Wales or may dispose of or deal with them so long as the total unencumbered value of the Respondent’s assets still in England and Wales remains above £ .

(2) If the total unencumbered value of the Respondent’s assets in England and Wales does not exceed £ , the Respondent must not remove any of those assets from England and Wales and must not dispose of or deal with any of them. If the Respondent has other assets outside England and Wales, he may dispose of or deal with those assets outside England and Wales so long as the total unencumbered value of all his assets whether in or outside England and Wales remains above £ .

PROVISION OF INFORMATION

9.

(1) Unless paragraph (2) applies, the Respondent must [immediately] [within  hours of service of this order] and to the best of his ability inform the Applicant’s solicitors of all his assets [in England and Wales] [worldwide] [exceeding £ in value] whether in his own name or not and whether solely or jointly owned, giving the value, location and details of all such assets.

(2) If the provision of any of this information is likely to incriminate the Respondent, he may be entitled to refuse to provide it, but is recommended to take legal advice before refusing to provide the information. Wrongful refusal to provide the information is contempt of court and may render the Respondent liable to be imprisoned, fined or have his assets seized.

10.  Within [ ] working days after being served with this order, the Respondent must swear and serve on the Applicant’s solicitors an affidavit setting out the above information.

EXCEPTIONS TO THIS ORDER

11.

(1) This order does not prohibit the Respondent from spending £ a week towards his ordinary living expenses and also £ [or a reasonable sum] on legal advice and representation. [But before spending any money the Respondent must tell the Applicant’s legal representatives where the money is to come from.]

([2) This order does not prohibit the Respondent from dealing with or disposing of any of his assets in the ordinary and proper course of business.]

(3) The Respondent may agree with the Applicant’s legal representatives that the above spending limits should be increased or that this order should be varied in any other respect, but any agreement must be in writing.

(4) The order will cease to have effect if the Respondent –

(a) provides security by paying the sum of £ into court, to be held to the order of the court; or

(b) makes provision for security in that sum by another method agreed with the Applicant’s legal representatives.

COSTS

12.  The costs of this application are reserved to the judge hearing the application on the return date.

VARIATION OR DISCHARGE OF THIS ORDER

13.  Anyone served with or notified of this order may apply to the court at any time to vary or discharge this order (or so much of it as affects that person), but they must first inform the Applicant’s solicitors. If any evidence is to be relied upon in support of the application, the substance of it must be communicated in writing to the Applicant’s solicitors in advance.

INTERPRETATION OF THIS ORDER

14.  A Respondent who is an individual who is ordered not to do something must not do it himself or in any other way. He must not do it through others acting on his behalf or on his instructions or with his encouragement.

15.  A Respondent which is not an individual which is ordered not to do something must not do it itself or by its directors, officers, partners, employees or agents or in any other way.

PARTIES OTHER THAN THE APPLICANT AND RESPONDENT

16.  Effect of this order

It is a contempt of court for any person notified of this order knowingly to assist in or permit a breach of this order. Any person doing so may be imprisoned, fined or have their assets seized.

17.  Set off by banks

This injunction does not prevent any bank from exercising any right of set off it may have in respect of any facility which it gave to the respondent before it was notified of this order.

18.  Withdrawals by the Respondent

No bank need enquire as to the application or proposed application of any money withdrawn by the Respondent if the withdrawal appears to be permitted by this order.

[For worldwide injunction]

19.  Persons outside England and Wales

(1) Except as provided in paragraph (2) below, the terms of this order do not affect or concern anyone outside the jurisdiction of this court.

(2) The terms of this order will affect the following persons in a country or state outside the jurisdiction of this court –

(a) the Respondent or his officer or agent appointed by power of attorney;

(b) any person who –

(i) is subject to the jurisdiction of this court;

(ii) has been given written notice of this order at his residence or place of business within the jurisdiction of this court; and

(iii) is able to prevent acts or omissions outside the jurisdiction of this court which constitute or assist in a breach of the terms of this order; and

(c) anyother person, only to the extent that this order is declared enforceable by or is enforced by a court in that country or state.

[For worldwide injunction]

20.  Assets located outside England and Wales

Nothing in this order shall, in respect of assets located outside England and Wales, prevent any third party from complying with –

(1) what it reasonably believes to be its obligations, contractual or otherwise, under the laws and obligations of the country or state in which those assets are situated or under the proper law of any contract between itself and the Respondent; and

(2) any orders of the courts of that country or state, provided that reasonable notice of any application for such an order is given to the Applicant’s solicitors.

COMMUNICATIONS WITH THE COURT

All communications to the court about this order should be sent to –

[Insert the address and telephone number of the appropriate Court Office]

If the order is made at the Royal Courts of Justice, communications should be addressed as follows –

Where the order is made in the Chancery Division

Room TM 5.07, Royal Courts of Justice, Strand, London WC2A 2LL quoting the case number. The telephone number is 020 7947 6322.

Where the order is made in the Queen's Bench Division

Room WG08, Royal Courts of Justice, Strand, London WC2A 2LL quoting the case number. The telephone number is 020 7947 6010.

Where the order is made in the Commercial Court

Room EB09, Royal Courts of Justice, Strand, London WC2A 2LL quoting the case number. The telephone number is 0207 947 6826.

The offices are open between 10 a.m. and 4.30 p.m. Monday to Friday.

SCHEDULE A

AFFIDAVITS

The Applicant relied on the following affidavits–

[name] [number of affidavit][date sworn][filed on behalf of]

SCHEDULE B

UNDERTAKINGS GIVEN TO THE COURT BY THE APPLICANT

(1)

If the court later finds that this order has caused loss to the Respondent, and decides that the Respondent should be compensated for that loss, the Applicant will comply with any order the court may make.

[(2)

The Applicant will –

(a) on or before [date] cause a written guarantee in the sum of £ to be issued from a bank with a place of business within England or Wales, in respect of any order the court may make pursuant to paragraph (1) above; and

(b) immediately upon issue of the guarantee, cause a copy of it to be served on the Respondent.]

(3)

As soon as practicable the Applicant will issue and serve a claim form [in the form of the draft produced to the court] [claiming the appropriate relief].

(4)

The Applicant will [swear and file an affidavit] [cause an affidavit to be sworn and filed] [substantially in the terms of the draft affidavit produced to the court] [confirming the substance of what was said to the court by the Applicant's counsel/solicitors].

(5)

The Applicant will serve upon the Respondent [together with this order] [as soon as practicable] –

(i) copies of the affidavits and exhibits containing the evidence relied upon by the Applicant, and any other documents provided to the court on the making of the application;

(ii) the claim form; and

(iii) an application notice for continuation of the order.

[(6)

Anyone notified of this order will be given a copy of it by the Applicant's legal representatives.]

(7)

The Applicant will pay the reasonable costs of anyone other than the Respondent which have been incurred as a result of this order including the costs of finding out whether that person holds any of the Respondent's assets and if the court later finds that this order has caused such person loss, and decides that such person should be compensated for that loss, the Applicant will comply with any order the court may make.

(8)

If this order ceases to have effect (for example, if the Respondent provides security or the Applicant does not provide a bank guarantee as provided for above) the Applicant will immediately take all reasonable steps to inform in writing anyone to whom he has given notice of this order, or who he has reasonable grounds for supposing may act upon this order, that it has ceased to have effect.

[(9)

The Applicant will not without the permission of the court use any information obtained as a result of this order for the purpose of any civil or criminal proceedings, either in England and Wales or in any other jurisdiction, other than this claim.]

[(10)

The Applicant will not without the permission of the court seek to enforce this order in any country outside England and Wales [or seek an order of a similar nature including orders conferring a charge or other security against the Respondent or the Respondent's assets].]

NAME AND ADDRESS OF APPLICANT’S LEGAL REPRESENTATIVES

The Applicant’s legal representatives are –

[Name, address, reference, fax and telephone numbers both in and out of office hours and e-mail]

THIS ORDER

1.  This is a Search Order made against [ ] (‘the Respondent’) on [ ] by Mr Justice [ ] on the application of [ ] (‘the Applicant’). The Judge read the Affidavits listed in Schedule F and accepted the undertakings set out in Schedules C, D and E at the end of this order.

2.  This order was made at a hearing without notice to the Respondent. The Respondent has a right to apply to the court to vary or discharge the order – see paragraph 27 below.

3.  There will be a further hearing in respect of this order on [ ] (‘the return date’).

4.  If there is more than one Respondent –

(a) unless otherwise stated, references in this order to ‘the Respondent’ mean both or all of them; and

(b) this order is effective against any Respondent on whom it is served or who is given notice of it.

5.  This order must be complied with by –

(a) the Respondent;

(b) any director, officer, partner or responsible employee of the Respondent; and

(c) if the Respondent is an individual, any other person having responsible control of the premises to be searched.

THE SEARCH

6.  The Respondent must permit the following persons^8–

(a) [ ] (‘the Supervising Solicitor’);

(b) [ ], a solicitor in the firm of [ ], the Applicant’s solicitors; and

(c) up to [ ] other persons[9] being [their identity or capacity] accompanying them,

(together ‘the search party’), to enter the premises mentioned in Schedule A to this order and any other premises of the Respondent disclosed under paragraph 18 below and any vehicles under the Respondent’s control on or around the premises (‘the premises’) so that they can search for, inspect, photograph or photocopy, and deliver into the safekeeping of the Applicant’s solicitors all the documents and articles which are listed in Schedule B to this order (‘the listed items’).

7.  Having permitted the search party to enter the premises, the Respondent must allow the search party to remain on the premises until the search is complete. In the event that it becomes necessary for any of those persons to leave the premises before the search is complete, the Respondent must allow them to re-enter the premises immediately upon their seeking re-entry on the same or the following day in order to complete the search.

RESTRICTIONS ON SEARCH

8.  This order may not be carried out at the same time as a police search warrant.

9.  Before the Respondent allows anybody onto the premises to carry out this order, he is entitled to have the Supervising Solicitor explain to him what it means in everyday language.

10.  The Respondent is entitled to seek legal advice and to ask the court to vary or discharge this order. Whilst doing so, he may ask the Supervising Solicitor to delay starting the search for up to 2 hours or such other longer period as the Supervising Solicitor may permit. However, the Respondent must –

(a) comply with the terms of paragraph 27 below;

(b) not disturb or remove any listed items; and

(c) permit the Supervising Solicitor to enter, but not start to search.

11.

(1) Before permitting entry to the premises by any person other than the Supervising Solicitor, the Respondent may, for a short time (not to exceed two hours, unless the Supervising Solicitor agrees to a longer period) –

(a) gather together any documents he believes may be incriminating or privileged; and

(b) hand them to the Supervising Solicitor for him to assess whether they are incriminating or privileged as claimed.

(2) If the Supervising Solicitor decides that the Respondent is entitled to withhold production of any of the documents on the ground that they are privileged or incriminating, he will exclude them from the search, record them in a list for inclusion in his report and return them to the Respondent.

(3) If the Supervising Solicitor believes that the Respondent may be entitled to withhold production of the whole or any part of a document on the ground that it or part of it may be privileged or incriminating, or if the Respondent claims to be entitled to withhold production on those grounds, the Supervising Solicitor will exclude it from the search and retain it in his possession pending further order of the court.

12.  If the Respondent wishes to take legal advice and gather documents as permitted, he must first inform the Supervising Solicitor and keep him informed of the steps being taken.

13.  No item may be removed from the premises until a list of the items to be removed has been prepared, and a copy of the list has been supplied to the Respondent, and he has been given a reasonable opportunity to check the list.

14.  The premises must not be searched, and items must not be removed from them, except in the presence of the Respondent.

15.  If the Supervising Solicitor is satisfied that full compliance with paragraphs 13 or 14 is not practicable, he may permit the search to proceed and items to be removed without fully complying with them.

DELIVERY UP OF ARTICLES/DOCUMENTS

16.  The Respondent must immediately hand over to the Applicant’s solicitors any of the listed items, which are in his possession or under his control, save for any computer or hard disk integral to any computer. Any items the subject of a dispute as to whether they are listed items must immediately be handed over to the Supervising Solicitor for safe keeping pending resolution of the dispute or further order of the court.

17.  The Respondent must immediately give the search party effective access to the computers on the premises, with all necessary passwords, to enable the computers to be searched. If they contain any listed items the Respondent must cause the listed items to be displayed so that they can be read and copied[10]. The Respondent must provide the Applicant’s Solicitors with copies of all listed items contained in the computers. All reasonable steps shall be taken by the Applicant and the Applicant’s solicitors to ensure that no damage is done to any computer or data. The Applicant and his representatives may not themselves search the Respondent’s computers unless they have sufficient expertise to do so without damaging the Respondent's system.

PROVISION OF INFORMATION

18.  The Respondent must immediately inform the Applicant’s Solicitors (in the presence of the Supervising Solicitor) so far as he is aware –

(a) where all the listed items are;

(b) the name and address of everyone who has supplied him, or offered to supply him, with listed items;

(c) the name and address of everyone to whom he has supplied, or offered to supply, listed items; and

(d) full details of the dates and quantities of every such supply and offer.

19.  Within [ ] working days after being served with this order the Respondent must swear and serve an affidavit setting out the above information^11.

PROHIBITED ACTS

20.  Except for the purpose of obtaining legal advice, the Respondent must not directly or indirectly inform anyone of these proceedings or of the contents of this order, or warn anyone that proceedings have been or may be brought against him by the Applicant until 4.30 p.m. on the return date or further order of the court.

21.  Until 4.30 p.m. on the return date the Respondent must not destroy, tamper with, cancel or part with possession, power, custody or control of the listed items otherwise than in accordance with the terms of this order.

22.

[Insert any negative injunctions.]

23.

[Insert any further order]

COSTS

24.  The costs of this application are reserved to the judge hearing the application on the return date.

RESTRICTIONS ON SERVICE

25.  This order may only be served between [ ] a.m./p.m. and [ ] a.m./p.m. [and on a weekday]12.

26.  This order must be served by the Supervising Solicitor, and paragraph 6 of the order must be carried out in his presence and under his supervision.

VARIATION AND DISCHARGE OF THIS ORDER

27.  Anyone served with or notified of this order may apply to the court at any time to vary or discharge this order (or so much of it as affects that person), but they must first inform the Applicant’s solicitors. If any evidence is to be relied upon in support of the application, the substance of it must be communicated in writing to the Applicant’s solicitors in advance.

INTERPRETATION OF THIS ORDER

28.  Any requirement that something shall be done to or in the presence of the Respondent means –

(a) if there is more than one Respondent, to or in the presence of any one of them; and

(b) if a Respondent is not an individual, to or in the presence of a director, officer, partner or responsible employee.

29.  A Respondent who is an individual who is ordered not to do something must not do it himself or in any other way. He must not do it through others acting on his behalf or on his instructions or with his encouragement.

30.  A Respondent which is not an individual which is ordered not to do something must not do it itself or by its directors, officers, partners, employees or agents or in any other way.

COMMUNICATIONS WITH THE COURT

All communications to the court about this order should be sent to –

[Insert the address and telephone number of the appropriate Court Office]

If the order is made at the Royal Courts of Justice, communications should be addressed as follows –

Where the order is made in the Chancery Division

Room TM 5.07, Royal Courts of Justice, Strand, London WC2A 2LL quoting the case number. The telephone number is 020 7947 6322.

Where the order is made in the Queen's Bench Division

Room WG08, Royal Courts of Justice, Strand, London WC2A 2LL quoting the case number. The telephone number is 020 7947 6010.

Where the order is made in the Commercial Court

Room EB09, Royal Courts of Justice, Strand, London WC2A 2LL quoting the case number. The telephone number is 0207 947 6826.

The offices are open between 10 a.m. and 4.30 p.m. Monday to Friday.

SCHEDULE A

THE PREMISES

SCHEDULE B

THE LISTED ITEMS

SCHEDULE C

UNDERTAKINGS GIVEN TO THE COURT BY THE APPLICANT

(1)

If the court later finds that this order or carrying it out has caused loss to the Respondent, and decides that the Respondent should be compensated for that loss, the Applicant will comply with any order the court may make. Further if the carrying out of this order has been in breach of the terms of this order or otherwise in a manner inconsistent with the Applicant’s solicitors’ duties as officers of the court, the Applicant will comply with any order for damages the court may make.

[(2)

As soon as practicable the Applicant will issue a claim form [in the form of the draft produced to the court] [claiming the appropriate relief].]

(3)

The Applicant will [swear and file an affidavit] [cause an affidavit to be sworn and filed] [substantially in the terms of the draft affidavit produced to the court] [confirming the substance of what was said to the court by the Applicant’s counsel/solicitors].

(4)

The Applicant will not, without the permission of the court, use any information or documents obtained as a result of carrying out this order nor inform anyone else of these proceedings except for the purposes of these proceedings (including adding further Respondents) or commencing civil proceedings in relation to the same or related subject matter to these proceedings until after the return date.

[(5)

The Applicant will maintain pending further order the sum of £ [ ] in an account controlled by the Applicant’s solicitors.]

[(6)

The Applicant will insure the items removed from the premises.]

SCHEDULE D

UNDERTAKINGS GIVEN BY THE APPLICANT'S SOLICITORS

(1)

The Applicant’s solicitors will provide to the Supervising Solicitor for service on the Respondent –

(i) a service copy of this order;

(ii) the claim form (with defendant’s response pack) or, if not issued, the draft produced to the court;

(iii) an application for hearing on the return date;

(iv) copies of the affidavits [or draft affidavits] and exhibits capable of being copied containing the evidence relied upon by the applicant;

(v) a note of any allegation of fact made orally to the court where such allegation is not contained in the affidavits or draft affidavits read by the judge; and

(vi) a copy of the skeleton argument produced to the court by the Applicant’s [counsel/solicitors].

(2)

The Applicants’ solicitors will answer at once to the best of their ability any question whether a particular item is a listed item.

(3)

Subject as provided below the Applicant’s solicitors will retain in their own safe keeping all items obtained as a result of this order until the court directs otherwise.

(4)

The Applicant’s solicitors will return the originals of all documents obtained as a result of this order (except original documents which belong to the Applicant) as soon as possible and in any event within [two] working days of their removal.

SCHEDULE E

UNDERTAKINGS GIVEN BY THE SUPERVISING SOLICITOR

(1)

The Supervising Solicitor will use his best endeavours to serve this order upon the Respondent and at the same time to serve upon the Respondent the other documents required to be served and referred to in paragraph (1) of Schedule D.

(2)

The Supervising Solicitor will offer to explain to the person served with the order its meaning and effect fairly and in everyday language, and to inform him of his right to take legal advice (including an explanation that the Respondent may be entitled to avail himself of the privilege against self-incrimination and legal professional privilege) and to apply to vary or discharge this order as mentioned in paragraph 27 above.

(3)

The Supervising Solicitor will retain in the safe keeping of his firm all items retained by him as a result of this order until the court directs otherwise.

(4)

Unless and until the court otherwise orders, or unless otherwise necessary to comply with any duty to the court pursuant to this order, the Supervising Solicitor shall not disclose to any person any information relating to those items, and shall keep the existence of such items confidential.

(5)

Within [48] hours of completion of the search the Supervising Solicitor will make and provide to the Applicant's solicitors, the Respondent or his solicitors and to the judge who made this order (for the purposes of the court file) a written report on the carrying out of the order.

SCHEDULE F

AFFIDAVITS

The Applicant relied on the following affidavits–

[name] [number of affidavit][date sworn][filed on behalf of]

NAME AND ADDRESS OF APPLICANT’S SOLICITORS

The Applicant’s solicitors are–

[Name, address, reference, fax and telephone numbers both in and out of office hours.]

Footnotes

Rule 25.1(1)(h). Back to text
Rule 25.1(1)(f). Back to text
Rule 23.7(1) and (2) and see rule 23.7(4) (short service). Back to text
See Part 22. Back to text
Rule 25.2(3). Back to text
1968 c. 60. Back to text
2006 c. 35. Back to text
Where the premises are likely to be occupied by an unaccompanied woman and the Supervising Solicitor is a man, at least one of the persons accompanying him should be a woman. Back to text
None of these persons should be people who could gain personally or commercially from anything they might read or see on the premises, unless their presence is essential. Back to text
If it is envisaged that the Respondent’s computers are to be imaged (i.e. the hard drives are to be copied wholesale, thereby reproducing listed items and other items indiscriminately), special provision needs to be made and independent computer specialists need to be appointed, who should be required to give undertakings to the court. Back to text
The period should ordinarily be longer than the period in paragraph (2) of Schedule D, if any of the information is likely to be included in listed items taken away of which the Respondent does not have copies. Back to text
Normally, the order should be served in the morning (not before 9.30 a.m.) and on a weekday to enable the Respondent more readily to obtain legal advice. Back to text

PRACTICE DIRECTION 25B – INTERIM PAYMENTS

This Practice Direction supplements CPR Part 25

Contents of this Practice Direction

Title
General
Evidence
INTERIM PAYMENT WHERE ACCOUNT TO BE TAKEN
Instalments
Compensation Recovery Payments
Adjustment of Final Judgment Figure

General

1.1  Rule 25.7 sets out the conditions to be satisfied and matters to be taken into account before the court will make an order for an interim payment.

1.2  The permission of the court must be obtained before making a voluntary interim payment in respect of a claim by a child or protected party.

(‘Child’ and ‘protected party’ have the same meaning as in rule 21.1(2).)

Evidence

2.1  An application for an interim payment of damages must be supported by evidence dealing with the following:

(1) the sum of money sought by way of an interim payment,

(2) the items or matters in respect of which the interim payment is sought,

(3) the sum of money for which final judgment is likely to be given,

(4) the reasons for believing that the conditions set out in rule 25.7 are satisfied,

(5) any other relevant matters,

(6) in claims for personal injuries, details of special damages and past and future loss, and

(7) in a claim under the Fatal Accidents Act 1976, details of the person(s) on whose behalf the claim is made and the nature of the claim.

2.2  Any documents in support of the application should be exhibited, including, in personal injuries claims, the medical report(s).

2.3  If a respondent to an application for an interim payment wishes to rely on written evidence at the hearing he must comply with the provisions of rule 25.6(4).

2.4  If the applicant wishes to rely on written evidence in reply he must comply with the provisions of rule 25.6(5).

INTERIM PAYMENT WHERE ACCOUNT TO BE TAKEN

2A.1  This section of this practice direction applies if a party seeks an interim payment under rule 25.7(b) where the court has ordered an account to be taken.

2A.2  If the evidence on the application for interim payment shows that the account is bound to result in a payment to the applicant the court will, before making an order for interim payment, order that the liable party pay to the applicant ‘the amount shown by the account to be due’.

Instalments

3  Where an interim payment is to be paid in instalments the order should set out:

(1) the total amount of the payment,

(2) the amount of each instalment,

(3) the number of instalments and the date on which each is to be paid, and

(4) to whom the payment should be made.

Compensation Recovery Payments

4.1  Where in a claim for personal injuries there is an application for an interim payment of damages –

(1) which is other than by consent;

(2) which either –

(i) falls under the heads of damage set out in column 1 of Schedule 2 to the Social Security (Recovery of Benefits) Act 1997 (‘the 1997 Act’) in respect of recoverable benefits received by the claimant set out in column 2 of that Schedule; or

(ii) includes damages in respect of a disease for which a lump sum payment within the definition in section 1A(2) of the 1997 Act has been, or is likely to be made; and

(3) where the defendant is liable to pay a recoverable amount (as defined in rule 36.15(1)(c)) to the Secretary of State,

the defendant should obtain from the Secretary of State a certificate (as defined in rule 36.15(1)(e)).

4.2  A copy of the certificate must be filed at the hearing of the application for an interim payment.

4.3  The order will set out the deductible amount (as defined in rule 36.15(1)(d)).

4.4  The payment made to the claimant will be the net amount but the interim payment for the purposes of paragraph 5 below will be the gross amount.

Adjustment of Final Judgment Figure

5.1  In this paragraph ‘judgment’ means:

(1) any order to pay a sum of money,

(2) a final award of damages,

(3) an assessment of damages.

5.2  In a final judgment where an interim payment has previously been made which is less than the total amount awarded by the judge, the order should set out in a preamble:

(1) the total amount awarded by the judge, and

(2) the amounts and dates of the interim payment(s).

5.3  The total amount awarded by the judge should then be reduced by the total amount of any interim payments, and an order made for entry of judgment and payment of the balance.

5.4  In a final judgment where an interim payment has previously been made which is more than the total amount awarded by the judge, the order should set out in a preamble:

(1) the total amount awarded by the judge, and

(2) the amounts and dates of the interim payment(s).

5.5  An order should then be made for repayment, reimbursement, variation or discharge under rule 25.8(2) and for interest on an overpayment under rule 25.8(5).

5.6  Practice Direction 40B provides further information concerning adjustment of the final judgment sum.

PART 27 - THE SMALL CLAIMS TRACK

Contents of this Part

Title | Number
Scope of this Part | Rule 27.1
Extent to which other Parts apply | Rule 27.2
Court’s power to grant a final remedy | Rule 27.3
Preparation for the hearing | Rule 27.4
Experts | Rule 27.5
Preliminary hearing | Rule 27.6
Power of court to add to, vary or revoke directions | Rule 27.7
Conduct of the hearing | Rule 27.8
Non-attendance of parties at a final hearing | Rule 27.9
Disposal without a hearing | Rule 27.10
Setting judgment aside and re-hearing | Rule 27.11
Costs on the small claims track | Rule 27.14
Claim re-allocated from the small claims track to another track | Rule 27.15

Scope of this Part

27.1

(1) This Part –

(a) sets out the special procedure for dealing with claims which have been allocated to the small claims track under Part 26; and

(b) limits the amount of costs that can be recovered in respect of a claim which has been allocated to the small claims track.

(Rule 27.14 deals with costs on the small claims track)

(2) A claim being dealt with under this Part is called a small claim.

(Rule 26.6 provides for the scope of the small claims track. A claim for a remedy for harassment or unlawful eviction relating, in either case, to residential premises shall not be allocated to the small claims track whatever the financial value of the claim. Otherwise, the small claims track will be the normal track for –

any claim which has a financial value of not more than £10,000 subject to the special provisions about claims for personal injuries and housing disrepair claims;
any claim for personal injuries which has a financial value of not more than £10,000 where the claim for damages for personal injuries is not more than £1,000; and
any claim which includes a claim by a tenant of residential premises against his landlord for repairs or other work to the premises where the estimated cost of the repairs or other work is not more than £1,000 and the financial value of any other claim for damages is not more than £1,000)

Extent to which other Parts apply

27.2

(1) The following Parts of these Rules do not apply to small claims –

(a) Part 25 (interim remedies) except as it relates to interim injunctions(GL);

(b) Part 31 (disclosure and inspection);

(c) Part 32 (evidence) except rule 32.1 (power of court to control evidence);

(d) Part 33 (miscellaneous rules about evidence);

(e) Part 35 (experts and assessors) except rules 35.1 (duty to restrict expert evidence), 35.3 (experts – overriding duty to the court), 35.7 (court’s power to direct that evidence is to be given by single joint expert) and 35.8 (instructions to a single joint expert);

(f) Subject to paragraph (3), Part 18 (further information);

(g) Part 36 (offers to settle); and

(h) Part 39 (hearings) except rule 39.2 (general rule– hearing to be in public).

(2) The other Parts of these Rules apply to small claims except to the extent that a rule limits such application.

(3) The court of its own initiative may order a party to provide further information if it considers it appropriate to do so.

Court’s power to grant a final remedy

27.3  The court may grant any final remedy in relation to a small claim which it could grant if the proceedings were on the fast track or the multi-track.

Preparation for the hearing

27.4

(1) After allocation the court will –

(a) give standard directions and fix a date for the final hearing;

(b) give special directions and fix a date for the final hearing;

(c) give special directions and direct that the court will consider what further directions are to be given no later than 28 days after the date the special directions were given;

(d) fix a date for a preliminary hearing under rule 27.6; or

(e) give notice that it proposes to deal with the claim without a hearing under rule 27.10 and invite the parties to notify the court by a specified date if they agree the proposal.

(2) The court will –

(a) give the parties at least 21 days’ notice of the date fixed for the final hearing, unless the parties agree to accept less notice; and

(b) inform them of the amount of time allowed for the final hearing.

(3) In this rule –

(a) ‘standard directions’ means –

(i) a direction that each party shall, at least 14 days before the date fixed for the final hearing, file and serve on every other party copies of all documents (including any expert’s report) on which he intends to rely at the hearing; and

(ii) any other standard directions set out in Practice Direction 27; and

(b) ‘special directions’ means directions given in addition to or instead of the standard directions.

Experts

27.5  No expert may give evidence, whether written or oral, at a hearing without the permission of the court.

(Rule 27.14(3)(d) provides for the payment of an expert’s fees)

Preliminary hearing

27.6

(1) The court may hold a preliminary hearing for the consideration of the claim, but only –

(a) where –

(i) it considers that special directions, as defined in rule 27.4, are needed to ensure a fair hearing; and

(ii) it appears necessary for a party to attend at court to ensure that he understands what he must do to comply with the special directions; or

(b) to enable it to dispose of the claim on the basis that one or other of the parties has no real prospect of success at a final hearing; or

(c) to enable it to strike out[GL] a statement of case or part of a statement of case on the basis that the statement of case, or the part to be struck out, discloses no reasonable grounds for bringing or defending the claim.

(2) When considering whether or not to hold a preliminary hearing, the court must have regard to the desirability of limiting the expense to the parties of attending court.

(3) Where the court decides to hold a preliminary hearing, it will give the parties at least 14 days’ notice of the date of the hearing.

(4) The court may treat the preliminary hearing as the final hearing of the claim if all the parties agree.

(5) At or after the preliminary hearing the court will–

(a) fix the date of the final hearing (if it has not been fixed already) and give the parties at least 21 days’ notice of the date fixed unless the parties agree to accept less notice;

(b) inform them of the amount of time allowed for the final hearing; and

(c) give any appropriate directions.

Power of court to add to, vary or revoke directions

27.7  The court may add to, vary or revoke directions.

Conduct of the hearing

27.8

(1) The court may adopt any method of proceeding at a hearing that it considers to be fair.

(2) Hearings will be informal.

(3) The strict rules of evidence do not apply.

(4) The court need not take evidence on oath.

(5) The court may limit cross-examination[GL].

(6) The court must give reasons for its decision.

Non-attendance of parties at a final hearing

27.9

(1) If a party who does not attend a final hearing–

(a) has given written notice to the court and the other party at least 7 days before the hearing date that he will not attend;

(b) has served on the other party at least 7 days before the hearing date any other documents which he has filed with the court; and

(c) has, in his written notice, requested the court to decide the claim in his absence and has confirmed his compliance with paragraphs (a) and (b) above,

the court will take into account that party’s statement of case and any other documents he has filed and served when it decides the claim.

(2) If a claimant does not –

(a) attend the hearing; and

(b) give the notice referred to in paragraph (1),

the court may strike out(GL) the claim.

(3) If –

(a) a defendant does not –

(i) attend the hearing; or

(ii) give the notice referred to in paragraph (1); and

(b) the claimant either –

(i) does attend the hearing; or

(ii) gives the notice referred to in paragraph (1),

the court may decide the claim on the basis of the evidence of the claimant alone.

(4) If neither party attends or gives the notice referred to in paragraph (1), the court may strike out the claim and any defence and counterclaim.

Disposal without a hearing

27.10  The court may, if all parties agree, deal with the claim without a hearing.

Setting judgment aside and re-hearing

27.11

(1) A party –

(a) who was neither present nor represented at the hearing of the claim; and

(b) who has not given written notice to the court under rule 27.9(1),

may apply for an order that a judgment under this Part shall be set aside[GL] and the claim re-heard.

(2) A party who applies for an order setting aside a judgment under this rule must make the application not more than 14 days after the day on which notice of the judgment was served on him.

(3) The court may grant an application under paragraph (2) only if the applicant –

(a) had a good reason for not attending or being represented at the hearing or giving written notice to the court under rule 27.9(1); and

(b) has a reasonable prospect of success at the hearing.

(4) If a judgment is set aside –

(a) the court must fix a new hearing for the claim; and

(b) the hearing may take place immediately after the hearing of the application to set the judgment aside and may be dealt with by the judge who set aside the judgment.

(5) A party may not apply to set aside a judgment under this rule if the court dealt with the claim without a hearing under rule 27.10.

Rules 27.12 and 27.13 are revoked.

Costs on the small claims track

27.14

(1) This rule applies to any case which has been allocated to the small claims track unless paragraph (5) applies.

(Rules 46.11 and 46.13 make provision in relation to orders for costs made before a claim has been allocated to the small claims track)

(2) The court may not order a party to pay a sum to another party in respect of that other party’s costs, fees and expenses, including those relating to an appeal, except –

(a) the fixed costs attributable to issuing the claim which –

(i) are payable under Part 45; or

(ii) would be payable under Part 45 if that Part applied to the claim;

(b) in proceedings which included a claim for an injunction or an order for specific performance a sum not exceeding the amount specified in Practice Direction 27 for legal advice and assistance relating to that claim;

(c) any court fees paid by that other party;

(d) expenses which a party or witness has reasonably incurred in travelling to and from a hearing or in staying away from home for the purposes of attending a hearing;

(e) a sum not exceeding the amount specified in Practice Direction 27 for any loss of earnings or loss of leave by a party or witness due to attending a hearing or to staying away from home for the purposes of attending a hearing;

(f) a sum not exceeding the amount specified in Practice Direction 27 for an expert’s fees;

(g) such further costs as the court may assess by the summary procedure and order to be paid by a party who has behaved unreasonably; and

(h) the Stage 1 and, where relevant, the Stage 2 fixed costs in rule 45.18 where –

(i) the claim was within the scope of the Pre-Action Protocol for Low Value Personal Injury Claims in Road Traffic Accidents (‘the RTA Protocol’) or the Pre-action Protocol for Low Value Personal Injury (Employers’ Liability and Public Liability) Claims (‘the EL/PL Protocol’);

(ii) the claimant reasonably believed that the claim was valued at more than the small claims track limit in accordance with paragraph 4.1(4) of the relevant Protocol; and

(iii) the defendant admitted liability under the process set out in the relevant Protocol; but

(iv) the defendant did not pay those Stage 1 and, where relevant, Stage 2 fixed costs; and

(i) in an appeal, the cost of any approved transcript reasonably incurred.

(3) A party’s rejection of an offer in settlement will not of itself constitute unreasonable behaviour under paragraph (2)(g) but the court may take it into consideration when it is applying the unreasonableness test.

(4) The limits on costs imposed by this rule also apply to any fee or reward for acting on behalf of a party to the proceedings charged by a person exercising a right of audience by virtue of an order under section 11 of the Courts and Legal Services Act 1990[1] (a lay representative).

5 Where – a the financial value of a claim exceeds the limit for the small claims track; but b the claim has been allocated to the small claims track in accordance with rule 26.7(3), the small claims track costs provisions will apply unless the parties agree that the fast track costs provisions are to apply.

6 Where the parties agree that the fast track costs provisions are to apply, the claim and any appeal will be treated for the purposes of costs as if it were proceeding on the fast track except that trial costs will be in the discretion of the court and will not exceed the amount set out for the value of claim in rule 46.2 (amount of fast track trial costs).

Claim re-allocated from the small claims track to another track

27.15  Where a claim is allocated to the small claims track and subsequently re-allocated to another track, rule 27.14 (costs on the small claims track) will cease to apply after the claim has been re-allocated and the fast track or multi-track costs rules will apply from the date of re-allocation.

Footnotes

1990 c.41. Back to text

PRACTICE DIRECTION 28 – THE FAST TRACK

This Practice Direction supplements CPR Part 28

Contents of this Practice Direction

Title
General
Case management
Directions on allocation
Variation of directions
Failure to comply with case management directions
Pre-trial check lists (listing questionnaires)
Directions the court will give on listing
The trial
Appendix

General

1.1  Attention is drawn in particular to the following Parts of the Civil Procedure Rules:

Part 1
The overriding objective

Section I of Part 3
The court’s case management powers

Part 26
Case management – preliminary stage

Part 31
Disclosure and inspection of documents

Part 32-34
Evidence

Part 35
Experts and assessors

and to the practice directions which relate to those Parts.

1.2  Attention is also drawn to:

Rule 26.6(5) – which makes provision about limitations on expert evidence and the length of trial in fast track cases.

Section VI of Part 45 – Fast Track Trial Costs

Rule 19.4A and Practice Direction 19A on joining the Crown in certain cases raising Convention rights issues.

Case management

2.1  Case management of cases allocated to the fast track will generally be by directions given at two stages in the case:

(1) at allocation to the track, and

(2) on the filing of pre-trial check lists (listing questionnaires).

2.2  The court will seek whenever possible to give directions at those stages only and to do so without the need for a hearing to take place. It will expect to do so with the co-operation of the parties.

2.3  The court will however hold a hearing to give directions whenever it appears necessary or desirable to do so, and where this happens because of the default of a party or his legal representative it will usually impose a sanction.

2.4  The court may give directions at any hearing on the application of a party or on its own initiative.

2.5  When any hearing has been fixed it is the duty of the parties to consider what directions the court should be asked to give and to make any application that may be appropriate to be dealt with at that hearing.

2.6  When the court fixes a hearing to give directions it will give the parties at least 3 days notice of the hearing.

2.7  Appendix A contains forms of directions. When making an order the court will as far as possible base its order on those forms. Agreed directions which the parties file and invite the court to make should also be based on those forms.

2.8  Where a party needs to apply for a direction of a kind not included in the case management timetable which has been set (for example to amend his statement of case or for further information to be given by another party) he must do so as soon as possible so as to minimise the need to change that timetable.

2.9  Courts will make arrangements to ensure that applications and other hearings are listed promptly to avoid delay in the conduct of cases.

Directions on allocation

3.1  Attention is drawn to the court’s duty under rule 28.2(2) to set a case management timetable and to fix a trial date or a trial period, and to the matters which are to be dealt with by directions under Rule 28.3(1).

3.2  The court will seek to tailor its directions to the needs of the case and the steps of which it is aware that the parties have already taken to prepare the case. In particular it will have regard to the extent to which Practice Direction (Pre-Action Conduct) or any pre-action protocol has or (as the case may be) has not been complied with.

3.3  At this stage the court’s first concern will be to ensure that the issues between the parties be identified and that the necessary evidence is prepared and disclosed.

3.4  The court may have regard to any document filed by a party with their directions questionnaire containing further information provided that the document states either that its contents have been agreed with every other party or that it has been served on every other party and when it was served.

3.5  If:

(1) the parties have filed agreed directions for the management of the case, and

(2) the court considers that the proposals are suitable,

it may approve them and give directions in the terms proposed.

3.6

(1) To obtain the court’s approval the agreed directions must:

(a) set out a timetable by reference to calendar dates for the taking of steps for the preparation of the case,

(b) include a date or a period (the trial period) when it is proposed that the trial will take place,

(c) include provision about disclosure of documents, and

(d) include provision about both factual and expert evidence.

(2) The latest proposed date for the trial or the end of the trial period must be not later than 30 weeks from the date the directions order is made.

(3) The trial period must not be longer than 3 weeks.

(4) The provision in (1)(c) above may:

(a) limit disclosure to standard disclosure between all parties or to less than that, and/or

(b) direct that disclosure will take place by the supply of copy documents without a list, but it must in that case either direct that the parties must serve a disclosure statement with the copies or record that they have agreed to disclose in that way without such a statement.

(5) The provision in (1)(d) may be to the effect that no expert evidence is required.

3.7  Directions agreed by the parties should also where appropriate contain provisions about:

(1) the filing of any reply or amended statement of case that may be required,

(2) dates for the service of requests for further information under Practice Direction 18 and questions to experts under rule 35.6 and when they are to be dealt with,

(3) the disclosure of evidence,

(4) the use of a single joint expert, or in cases where the use of a single expert has not been agreed the exchange and agreement of expert evidence (including whether exchange is to be simultaneous or sequential) and without prejudice discussions of the experts.

3.8  If the court does not approve the agreed directions filed by the parties but decides that it will give directions on its own initiative without a hearing, it will take them into account in deciding what directions to give.

3.9  Where the court is to give directions on its own initiative and it is not aware of any steps taken by the parties other than the service of statements of case, its general approach will be:

(1) to give directions for the filing and service of any further information required to clarify either party’s case,

(2) to direct standard disclosure between the parties,

(3) to direct the disclosure of witness statements by way of simultaneous exchange,

(4) to give directions for a single joint expert unless there is good reason not to do so,

(5) in cases where directions for a single expert are not given:

(a) to direct disclosure of experts’ reports by way of simultaneous exchange, and

(b) if experts’ reports are not agreed, to direct a discussion between the experts for the purpose set out in rule 35.12(1) and the preparation of a report under rule 35.12(3).

3.10

(1) If it appears to the court that the claim is one which will be allocated to the fast track but that it cannot properly give directions on its own initiative or approve agreed directions that have been filed, the court may either:

(a) allocate the claim to the fast track, fix a trial date or trial period and direct that a case management hearing is to be listed and give directions at that hearing, or

(b) direct that an allocation hearing is to be listed and give directions at that hearing.

(2) In either case the hearing will be listed as promptly as possible.

3.11  Where the court is proposing on its own initiative to make an order under rule 35.15 (which gives the court power to appoint an assessor), the court must, unless the parties have consented in writing to the order, list a directions hearing.

3.12  The table set out below contains a typical timetable the court may give for the preparation of the case.

Disclosure | 4 weeks
Exchange of witness statements | 10 weeks
Exchange of experts’ reports | 14 weeks
Sending of pre-trial check lists (listing questionnaires) by the court | 20 weeks
Filing of completed pre-trial check lists | 22 weeks
Hearing | 30 weeks

These periods will run from the date of the notice of allocation.

3.13

(1) Where it considers that some or all of the steps in that timetable are not necessary the court may omit them and direct an earlier trial.

(2) This may happen where the court is informed that Practice Direction (Pre-Action Conduct) or any pre-action protocol has been complied with or that steps which it would otherwise order to be taken have already been taken.

(3) It may also happen where an application (for example for summary judgment or for an injunction) has been heard before allocation and little or no further preparation is required. In such a case the court may dispense with the need for a pre-trial check list.

Variation of directions

4.1  This paragraph deals with the procedure to be adopted:

(1) where a party is dissatisfied with a direction given by the court,

(2) where the parties agree about changes they wish made to the directions given, or

(3) where a party wishes to apply to vary a direction.

4.2

(1) It is essential that any party who wishes to have a direction varied takes steps to do so as soon as possible.

(2) The court will assume for the purposes of any later application that a party who did not appeal and who made no application to vary within 14 days of service of the order containing the directions was content that they were correct in the circumstances then existing.

4.3

(1) Where a party is dissatisfied with a direction given or other order made by the court he may appeal or apply to the court for it to reconsider its decision.

(2) He should appeal if the direction was given or the order was made at a hearing at which he was present or represented, or of which he had due notice.

(3) In any other case he should apply to the court to reconsider its decision.

(4) If an application is made for the court to reconsider its decision:

(a) it will usually be heard by the judge who gave the directions or another judge of the same level,

(b) the court will give all parties at least 3 days notice of the hearing, and

(c) the court may confirm its decision or make a different order.

4.4  Where there has been a change in the circumstances since the order was made the court may set aside or vary any direction it has given. It may do so on application or on its own initiative.

4.5  Where the parties agree about changes to be made to the directions given:

(1) If rule 2.11 (variation by agreement of a date set by the court for doing any act other than those stated in the note to that rule) or rule 31.5, 31.10(8) or 31.13 (agreements about disclosure) applied the parties need not file the written agreement.

(2)

(a) In any other case the parties must apply for an order by consent.

(b) The parties must file a draft of the order sought and an agreed statement of the reasons why the variation is sought.

(c) The court may make an order in the agreed terms or in other terms without a hearing, but it may direct that a hearing is to be listed.

Failure to comply with case management directions

5.1  Where a party has failed to comply with a direction given by the court any other party may apply for an order to enforce compliance or for a sanction to be imposed or both of these.

5.2  The party entitled to apply for such an order must do so without delay but should first warn the other party of his intention to do so.

5.3  The court may take any such delay into account when it decides whether to make an order imposing a sanction or whether to grant relief from a sanction imposed by the rules or any practice direction.

5.4

(1) The court will not allow a failure to comply with directions to lead to the postponement of the trial unless the circumstances of the case are exceptional.

(2) If it is practicable to do so the court will exercise its powers in a manner that enables the case to come on for trial on the date or within the period previously set.

(3) In particular the court will assess what steps each party should take to prepare the case for trial, direct that those steps are taken in the shortest possible time and impose a sanction for non-compliance. Such a sanction may, for example, deprive a party of the right to raise or contest an issue or to rely on evidence to which the direction relates.

(4) Where it appears that one or more issues are or can be made ready for trial at the time fixed while others cannot, the court may direct that the trial will proceed on the issues which are or will then be ready, and order that no costs will be allowed for any later trial of the remaining issues or that those costs will be paid by the party in default.

(5) Where the court has no option but to postpone the trial it will do so for the shortest possible time and will give directions for the taking of the necessary steps in the meantime as rapidly as possible.

(6) Litigants and lawyers must be in no doubt that the court will regard the postponement of a trial as an order of last resort. The court may exercise its power to require a party as well as his legal representative to attend court at a hearing where such an order is to be sought.

Pre-trial check lists (listing questionnaires)

6.1

(1) The pre-trial check list (listing questionnaire) will be in Form N170.

(2) Unless it has dispensed with pre-trial check lists, the court will send Forms N170 and N171 (Notice of date for return of the pre-trial check list) to each party no later than 2 weeks before the date specified in the notice of allocation or in any later direction of the court for the return of the completed check lists.

(3) When all the pre-trial check lists have been filed or when the time for filing them has expired and where a party has filed a pre-trial checklist but another party has not done so, the file will be placed before a judge for his directions.

(4) Although the Rules do not require the parties to exchange copies of the check lists before they are filed they are encouraged to do so to avoid the court being given conflicting or incomplete information.

Attention is drawn to the Costs Practice Direction, Section 6, which requires a costs estimate to be filed and served at the same time as the pre-trial check list is filed.

6.2  Attention is drawn to rule 28.6(1) (which sets out the court’s duty at the pre-trial check list stage) and to rule 28.5(4) (which sets out circumstances in which the court may decide to hold a hearing).

6.3  Where the judge decides to hold a hearing under rule 28.5(4) the court will fix a date which is as early as possible and the parties will be given at least 3 days’ notice of the date.

The notice of such a hearing will be in Form N153.

6.4  The court’s general approach will be as set out in the following paragraphs. The court may however decide to make other orders, and in particular the court will take into account the steps, if any, which the parties have taken to prepare the case for trial.

6.5

(1) Where no party files a pre-trial checklist the court will order that unless a completed pre-trial checklist is filed within 7 days from service of that order, the claim, defence and any counterclaim will be struck out without further order of the court.

(2) Where a party files a pre-trial check list but another party does not do so, the court normally will give directions. These will usually fix or confirm the trial date and provide for steps to be taken to prepare the case for trial.

Directions the court will give on listing

7.1  Directions the court must give:

(1) The court must confirm or fix the trial date, specify the place of trial and give a time estimate. The trial date must be fixed and the case listed on the footing that the hearing will end on the same calendar day as that on which it commenced.

(2) The court will serve a notice of hearing on the parties at least 3 weeks before the hearing unless they agree to accept shorter notice or the court authorises shorter service under rule 28.6(2), and

(3) The notice of hearing will be in Form N172.

7.2  Other directions:

(1) The parties should seek to agree directions and may file the proposed order. The court may make an order in those terms or it may make a different order.

(2) Agreed directions should include provision about:

(a) evidence,

(b) a trial timetable and time estimate,

(c) the preparation of a trial bundle,

(d) any other matter needed to prepare the case for trial.

(3) The court will include such of these provisions as are appropriate in any order that it may make, whether or not the parties have filed agreed directions.

(4)

(a) A direction giving permission to use expert evidence will say whether it gives permission for oral evidence or reports or both and will name the experts concerned.

(b) The court will not make a direction giving permission for an expert to give oral evidence unless it believes it is necessary in the interests of justice to do so.

(c) Where no ‘without prejudice’ meeting or other discussion between experts has taken place the court may grant that permission conditionally on such a discussion taking place and a report being filed before the trial.

7.3  The principles set out in paragraph 4 of this practice direction about the variation of directions apply also to directions given at this stage.

The trial

8.1  The trial will normally take place at the court where the case is being managed, but it may be at another court if it is appropriate having regard to the needs of the parties and the availability of court resources.

8.2  The judge will generally have read the papers in the trial bundle and may dispense with an opening address.

8.3  The judge may confirm or vary any timetable given previously, or if none has been given set his own.

8.4  Attention is drawn to the provisions in Part 32 and the following parts of the Rules about evidence, and in particular –

(1) to rule 32.1 (court’s power to control evidence and to restrict cross-examination), and

(2) to rule 32.5(2) (witness statements to stand as evidence in chief).

8.5  At the conclusion of the trial the judge will normally summarily assess the costs of the claim in accordance with rule 44.6 and Section VI of Part 45 (fast track trial costs). Attention is drawn to the steps the practice directions about costs requires the parties to take.

8.6  Where a trial is not finished on the day for which it is listed the judge will normally sit on the next court day to complete it.

Appendix : FAST TRACK STANDARD DIRECTIONS

Further statements of case

The                        must file a                        and serve a copy on                        no later than                        .

Requests for further information

Any request for clarification or further information based on another party’s statement of case shall be served no later than

[Any such request shall be dealt with no later than ].

Disclosure of documents

[No disclosure of documents is required]

[[Each party] [The                        ]

shall give [to the                        ]

[to every other party] standard disclosure of documents

[relating to                        ]

by serving copies together with a disclosure statement no

later than                        ]

[Disclosure shall take place as follows:

[Each party shall give standard discovery to every other party by list]

[Disclosure is limited to [standard] [disclosure by the

to the                        ] [of documents relating to damage]

[the following documents                        ]

[The latest date for delivery of the lists is                        ]

[The latest date for service of any request to inspect or for a copy

of a document is                        ]]

Witnesses of fact

Each party shall serve on every other party the witness statements of all witnesses of fact on whom he intends to rely.

There shall be simultaneous exchange of such statements no later than

Expert evidence

[No expert evidence being necessary, no party has permission to call or rely on expert evidence].

[On it appearing to the court that expert evidence is necessary on the issue of

[                        ]

and that that evidence should be given by the report of a single expert instructed jointly by the parties, the                                        shall no later than                        inform the court whether or not such an expert has been instructed].

[The expert evidence on the issue of                        shall be                    limited to a single expert                    jointly instructed by the parties.

If the parties cannot agree by                    who that expert is to be and about the payment of his fees either party may apply for further directions.

Unless the parties agree in writing or the court orders otherwise, the fees and expenses of such an expert shall be paid to him [by the parties equally] [                        ] and be limited to £      .

[The report of the expert shall be filed at the court no later than                        ].

[No party shall be entitled to recover by way of costs from any other party more than £      for the fees or                        expenses of an expert].

The parties shall exchange reports setting out the substance of any expert evidence on which they intend to rely.

[The exchange shall take place simultaneously no later than                        ].

[The                                        shall serve his report(s) no later than the                        and the                        shall serve his reports no later than the                        ].

[The exchange of reports relating to [causation] [                        ] shall take place simultaneously no later than                        .

The                        shall serve his report(s) relating to [damage] [                        ] no later than and the                        shall serve his reports relating to it no later than                        ].

Reports shall be agreed if possible no later than [      days after service] [       ].

[If the reports are not agreed within that time there shall be a without prejudice discussion between the relevant experts no later than                        to identify the                        issues between them and to reach agreement if possible.

The experts shall prepare for the court a statement of the issues on which they agree and on which they disagree with a summary of their reasons, and that statement shall be filed with the court [no later than                        ] [with] [no later than the date for filing] [the pre-trial check list].

[Each party has permission to use [                        ] as expert witness(es) to give [oral] evidence [in the form of a                        report] at the trial in the field of                        provided that the substance of the evidence to be given has been disclosed as above and has not been agreed].

[Each party has permission to use in evidence                        experts’ report(s) [and the court will consider when the claim is listed for trial whether expert oral evidence will be allowed].]

(see paragraphs 6, 7 and 9 of Practice Direction 35)

Questions to experts

The time for service on another party of any question addressed to an expert instructed by that party is not later than          days after service of that expert’s report.

Any such question shall be answered within          days of service.

Requests for information etc.

Each party shall serve any request for clarification or further information based on any document disclosed or statement served by another party no later than          days after disclosure or service.

Any such request shall be dealt with within          days of service.

Documents to be filed with pre-trial check lists

The parties must file with their listing questionnaires copies of [their experts’ reports] [witness statements] [replies to requests for further information]

Dates for filing pre-trial check lists and the trial

Each party must file a completed pre-trial check list no later than                                        .

The trial of this case will take place [on                    ] [on a date to be fixed between                    and                    ].

Directions following filing of pre-trial check list

Expert evidence

The parties have permission to rely at the trial on expert evidence as follows:

The claimant: | Oral evidence –
| Written evidence –
The defendant: | Oral evidence –

| Written evidence –

Trial timetable

The time allowed for the trial is

[The timetable for the trial may be agreed by the parties, subject to the approval of the trial judge].

[The timetable for the trial (subject to the approval of the trial judge) will be that                        ].

[The evidence in chief for each party will be contained in witness statements and reports, the time allowed for cross-examination by the defendant is limited to                        and the time allowed for cross-examination by the claimant is limited to                        ].

[The time allowed for the claimant’s evidence is                        . The time allowed for the defendant’s evidence is                        ].

The time allowed for the submissions on behalf of each party is                        .

The remainder of the time allowed for the trial (being                        ) is reserved for the judge to consider and give the judgment and to deal with costs].

Trial bundle etc.

The claimant shall lodge an indexed bundle of documents contained in a ring binder and with each page clearly numbered at the court not more than 7 days and not less than 3 days before the start of the trial.

[A case summary (which should not exceed 250 words) outlining the matters still in issue, and referring where appropriate to the relevant documents shall be included in the bundle for the assistance of the judge in reading the papers before the trial].

[The parties shall seek to agree the contents of the trial bundle and the case summary].

Settlement

Each party must inform the court immediately if the claim is settled whether or not it is then possible to file a draft consent order to give effect to their agreement.

PART 31 - DISCLOSURE AND INSPECTION OF DOCUMENTS

Contents of this Part

Scope of this Part

31.1

(1) This Part sets out rules about the disclosure and inspection of documents.

(2) This Part applies to all claims except a claim on the small claims track.

Meaning of disclosure

31.2  A party discloses a document by stating that the document exists or has existed.

Right of inspection of a disclosed document

31.3

(1) A party to whom a document has been disclosed has a right to inspect that document except where –

(a) the document is no longer in the control of the party who disclosed it;

(b) the party disclosing the document has a right or a duty to withhold inspection of it;

(c) paragraph (2) applies; or

(d) rule 78.26 applies.

(Rule 31.8 sets out when a document is in the control of a party)

(Rule 31.19 sets out the procedure for claiming a right or duty to withhold inspection)

(Rule 78.26 contains rules in relation to the disclosure and inspection of evidence arising out of mediation of certain cross-border disputes.)

(2) Where a party considers that it would be disproportionate to the issues in the case to permit inspection of documents within a category or class of document disclosed under rule 31.6(b) –

(a) he is not required to permit inspection of documents within that category or class; but

(b) he must state in his disclosure statement that inspection of those documents will not be permitted on the grounds that to do so would be disproportionate.

(Rule 31.6 provides for standard disclosure)

(Rule 31.10 makes provision for a disclosure statement)

(Rule 31.12 provides for a party to apply for an order for specific inspection of documents)

Meaning of document

31.4  In this Part –

‘document’ means anything in which information of any description is recorded; and

‘copy’, in relation to a document, means anything onto which information recorded in the document has been copied, by whatever means and whether directly or indirectly.

Disclosure

31.5

(1) In all claims to which rule 31.5(2) does not apply –

(a) an order to give disclosure is an order to give standard disclosure unless the court directs otherwise;

(b) the court may dispense with or limit standard disclosure; and

(c) the parties may agree in writing to dispense with or to limit standard disclosure.

(2) Unless the court otherwise orders, paragraphs (3) to (8) apply to all multi-track claims, other than those which include a claim for personal injuries.

(3) Not less than 14 days before the first case management conference each party must file and serve a report verified by a statement of truth, which –

(a) describes briefly what documents exist or may exist that are or may be relevant to the matters in issue in the case;

(b) describes where and with whom those documents are or may be located;

(c) in the case of electronic documents, describes how those documents are stored;

(d) estimates the broad range of costs that could be involved in giving standard disclosure in the case, including the costs of searching for and disclosing any electronically stored documents; and

(e) states which of the directions under paragraphs (7) or (8) are to be sought.

(4) In cases where the Electronic Documents Questionnaire has been exchanged, the Questionnaire should be filed with the report required by paragraph (3).

(5) Not less than seven days before the first case management conference, and on any other occasion as the court may direct, the parties must, at a meeting or by telephone, discuss and seek to agree a proposal in relation to disclosure that meets the overriding objective.

(6) If –

(a) the parties agree proposals for the scope of disclosure; and

(b) the court considers that the proposals are appropriate in all the circumstances,

the court may approve them without a hearing and give directions in the terms proposed.

(7) At the first or any subsequent case management conference, the court will decide, having regard to the overriding objective and the need to limit disclosure to that which is necessary to deal with the case justly, which of the following orders to make in relation to disclosure –

(a) an order dispensing with disclosure;

(b) an order that a party disclose the documents on which it relies, and at the same time request any specific disclosure it requires from any other party;

(c) an order that directs, where practicable, the disclosure to be given by each party on an issue by issue basis;

(d) an order that each party disclose any documents which it is reasonable to suppose may contain information which enables that party to advance its own case or to damage that of any other party, or which leads to an enquiry which has either of those consequences;

(e) an order that a party give standard disclosure;

(f) any other order in relation to disclosure that the court considers appropriate.

(8) The court may at any point give directions as to how disclosure is to be given, and in particular –

(a) what searches are to be undertaken, of where, for what, in respect of which time periods and by whom and the extent of any search for electronically stored documents;

(b) whether lists of documents are required;

(c) how and when the disclosure statement is to be given;

(d) in what format documents are to be disclosed (and whether any identification is required);

(e) what is required in relation to documents that once existed but no longer exist; and

(f) whether disclosure shall take place in stages.

(9) To the extent that the documents to be disclosed are electronic, the provisions of Practice Direction 31B – Disclosure of Electronic Documents will apply in addition to paragraphs (3) to (8).

Standard disclosure – what documents are to be disclosed

31.6  Standard disclosure requires a party to disclose only–

(a) the documents on which he relies; and

(b) the documents which –

(i) adversely affect his own case;

(ii) adversely affect another party’s case; or

(iii) support another party’s case; and

(c) the documents which he is required to disclose by a relevant practice direction.

Duty of search

31.7

(1) When giving standard disclosure, a party is required to make a reasonable search for documents falling within rule 31.6(b) or (c).

(2) The factors relevant in deciding the reasonableness of a search include the following –

(a) the number of documents involved;

(b) the nature and complexity of the proceedings;

(c) the ease and expense of retrieval of any particular document; and

(d) the significance of any document which is likely to be located during the search.

(3) Where a party has not searched for a category or class of document on the grounds that to do so would be unreasonable, he must state this in his disclosure statement and identify the category or class of document.

(Rule 31.10 makes provision for a disclosure statement)

Duty of disclosure limited to documents which are or have been in a party’s control

31.8

(1) A party’s duty to disclose documents is limited to documents which are or have been in his control.

(2) For this purpose a party has or has had a document in his control if –

(a) it is or was in his physical possession;

(b) he has or has had a right to possession of it; or

(c) he has or has had a right to inspect or take copies of it.

Disclosure of copies

31.9

(1) A party need not disclose more than one copy of a document.

(2) A copy of a document that contains a modification, obliteration or other marking or feature –

(a) on which a party intends to rely; or

(b) which adversely affects his own case or another party’s case or supports another party’s case;

shall be treated as a separate document.

(Rule 31.4 sets out the meaning of a copy of a document)

Procedure for standard disclosure

31.10

(1) The procedure for standard disclosure is as follows.

(2) Each party must make and serve on every other party, a list of documents in the relevant practice form.

(3) The list must identify the documents in a convenient order and manner and as concisely as possible.

(4) The list must indicate –

(a) those documents in respect of which the party claims a right or duty to withhold inspection; and

(b)

(i) those documents which are no longer in the party’s control; and

(ii) what has happened to those documents.

(Rule 31.19 (3) and (4) require a statement in the list of documents relating to any documents inspection of which a person claims he has a right or duty to withhold)

(5) The list must include a disclosure statement.

(6) A disclosure statement is a statement made by the party disclosing the documents –

(a) setting out the extent of the search that has been made to locate documents which he is required to disclose;

(b) certifying that he understands the duty to disclose documents; and

(c) certifying that to the best of his knowledge he has carried out that duty.

(7) Where the party making the disclosure statement is a company, firm, association or other organisation, the statement must also–

(a) identify the person making the statement; and

(b) explain why he is considered an appropriate person to make the statement.

(8) The parties may agree in writing –

(a) to disclose documents without making a list; and

(b) to disclose documents without the disclosing party making a disclosure statement.

(9) A disclosure statement may be made by a person who is not a party where this is permitted by a relevant practice direction.

Duty of disclosure continues during proceedings

31.11

(1) Any duty of disclosure continues until the proceedings are concluded.

(2) If documents to which that duty extends come to a party’s notice at any time during the proceedings, he must immediately notify every other party.

Specific disclosure or inspection

31.12

(1) The court may make an order for specific disclosure or specific inspection.

(2) An order for specific disclosure is an order that a party must do one or more of the following things –

(a) disclose documents or classes of documents specified in the order;

(b) carry out a search to the extent stated in the order;

(c) disclose any documents located as a result of that search.

(3) An order for specific inspection is an order that a party permit inspection of a document referred to in rule 31.3(2).

(Rule 31.3(2) allows a party to state in his disclosure statement that he will not permit inspection of a document on the grounds that it would be disproportionate to do so)

(Rule 78.26 contains rules in relation to the disclosure and inspection of evidence arising out of mediation of certain cross-border disputes.)

Disclosure in stages

31.13  The parties may agree in writing, or the court may direct, that disclosure or inspection or both shall take place in stages.

Documents referred to in statements of case etc.

31.14

(1) A party may inspect a document mentioned in –

(a) a statement of case;

(b) a witness statement;

(c) a witness summary; or

(d) an affidavit(GL).

(e) Revoked.

(2) Subject to rule 35.10(4), a party may apply for an order for inspection of any document mentioned in an expert's report which has not already been disclosed in the proceedings.

(Rule 35.10(4) makes provision in relation to instructions referred to in an expert’s report)

Inspection and copying of documents

31.15  Where a party has a right to inspect a document–

(a) that party must give the party who disclosed the document written notice of his wish to inspect it;

(b) the party who disclosed the document must permit inspection not more than 7 days after the date on which he received the notice; and

(c) that party may request a copy of the document and, if he also undertakes to pay reasonable copying costs, the party who disclosed the document must supply him with a copy not more than 7 days after the date on which he received the request.

(Rule 31.3 and 31.14 deal with the right of a party to inspect a document)

Disclosure before proceedings start

31.16

(1) This rule applies where an application is made to the court under any Act for disclosure before proceedings have started^1.

(2) The application must be supported by evidence.

(3) The court may make an order under this rule only where–

(a) the respondent is likely to be a party to subsequent proceedings;

(b) the applicant is also likely to be a party to those proceedings;

(c) if proceedings had started, the respondent’s duty by way of standard disclosure, set out in rule 31.6, would extend to the documents or classes of documents of which the applicant seeks disclosure; and

(d) disclosure before proceedings have started is desirable in order to –

(i) dispose fairly of the anticipated proceedings;

(ii) assist the dispute to be resolved without proceedings; or

(iii) save costs.

(4) An order under this rule must –

(a) specify the documents or the classes of documents which the respondent must disclose; and

(b) require him, when making disclosure, to specify any of those documents –

(i) which are no longer in his control; or

(ii) in respect of which he claims a right or duty to withhold inspection.

(5) Such an order may –

(a) require the respondent to indicate what has happened to any documents which are no longer in his control; and

(b) specify the time and place for disclosure and inspection.

(Rule 78.26 contains rules in relation to the disclosure and inspection of evidence arising out of mediation of certain cross-border disputes.)

Orders for disclosure against a person not a party

31.17

(1) This rule applies where an application is made to the court under any Act for disclosure by a person who is not a party to the proceedings[2].

(2) The application must be supported by evidence.

(3) The court may make an order under this rule only where–

(a) the documents of which disclosure is sought are likely to support the case of the applicant or adversely affect the case of one of the other parties to the proceedings; and

(b) disclosure is necessary in order to dispose fairly of the claim or to save costs.

(4) An order under this rule must –

(a) specify the documents or the classes of documents which the respondent must disclose; and

(b) require the respondent, when making disclosure, to specify any of those documents –

(i) which are no longer in his control; or

(ii) in respect of which he claims a right or duty to withhold inspection.

(5) Such an order may –

(a) require the respondent to indicate what has happened to any documents which are no longer in his control; and

(b) specify the time and place for disclosure and inspection.

Rule 78.26 contains rules in relation to the disclosure and inspection of evidence arising out of mediation of certain cross-border disputes.)

Rules not to limit other powers of the court to order disclosure

31.18  Rules 31.16 and 31.17 do not limit any other power which the court may have to order –

(a) disclosure before proceedings have started; and

(b) disclosure against a person who is not a party to proceedings.

Claim to withhold inspection or disclosure of a document

31.19

(1) A person may apply, without notice, for an order permitting him to withhold disclosure of a document on the ground that disclosure would damage the public interest.

(2) Unless the court orders otherwise, an order of the court under paragraph (1) –

(a) must not be served on any other person; and

(b) must not be open to inspection by any person.

(3) A person who wishes to claim that he has a right or a duty to withhold inspection of a document, or part of a document, must state in writing –

(a) that he has such a right or duty; and

(b) the grounds on which he claims that right or duty.

(4) The statement referred to in paragraph (3) must be made–

(a) in the list in which the document is disclosed; or

(b) if there is no list, to the person wishing to inspect the document.

(5) A party may apply to the court to decide whether a claim made under paragraph (3) should be upheld.

(6) For the purpose of deciding an application under paragraph (1) (application to withhold disclosure) or paragraph (3) (claim to withhold inspection) the court may –

(a) require the person seeking to withhold disclosure or inspection of a document to produce that document to the court; and

(b) invite any person, whether or not a party, to make representations.

(7) An application under paragraph (1) or paragraph (5) must be supported by evidence.

(8) This Part does not affect any rule of law which permits or requires a document to be withheld from disclosure or inspection on the ground that its disclosure or inspection would damage the public interest.

Restriction on use of a privileged document inspection of which has been inadvertently allowed

31.20  Where a party inadvertently allows a privileged(GL) document to be inspected, the party who has inspected the document may use it or its contents only with the permission of the court.

Consequence of failure to disclose documents or permit inspection

31.21  A party may not rely on any document which he fails to disclose or in respect of which he fails to permit inspection unless the court gives permission.

Subsequent use of disclosed documents and completed Electronic Documents Questionnaires

31.22

(1) A party to whom a document has been disclosed may use the document only for the purpose of the proceedings in which it is disclosed, except where –

(a) the document has been read to or by the court, or referred to, at a hearing which has been held in public;

(b) the court gives permission; or

(c) the party who disclosed the document and the person to whom the document belongs agree.

(2) The court may make an order restricting or prohibiting the use of a document which has been disclosed, even where the document has been read to or by the court, or referred to, at a hearing which has been held in public.

(3) An application for such an order may be made –

(a) by a party; or

(b) by any person to whom the document belongs.

(4) For the purpose of this rule, an Electronic Documents Questionnaire which has been completed and served by another party pursuant to Practice Direction 31B is to be treated as if it is a document which has been disclosed.

False disclosure statements

31.23

(1) Proceedings for contempt of court may be brought against a person if he makes, or causes to be made, a false disclosure statement, without an honest belief in its truth.

(Section 6 of Part 81 contains provisions in relation to committal for making a false disclosure statement.)

2 Proceedings under this rule may be brought only – a by the Attorney General; or b with the permission of the court.

Footnotes

An application for disclosure before proceedings have started is permitted under section 33 of the Supreme Court Act 1981 (c.54) or section 52 of the County Courts Act 1984 (c.28). Back to text
An application for disclosure against a person who is not a party to proceedings is permitted under section 34 of the Supreme Court Act 1981 (c.54) or section 53 of the County Courts Act 1984 (c.28). Back to text

PRACTICE DIRECTION 32 – EVIDENCE

This Practice Direction supplements CPR Part 32

Contents of this Practice Direction

EVIDENCE IN GENERAL

1.1  Rule 32.2 sets out how evidence is to be given and facts are to be proved.

1.2  Evidence at a hearing other than the trial should normally be given by witness statement[1] (see paragraph 17 onwards). However a witness may give evidence by affidavit if he wishes to do so^2 (and see paragraph 1.4 below).

1.3  Statements of case (see paragraph 26 onwards) and application notices[3] may also be used as evidence provided that their contents have been verified by a statement of truth^4.

(For information regarding evidence by deposition see Part 34 and Practice Direction 34A.)

1.4  Affidavits must be used as evidence in the following instances:

(1) where sworn evidence is required by an enactment[5], rule, order or practice direction, and

(2) in any application for a search order, a freezing injunction, or an order requiring an occupier to permit another to enter his land.

(Part 81 - Applications and proceedings in relation to contempt of court, and the Practice Direction accompanying that Part, contain provisions about evidence in relation to contempt of court. Particular attention is drawn to rules 81.10, 81.11, 81.14, 81.15, 81.26 and Practice Direction 81 paragraphs 4.5 and 14.1.)

3 in any application for an order against anyone for alleged contempt of court.

1.5  If a party believes that sworn evidence is required by a court in another jurisdiction for any purpose connected with the proceedings, he may apply to the court for a direction that evidence shall be given only by affidavit on any pre-trial applications.

1.6  The court may give a direction under rule 32.15 that evidence shall be given by affidavit instead of or in addition to a witness statement or statement of case:

(1) on its own initiative, or

(2) after any party has applied to the court for such a direction.

1.7  An affidavit, where referred to in the Civil Procedure Rules or a practice direction, also means an affirmation unless the context requires otherwise.

AFFIDAVITS

Deponent

2  A deponent is a person who gives evidence by affidavit or affirmation.

Heading

3.1  The affidavit should be headed with the title of the proceedings (see paragraph 4 of Practice Direction 7A and paragraph 7 of Practice Direction 20); where the proceedings are between several parties with the same status it is sufficient to identify the parties as follows:

3.2  At the top right hand corner of the first page (and on the backsheet) there should be clearly written:

(1) the party on whose behalf it is made,

(2) the initials and surname of the deponent,

(3) the number of the affidavit in relation to that deponent,

(4) the identifying initials and number of each exhibit referred to, and

(5) the date sworn.

Body of affidavit

4.1  The affidavit must, if practicable, be in the deponent’s own words, the affidavit should be expressed in the first person and the deponent should:

(1) commence ‘I (full name) of (address) state on oath ……’,

(2) if giving evidence in his professional, business or other occupational capacity, give the address at which he works in (1) above, the position he holds and the name of his firm or employer,

(3) give his occupation or, if he has none, his description, and

(4) state if he is a party to the proceedings or employed by a party to the proceedings, if it be the case.

4.2  An affidavit must indicate:

(1) which of the statements in it are made from the deponent’s own knowledge and which are matters of information or belief, and

(2) the source for any matters of information or belief.

4.3  Where a deponent:

(1) refers to an exhibit or exhibits, he should state‘there is now shown to me marked ‘…’ the (description of exhibit)’, and

(2) makes more than one affidavit (to which there are exhibits) in the same proceedings, the numbering of the exhibits should run consecutively throughout and not start again with each affidavit.

Jurat

5.1  The jurat of an affidavit is a statement set out at the end of the document which authenticates the affidavit.

5.2  It must:

(1) be signed by all deponents,

(2) be completed and signed by the person before whom the affidavit was sworn whose name and qualification must be printed beneath his signature,

(3) contain the full address of the person before whom the affidavit was sworn, and

(4) follow immediately on from the text and not be put on a separate page.

Format of affidavits

6.1  An affidavit should:

(1) be produced on durable quality A4 paper with a 3.5cm margin,

(2) be fully legible and should normally be typed on one side of the paper only,

(3) where possible, be bound securely in a manner which would not hamper filing, or otherwise each page should be endorsed with the case number and should bear the initials of the deponent and of the person before whom it was sworn,

(4) have the pages numbered consecutively as a separate document (or as one of several documents contained in a file),

(5) be divided into numbered paragraphs,

(6) have all numbers, including dates, expressed in figures, and

(7) give the reference to any document or documents mentioned either in the margin or in bold text in the body of the affidavit.

6.2  It is usually convenient for an affidavit to follow the chronological sequence of events or matters dealt with; each paragraph of an affidavit should as far as possible be confined to a distinct portion of the subject.

Inability of Deponent to read or sign affidavit

7.1  Where an affidavit is sworn by a person who is unable to read or sign it, the person before whom the affidavit is sworn must certify in the jurat that:

(1) he read the affidavit to the deponent,

(2) the deponent appeared to understand it, and

(3) the deponent signed or made his mark, in his presence.

7.2  If that certificate is not included in the jurat, the affidavit may not be used in evidence unless the court is satisfied that it was read to the deponent and that he appeared to understand it. Two versions of the form of jurat with the certificate are set out at Annex 1 to this practice direction.

Alterations to affidavits

8.1  Any alteration to an affidavit must be initialled by both the deponent and the person before whom the affidavit was sworn.

8.2  An affidavit which contains an alteration that has not been initialled may be filed or used in evidence only with the permission of the court.

Who may administer oaths and take affidavits

9.1  Only the following may administer oaths and take affidavits –

(1) a commissioner for oaths[6];

(2) omitted;

(3) other persons specified by statute[7];

(4) certain officials of the Senior Courts[8];

(5) a circuit judge or district judge^9;

(6) any justice of the peace[10]; and

(7) certain officials of any county court appointed by the judge of that court for the purpose[11].

9.2  An affidavit must be sworn before a person independent of the parties or their representatives.

Filing of affidavits

10.1  If the court directs that an affidavit is to be filed^12, it must be filed in the court or Division, or Office or Registry of the court or Division where the action in which it was or is to be used, is proceeding or will proceed.

10.2  Where an affidavit is in a foreign language:

(1) the party wishing to rely on it –

(a) must have it translated, and

(b) must file the foreign language affidavit with the court, and

(2) the translator must make and file with the court an affidavit verifying the translation and exhibiting both the translation and a copy of the foreign language affidavit.

EXHIBITS

Manner of exhibiting documents

11.1  A document used in conjunction with an affidavit should be:

(1) produced to and verified by the deponent, and remain separate from the affidavit, and

(2) identified by a declaration of the person before whom the affidavit was sworn.

11.2  The declaration should be headed with the name of the proceedings in the same way as the affidavit.

11.3  The first page of each exhibit should be marked:

(1) as in paragraph 3.2 above, and

(2) with the exhibit mark referred to in the affidavit.

Letters

12.1  Copies of individual letters should be collected together and exhibited in a bundle or bundles. They should be arranged in chronological order with the earliest at the top, and firmly secured.

12.2  When a bundle of correspondence is exhibited, the exhibit should have a front page attached stating that the bundle consists of original letters and copies. They should be arranged and secured as above and numbered consecutively.

Other documents

13.1  Photocopies instead of original documents may be exhibited provided the originals are made available for inspection by the other parties before the hearing and by the judge at the hearing.

13.2  Court documents must not be exhibited (official copies of such documents prove themselves).

13.3  Where an exhibit contains more than one document, a front page should be attached setting out a list of the documents contained in the exhibit; the list should contain the dates of the documents.

Exhibits other than documents

14.1  Items other than documents should be clearly marked with an exhibit number or letter in such a manner that the mark cannot become detached from the exhibit.

14.2  Small items may be placed in a container and the container appropriately marked.

General provisions

15.1  Where an exhibit contains more than one document:

(1) the bundle should not be stapled but should be securely fastened in a way that does not hinder the reading of the documents, and

(2) the pages should be numbered consecutively at bottom centre.

15.2  Every page of an exhibit should be clearly legible; typed copies of illegible documents should be included, paginated with ‘a’ numbers.

15.3  Where affidavits and exhibits have become numerous, they should be put into separate bundles and the pages numbered consecutively throughout.

15.4  Where on account of their bulk the service of exhibits or copies of exhibits on the other parties would be difficult or impracticable, the directions of the court should be sought as to arrangements for bringing the exhibits to the attention of the other parties and as to their custody pending trial.

Affirmations

16  All provisions in this or any other practice direction relating to affidavits apply to affirmations with the following exceptions:

(1) the deponent should commence ‘I (name) of (address) do solemnly and sincerely affirm ……’, and

(2) in the jurat the word ‘sworn’ is replaced by the word ‘affirmed’.

WITNESS STATEMENTS

Heading

17.1  The witness statement should be headed with the title of the proceedings (see paragraph 4 of Practice Direction 7A and paragraph 7 of Practice Direction 20); where the proceedings are between several parties with the same status it is sufficient to identify the parties as follows:

17.2  At the top right hand corner of the first page there should be clearly written:

(1) the party on whose behalf it is made,

(2) the initials and surname of the witness,

(3) the number of the statement in relation to that witness,

(4) the identifying initials and number of each exhibit referred to, and

(5) the date the statement was made.

Body of witness statement

18.1  The witness statement must, if practicable, be in the intended witness’s own words, the statement should be expressed in the first person and should also state:

(1) the full name of the witness,

(2) his place of residence or, if he is making the statement in his professional, business or other occupational capacity, the address at which he works, the position he holds and the name of his firm or employer,

(3) his occupation, or if he has none, his description, and

(4) the fact that he is a party to the proceedings or is the employee of such a party if it be the case.

18.2  A witness statement must indicate:

(1) which of the statements in it are made from the witness’s own knowledge and which are matters of information or belief, and

(2) the source for any matters of information or belief.

18.3  An exhibit used in conjunction with a witness statement should be verified and identified by the witness and remain separate from the witness statement.

18.4  Where a witness refers to an exhibit or exhibits, he should state ‘I refer to the (description of exhibit) marked‘…’’.

18.5  The provisions of paragraphs 11.3 to 15.4 (exhibits) apply similarly to witness statements as they do to affidavits.

18.6  Where a witness makes more than one witness statement to which there are exhibits, in the same proceedings, the numbering of the exhibits should run consecutively throughout and not start again with each witness statement.

Format of witness statement

19.1  A witness statement should:

(1) be produced on durable quality A4 paper with a 3.5cm margin,

(2) be fully legible and should normally be typed on one side of the paper only,

(3) where possible, be bound securely in a manner which would not hamper filing, or otherwise each page should be endorsed with the case number and should bear the initials of the witness,

(4) have the pages numbered consecutively as a separate statement (or as one of several statements contained in a file),

(5) be divided into numbered paragraphs,

(6) have all numbers, including dates, expressed in figures, and

(7) give the reference to any document or documents mentioned either in the margin or in bold text in the body of the statement.

19.2  It is usually convenient for a witness statement to follow the chronological sequence of the events or matters dealt with, each paragraph of a witness statement should as far as possible be confined to a distinct portion of the subject.

Statement of Truth

20.1  A witness statement is the equivalent of the oral evidence which that witness would, if called, give in evidence; it must include a statement by the intended witness that he believes the facts in it are true^13.

20.2  To verify a witness statement the statement of truth is as follows:

‘I believe that the facts stated in this witness statement are true’.

20.3  Attention is drawn to rule 32.14 which sets out the consequences of verifying a witness statement containing a false statement without an honest belief in its truth.

(Paragraph 3A of Practice Direction 22 sets out the procedure to be followed where the person who should sign a document which is verified by a statement of truth is unable to read or sign the document.)

21  Omitted

Alterations to witness statements

22.1  Any alteration to a witness statement must be initialled by the person making the statement or by the authorised person where appropriate (see paragraph 21).

22.2  A witness statement which contains an alteration that has not been initialled may be used in evidence only with the permission of the court.

Filing of witness statements

23.1  If the court directs that a witness statement is to be filed[14], it must be filed in the court or Division, or Office or Registry of the court or Division where the action in which it was or is to be used, is proceeding or will proceed.

23.2  Where the court has directed that a witness statement in a foreign language is to be filed:

(1) the party wishing to rely on it must –

(a) have it translated, and

(b) file the foreign language witness statement with the court, and

(2) the translator must make and file with the court an affidavit verifying the translation and exhibiting both the translation and a copy of the foreign language witness statement.

Certificate of court officer

24.1  Where the court has ordered that a witness statement is not to be open to inspection by the public[15] or that words or passages in the statement are not to be open to inspection^16 the court officer will so certify on the statement and make any deletions directed by the court under rule 32.13(4).

Defects in affidavits, witness statements and exhibits

25.1  Where:

(1) an affidavit,

(2) a witness statement, or

(3) an exhibit to either an affidavit or a witness statement,

does not comply with Part 32 or this practice direction in relation to its form, the court may refuse to admit it as evidence and may refuse to allow the costs arising from its preparation.

25.2  Permission to file a defective affidavit or witness statement or to use a defective exhibit may be obtained from a judge[17] in the court where the case is proceeding.

STATEMENTS OF CASE

26.1  A statement of case may be used as evidence in an interim application provided it is verified by a statement of truth^18.

26.2  To verify a statement of case the statement of truth should be set out as follows:

‘[I believe][the (party on whose behalf the statement of case is being signed) believes] that the facts stated in the statement of case are true’.

26.3  Attention is drawn to rule 32.14 which sets out the consequences of verifying a witness statement containing a false statement without an honest belief in its truth.

(For information regarding statements of truth see Part 22 and Practice Direction 22.)

(Practice Directions 7A and 17 provide further information concerning statements of case.)

AGREED BUNDLES FOR HEARINGS

27.1  The court may give directions requiring the parties to use their best endeavours to agree a bundle or bundles of documents for use at any hearing.

27.2  All documents contained in bundles which have been agreed for use at a hearing shall be admissible at that hearing as evidence of their contents, unless –

(1) the court orders otherwise; or

(2) a party gives written notice of objection to the admissibility of particular documents.

OMITTED

28  28.1 1 Where a party alleges that a statement of truth or a disclosure statement is false the party must refer that allegation to the court dealing with the claim in which the statement of truth or disclosure statement has been made. 2 The court may –   a excercise any of its powers under the rules; b initiate steps to consider if there is a contempt of court and, where there is, to punish it; (Practice Direction RSC 52 and CCR 29 makes provision where committal to prison is a possibility if contempt is proved) c direct the party making the allegation to refer the matter to the Attorney General with a request that the Attorney General consider whether to bring proceedings for contempt of court. 28.2 1 A request to the Attorney General must be made in writing and sent to the Attorney General’s Office at 20 Victoria Street, London, SW1H 0NF. The request must be accompanied by a copy of the order directing that the matter be referred to the Attorney General and must –  a identify thestatement said to be false; b explain –  i why it is false; and ii why the maker knew the statement to be false at the time it was made; and c explain why contempt proceedings would be appropriate in the light of the overriding objective in Part 1. 2 The Attorney General prefers a request that comes from the court to one made direct by a party to the claim in which the alleged contempt occurred without prior consideration by the court. A request to the Attorney General is not a way of appealing against, or reviewing the decision of the judge. 28.3 Where a party makes an application to the court for permission to commence proceedings for contempt of court, it must be supported by written evidence of the facts and matters specified in paragraph 28.2(1) and the result of the request to the Attorney General made by the applicant. 28.4 The rules do not change the law of contempt or introduce new categories of contempt. A person applying to commence such proceedings should consider whether the incident complainedof does amount to contempt of court and whether such proceedings would further the overriding objective in Part 1 of the Civil Procedure Rules.

VIDEO CONFERENCING

29.1  Guidance on the use of video conferencing in the civil courts is set out at Annex 3 to this practice direction.

A list of the sites which are available for video conferencing can be found on Her Majesty's Courts and Tribunals Service website.

ANNEX 1

Certificate to be used where a deponent to an affidavit is unable to read or sign it

Sworn at ……… this …… day of ……… Before me, I having first read over the contents of this affidavit to the deponent [if there are exhibits, add ‘and explained the nature and effect of the exhibits referred to in it’] who appeared to understand it and approved its content as accurate, and made his mark on the affidavit in my presence.

Or; (after, Before me) the witness to the mark of the deponent having been first sworn that he had read over etc. (as above) and that he saw him make his mark on the affidavit. (Witness must sign).

Certificate to be used where a deponent to an affirmation is unable to read or sign it

Affirmed at ……… this …… day of ……… Before me, I having first read over the contents of this affirmation to the deponent [if there are exhibits,add ‘and explained the nature and effect of the exhibits referred to in it’] who appeared to understand it and approved its content as accurate, and made his mark on the affirmation in my presence.

Or, (after, Before me) the witness to the mark of the deponent having been first sworn that he had read over etc. (as above) and that he saw him make his mark on the affirmation. (Witness must sign).

ANNEX 2

Omitted

ANNEX 3

VIDEO CONFERENCING GUIDANCE

This guidance is for the use of video conferencing (VCF) in civil proceedings. It is in part based, with permission, upon the protocol of the Federal Court of Australia. It is intended to provide a guide to all persons involved in the use of VCF, although it does not attempt to cover all the practical questions which might arise.

Video conferencing generally

1.  The guidance covers the use of VCF equipment both (a) in a courtroom, whether via equipment which is permanently placed there or via a mobile unit, and (b) in a separate studio or conference room. In either case, the location at which the judge sits is referred to as the ‘local site’. The other site or sites to and from which transmission is made are referred to as ‘the remote site’ and in any particular case any such site may be another courtroom. The guidance applies to cases where VCF is used for the taking of evidence and also to its use for other parts of any legal proceedings (for example, interim applications, case management conferences, pre-trial reviews).

2.  VCF may be a convenient way of dealing with any part of proceedings: it can involve considerable savings in time and cost. Its use for the taking of evidence from overseas witnesses will, in particular, be likely to achieve a material saving of costs, and such savings may also be achieved by its use for taking domestic evidence. It is, however, inevitably not as ideal as having the witness physically present in court. Its convenience should not therefore be allowed to dictate its use. A judgment must be made in every case in which the use of VCF is being considered not only as to whether it will achieve an overall cost saving but as to whether its use will be likely to be beneficial to the efficient, fair and economic disposal of the litigation. In particular, it needs to be recognised that the degree of control a court can exercise over a witness at the remote site is or may be more limited than it can exercise over a witness physically before it.

3.  When used for the taking of evidence, the objective should be to make the VCF session as close as possible to the usual practice in a trial court where evidence is taken in open court. To gain the maximum benefit, several differences have to be taken into account. Some matters, which are taken for granted when evidence is taken in the conventional way, take on a different dimension when it is taken by VCF: for example, the administration of the oath, ensuring that the witness understands who is at the local site and what their various roles are, the raising of any objections to the evidence and the use of documents.

4.  It should not be presumed that all foreign governments are willing to allow their nationals or others within their jurisdiction to be examined before a court in England or Wales by means of VCF. If there is any doubt about this, enquiries should be directed to the Foreign and Commonwealth Office (International Legal Matters Unit, Consular Division) with a view to ensuring that the country from which the evidence is to be taken raises no objection to it at diplomatic level. The party who is directed to be responsible for arranging the VCF (see paragraph 8 below) will be required to make all necessary inquiries about this well in advance of the VCF and must be able to inform the court what those inquiries were and of their outcome.

5.  Time zone differences need to be considered when a witness abroad is to be examined in England or Wales by VCF. The convenience of the witness, the parties, their representatives and the court must all be taken into account. The cost of the use of a commercial studio is usually greater outside normal business hours.

6.  Those involved with VCF need to be aware that, even with the most advanced systems currently available, there are the briefest of delays between the receipt of the picture and that of the accompanying sound. If due allowance is not made for this, there will be a tendency to ‘speak over’ the witness, whose voice will continue to be heard for a millisecond or so after he or she appears on the screen to have finished speaking.

7.  With current technology, picture quality is good, but not as good as a television picture. The quality of the picture is enhanced if those appearing on VCF monitors keep their movements to a minimum.

Preliminary arrangements

8.  The court's permission is required for any part of any proceedings to be dealt with by means of VCF. Before seeking a direction, the applicant should notify the listing officer, diary manager or other appropriate court officer of the intention to seek it, and should enquire as to the availability of court VCF equipment for the day or days of the proposed VCF. The application for a direction should be made to the Master, District Judge or Judge, as may be appropriate. If all parties consent to a direction, permission can be sought by letter, fax or e-mail, although the court may still require an oral hearing. All parties are entitled to be heard on whether or not such a direction should be given and as to its terms. If a witness at a remote site is to give evidence by an interpreter, consideration should be given at this stage as to whether the interpreter should be at the local site or the remote site. If a VCF direction is given, arrangements for the transmission will then need tobe made. The court will ordinarily direct that the party seeking permission to use VCF is to be responsible for this. That party is hereafter referred to as ‘the VCF arranging party’.

9.  Subject to any order to the contrary, all costs of the transmission, including the costs of hiring equipment and technical personnel to operate it, will initially be the responsibility of, and must be met by, the VCF arranging party. All reasonable efforts should be made to keep the transmission to a minimum and so keep the costs down. All such costs will be considered to be part of the costs of the proceedings and the court will determine at such subsequent time as is convenient or appropriate who, as between the parties, should be responsible for them and (if appropriate) in what proportions.

10.  The local site will, if practicable, be a courtroom but it may instead be an appropriate studio or conference room. The VCF arranging party must contact the listing officer, diary manager or other appropriate officer of the court which made the VCF direction and make arrangements for the VCF transmission. Details of the remote site, and of the equipment to be used both at the local site (if not being supplied by the court) and the remote site (including the number of ISDN lines and connection speed), together with all necessary contact names and telephone numbers, will have to be provided to the listing officer, diary manager or other court officer. The court will need to be satisfied that any equipment provided by the parties for use at the local site and also that at the remote site is of sufficient quality for a satisfactory transmission. The VCF arranging party must ensure that an appropriate person will be present at the local site to supervise the operation of the VCF throughoutthe transmission in order to deal with any technical problems. That party must also arrange for a technical assistant to be similarly present at the remote site for like purposes.

11.  It is recommended that the judge, practitioners and witness should arrive at their respective VCF sites about 20 minutes prior to the scheduled commencement of the transmission.

12.  If the local site is not a courtroom, but a conference room or studio, the judge will need to determine who is to sit where. The VCF arranging party must take care to ensure that the number of microphones is adequate for the speakers and that the panning of the camera for the practitioners' table encompasses all legal representatives so that the viewer can see everyone seated there.

13.  The proceedings, wherever they may take place, form part of a trial to which the public is entitled to have access (unless the court has determined that they should be heard in private). If the local site is to be a studio or conference room, the VCF arranging party must ensure that it provides sufficient accommodation to enable a reasonable number of members of the public to attend.

14.  In cases where the local site is a studio or conference room, the VCF arranging party should make arrangements, if practicable, for the royal coat of arms to be placed above the judge's seat.

15.  In cases in which the VCF is to be used for the taking of evidence, the VCF arranging party must arrange for recording equipment to be provided by the court which made the VCF direction so that the evidence can be recorded. An associate will normally be present to operate the recording equipment when the local site is a courtroom. The VCF arranging party should take steps to ensure that an associate is present to do likewise when it is a studio or conference room. The equipment should be set up and tested before the VCF transmission. It will often be a valuable safeguard for the VCF arranging party also to arrange for the provision of recording equipment at the remote site. This will provide a useful back-up if there is any reduction in sound quality during the transmission. A direction from the court for the making of such a back-up recording must, however, be obtained first. This is because the proceedings are court proceedings and, save as directed by the court, no other recording of them must be made. The court will direct what is to happen to the back-up recording.

16.  Some countries may require that any oath or affirmation to be taken by a witness accord with local custom rather than the usual form of oath or affirmation used in England and Wales. The VCF arranging party must make all appropriate prior inquiries and put in place all arrangements necessary to enable the oath or affirmation to be taken in accordance with any local custom. That party must be in a position to inform the court what those inquiries were, what their outcome was and what arrangements have been made. If the oath or affirmation can be administered in the manner normal in England and Wales, the VCF arranging party must arrange in advance to have the appropriate holy book at the remote site. The associate will normally administer the oath.

17.  Consideration will need to be given in advance to the documents to which the witness is likely to be referred. The parties should endeavour to agree on this. It will usually be most convenient for a bundle of the copy documents to be prepared in advance, which the VCF arranging party should then send to the remote site.

18.  Additional documents are sometimes quite properly introduced during the course of a witness's evidence. To cater for this, the VCF arranging party should ensure that equipment is available to enable documents to be transmitted between sites during the course of the VCF transmission. Consideration should be given to whether to use a document camera. If it is decided to use one, arrangements for its use will need to be established in advance. The panel operator will need to know the number and size of documents or objects if their images are to be sent by document camera. In many cases, a simpler and sufficient alternative will be to ensure that there are fax transmission and reception facilities at the participating sites.

The hearing

19.  The procedure for conducting the transmission will be determined by the judge. He will determine who is to control the cameras. In cases where the VCF is being used for an application in the course of the proceedings, the judge will ordinarily not enter the local site until both sites are on line. Similarly, at the conclusion of the hearing, he will ordinarily leave the local site while both sites are still on line. The following paragraphs apply primarily to cases where the VCF is being used for the taking of the evidence of a witness at a remote site. In all cases, the judge will need to decide whether court dress is appropriate when using VCF facilities. It might be appropriate when transmitting from courtroom to courtroom. It might not be when a commercial facility is being used.

20.  At the beginning of the transmission, the judge will probably wish to introduce himself and the advocates to the witness. He will probably want to know who is at the remote site and will invite the witness to introduce himself and anyone else who is with him. He may wish to give directions as to the seating arrangements at the remote site so that those present are visible at the local site during the taking of the evidence. He will probably wish to explain to the witness the method of taking the oath or of affirming, the manner in which the evidence will be taken, and who will be conducting the examination and cross-examination. He will probably also wish to inform the witness of the matters referred to in paragraphs 6 and 7 above (co-ordination of picture with sound, and picture quality).

21.  The examination of the witness at the remote site should follow as closely as possible the practice adopted when a witness is in the courtroom. During examination, cross-examination and re-examination, the witness must be able to see the legal representative asking the question and also any other person (whether another legal representative or the judge) making any statements in regard to the witness's evidence. It will in practice be most convenient if everyone remains seated throughout the transmission.

Footnotes

See rule 32.6(1). Back to text

See rule 32.15(2). Back to text

See Part 23 for information about making an application. Back to text

Rule 32.6(2) and see Part 22 for information about the statement of truth. Back to text

See, e.g., s.3(5)(a) of the Protection from Harassment Act 1997. Back to text

Commissioner for Oaths Act 1889 and 1891. Back to text

Sections 12 and 18 of, and Schedules 2 and 4 to, the Legal Services Act 2007. Back to text

Section 2 of the Commissioners for Oaths Act 1889. Back to text

Section 58 of the County Courts Act 1984. Back to text

Section 58 as above. Back to text

Section 58 as above. Back to text

Rules 32.1(3) and 32.4(3)(b). Back to text

See Part 22 for information about the statement of truth. Back to text

Rule 32.4(3)(b). Back to text

Rule 32.13(2). Back to text

Rule 32.13(4). Back to text

Rule 2.3(1); definition of judge. Back to text
See rule 32.6(2)(a). Back to text

PART 33 - MISCELLANEOUS RULES ABOUT EVIDENCE

Contents of this Part

Title | Number
Introductory | Rule 33.1
Notice of intention to rely on hearsay evidence | Rule 33.2
Circumstances in which notice of intention to rely on hearsay evidence is not required | Rule 33.3
Power to call witness for cross-examination on hearsay evidence | Rule 33.4
Credibility | Rule 33.5
Use of plans, photographs and models as evidence | Rule 33.6
Evidence of finding on question of foreign law | Rule 33.7
Evidence of consent of trustee to act | Rule 33.8
Human Rights | Rule 33.9

Introductory

33.1

In this Part –

(a) ‘hearsay’ means a statement made, otherwise than by a person while giving oral evidence in proceedings, which is tendered as evidence of the matters stated; and

(b) references to hearsay include hearsay of whatever degree.

Notice of intention to rely on hearsay evidence

33.2

(1) Where a party intends to rely on hearsay evidence at trial and either –

(a) that evidence is to be given by a witness giving oral evidence; or

(b) that evidence is contained in a witness statement of a person who is not being called to give oral evidence;

that party complies with section 2(1)(a) of the Civil Evidence Act 1995^1 serving a witness statement on the other parties in accordance with the court’s order.

(2) Where paragraph (1)(b) applies, the party intending to rely on the hearsay evidence must, when he serves the witness statement –

(a) inform the other parties that the witness is not being called to give oral evidence; and

(b) give the reason why the witness will not be called.

(3) In all other cases where a party intends to rely on hearsay evidence at trial, that party complies with section 2(1)(a) of the Civil Evidence Act 1995 by serving a notice on the other parties which –

(a) identifies the hearsay evidence;

(b) states that the party serving the notice proposes to rely on the hearsay evidence at trial; and

(c) gives the reason why the witness will not be called.

(4) The party proposing to rely on the hearsay evidence must –

(a) serve the notice no later than the latest date for serving witness statements; and

(b) if the hearsay evidence is to be in a document, supply a copy to any party who requests him to do so.

Circumstances in which notice of intention to rely on hearsay evidence is not required

33.3  Section 2(1) of the Civil Evidence Act 1995 (duty to give notice of intention to rely on hearsay evidence) does not apply –

(a) to evidence at hearings other than trials;

(aa) to an affadavit or witness statement which is to be used at trial but which does not contain hearsay evidence;

(b) to a statement which a party to a probate action wishes to put in evidence and which is alleged to have been made by the person whose estate is the subject of the proceedings; or

(c) where the requirement is excluded by a practice direction.

Power to call witness for cross-examination on hearsay evidence

33.4

(1) Where a party –

(a) proposes to rely on hearsay evidence; and

(b) does not propose to call the person who made the original statement to give oral evidence,

the court may, on the application of any other party, permit that party to call the maker of the statement to be cross-examined on the contents of the statement.

(2) An application for permission to cross-examine under this rule must be made not more than 14 days after the day on which a notice of intention to rely on the hearsay evidence was served on the applicant.

Credibility

33.5

(1) Where a party –

(a) proposes to rely on hearsay evidence; but

(b) does not propose to call the person who made the original statement to give oral evidence; and

(c) another party wishes to call evidence to attack the credibility of the person who made the statement,

the party who so wishes must give notice of his intention to the party who proposes to give the hearsay statement in evidence.

(2) A party must give notice under paragraph (1) not more than 14 days after the day on which a hearsay notice relating to the hearsay evidence was served on him.

Use of plans, photographs and models as evidence

33.6

(1) This rule applies to evidence (such as a plan, photograph or model) which is not –

(a) contained in a witness statement, affidavit(GL) or expert’s report;

(b) to be given orally at trial; or

(c) evidence of which prior notice must be given under rule 33.2.

(2) This rule includes documents which may be received in evidence without further proof under section 9 of the Civil Evidence Act 1995^2.

(3) Unless the court orders otherwise the evidence shall not be receivable at a trial unless the party intending to put it in evidence has given notice to the other parties in accordance with this rule.

(4) Where the party intends to use the evidence as evidence of any fact then, except where paragraph (6) applies, he must give notice not later than the latest date for serving witness statements.

(5) He must give notice at least 21 days before the hearing at which he proposes to put in the evidence, if –

(a) there are not to be witness statements; or

(b) he intends to put in the evidence solely in order to disprove an allegation made in a witness statement.

(6) Where the evidence forms part of expert evidence, he must give notice when the expert’s report is served on the other party.

(7) Where the evidence is being produced to the court for any reason other than as part of factual or expert evidence, he must give notice at least 21 days before the hearing at which he proposes to put in the evidence.

(8) Where a party has given notice that he intends to put in the evidence, he must give every other party an opportunity to inspect it and to agree to its admission without further proof.

Evidence of finding on question of foreign law

33.7

(1) This rule sets out the procedure which must be followed by a party who intends to put in evidence a finding on a question of foreign law by virtue of section 4(2) of the Civil Evidence Act 1972^3.

(2) He must give any other party notice of his intention.

(3) He must give the notice –

(a) if there are to be witness statements, not later than the latest date for serving them; or

(b) otherwise, not less than 21 days before the hearing at which he proposes to put the finding in evidence.

(4) The notice must –

(a) specify the question on which the finding was made; and

(b) enclose a copy of a document where it is reported or recorded.

Evidence of consent of trustee to act

33.8  A document purporting to contain the written consent of a person to act as trustee and to bear his signature verified by some other person is evidence of such consent.

Human Rights

33.9

(1) This rule applies where a claim is –

(a) for a remedy under section 7 of the Human Rights Act 1998 in respect of a judicial act which is alleged to have infringed the claimant’s Article 5 Convention rights; and

(b) based on a finding by a court or tribunal that the claimant’s Convention rights have been infringed.

(2) The court hearing the claim –

(a) may proceed on the basis of the finding of that other court or tribunal that there has been an infringement but it is not required to do so, and

(b) may reach its own conclusion in the light of that finding and of the evidence heard by that other court or tribunal.

Footnotes

1995 c.38. Section 2 provides that a party proposing to bring hearsay evidence must notify any other party of that fact and, on request, give particulars of or relating to the evidence. Back to text
Section 9 of the Civil Evidence Act 1995 provides that documents that form part of the records of a business or public authority, as defined in that section, may be received in evidence without further proof. Back to text
1972 c.30. Back to text

PART 34 - WITNESSES, DEPOSITIONS AND EVIDENCE FOR FOREIGN COURTS

Contents of this Part

Title | Number
I WITNESSES AND DEPOSITIONS |

Scope of this Section | Rule 34.1
Witness summonses | Rule 34.2
Issue of a witness summons | Rule 34.3
Witness summons in aid of inferior court or of tribunal | Rule 34.4
Time for serving a witness summons | Rule 34.5
Who is to serve a witness summons | Rule 34.6
Right of witness to travelling expenses and compensation for loss of time | Rule 34.7
Evidence by deposition | Rule 34.8
Conduct of examination | Rule 34.9
Enforcing attendance of witness | Rule 34.10
Use of deposition at a hearing | Rule 34.11
Restrictions on subsequent use of deposition taken for the purpose of any hearing except the trial | Rule 34.12
Where a person to be examined is out of the jurisdiction – letter of request | Rule 34.13
Letter of request – Proceeds of Crime Act 2002 | Rule 34.13A
Fees and expenses of examiner of the court | Rule 34.14
Examiners of the court | Rule 34.15
II EVIDENCE FOR FOREIGN COURTS |

Scope and interpretation | Rule 34.16
Application for order | Rule 34.17
Examination | Rule 34.18
Dealing with deposition | Rule 34.19
Claim to privilege | Rule 34.20
Order under 1975 Act as applied by Patents Act 1977 | Rule 34.21
III TAKING OF EVIDENCE – MEMBER STATES OF THE EUROPEAN UNION |

Interpretation | Rule 34.22
Where a person to be examined is in another Regulation State | Rule 34.23
Evidence for courts of other Regulation States | Rule 34.24

I WITNESSES AND DEPOSITIONS

Scope of this Section

34.1

(1) This Section of this Part provides –

(a) for the circumstances in which a person may be required to attend court to give evidence or to produce a document; and

(b) for a party to obtain evidence before a hearing to be used at the hearing.

(2) In this Section, reference to a hearing includes a reference to the trial.

Back to top

Witness summonses

34.2

(1) A witness summons is a document issued by the court requiring a witness to –

(a) attend court to give evidence; or

(b) produce documents to the court.

(2) A witness summons must be in the relevant practice form.

(3) There must be a separate witness summons for each witness.

(4) A witness summons may require a witness to produce documents to the court either –

(a) on the date fixed for a hearing; or

(b) on such date as the court may direct.

(5) The only documents that a summons under this rule can require a person to produce before a hearing are documents which that person could be required to produce at the hearing.

Issue of a witness summons

34.3

(1) A witness summons is issued on the date entered on the summons by the court.

(2) A party must obtain permission from the court where he wishes to –

(a) have a summons issued less than 7 days before the date of the trial;

(b) have a summons issued for a witness to attend court to give evidence or to produce documents on any date except the date fixed for the trial; or

(c) have a summons issued for a witness to attend court to give evidence or to produce documents at any hearing except the trial.

(3) A witness summons must be issued by –

(a) the court where the case is proceeding; or

(b) the court where the hearing in question will be held.

(4) The court may set aside(GL) or vary a witness summons issued under this rule.

Witness summons in aid of inferior court or of tribunal

34.4

(1) The court may issue a witness summons in aid of an inferior court or of a tribunal.

(2) The court which issued the witness summons under this rule may set it aside.

(3) In this rule, ‘inferior court or tribunal’ means any court or tribunal that does not have power to issue a witness summons in relation to proceedings before it.

Time for serving a witness summons

34.5

(1) The general rule is that a witness summons is binding if it is served at least 7 days before the date on which the witness is required to attend before the court or tribunal.

(2) The court may direct that a witness summons shall be binding although it will be served less than 7 days before the date on which the witness is required to attend before the court or tribunal.

(3) A witness summons which is –

(a) served in accordance with this rule; and

(b) requires the witness to attend court to give evidence,

is binding until the conclusion of the hearing at which the attendance of the witness is required.

Who is to serve a witness summons

34.6

(1) A witness summons is to be served by the court unless the party on whose behalf it is issued indicates in writing, when he asks the court to issue the summons, that he wishes to serve it himself.

(2) Where the court is to serve the witness summons, the party on whose behalf it is issued must deposit, in the court office, the money to be paid or offered to the witness under rule 34.7.

Right of witness to travelling expenses and compensation for loss of time

34.7

At the time of service of a witness summons the witness must be offered or paid –

(a) a sum reasonably sufficient to cover his expenses in travelling to and from the court; and

(b) such sum by way of compensation for loss of time as may be specified in Practice Direction 34A.

Evidence by deposition

34.8

(1) A party may apply for an order for a person to be examined before the hearing takes place.

(2) A person from whom evidence is to be obtained following an order under this rule is referred to as a ‘deponent’ and the evidence is referred to as a ‘deposition’.

(3) An order under this rule shall be for a deponent to be examined on oath before –

(a) a judge;

(b) an examiner of the court; or

(c) such other person as the court appoints.

(Rule 34.15 makes provision for the appointment of examiners of the court)

(4) The order may require the production of any document which the court considers is necessary for the purposes of the examination.

(5) The order must state the date, time and place of the examination.

(6) At the time of service of the order the deponent must be offered or paid –

(a) a sum reasonably sufficient to cover his expenses in travelling to and from the place of examination; and

(b) such sum by way of compensation for loss of time as may be specified in Practice Direction 34A.

(7) Where the court makes an order for a deposition to be taken, it may also order the party who obtained the order to serve a witness statement or witness summary in relation to the evidence to be given by the person to be examined.

(Part 32 contains the general rules about witness statements and witness summaries)

Conduct of examination

34.9

(1) Subject to any directions contained in the order for examination, the examination must be conducted in the same way as if the witness were giving evidence at a trial.

(2) If all the parties are present, the examiner may conduct the examination of a person not named in the order for examination if all the parties and the person to be examined consent.

(3) The examiner may conduct the examination in private if he considers it appropriate to do so.

(4) The examiner must ensure that the evidence given by the witness is recorded in full.

(5) The examiner must send a copy of the deposition –

(a) to the person who obtained the order for the examination of the witness; and

(b) to the court where the case is proceeding.

(6) The party who obtained the order must send each of the other parties a copy of the deposition which he receives from the examiner.

Enforcing attendance of witness

34.10

(1) If a person served with an order to attend before an examiner –

(a) fails to attend; or

(b) refuses to be sworn for the purpose of the examination or to answer any lawful question or produce any document at the examination,

a certificate of his failure or refusal, signed by the examiner, must be filed by the party requiring the deposition.

(2) On the certificate being filed, the party requiring the deposition may apply to the court for an order requiring that person to attend or to be sworn or to answer any question or produce any document, as the case may be.

(3) An application for an order under this rule may be made without notice.

(4) The court may order the person against whom an order is made under this rule to pay any costs resulting from his failure or refusal.

Use of deposition at a hearing

34.11

(1) A deposition ordered under rule 34.8 may be given in evidence at a hearing unless the court orders otherwise.

(2) A party intending to put in evidence a deposition at a hearing must serve notice of his intention to do so on every other party.

(3) He must serve the notice at least 21 days before the day fixed for the hearing.

(4) The court may require a deponent to attend the hearing and give evidence orally.

(5) Where a deposition is given in evidence at trial, it shall be treated as if it were a witness statement for the purposes of rule 32.13 (availability of witness statements for inspection).

Restrictions on subsequent use of deposition taken for the purpose of any hearing except the trial

34.12

(1) Where the court orders a party to be examined about his or any other assets for the purpose of any hearing except the trial, the deposition may be used only for the purpose of the proceedings in which the order was made.

(2) However, it may be used for some other purpose –

(a) by the party who was examined;

(b) if the party who was examined agrees; or

(c) if the court gives permission.

Where a person to be examined is out of the jurisdiction – letter of request

34.13

(1) This rule applies where a party wishes to take a deposition from a person who is –

(a) out of the jurisdiction; and

(b) not in a Regulation State within the meaning of Section III of this Part.

(1A) The High Court may order the issue of a letter of request to the judicial authorities of the country in which the proposed deponent is.

(2) A letter of request is a request to a judicial authority to take the evidence of that person, or arrange for it to be taken.

(3) The High Court may make an order under this rule in relation to county court proceedings.

(4) If the government of a country allows a person appointed by the High Court to examine a person in that country, the High Court may make an order appointing a special examiner for that purpose.

(5) A person may be examined under this rule on oath or affirmation or in accordance with any procedure permitted in the country in which the examination is to take place.

(6) If the High Court makes an order for the issue of a letter of request, the party who sought the order must file –

(a) the following documents and, except where paragraph (7) applies, a translation of them –

(i) a draft letter of request;

(ii) a statement of the issues relevant to the proceedings;

(iii) a list of questions or the subject matter of questions to be put to the person to be examined; and

(b) an undertaking to be responsible for the Secretary of State’s expenses.

(7) There is no need to file a translation if –

(a) English is one of the official languages of the country where the examination is to take place; or

(b) a practice direction has specified that country as a country where no translation is necessary.

Letter of request – Proceeds of Crime Act 2002

34.13A

(1) This rule applies where a party to existing or contemplated proceedings in –

(a) the High Court; or

(b) a magistrates' court,

under Part 5 of the Proceeds of Crime Act 2002^3 (civil recovery of the proceeds etc. of unlawful conduct) wishes to take a deposition from a person who is out of the jurisdiction.

(2) The High Court may, on the application of such a party, order the issue of a letter of request to the judicial authorities of the country in which the proposed deponent is.

(3) Paragraphs (4) to (7) of rule 34.13 shall apply irrespective of where the proposed deponent is, and rule 34.23 shall not apply in cases where the proposed deponent is in a Regulation State within the meaning of Section III of this Part.

Fees and expenses of examiner of the court

34.14

(1) An examiner of the court may charge a fee for the examination.

(2) He need not send the deposition to the court unless the fee is paid.

(3) The examiner’s fees and expenses must be paid by the party who obtained the order for examination.

(4) If the fees and expenses due to an examiner are not paid within a reasonable time, he may report that fact to the court.

(5) The court may order the party who obtained the order for examination to deposit in the court office a specified sum in respect of the examiner’s fees and, where it does so, the examiner will not be asked to act until the sum has been deposited.

(6) An order under this rule does not affect any decision as to the party who is ultimately to bear the costs of the examination.

Examiners of the court

34.15

(1) The Lord Chancellor shall appoint persons to be examiners of the court.

(2) The persons appointed shall be barristers or solicitor-advocates who have been practising for a period of not less than three years.

(3) The Lord Chancellor may revoke an appointment at any time.

II EVIDENCE FOR FOREIGN COURTS

Scope and interpretation

34.16

(1) This Section applies to an application for an order under the 1975 Act for evidence to be obtained, other than an application made as a result of a request by a court in another Regulation State.

(2) In this Section –

(a) ‘the 1975 Act’ means the Evidence (Proceedings in Other Jurisdictions) Act 1975(^2); and

(b) ‘Regulation State’ has the same meaning as in Section III of this Part.

Application for order

34.17  An application for an order under the 1975 Act for evidence to be obtained –

(a) must be –

(i) made to the High Court;

(ii) supported by written evidence; and

(iii) accompanied by the request as a result of which the application is made, and where appropriate, a translation of the request into English; and

(b) may be made without notice.

Examination

34.18

(1) The court may order an examination to be taken before –

(a) any fit and proper person nominated by the person applying for the order;

(b) an examiner of the court; or

(c) any other person whom the court considers suitable.

(2) Unless the court orders otherwise –

(a) the examination will be taken as provided by rule 34.9; and

(b) rule 34.10 applies.

(3) The court may make an order under rule 34.14 for payment of the fees and expenses of the examination.

Dealing with deposition

34.19

(1) The examiner must send the deposition of the witness to the Senior Master unless the court orders otherwise.

(2) The Senior Master will –

(a) give a certificate sealed with the seal of the Senior Courts for use out of the jurisdiction identifying the following documents –

(i) the request;

(ii) the order of the court for examination; and

(iii) the deposition of the witness; and

(b) send the certificate and the documents referred to in paragraph (a) to –

(i) the Secretary of State; or

(ii) where the request was sent to the Senior Master by another person in accordance with a Civil Procedure Convention, to that other person,

for transmission to the court or tribunal requesting the examination.

Claim to privilege

34.20

(1) This rule applies where –

(a) a witness claims to be exempt from giving evidence on the ground specified in section 3(1)(b) of the 1975 Act; and

(b) That claim is not supported or conceded as referred to in section 3(2) of that Act.

(2) The examiner may require the witness to give the evidence which he claims to be exempt from giving.

(3) Where the examiner does not require the witness to give that evidence, the court may order the witness to do so.

(4) An application for an order under paragraph (3) may be made by the person who obtained the order under section 2 of the 1975 Act.

(5) Where such evidence is taken –

(a) it must be contained in a document separate from the remainder of the deposition;

(b) the examiner will send to the Senior Master –

(i) the deposition; and

(ii) a signed statement setting out the claim to be exempt and the ground on which it was made;

(6) On receipt of the statement referred to in paragraph (5)(b)(ii), the Senior Master will –

(a) retain the document containing the part of the witness's evidence to which the claim to be exempt relates; and

(b) send the statement and a request to determine that claim to the foreign court or tribunal together with the documents referred to in rule 34.17.

(7) The Senior Master will –

(a) if the claim to be exempt is rejected by the foreign court or tribunal, send the document referred to in paragraph (5)(a) to that court or tribunal;

(b) if the claim is upheld, send the document to the witness; and

(c) in either case, notify the witness and person who obtained the order under section 2 of the foreign court or tribunal's decision.

Order under 1975 Act as applied by Patents Act 1977

34.21  Where an order is made for the examination of witnesses under section 1 of the 1975 Act as applied by section 92 of the Patents Act 1977^1 the court may permit an officer of the European Patent Office to –

(a) attend the examination and examine the witnesses; or

(b) request the court or the examiner before whom the examination takes place to put specified questions to them.

III TAKING OF EVIDENCE – MEMBER STATES OF THE EUROPEAN UNION

Interpretation

34.22  In this Section –

(a) ‘designated court’ has the meaning given in Practice Direction 34A;

(b) ‘Regulation State’ has the same meaning as 'Member State' in the Taking of Evidence Regulation, that is all Member States except Denmark;

(c) ‘the Taking of Evidence Regulation’ means Council Regulation (EC) No. 1206/2001 of 28 May 2001 on co-operation between the courts of the Member States in the taking of evidence in civil and commercial matters.

Where a person to be examined is in another Regulation State

34.23

(1) Subject to rule 34.13A, this rule applies where a party wishes to take a deposition from a person who is in another Regulation State–

(a) outside the jurisdiction; and

(b) in a Regulation State.

(2) The court may order the issue of a request to a designated court (‘the requested court’) in the Regulation State in which the proposed deponent is.

(3) If the court makes an order for the issue of a request, the party who sought the order must file –

(a) a draft Form A as set out in the annex to the Taking of Evidence Regulation (request for the taking of evidence);

(b) except where paragraph (4) applies, a translation of the form;

(c) an undertaking to be responsible for costs sought by the requested court in relation to –

(i) fees paid to experts and interpreters; and

(ii) where requested by that party, the use of special procedures or communications technology; and

(d) an undertaking to be responsible for the court's expenses.

(4) There is no need to file a translation if –

(a) English is one of the official languages of the Regulation State where the examination is to take place; or

(b) the Regulation State has indicated, in accordance with the Taking of Evidence Regulation, that English is a language which it will accept.

(5) Where article 17 of the Taking of Evidence Regulation (direct taking of evidence by the requested court) allows evidence to be taken directly in another Regulation State, the court may make an order for the submission of a request in accordance with that article.

(6) If the court makes an order for the submission of a request under paragraph (5), the party who sought the order must file –

(a) a draft Form I as set out in the annex to the Taking of Evidence Regulation (request for direct taking of evidence);

(b) except where paragraph (4) applies, a translation of the form; and

(c) an undertaking to be responsible for the court's expenses.

Evidence for courts of other Regulation States

34.24

(1) This rule applies where a court in another Regulation State (‘the requesting court’) issues a request for evidence to be taken from a person who is in the jurisdiction.

(2) An application for an order for evidence to be taken –

(a) must be made to a designated court;

(b) must be accompanied by –

(i) the form of request for the taking of evidence as a result of which the application is made; and

(ii) where appropriate, a translation of the form of request; and

(c) may be made without notice.

(3) Rule 34.18(1) and (2) apply.

(4) The examiner must send –

(a) the deposition to the court for transmission to the requesting court; and

(b) a copy of the deposition to the person who obtained the order for evidence to be taken.

Footnotes

1977 c.37. Back to text

1975 c.34. Back to text

2002 c.29. Back to text

PART 36 - OFFERS TO SETTLE

Contents of this Part

Scope of this Part

36.A1

(1) This Part contains rules about –

(a) offers to settle; and

(b) the consequences where an offer to settle is made in accordance with this Part.

(2) Section I of this Part contains rules about offers to settle other than where Section II applies.

(3) Section II of this Part contains rules about offers to settle where the parties have followed the Pre-Action Protocol for Low Value Personal Injury Claims in Road Traffic Accidents (‘the RTA Protocol’) or the Pre-action Protocol for Low Value Personal Injury (Employers’ Liability and Public Liability) Claims (‘the EL/PL Protocol’) and have started proceedings under Part 8 in accordance with Practice Direction 8B.

I PART 36 OFFERS TO SETTLE

Scope of this Part

36.1

(1) This Section does not apply to an offer to settle to which Section II of this Part applies.

(2) Nothing in this Section prevents a party making an offer to settle in whatever way he chooses, but if the offer is not made in accordance with rule 36.2, it will not have the consequences specified in rules 36.10, 36.11 and 36.14.

(Rule 44.2 requires the court to consider an offer to settle that does not have the costs consequences set out in this Section in deciding what order to make about costs)

Form and content of a Part 36 offer

36.2

(1) An offer to settle which is made in accordance with this rule is called a Part 36 offer.

(2) A Part 36 offer must –

(a) be in writing;

(b) state on its face that it is intended to have the consequences of Section I of Part 36;

(c) specify a period of not less than 21 days within which the defendant will be liable for the claimant's costs in accordance with rule 36.10 if the offer is accepted;

(d) state whether it relates to the whole of the claim or to part of it or to an issue that arises in it and if so to which part or issue; and

(e) state whether it takes into account any counterclaim.

(Rule 36.7 makes provision for when a Part 36 offer is made)

(3) Rule 36.2(2)(c) does not apply if the offer is made less than 21 days before the start of the trial.

(4) In appropriate cases, a Part 36 offer must contain such further information as is required by rule 36.5 (Personal injury claims for future pecuniary loss), rule 36.6 (Offer to settle a claim for provisional damages), and rule 36.15 (Deduction of benefits).

(5) An offeror may make a Part 36 offer solely in relation to liability.

Part 36 offers – general provisions

36.3

(1) In this Part –

(a) the party who makes an offer is the ‘offeror’;

(b) the party to whom an offer is made is the ‘offeree’; and

(c) ‘the relevant period’ means –

(i) in the case of an offer made not less than 21 days before trial, the period stated under rule 36.2(2)(c) or such longer period as the parties agree;

(ii) otherwise, the period up to end of the trial or such other period as the court has determined.

(2) A Part 36 offer –

(a) may be made at any time, including before the commencement of proceedings; and

(b) may be made in appeal proceedings.

(3) A Part 36 offer which offers to pay or offers to accept a sum of money will be treated as inclusive of all interest until –

(a) the date on which the period stated under rule 36.2(2)(c) expires; or

(b) if rule 36.2(3) applies, a date 21 days after the date the offer was made.

(4) A Part 36 offer shall have the consequences set out in this Section only in relation to the costs of the proceedings in respect of which it is made, and not in relation to the costs of any appeal from the final decision in those proceedings.

(5) Before expiry of the relevant period, a Part 36 offer may be withdrawn or its terms changed to be less advantageous to the offeree, only if the court gives permission.

(6) After expiry of the relevant period and provided that the offeree has not previously served notice of acceptance, the offeror may withdraw the offer or change its terms to be less advantageous to the offeree without the permission of the court.

(7) The offeror does so by serving written notice of the withdrawal or change of terms on the offeree.

(Rule 36.14(6) deals with the costs consequences following judgment of an offer that is withdrawn)

Part 36 offers – defendants' offers

36.4

(1) Subject to rule 36.5(3) and rule 36.6(1), a Part 36 offer by a defendant to pay a sum of money in settlement of a claim must be an offer to pay a single sum of money.

(2) But, an offer that includes an offer to pay all or part of the sum, if accepted, at a date later than 14 days following the date of acceptance will not be treated as a Part 36 offer unless the offeree accepts the offer.

Personal injury claims for future pecuniary loss

36.5

(1) This rule applies to a claim for damages for personal injury which is or includes a claim for future pecuniary loss.

(2) An offer to settle such a claim will not have the consequences set out in rules 36.10, 36.11 and 36.14 unless it is made by way of a Part 36 offer under this rule.

(3) A Part 36 offer to which this rule applies may contain an offer to pay, or an offer to accept –

(a) the whole or part of the damages for future pecuniary loss in the form of –

(i) a lump sum; or

(ii) periodical payments; or

(iii) both a lump sum and periodical payments;

(b) the whole or part of any other damages in the form of a lump sum.

(4) A Part 36 offer to which this rule applies –

(a) must state the amount of any offer to pay the whole or part of any damages in the form of a lump sum;

(b) may state –

(i) what part of the lump sum, if any, relates to damages for future pecuniary loss; and

(ii) what part relates to other damages to be accepted in the form of a lump sum;

(c) must state what part of the offer relates to damages for future pecuniary loss to be paid or accepted in the form of periodical payments and must specify –

(i) the amount and duration of the periodical payments;

(ii) the amount of any payments for substantial capital purchases and when they are to be made; and

(iii) that each amount is to vary by reference to the retail prices index (or to some other named index, or that it is not to vary by reference to any index); and

(d) must state either that any damages which take the form of periodical payments will be funded in a way which ensures that the continuity of payment is reasonably secure in accordance with section 2(4) of the Damages Act 1996 or how such damages are to be paid and how the continuity of their payment is to be secured.

(5) Rule 36.4 applies to the extent that a Part 36 offer by a defendant under this rule includes an offer to pay all or part of any damages in the form of a lump sum.

(6) Where the offeror makes a Part 36 offer to which this rule applies and which offers to pay or to accept damages in the form of both a lump sum and periodical payments, the offeree may only give notice of acceptance of the offer as a whole.

(7) If the offeree accepts a Part 36 offer which includes payment of any part of the damages in the form of periodical payments, the claimant must, within 7 days of the date of acceptance, apply to the court for an order for an award of damages in the form of periodical payments under rule 41.8.

(Practice Direction 41B contains information about periodical payments under the Damages Act 1996)

Offer to settle a claim for provisional damages

36.6

(1) An offeror may make a Part 36 offer in respect of a claim which includes a claim for provisional damages.

(2) Where he does so, the Part 36 offer must specify whether or not the offeror is proposing that the settlement shall include an award of provisional damages.

(3) Where the offeror is offering to agree to the making of an award of provisional damages the Part 36 offer must also state –

(a) that the sum offered is in satisfaction of the claim for damages on the assumption that the injured person will not develop the disease or suffer the type of deterioration specified in the offer;

(b) that the offer is subject to the condition that the claimant must make any claim for further damages within a limited period; and

(c) what that period is.

(4) Rule 36.4 applies to the extent that a Part 36 offer by a defendant includes an offer to agree to the making of an award of provisional damages.

(5) If the offeree accepts the Part 36 offer, the claimant must, within 7 days of the date of acceptance, apply to the court for an order for an award of provisional damages under rule 41.2.

Time when a Part 36 offer is made

36.7

(1) A Part 36 offer is made when it is served on the offeree.

(2) A change in the terms of a Part 36 offer will be effective when notice of the change is served on the offeree.

(Rule 36.3 makes provision about when permission is required to change the terms of an offer to make it less advantageous to the offeree)

Clarification of a Part 36 offer

36.8

(1) The offeree may, within 7 days of a Part 36 offer being made, request the offeror to clarify the offer.

(2) If the offeror does not give the clarification requested under paragraph (1) within 7 days of receiving the request, the offeree may, unless the trial has started, apply for an order that he does so.

(Part 23 contains provisions about making an application to the court)

(3) If the court makes an order under paragraph (2), it must specify the date when the Part 36 offer is to be treated as having been made.

Acceptance of a Part 36 offer

36.9

(1) A Part 36 offer is accepted by serving written notice of the acceptance on the offeror.

(2) Subject to rule 36.9(3), a Part 36 offer may be accepted at any time (whether or not the offeree has subsequently made a different offer) unless the offeror serves notice of withdrawal on the offeree.

(Rule 21.10 deals with compromise etc. by or on behalf of a child or protected party.)

(3) The court's permission is required to accept a Part 36 offer where –

(a) rule 36.12(4) applies;

(b) rule 36.15(3)(b) applies, the relevant period has expired and further deductible amounts have been paid to the claimant since the date of the offer;

(c) an apportionment is required under rule 41.3A; or

(d) the trial has started.

(Rule 36.12 deals with offers by some but not all of multiple defendants)

(Rule 36.15 defines ‘deductible amounts’.)

(Rule 41.3A requires an apportionment in proceedings under the Fatal Accidents Act 1976 and Law Reform (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 1934)

(4) Where the court gives permission under paragraph (3), unless all the parties have agreed costs, the court will make an order dealing with costs, and may order that the costs consequences set out in rule 36.10 will apply.

(5) Unless the parties agree, a Part 36 offer may not be accepted after the end of the trial but before judgment is handed down.

Costs consequences of acceptance of a Part 36 offer

36.10

(1) Subject to rule 36.10A and to paragraphs (2) and (4)(a) of this rule, where a Part 36 offer is accepted within the relevant period the claimant will be entitled to the costs of the proceedings up to the date on which notice of acceptance was served on the offeror.

(2) Where –

(a) a defendant’s Part 36 offer relates to part only of the claim; and

(b) at the time of serving notice of acceptance within the relevant period the claimant abandons the balance of the claim,

the claimant will be entitled to the costs of the proceedings up to the date of serving notice of acceptance unless the court orders otherwise.

(3) Costs under paragraphs (1) and (2) of this rule will be assessed on the standard basis if the amount of costs is not agreed.

(Rule 44.3(2) explains the standard basis for assessment of costs)

(Rule 44.9 contains provisions about when a costs order is deemed to have been made and applying for an order under section 194(3) of the Legal Services Act 2007.)

(4) Where –

(a) a Part 36 offer that was made less than 21 days before the start of trial is accepted; or

(b) a Part 36 offer is accepted after expiry of the relevant period,

if the parties do not agree the liability for costs, the court will make an order as to costs.

(5) Where paragraph (4)(b) applies, unless the court orders otherwise –

(a) the claimant will be entitled to the costs of the proceedings up to the date on which the relevant period expired; and

(b) the offeree will be liable for the offeror’s costs for the period from the date of expiry of the relevant period to the date of acceptance.

(6) The claimant’s costs include any costs incurred in dealing with the defendant’s counterclaim if the Part 36 offer states that it takes into account the counterclaim.

Costs consequences of acceptance of a Part 36 offer where Section IIIA of Part 45 applies

36.10A

(1) This rule applies where a claim no longer continues under the RTA or EL/PL Protocol pursuant to rule 45.29A(1).

(2) Where a Part 36 offer is accepted within the relevant period, the claimant will be entitled to the fixed costs in Table 6B, Table 6C or Table 6D in Section IIIA of Part 45 for the stage applicable at the date on which notice of acceptance was served on the offeror.

(3) Where—

(a) a defendant’s Part 36 offer relates to part only of the claim; and

(b) at the time of serving notice of acceptance within the relevant period the claimant abandons the balance of the claim,

the claimant will be entitled to the fixed costs in paragraph (2).

(4) Subject to paragraph (5), where a defendant’s Part 36 offer is accepted after the relevant period—

(a) the claimant will be entitled to the fixed costs in Table 6B, Table 6C or Table 6D in Section IIIA of Part 45 for the stage applicable at the date on which the relevant period expired; and

(b) the claimant will be liable for the defendant’s costs for the period from the date of expiry of the relevant period to the date of acceptance.

(5) Where the claimant accepts the defendant’s Protocol offer after the date on which the claim leaves the Protocol—

(a) the claimant will be entitled to the applicable Stage 1 and Stage 2 fixed costs in Table 6 or Table 6A in Section III of Part 45; and

(b) the claimant will be liable for the defendant’s costs from the date on which the Protocol offer is deemed to be made to the date of acceptance.

(6) For the purposes of this rule a defendant’s Protocol offer is either—

(a) defined in accordance with rules 36.17 and 36.18; or

(b) if the claim leaves the Protocol before the Court Proceedings Pack Form is sent to the defendant—

(i) the last offer made by the defendant before the claim leaves the Protocol; and

(ii) deemed to be made on the first business day after the claim leaves the Protocol.

(7) A reference to the ‘Court Proceedings Pack Form’ is a reference to the form used in the Protocol.

(8) Fixed costs shall be calculated by reference to the amount of the offer which is accepted.

(9) Where the parties do not agree the liability for costs, the court will make an order as to costs.

(10) Where the court makes an order for costs in favour of the defendant—

(a) the court will have regard to; and

(b) the amount of costs ordered shall not exceed,

the fixed costs in Table 6B, Table 6C or Table 6D in Section IIIA of Part 45 applicable at the date of acceptance, less the fixed costs to which the claimant is entitled under paragraph (4) or (5).

(11) The parties are entitled to disbursements allowed in accordance with rule 45.29I incurred in any period for which costs are payable to them.

The effect of acceptance of a Part 36 offer

36.11

(1) If a Part 36 offer is accepted, the claim will be stayed(GL).

(2) In the case of acceptance of a Part 36 offer which relates to the whole claim the stay(GL) will be upon the terms of the offer.

(3) If a Part 36 offer which relates to part only of the claim is accepted –

(a) the claim will be stayed as to that part upon the terms of the offer; and

(b) subject to rule 36.10(2), unless the parties have agreed costs, the liability for costs shall be decided by the court.

(4) If the approval of the court is required before a settlement can be binding, any stay which would otherwise arise on the acceptance of a Part 36 offer will take effect only when that approval has been given.

(5) Any stay arising under this rule will not affect the power of the court –

(a) to enforce the terms of a Part 36 offer;

(b) to deal with any question of costs (including interest on costs) relating to the proceedings.

(6) Unless the parties agree otherwise in writing, where a Part 36 offer by a defendant that is or that includes an offer to pay a single sum of money is accepted, that sum must be paid to the offeree within 14 days of the date of –

(a) acceptance; or

(b) the order when the court makes an order under rule 41.2 (order for an award of provisional damages) or rule 41.8 (order for an award of periodical payments), unless the court orders otherwise.

(7) If the accepted sum is not paid within 14 days or such other period as has been agreed the offeree may enter judgment for the unpaid sum.

(8) Where –

(a) a Part 36 offer (or part of a Part 36 offer) which is not an offer to which paragraph (6) applies is accepted; and

(b) a party alleges that the other party has not honoured the terms of the offer,

that party may apply to enforce the terms of the offer without the need for a new claim.

Acceptance of a Part 36 offer made by one or more, but not all, defendants

36.12

(1) This rule applies where the claimant wishes to accept a Part 36 offer made by one or more, but not all, of a number of defendants.

(2) If the defendants are sued jointly or in the alternative, the claimant may accept the offer if –

(a) he discontinues his claim against those defendants who have not made the offer; and

(b) those defendants give written consent to the acceptance of the offer.

(3) If the claimant alleges that the defendants have a several liability(GL) to him, the claimant may –

(a) accept the offer; and

(b) continue with his claims against the other defendants if he is entitled to do so.

(4) In all other cases the claimant must apply to the court for an order permitting him to accept the Part 36 offer.

Restriction on disclosure of a Part 36 offer

36.13

(1) A Part 36 offer will be treated as ‘without prejudice(GL) except as to costs’.

(2) The fact that a Part 36 offer has been made must not be communicated to the trial judge or to the judge (if any) allocated in advance to conduct the trial until the case has been decided.

(3) Paragraph (2) does not apply –

(a) where the defence of tender before claim(GL) has been raised;

(b) where the proceedings have been stayed(GL) under rule 36.11 following acceptance of a Part 36 offer; or

(c) where the offeror and the offeree agree in writing that it should not apply.

Costs consequences following judgment

36.14

(1) Subject to rule 36.14A, this rule applies where upon judgment being entered –

(a) a claimant fails to obtain a judgment more advantageous than a defendant’s Part 36 offer; or

(b) judgment against the defendant is at least as advantageous to the claimant as the proposals contained in a claimant’s Part 36 offer.

(1A) For the purposes of paragraph (1), in relation to any money claim or money element of a claim, ‘more advantageous’ means better in money terms by any amount, however small, and ‘at least as advantageous’ shall be construed accordingly.

(2) Subject to paragraph (6), where rule 36.14(1)(a) applies, the court will, unless it considers it unjust to do so, order that the defendant is entitled to –

(a) costs from the date on which the relevant period expired; and

(b) interest on those costs.

(3) Subject to paragraph (6), where rule 36.14(1)(b) applies, the court will, unless it considers it unjust to do so, order that the claimant is entitled to –

(a) interest on the whole or part of any sum of money (excluding interest) awarded at a rate not exceeding 10% above base rate(GL) for some or all of the period starting with the date on which the relevant period expired;

(b) his costs on the indemnity basis from the date on which the relevant period expired; and

(c) interest on those costs at a rate not exceeding 10% above base rate[GL]; and

(d) an additional amount, which shall not exceed £75,000, calculated by applying the prescribed percentage set out below to an amount which is –

(i) where the claim is or includes a money claim, the sum awarded to the claimant by the court; or

(ii) where the claim is only a non-monetary claim, the sum awarded to the claimant by the court in respect of costs –

(4) In considering whether it would be unjust to make the orders referred to in paragraphs (2) and (3) above, the court will take into account all the circumstances of the case including –

(a) the terms of any Part 36 offer;

(b) the stage in the proceedings when any Part 36 offer was made, including in particular how long before the trial started the offer was made;

(c) the information available to the parties at the time when the Part 36 offer was made; and

(d) the conduct of the parties with regard to the giving or refusing to give information for the purposes of enabling the offer to be made or evaluated.

(5) Where the court awards interest under this rule and also awards interest on the same sum and for the same period under any other power, the total rate of interest may not exceed 10% above base rate(GL).

(6) Paragraphs (2) and (3) of this rule do not apply to a Part 36 offer –

(a) that has been withdrawn;

(b) that has been changed so that its terms are less advantageous to the offeree, and the offeree has beaten the less advantageous offer;

(c) made less than 21 days before trial, unless the court has abridged the relevant period.

(Rule 44.2 requires the court to consider an offer to settle that does not have the costs consequences set out in this Section in deciding what order to make about costs)

Costs consequences following judgment where Section IIIA of Part 45 applies

36.14A

(1) Where a claim no longer continues under the RTA or EL/PL Protocol pursuant to rule 45.29A(1), rule 36.14 applies with the following modifications.

(2) Subject to paragraph (3), where an order for costs is made pursuant to rule 36.14(2)—

(a) the claimant will be entitled to the fixed costs in Table 6B, 6C or 6D in Section IIIA of Part 45 for the stage applicable at the date on which the relevant period expired; and

(b) the claimant will be liable for the defendant’s costs from the date on which the relevant period expired to the date of judgment.

(3) Where the claimant fails to obtain a judgment more advantageous than the defendant’s Protocol offer—

(a) the claimant will be entitled to the applicable Stage 1 and Stage 2 fixed costs in Table 6 or Table 6A in Section III of Part 45; and

(b) the claimant will be liable for the defendant’s costs from the date on which the Protocol offer is deemed to be made to the date of judgment; and

(c) in this rule, the amount of the judgment is less than the Protocol offer where the judgment is less than the offer once deductible amounts identified in the judgment are deducted.

('Deductible amount' is defined in rule 36.15(1)(d).)

(4) For the purposes of this rule a defendant’s Protocol offer is either—

(a) defined in accordance with rules 36.17 and 36.18; or

(b) if the claim leaves the Protocol before the Court Proceedings Pack Form is sent to the defendant—

(i) the last offer made by the defendant before the claim leaves the Protocol; and

(ii) deemed to be made on the first business day after the claim leaves the Protocol.

(5) A reference to the ‘Court Proceedings Pack Form’ is a reference to the form used in the Protocol.

(6) Fixed costs shall be calculated by reference to the amount which is awarded.

(7) Where the court makes an order for costs in favour of the defendant—

(a) the court will have regard to; and

(b) the amount of costs ordered shall not exceed,

the fixed costs in Table 6B, 6C or 6D in Section IIIA of Part 45 applicable at the date of judgment, less the fixed costs to which the claimant is entitled under paragraph (2) or (3).

(8) The parties are entitled to disbursements allowed in accordance with rule 45.29I incurred in any period for which costs are payable to them.

Deduction of benefits and lump sum payments

36.15

(1) In this rule and rule 36.9 –

(a) ‘the 1997 Act’ means the Social Security (Recovery of Benefits) Act 1997[1];

(b) ‘the 2008 Regulations’ means the Social Security (Recovery of Benefits)(Lump Sum Payments) Regulations 2008^2;

(c) ‘recoverable amount’ means –

(i) ‘recoverable benefits’ as defined in section 1(4)(c) of the 1997 Act; and

(ii) ‘recoverable lump sum payments’ as defined in regulation 4 of the 2008 Regulations;

(d) ‘deductible amount’ means –

(i) any benefits by the amount of which damages are to be reduced in accordance with section 8 of, and Schedule 2 to the 1997 Act (‘deductible benefits’); and

(ii) any lump sum payment by the amount of which damages are to be reduced in accordance with regulation 12 of the 2008 Regulations (‘deductible lump sum payments’); and

(e) ‘certificate’ –

(i) in relation to recoverable benefits is construed in accordance with the provisions of the 1997 Act; and

(i) in relation to recoverable lump sum payments has the meaning given in section 29 of the 1997 Act as applied by regulation 2 of, and modified by Schedule 1 to the 2008 Regulations.

(2) This rule applies where a payment to a claimant following acceptance of a Part 36 offer would be a compensation payment as defined in section 1(4)(b) or 1A(5)(b) of the 1997 Act.

(3) A defendant who makes a Part 36 offer should state either –

(a) that the offer is made without regard to any liability for recoverable amounts; or

(b) that it is intended to include any deductible amounts.

(4) Where paragraph (3)(b) applies, paragraphs (5) to (9) of this rule will apply to the Part 36 offer.

(5) Before making the Part 36 offer, the offeror must apply for a certificate.

(6) Subject to paragraph (7), the Part 36 offer must state –

(a) the amount of gross compensation;

(b) the name and amount of any deductible amount by which the gross amount is reduced; and

(c) the net amount of compensation.

(7) If at the time the offeror makes the Part 36 offer, the offeror has applied for, but has not received a certificate, the offeror must clarify the offer by stating the matters referred to in paragraphs (6)(b) and (6)(c) not more than 7 days after receipt of the certificate.

(8) For the purposes of rule 36.14(1)(a), a claimant fails to recover more than any sum offered (including a lump sum offered under rule 36.5) if the claimant fails upon judgment being entered to recover a sum, once deductible amounts identified in the judgment have been deducted, greater than the net amount stated under paragraph (6)(c).

(Section 15(2) of the 1997 Act provides that the court must specify the compensation payment attributable to each head of damage. Schedule 1 to the 2008 Regulations modifies section 15 of the 1997 Act in relation to lump sum payments and provides that the court must specify the compensation payment attributable to each or any dependant who has received a lump sum payment.)

(9) Where –

(a) further deductible amounts have accrued since the Part 36 offer was made; and

(b) the court gives permission to accept the Part 36 offer,

the court may direct that the amount of the offer payable to the offeree shall be reduced by a sum equivalent to the deductible amounts paid to the claimant since the date of the offer.

(Rule 36.9(3)(b) states that permission is required to accept an offer where the relevant period has expired and further deductible amounts have been paid to the claimant)

II RTA PROTOCOL AND EL/PL PROTOCOL OFFERS TO SETTLE

Scope of this Section

36.16

(1) Where this Section applies Section I does not apply.

(2) This Section applies to an offer to settle where the parties have followed the RTA Protocol or the EL/PL Protocol and started proceedings under Part 8 in accordance with Practice Direction 8B (‘the Stage 3 Procedure’).

(3) A reference to the ‘Court Proceedings Pack Form’ is a reference to the form used in the Protocol.

(4) Nothing in this Section prevents a party making an offer to settle in whatever way that party chooses, but if the offer is not made in accordance with this Section, it will not have any costs consequences.

Form and content of a Protocol offer

36.17

(1) An offer to settle which is made in accordance with this rule is called a Protocol offer.

(2) A Protocol offer must –

(a) be set out in the Court Proceedings Pack (Part B) Form; and

(b) contain the final total amount of the offer from both parties.

Time when a Protocol offer is made

36.18  The Protocol offer is deemed to be made on the first business day after the Court Proceedings Pack (Part A and Part B) Form is sent to the defendant.

General provisions

36.19  A Protocol offer –

(a) is treated as exclusive of all interest; and

(b) has the consequences set out in this Section only in relation to the fixed costs of the Stage 3 Procedure as provided for in rule 45.18, and not in relation to the costs of any appeal from the final decision of those proceedings.

Restrictions on disclosure of a Protocol offer

36.20

(1) The amount of the Protocol offer must not be communicated to the court until the claim is determined.

(2) Any other offer to settle must not be communicated to the court at all.

(3) Once the claim is determined, the court will examine the Protocol offer.

Costs consequences following judgment

36.21

(1) This rule applies where, on the determination by the court, the claimant obtains judgment against the defendant for an amount of damages that is –

(a) less than or equal to the amount of the defendant’s Protocol offer;

(b) more than the defendant’s Protocol offer but less than the claimant's Protocol offer; or

(c) equal to or more than the claimant’s Protocol offer.

(2) Where paragraph (1)(a) applies, the court will order the claimant to pay –

(a) the fixed costs in rule 45.26; and

(b) interest on those fixed costs from the first business day after the deemed date of the Protocol offer under rule 36.18.

(3) Where paragraph (1)(b) applies, the court will order the defendant to pay the fixed costs in rule 45.20.

(4) Where paragraph (1)(c) applies, the court will order the defendant to pay –

(a) interest on the whole of the damages awarded at a rate not exceeding 10% above base rate for some or all of the period starting with the date specified in rule 36.18;

(b) the fixed costs in rule 45.20;

(c) interest on those costs at a rate not exceeding 10% above base rate; and

(d) an additional amount calculated in accordance with rule 36.14(3)(d).

Deduction of benefits

36.22  For the purposes of rule 36.21(1)(a) the amount of the judgment is less than the Protocol offer where the judgment is less than that offer once deductible amounts identified in the judgment are deducted.

(‘Deductible amount’ is defined in rule 36.15(1)(d).)

Footnotes

1997 c. 27. Back to text
S.I. 2008/1596. Back to text

PART 38 - DISCONTINUANCE

Contents of this Part

Scope of this Part

38.1

(1) The rules in this Part set out the procedure by which a claimant may discontinue all or part of a claim.

(2) A claimant who –

(a) claims more than one remedy; and

(b) subsequently abandons his claim to one or more of the remedies but continues with his claim for the other remedies,

is not treated as discontinuing all or part of a claim for the purposes of this Part.

(The procedure for amending a statement of case, set out in Part 17, applies where a claimant abandons a claim for a particular remedy but wishes to continue with his claim for other remedies)

Right to discontinue claim

38.2

(1) A claimant may discontinue all or part of a claim at any time.

(2) However –

(a) a claimant must obtain the permission of the court if he wishes to discontinue all or part of a claim in relation to which –

(i) the court has granted an interim injunction(GL); or

(ii) any party has given an undertaking to the court;

(b) where the claimant has received an interim payment in relation to a claim (whether voluntarily or pursuant to an order under Part 25), he may discontinue that claim only if –

(i) the defendant who made the interim payment consents in writing; or

(ii) the court gives permission;

(c) where there is more than one claimant, a claimant may not discontinue unless –

(i) every other claimant consents in writing; or

(ii) the court gives permission.

(3) Where there is more than one defendant, the claimant may discontinue all or part of a claim against all or any of the defendants.

Procedure for discontinuing

38.3

(1) To discontinue a claim or part of a claim, a claimant must –

(a) file a notice of discontinuance; and

(b) serve a copy of it on every other party to the proceedings.

(2) The claimant must state in the notice of discontinuance which he files that he has served notice of discontinuance on every other party to the proceedings.

(3) Where the claimant needs the consent of some other party, a copy of the necessary consent must be attached to the notice of discontinuance.

(4) Where there is more than one defendant, the notice of discontinuance must specify against which defendants the claim is discontinued.

Right to apply to have notice of discontinuance set aside

38.4

(1) Where the claimant discontinues under rule 38.2(1) the defendant may apply to have the notice of discontinuance set aside(GL).

(2) The defendant may not make an application under this rule more than 28 days after the date when the notice of discontinuance was served on him.

When discontinuance takes effect where permission of the court is not needed

38.5

(1) Discontinuance against any defendant takes effect on the date when notice of discontinuance is served on him under rule 38.3(1).

(2) Subject to rule 38.4, the proceedings are brought to an end as against him on that date.

(3) However, this does not affect proceedings to deal with any question of costs.

Liability for costs

38.6

(1) Unless the court orders otherwise, a claimant who discontinues is liable for the costs which a defendant against whom the claimant discontinues incurred on or before the date on which notice of discontinuance was served on the defendant.

(2) If proceedings are only partly discontinued –

(a) the claimant is liable under paragraph (1) for costs relating only to the part of the proceedings which he is discontinuing; and

(b) unless the court orders otherwise, the costs which the claimant is liable to pay must not be assessed until the conclusion of the rest of the proceedings.

(3) This rule does not apply to claims allocated to the small claims track.

(Rule 44.9 provides for the basis of assessment where the right to costs arises on discontinuance and contains provisions about when a costs order is deemed to have been made and applying for an order under section 194(3) of the Legal Services Act 2007)

Discontinuance and subsequent proceedings

38.7  A claimant who discontinues a claim needs the permission of the court to make another claim against the same defendant if –

(a) he discontinued the claim after the defendant filed a defence; and

(b) the other claim arises out of facts which are the same or substantially the same as those relating to the discontinued claim.

Stay of remainder of partly discontinued proceedings where costs not paid

38.8

(1) This rule applies where –

(a) proceedings are partly discontinued;

(b) a claimant is liable to –

(i) pay costs under rule 38.6; or

(ii) make a payment pursuant to an order under section 194(3) of the Legal Services Act 2007; and

(c) the claimant fails to pay those costs or make the payment within 14 days of –

(i) the date on which the parties agreed the sum payable by the claimant; or

(ii) the date on which the court ordered the costs to be paid or the payment to be made.

(2) Where this rule applies, the court may stay(GL) the remainder of the proceedings until the claimant pays the whole of the costs which the claimant is liable to pay under rule 38.6 or makes the payment pursuant to an order under section 194(3) of the Legal Services Act 2007.

(Rules 44.9 and 46.7 contain provisions about applying for an order under section 194(3) of the Legal Services Act 2007.)

PART 40 - JUDGMENTS, ORDERS, SALE OF LAND ETC.

Contents of this Part

Title | Number
I JUDGMENTS AND ORDERS |

Scope of this section | Rule 40.1
Standard requirements | Rule 40.2
Drawing up and filing of judgments and orders | Rule 40.3
Service of judgments and orders | Rule 40.4
Power to require judgment or order to be served on a party as well as his solicitor | Rule 40.5
Consent judgments and orders | Rule 40.6
When judgment or order takes effect | Rule 40.7
Time from which interest begins to run | Rule 40.8
Who may apply to set aside or vary a judgment or order | Rule 40.9
Judgment against a State in default of acknowledgment of service | Rule 40.10
Time for complying with a judgment or order | Rule 40.11
Correction of errors in judgments and orders | Rule 40.12
Cases where court gives judgment both on claim and counterclaim | Rule 40.13
Judgment in favour of certain part owners relating to the detention of goods | Rule 40.14
II SALE OF LAND ETC. AND CONVEYANCING COUNSEL |

Scope of this Section | Rule 40.15
Power to order sale etc. | Rule 40.16
Power to order delivery up of possession etc. | Rule 40.17
Reference to conveyancing counsel | Rule 40.18
Party may object to report | Rule 40.19
III DECLARATORY JUDGMENTS |

Declaratory Judgments | Rule 40.20

I JUDGMENTS AND ORDERS

Scope of this section

40.1  This Section sets out rules about judgments and orders which apply except where any other of these Rules or a practice direction makes a different provision in relation to the judgment or order in question.

Standard requirements

40.2

(1) Every judgment or order must state the name and judicial title of the person who made it, unless it is –

(a) default judgment entered under rule 12.4(1) (entry of default judgment where judgment is entered by a court officer) or a default costs certificate obtained under rule 47.11;

(b) judgment entered under rule 14.4, 14.5, 14.6, 14.7 and 14.9 (entry of judgment on admission where judgment is entered by a court officer);

(c) a consent order under rule 40.6(2) (consent orders made by court officers);

(d) an order made by a court officer under rule 70.5 (orders to enforce awards as if payable under a court order); or

(e) an order made by a court officer under rule 71.2 (orders to obtain information from judgment debtors).

(2) Every judgment or order must –

(a) bear the date on which it is given or made; and

(b) be sealed(GL) by the court.

(3) Paragraph (4) applies where a party applies for permission to appeal against a judgment or order at the hearing at which the judgment or order was made.

(4) Where this paragraph applies, the judgment or order shall state –

(a) whether or not the judgment or order is final;

(b) whether an appeal lies from the judgment or order and, if so, to which appeal court;

(c) whether the court gives permission to appeal; and

(d) if not, the appropriate appeal court to which any further application for permission may be made.

(Paragraph 4.3B of Practice Direction 52 deals with the court’s power to adjourn a hearing where a judgment or order is handed down and no application for permission to appeal is made at that hearing)

Drawing up and filing of judgments and orders

40.3

(1) Except as is provided at paragraph (4) below or by any Practice Direction, every judgment or order will be drawn up by the court unless –

(a) the court orders a party to draw it up;

(b) a party, with the permission of the court, agrees to draw it up;

(c) the court dispenses with the need to draw it up; or

(d) it is a consent order under rule 40.6.

(2) The court may direct that –

(a) a judgment or an order drawn up by a party must be checked by the court before it is sealed(GL); or

(b) before a judgment or an order is drawn up by the court, the parties must file an agreed statement of its terms.

(3) Where a judgment or an order is to be drawn up by a party –

(a) he must file it no later than 7 days after the date on which the court ordered or permitted him to draw it up so that it can be sealed(GL) by the court; and

(b) if he fails to file it within that period, any other party may draw it up and file it.

(4) Except for orders made by the court of its own initiative and unless the court otherwise orders, every judgment or order made in claims proceeding in the Queen’s Bench Division at the Royal Courts of Justice, other than in the Administrative Court, will be drawn up by the parties, and rule 40.3 is modified accordingly.

Service of judgments and orders

40.4

(1) Where a judgment or an order has been drawn up by a party and is to be served by the court –

(a) the party who drew it up must file a copy to be retained at court and sufficient copies for service on him and on the other parties; and

(b) once it has been sealed[GL], the court must serve a copy of it on each party to the proceedings.

(2) Unless the court directs otherwise, any order made otherwise than at trial must be served on –

(a) the applicant and the respondent; and

(b) any other person on whom the court orders it to be served.

(Rule 6.21 sets out who is to serve a document other than the claim form.)

Power to require judgment or order to be served on a party as well as his solicitor

40.5

Where the party on whom a judgment or order is to be served is acting by a solicitor, the court may order the judgment or order to be served on the party as well as on his solicitor.

Consent judgments and orders

40.6

(1) This rule applies where all the parties agree the terms in which a judgment should be given or an order should be made.

(2) A court officer may enter and seal(GL) an agreed judgment or order if –

(a) the judgment or order is listed in paragraph (3);

(b) none of the parties is a litigant in person; and

(c) the approval of the court is not required by these Rules, a practice direction or any enactment before an agreed order can be made.

(3) The judgments and orders referred to in paragraph (2) are –

(a) a judgment or order for –

(i) the payment of an amount of money (including a judgment or order for damages or the value of goods to be decided by the court); or

(ii) the delivery up of goods with or without the option of paying the value of the goods or the agreed value.

(b) an order for –

(i) the dismissal of any proceedings, wholly or in part;

(ii) the stay(GL) of proceedings on agreed terms, disposing of the proceedings, whether those terms are recorded in a schedule to the order or elsewhere;

(iii) the stay of enforcement of a judgment, either unconditionally or on condition that the money due under the judgment is paid by instalments specified in the order;

(iv) the setting aside under Part 13 of a default judgment which has not been satisfied;

(v) the payment out of money which has been paid into court;

(vi) the discharge from liability of any party;

(vii) the payment, assessment or waiver of costs, or such other provision for costs as may be agreed.

(4) Rule 40.3 (drawing up and filing of judgments and orders) applies to judgments and orders entered and sealed by a court officer under paragraph (2) as it applies to other judgments and orders.

(5) Where paragraph (2) does not apply, any party may apply for a judgment or order in the terms agreed.

(6) The court may deal with an application under paragraph (5) without a hearing.

(7) Where this rule applies –

(a) the order which is agreed by the parties must be drawn up in the terms agreed;

(b) it must be expressed as being ‘By Consent’;

(c) it must be signed by the legal representative acting for each of the parties to whom the order relates or, where paragraph (5) applies, by the party if he is a litigant in person.

When judgment or order takes effect

40.7

(1) A judgment or order takes effect from the day when it is given or made, or such later date as the court may specify.

(2) This rule applies to all judgments and orders except those to which rule 40.10 (judgment against a State) applies.

Time from which interest begins to run

40.8

(1) Where interest is payable on a judgment pursuant to section 17 of the Judgments Act 1838^1 or section 74 of the County Courts Act 1984^2, the interest shall begin to run from the date that judgment is given unless –

(a) a rule in another Part or a practice direction makes different provision; or

(b) the court orders otherwise.

(2) The court may order that interest shall begin to run from a date before the date that judgment is given.

Who may apply to set aside or vary a judgment or order

40.9  A person who is not a party but who is directly affected by a judgment or order may apply to have the judgment or order set aside or varied.

Judgment against a State in default of acknowledgment of service

40.10

(1) Where the claimant obtains default judgment under Part 12 on a claim against a State where the defendant has failed to file an acknowledgment of service, the judgment does not take effect until 2 months after service on the State of –

(a) a copy of the judgment; and

(b) a copy of the evidence in support of the application for permission to enter default judgment (unless the evidence has already been served on the State in accordance with an order made under Part 12).

(2) In this rule, ‘State’ has the meaning given by section 14 of the State Immunity Act 1978^3.

Time for complying with a judgment or order

40.11  A party must comply with a judgment or order for the payment of an amount of money (including costs) within 14 days of the date of the judgment or order, unless –

(a) the judgment or order specifies a different date for compliance (including specifying payment by instalments);

(b) any of these Rules specifies a different date for compliance; or

(c) the court has stayed the proceedings or judgment.

(Parts 12 and 14 specify different dates for complying with certain default judgments and judgments on admissions)

Correction of errors in judgments and orders

40.12

(1) The court may at any time correct an accidental slip or omission in a judgment or order.

(2) A party may apply for a correction without notice.

Cases where court gives judgment both on claim and counterclaim

40.13

(1) This rule applies where the court gives judgment for specified amounts both for the claimant on his claim and against the claimant on a counterclaim.

(2) If there is a balance in favour of one of the parties, it may order the party whose judgment is for the lesser amount to pay the balance.

(3) In a case to which this rule applies, the court may make a separate order as to costs against each party.

Judgment in favour of certain part owners relating to the detention of goods

40.14

(1) In this rule ‘part owner’ means one of two or more persons who have an interest in the same goods.

(2) Where –

(a) a part owner makes a claim relating to the detention of the goods; and

(b) the claim is not based on a right to possession,

any judgment or order given or made in respect of the claim is to be for the payment of damages only, unless the claimant had the written authority of every other part owner of the goods to make the claim on his behalf as well as for himself.

(3) This rule applies notwithstanding anything in subsection (3) of section 3 of the Torts (Interference with Goods) Act 1977^4, but does not affect the remedies and jurisdiction mentioned in subsection (8) of that section.

II SALE OF LAND ETC. AND CONVEYANCING COUNSEL

Scope of this Section

40.15

(1) This Section –

(a) deals with the court’s power to order the sale, mortgage, partition or exchange of land; and

(b) contains provisions about conveyancing counsel.

(Section 131 of the Supreme Court Act 19815 (provides for the appointment of the conveyancing counsel of the Supreme Court)

(2) In this Section ‘land’ includes any interest in, or right over, land.

Power to order sale etc.

40.16  In any proceedings relating to land, the court may order the land, or part of it, to be –

(a) sold;

(b) mortgaged;

(c) exchanged; or

(d) partitioned.

Power to order delivery up of possession etc.

40.17  Where the court has made an order under rule 40.16, it may order any party to deliver up to the purchaser or any other person –

(a) possession of the land;

(b) receipt of rents or profits relating to it; or

(c) both.

Reference to conveyancing counsel

40.18

(1) The court may direct conveyancing counsel to investigate and prepare a report on the title of any land or to draft any document.

(2) The court may take the report on title into account when it decides the issue in question.

(Provisions dealing with the fees payable to conveyancing counsel are set out in paragraph 5.2 of Practice Direction 44.)

Party may object to report

40.19

(1) Any party to the proceedings may object to the report on title prepared by conveyancing counsel.

(2) Where there is an objection, the issue will be referred to a judge for determination.

(Part 23 contains general rules about making an application)

III DECLARATORY JUDGMENTS

Declaratory Judgments

40.20  The court may make binding declarations whether or not any other remedy is claimed.

Footnotes

1838 c.110. Section 17 was amended by S.I. 1998/2940. Back to text
1984 c.28. Section 74 was amended by section 2 of the Private International Law (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 1995 (c.42). Back to text
1978 c.33. Back to text

1977 c.32. Back to text

1981 c.54; section 131 was amended by the Courts and Legal Services Act 1990 (c.41), Schedule 10, paragraph 48. Back to text

PRACTICE DIRECTION 40E – RESERVED JUDGMENTS

This Practice Direction supplements CPR Part 40

Contents of this Practice Direction

Title | Number
Scope and interpretation | Para. 1.1
Availability of reserved judgments before handing down | Para. 2.1
Corrections to the draft judgment | Para. 3.1
Orders consequential on judgment | Para. 4.1
Attendance at handing down | Para. 5.1

Scope and interpretation

1.1

This Practice Direction applies to all reserved judgments which the court intends to hand down in writing.

1.2

In this Practice Direction –

(a) ‘relevant court office’ means the office of the court in which judgment is to be given; and

(b) ‘working day’ means any day on which the relevant court office is open.

Availability of reserved judgments before handing down

2.1

Where judgment is to be reserved the judge (or Presiding Judge) may, at the conclusion of the hearing, invite the views of the parties’ legal representatives as to the arrangements made for the handing down of the judgment.

2.2

Unless the court directs otherwise, the following provisions of this paragraph apply where the judge or Presiding Judge is satisfied that the judgment will attract no special degree of confidentiality or sensitivity.

2.3

The court will provide a copy of the draft judgment to the parties’ legal representatives by 4 p.m. on the second working day before handing down, or at such other time as the court may direct.

2.4

A copy of the draft judgment may be supplied, in confidence, to the parties provided that –

(a) neither the draft judgment nor its substance is disclosed to any other person or used in the public domain; and

(b) no action is taken (other than internally) in response to the draft judgment, before the judgment is handed down.

2.5

Where a copy of the draft judgment is supplied to a party’s legal representatives in electronic form, they may supply a copy to that party in the same form.

2.6

If a party to whom a copy of the draft judgment is supplied under paragraph 2.4 is a partnership, company, government department, local authority or other organisation of a similar nature, additional copies may be distributed in confidence within the organisation, provided that all reasonable steps are taken to preserve its confidential nature and the requirements of paragraph 2.4 are adhered to.

2.7

If the parties or their legal representatives are in any doubt about the persons to whom copies of the draft judgment may be distributed they should enquire of the judge or Presiding Judge.

2.8

Any breach of the obligations or restrictions under paragraph 2.4 or failure to take all reasonable steps under paragraph 2.6 may be treated as contempt of court.

2.9

The case will be listed for judgment, and judgment handed down at the appropriate time.

Corrections to the draft judgment

3.1

Unless the parties or their legal representatives are told otherwise when the draft judgment is circulated, any proposed corrections to the draft judgment should be sent to the clerk of the judge who prepared the draft with a copy to any other party.

Orders consequential on judgment

4.1

Following the circulation of the draft judgment the parties or their legal representatives must seek to agree orders consequential upon the judgment.

4.2

In respect of any draft agreed order the parties must –

(a) fax or e-mail a copy to the clerk to the judge or Presiding Judge (together with any proposed corrections or amendments to the draft judgment); and

(b) file four copies (with completed backsheets) in the relevant court office, by 12 noon on the working day before handing down.

4.3

A copy of a draft order must bear the case reference, the date of handing down and the name of the judge or Presiding Judge.

4.4

Where a party wishes to apply for an order consequential on the judgment the application must be made by filing written submissions with the clerk to the judge or Presiding Judge by 12 noon on the working day before handing down.

4.5

Unless the court orders otherwise –

(a) where judgment is to be given by an appeal court (which has the same meaning as in rule 52.1(3)(b)), the application will be determined without a hearing; and

(b) where judgment is to be given by any other court, the application will be determined at a hearing.

Attendance at handing down

5.1

If there is not to be an oral hearing of an application for an order consequential on judgment –

(a) the parties’ advocates need not attend on the handing down of judgment; and

(b) the judgment may be handed down by a judge sitting alone.

5.2

Where paragraph 5.1(a) applies but an advocate does attend the handing down of judgment, the court may if it considers such attendance unnecessary, disallow the costs of the attendance.

PRACTICE DIRECTION 40F - NON-DISCLOSURE INJUNCTIONS INFORMATION COLLECTION SCHEME

Contents of this Practice Direction

Title
Annex

1.

This Practice Direction provides for a scheme for the recording, and transmission to the Ministry of Justice for analysis, of certain data in relation to injunctions[GL] prohibiting publication of private or confidential information. The purpose of the scheme is to enable the Ministry of Justice to collate and publish, in anonymised form, information about applications for injunctions where section 12 of the Human Rights Act 1998 is engaged.

2.

The scheme applies in any civil proceedings in the High Court or Court of Appeal in which the court considers an application for an injunction prohibiting the publication of private or confidential information, the continuation of such an injunction, or an appeal against the grant or refusal of such an injunction. The scheme does not apply to proceedings to which the Family Procedure Rules 2010 apply, to immigration or asylum proceedings, to proceedings which raise issues of national security or to proceedings to which Part 21 applies.

3.

An injunction to which this Practice Direction applies is called a ‘Non-disclosure injunction’.

4.

Except where a direction under paragraph 6 is made, following the hearing of an application for a non-disclosure injunction[GL] or any appeal against the grant or refusal of any such injunction the judge will record the following information in the form attached in the Annex (the information) –

(a) the claim or application number;

(b) whether the hearing was of –

(i) an application for an interim injunction;

(ii) an application for an extension or variation of an interim injunction;

(iii) an application for a final injunction; or

(iv) an appeal against the grant or refusal of an interim or final injunction.

(c) whether the hearing was on notice, or without notice to –

(i) the defendant; or

(ii) any third party liable to be affected by the order.

(d) whether the parties consented to the order;

(e) whether any derogations from the principle of open justice were sought, and if so –

(i) what they were;

(ii) whether they were granted;

(iii) if granted, whether with the parties’ consent.

5.

Derogations from the principle of open justice include, but are not limited to –

(a) an order that the hearing be held wholly or partly in private;

(b) an order that the names of one or more of the parties not be disclosed;

(c) an order that access to documents on the court file be restricted (under rule 5.4C or the inherent jurisdiction);

(d) an order that the provision of documents to third parties be restricted (under Practice Direction 25A, paragraph 9.2); and

(e) an order prohibiting disclosure of the existence of the proceedings or the order.

6.

Subject to any express direction to the contrary in the order, any order made by the court on an application for a non-disclosure injunction[GL] or appeal from the grant or refusal of such an injunction shall be deemed to include a provision giving permission to a court officer to transmit the information to the Chief Statistician in the Ministry of Justice in order for it to be analysed and published in such form as does not enable the public identification of the parties to any proceedings.

7.

If, in exceptional circumstances, the judge makes any direction under paragraph 6, the judge shall report that fact, and the nature of any derogation from open justice contained in the non-disclosure injunction to the Master of the Rolls. The Master of the Rolls is, following consultation with the judge, entitled to transmit such information as he sees fit to the Chief Statistician to enable publication by the Ministry of Justice of the bare fact that an injunction of that type had been made.

8.

Once completed the form in the Annex will be sent by a court officer to the Chief Statistician in the Ministry of Justice.

Annex

High Court and Court of Appeal privacy injunctions statistics form (PDF 0.03mb)

PRACTICE DIRECTION 41A – PROVISIONAL DAMAGES

This practice direction supplements CPR Part 41

Claims for provisional damages

1.1

CPR Part 16 and Practice Direction 16 set out information which must be included in the particulars of claim if a claim for provisional damages is made.

Judgment for an award of provisional damages

2.1

When giving judgment at trial the judge will:

(1) specify the disease or type of deterioration, or diseases or types of deterioration, which

(a) for the purpose of the award of immediate damages it has been assumed will not occur, and

(b) will entitle the claimant to further damages if it or they do occur at a future date,

(2) give an award of immediate damages,

(3) specify the period or periods within which an application for further damages may be made in respect of each disease or type of deterioration, and

(4) direct what documents are to be filed and preserved as the case file in support of any application for further damages.

2.2

The claimant may make an application or applications to extend the periods referred to in paragraph 2.1(3) above[1].

2.3

A period specified under paragraph 2.1(3) may be expressed as being for the duration of the life of the claimant.

2.4

The documents to be preserved as the case file (‘the case file documents’) referred to in paragraph 2.1(4) will be set out in a schedule to the judgment as entered.

2.5

Causation of any further damages within the scope of the order shall be determined when any application for further damages is made.

2.6

A form for a provisional damages judgment is set out in the Annex to this practice direction.

The case file

3.1

The case file documents must be preserved until the expiry of the period or periods specified or of any extension of them.

3.2

The case file documents will normally include:

(1) the judgment as entered,

(2) the statements of case,

(3) a transcript of the judge’s oral judgment,

(4) all medical reports relied on, and

(5) a transcript of any parts of the claimant’s own evidence which the judge considers necessary.

3.3

The associate/court clerk will:

(1) ensure that the case file documents are provided by the parties where necesary and filed on the court file,

(2) endorse the court file

(a) to the effect that it contains the case file documents, and

(b) with the period during which the case file documents must be preserved, and

(3) preserve the case file documents in the court office where the proceedings took place.

3.4

Any subsequent order:

(1) extending the period within which an application for further damages may be made, or

(2) of the Court of Appeal discharging or varying the provisions of the original judgment or of any subsequent order under sub-paragraph (1) above,

will become one of the case file documents and must be preserved accordingly and any variation of the period within which an application for further damages may be made should be endorsed on the court file containing the case file documents.

3.5

On an application to extend the periods referred to in paragraph 2.1(3) above a current medical report should be filed.

3.6

Legal representatives are reminded that it is their duty to preserve their own case file.

Consent orders

4.1

An application to give effect to a consent order for provisional damages should be made in accordance with CPR Part 23. If the claimant is a child or protected party[2] the approval of the court must also be sought and the application for approval will normally be dealt with at a hearing.

4.2

The order should be in the form of a consent judgment and should contain:

(1) the matters set out in paragraph 2.1(1) to (3) above, and

(2) a direction as to the documents to be preserved as the case file documents, which will normally be

(a) the consent judgment,

(b) any statements of case,

(c) an agreed statement of facts, and

(d) any agreed medical report(s).

4.3

The claimant or his legal representative must lodge the case file documents in the court office where the proceedings are taking place for inclusion in the court file. The court file should be endorsed as in paragraph 3.3(2) above, and the case file documents preserved as in paragraph 3.3(3) above.

Default judgment

5.1

Where a defendant:

(1) fails to file an acknowledgment of service in accordance with CPR Part 10, and

(2) fails to file a defence in accordance with CPR Part 15,

within the time specified for doing so, the claimant may not, unless he abandons his claim for provisional damages, enter judgment in default but should make an application in accordance with CPR Part 23 for directions.

5.2

The Master or district judge will normally direct the following issues to be decided:

(1) whether the claim is an appropriate one for an award of provisional damages and if so, on what terms, and

(2) the amount of immediate damages.

5.3

If the judge makes an award of provisional damages, the provisions of paragraph 3 above apply.

ANNEX

(Example of an award of provisional damages after trial)

(Title of proceedings)

THIS CLAIM having been tried before [title and name of judge] without a jury at [the Royal Courts of Justice or as may be] and [title and name of judge] having ordered that judgment as set out below be entered for the claimant

IT IS ORDERED –

(1) that the defendant pay the claimant by way of immediate damages the sum of £............... (being (i) £.............. for special damages and £............. [agreed interest][interest at the rate of ...... from...........to............] (ii) £.............. for general damages and £.............. [agreed interest][interest at the rate of 2% from......... to...........] and (iii) £............... for loss of future earnings and/or earning capacity) on the assumption that the claimant would not at a future date as a result of the act or omission giving rise to the claim develop the following disease/type of deterioration namely [set out disease or type of deterioration]

(2) that if the claimant at a further date does develop that [disease][type of deterioration] he should be entitled to apply for further damages provided that the application is made on or before [set out period]

(3) that the documents set out in the schedule to this order be filed on the court file and preserved as the case file until the expiry of the period set out in paragraph (2) above or of any extension of that period which has been ordered

(4) (costs)

SCHEDULE

(list documents referred to in paragraph (3))

Footnotes

1. See CPR rule 41.2(3). Back to text

2. See Part 21 for the meaning of ‘child’ and ‘protected party’. Back to text

PART 42 - CHANGE OF SOLICITOR

Contents of this Part

Title | Number
Solicitor acting for a party | Rule 42.1
Change of solicitor – duty to give notice | Rule 42.2
Order that a solicitor has ceased to act | Rule 42.3
Removal of solicitor who has ceased to act on application of another party | Rule 42.4

Solicitor acting for a party

42.1  Where the address for service of a party is the business address of his solicitor, the solicitor will be considered to be acting for that party until the provisions of this Part have been complied with.

(Part 6 contains provisions about the address for service)

Change of solicitor – duty to give notice

42.2

(1) This rule applies where –

(a) a party for whom a solicitor is acting wants to change his solicitor;

(b) a party, after having conducted the claim in person, appoints a solicitor to act on his behalf (except where the solicitor is appointed only to act as an advocate for a hearing); or

(c) a party, after having conducted the claim by a solicitor, intends to act in person.

(2) Where this rule applies, the party or his solicitor (where one is acting) must –

(a) file notice of the change; and

(b) serve notice of the change on every other party and, where paragraph (1)(a) or (c) applies, on the former solicitor.

(3) The notice must state the party’s new address for service.

(4) The notice filed at court must state that notice has been served as required by paragraph (2)(b).

(5) Subject to paragraph (6), where a party has changed his solicitor or intends to act in person, the former solicitor will be considered to be the party’s solicitor unless and until –

(a) notice is filed and served in accordance with paragraph (2); or

(b) the court makes an order under rule 42.3 and the order is served as required by paragraph (3) of that rule.

(6) Where the certificate of a LSC funded client or an assisted person is revoked or discharged –

(a) the solicitor who acted for that person will cease to be the solicitor acting in the case as soon as his retainer is determined –

(i) under regulation 4 of the Community Legal Service (Costs) Regulations 2000[1]; or

(ii) under regulation 83 of the Civil Legal Aid (General) Regulations 1989^2; and

(b) if that person wishes to continue –

(i) where he appoints a solicitor to act on his behalf, paragraph (2) will apply as if he had previously conducted the claim in person; and

(ii) where he wants to act in person, he must give an address for service.

(Rules 6.23 and 6.24 contain provisions about a party’s address for service.)

(7) ‘Certificate’ in paragraph (6) means –

(a) in the case of a LSC funded client, a certificate issued under the Funding Code (approved under section 9 of the Access to Justice Act 1999[3]), or

(b) in the case of an assisted person, a certificate within the meaning of the Civil Legal Aid (General) Regulations 1989.

Order that a solicitor has ceased to act

42.3

(1) A solicitor may apply for an order declaring that he has ceased to be the solicitor acting for a party.

(2) Where an application is made under this rule –

(a) notice of the application must be given to the party for whom the solicitor is acting, unless the court directs otherwise; and

(b) the application must be supported by evidence.

(3) Where the court makes an order that a solicitor has ceased to act –

(a) a copy of the order must be served on every party to the proceedings; and

(b) if it is served by a party or the solicitor, the party or the solicitor (as the case may be) must file a certificate of service.

Removal of solicitor who has ceased to act on application of another party

42.4

(1) Where –

(a) a solicitor who has acted for a party –

(i) has died;

(ii) has become bankrupt;

(iii) has ceased to practice; or

(iv) cannot be found; and

(b) the party has not given notice of a change of solicitor or notice of intention to act in person as required by rule 42.2(2),

any other party may apply for an order declaring that the solicitor has ceased to be the solicitor acting for the other party in the case.

(2) Where an application is made under this rule, notice of the application must be given to the party to whose solicitor the application relates unless the court directs otherwise.

(3) Where the court makes an order made under this rule –

(a) a copy of the order must be served on every other party to the proceedings; and

(b) where it is served by a party, that party must file a certificate of service.

Footnotes

S.I. 2000/441. Back to text
S.I. 1989/339 to which there are amendments not relevant to these Rules. Back to text
1999 c.22. Back to text

PRACTICE DIRECTION 44 - GENERAL RULES ABOUT COSTS

This Practice Direction supplements Part 44

Contents of this Practice Direction

Title | Number
SECTION I – GENERAL |
Documents and forms |
Special provisions relating to VAT |
Scope of this subsection | Para. 2.1
VAT Registration Number | Para. 2.2
Entitlement to VAT on Costs | Para. 2.3
Form of bill of costs where VAT rate changes | Para. 2.7
Apportionment | Para. 2.9
Change in VAT rate between the conclusion of a detailed settlement and the issue of a final certificate | Para. 2.10
Disbursements not classified as such for VAT purposes | Para. 2.11
Litigants in person | Para. 2.12
Government Departments | Para. 2.13
Payment pursuant to an order under section 194(3) of the 2007 Act | Para. 2.14
Costs budgets |
Court's discretion as to costs: rule 44.2 |
Fees of Counsel |
Basis of assessment: rule 44.3 |
Costs on the indemnity basis | Para. 6.1
Costs on the standard basis | Para. 6.2
Amount of costs where costs are payable pursuant to a contract: rule 44.5 |
Application of rule 44.5 | Para. 7.1
Costs relating to a mortgage | Para. 7.2
Procedure for assessing costs: rule 44.6 |
Summary assessment: general provisions |
When the court should consider whether to make a summary assessment | Para. 9.1
Timing of summary assessment | Para. 9.2
Summary assessment of mortgagee's costs | Para. 9.3
Consent orders | Para. 9.4
Duty of parties and legal representatives | Para. 9.5
No summary assessment by a costs officer | Para. 9.7
Assisted persons etc | Para. 9.8
Children or protected parties | Para. 9.9
Disproportionate or unreasonable costs | Para. 9.10
Legal representative's duty to notify party: rule 44.8 |
Court's powers in relation to misconduct: rule 44.11 |
SECTION II – QUALIFIED ONE-WAY COSTS SHIFTING |
Qualified one-way costs shifting |

SECTION I – GENERAL

Documents and forms

1.1

In respect of any document which is required by Practice Directions 44 to 47 to be signed by a party or that party's legal representative, the provisions of Practice Direction 22 relating to who may sign apply as if the document in question was a statement of truth. Statements of truth are not required in assessment proceedings unless a rule or Practice Direction so requires or the court so orders.

(Practice Direction 22 makes provision for cases in which a party is a child, a protected party or a company or other corporation and cases in which a document is signed on behalf of a partnership.)

1.2

Form N260 is a model form of Statement of Costs to be used for summary assessments.

(Further details about Statements of Costs are given in paragraph 9.5 below.)

Precedents A, B and C in the Schedule of Costs Precedents annexed to this Practice Direction are model forms of bills of costs to be used for detailed assessments. A party wishing to rely upon a bill which departs from the model forms should include in the background information of the bill an explanation for that departure.

(Further details about bills of costs are given in Practice Direction 47.)

Special provisions relating to VAT

Scope of this subsection

2.1

This subsection deals with claims for VAT) which are made in respect of costs being dealt with by way of summary assessment or detailed assessment.

VAT Registration Number

2.2

The number allocated by HMRC to every person registered under the Value Added Tax Act 1994 (except a Government Department) must appear in a prominent place at the head of every statement, bill of costs, fee sheet, account or voucher on which VAT is being included as part of a claim for costs.

Entitlement to VAT on Costs

2.3

VAT should not be included in a claim for costs if the receiving party is able to recover the VAT as input tax. Where the receiving party is able to obtain credit from HMRC for a proportion of the VAT as input tax, only that proportion which is not eligible for credit should be included in the claim for costs.

2.4

The receiving party has responsibility for ensuring that VAT is claimed only when the receiving party is unable to recover the VAT or a proportion thereof as input tax.

2.5

Where there is a dispute as to whether VAT is properly claimed the receiving party must provide a certificate signed by the legal representatives or the auditors of the receiving party substantially in the form illustrated in Precedent F in the Schedule of Costs Precedents annexed to Practice Direction 47. Where the receiving party is a litigant in person who is claiming VAT, evidence to support the claim (such as a letter from HMRC) must be produced at the hearing at which the costs are assessed.

2.6

Where there is a dispute as to whether any service in respect of which a charge is proposed to be made in the bill is zero rated or exempt from VAT, reference should be made to HMRC and its view obtained and made known at the hearing at which the costs are assessed. Such enquiry should be made by the receiving party. In the case of a bill from a solicitor to the solicitor's legal representative's own client, such enquiry should be made by the client.

Form of bill of costs where VAT rate changes

2.7

Where there is a change in the rate of VAT, suppliers of goods and services are entitled by sections 88 (1) and 88(2) of the Value Added Tax Act 1994 in most circumstances to elect whether the new or the old rate of VAT should apply to a supply where the basic and actual tax points span a period during which the rate changed.

2.8

It will be assumed, unless a contrary indication is given in writing, that an election to take advantage of the provisions mentioned in paragraph 2.7 and to charge VAT at the lower rate has been made. In any case in which an election to charge at the lower rate is not made, such a decision must be justified to the court assessing the costs.

Apportionment

2.9

Subject to 2.7 and 2.8, all bills of costs, fees and disbursements on which VAT is included must be divided into separate parts so as to show work done before, on and after the date or dates from which any change in the rate of VAT takes effect. Where, however, a lump sum charge is made for work which spans a period during which there has been a change in VAT rates, and paragraphs 2.7 and 2.8 above do not apply, reference should be made to paragraphs 30.7 or 30.8 of the VAT Guide (Notice 700) (or any revised edition of that notice) published by HMRC. If necessary, the lump sum should be apportioned. The totals of profit costs and disbursements in each part must be carried separately to the summary.

SECTION II – QUALIFIED ONE-WAY COSTS SHIFTING

Qualified one-way costs shifting

12.1

This subsection applies to proceedings to which Section II of Part 44 applies.

12.2

Examples of claims made for the financial benefit of a person other than the claimant or a dependant within the meaning of section 1(3) of the Fatal Accidents Act 1976 within the meaning of rule 44.16(2) are subrogated claims and claims for credit hire.

12.3

‘Gratuitous provision of care’ within the meaning of rule 44.16(2)(a) includes the provision of personal services rendered gratuitously by persons such as relatives and friends for things such as personal care, domestic assistance, childminding, home maintenance and decorating, gardening and chauffeuring.

12.4

In a case to which rule 44.16(1) applies (fundamentally dishonest claims) –

(a) the court will normally direct that issues arising out of an allegation that the claim is fundamentally dishonest be determined at the trial;

(b) where the proceedings have been settled, the court will not, save in exceptional circumstances, order that issues arising out of an allegation that the claim was fundamentally dishonest be determined in those proceedings;

(c) where the claimant has served a notice of discontinuance, the court may direct that issues arising out of an allegation that the claim was fundamentally dishonest be determined notwithstanding that the notice has not been set aside pursuant to rule 38.4;

(d) the court may, as it thinks fair and just, determine the costs attributable to the claim having been found to be fundamentally dishonest.

12.5

The court has power to make an order for costs against a person other than the claimant under section 51(3) of the Senior Courts Act 1981 and rule 46.2. In a case to which rule 44.16(2)(a) applies (claims for the benefit of others) –

(a) the court will usually order any person other than the claimant for whose financial benefit such a claim was made to pay all the costs of the proceedings or the costs attributable to the issues to which rule 44.16(2)(a) applies, or may exceptionally make such an order permitting the enforcement of such an order for costs against the claimant.

(b) the court may, as it thinks fair and just, determine the costs attributable to claims for the financial benefit of persons other than the claimant.

12.6

In proceedings to which rule 44.16 applies, the court will normally order the claimant or, as the case may be, the person for whose benefit a claim was made to pay costs notwithstanding that the aggregate amount in money terms of such orders exceeds the aggregate amount in money terms of any orders for damages, interest and costs made in favour of the claimant.

12.7

Assessments of costs may be on a standard or indemnity basis and may be subject to a summary or detailed assessment.

PART 45 - FIXED COSTS

Contents of this Part

I FIXED COSTS

Scope of this Section

45.1

(1) This Section sets out the amounts which, unless the court orders otherwise, are to be allowed in respect of legal representatives’ charges.

(2) This Section applies where –

(a) the only claim is a claim for a specified sum of money where the value of the claim exceeds £25 and –

(i) judgment in default is obtained under rule 12.4(1);

(ii) judgment on admission is obtained under rule 14.4(3);

(iii) judgment on admission on part of the claim is obtained under rule 14.5(6);

(iv) summary judgment is given under Part 24;

(v) the court has made an order to strike out a defence under rule 3.4(2)(a) as disclosing no reasonable grounds for defending the claim; or

(vi) rule 45.4 applies;

(b) the only claim is a claim where the court gave a fixed date for the hearing when it issued the claim and judgment is given for the delivery of goods, and the value of the claim exceeds £25;

(c) the claim is for the recovery of land, including a possession claim under Part 55, whether or not the claim includes a claim for a sum of money and the defendant gives up possession, pays the amount claimed, if any, and the fixed commencement costs stated in the claim form;

(d) the claim is for the recovery of land, including a possession claim under Part 55, where one of the grounds for possession is arrears of rent, for which the court gave a fixed date for the hearing when it issued the claim and judgment is given for the possession of land (whether or not the order for possession is suspended on terms) and the defendant –

(i) has neither delivered a defence, or counterclaim, nor otherwise denied liability; or

(ii) has delivered a defence which is limited to specifying his proposals for the payment of arrears of rent;

(e) the claim is a possession claim under Section II of Part 55 (accelerated possession claims of land let on an assured shorthold tenancy) and a possession order is made where the defendant has neither delivered a defence, or counterclaim, nor otherwise denied liability;

(f) the claim is a demotion claim under Section III of Part 65 or a demotion claim is made in the same claim form in which a claim for possession is made under Part 55 and that demotion claim is successful; or

(g) a judgment creditor has taken steps under Parts 70 to 73 to enforce a judgment or order.

(Practice Direction 7B sets out the types of case where a court will give a fixed date for a hearing when it issues a claim.)

(3) No sum in respect of legal representatives’ charges will be allowed where the only claim is for a sum of money or goods not exceeding £25.

(4) Any appropriate court fee will be allowed in addition to the costs set out in this Section.

(5) The claim form may include a claim for fixed commencement costs.

Amount of fixed commencement costs in a claim for the recovery of money or goods

45.2

(1) The amount of fixed commencement costs in a claim to which rule 45.1(2)(a) or (b) applies –

(a) will be calculated by reference to Table 1; and

(b) the amount claimed, or the value of the goods claimed if specified, in the claim form is to be used for determining the band in Table 1 that applies to the claim.

(2) The amounts shown in Table 4 are to be allowed in addition, if applicable.

TABLE 1

When defendant only liable for fixed commencement costs

45.3  Where –

(a) the only claim is for a specified sum of money; and

(b) the defendant pays the money claimed within 14 days after being served with the particulars of claim, together with the fixed commencement costs stated in the claim form,

the defendant is not liable for any further costs unless the court orders otherwise.

Costs on entry of judgment in a claim for the recovery of money or goods

45.4  Where –

(a) the claimant has claimed fixed commencement costs under rule 45.2; and

(b) judgment is entered in a claim to which rule 45.1(2)(a) or (b) applies in the circumstances specified in Table 2, the amount to be included in the judgment for the claimant’s legal representative’s charges is the total of –

(i) the fixed commencement costs; and

(ii) ii) the relevant amount shown in Table 2.

TABLE 2

Amount of fixed commencement costs in a claim for the recovery of land or a demotion claim

45.5

(1) The amount of fixed commencement costs in a claim to which rule 45.1(2)(c), (d) or (f) applies will be calculated by reference to Table 3.

(2) The amounts shown in Table 4 are to be allowed in addition, if applicable.

TABLE 3

Costs on entry of judgment in a claim for the recovery of land or a demotion claim

45.6

(1) Where –

(a) the claimant has claimed fixed commencement costs under rule 45.5; and

(b) judgment is entered in a claim to which rule 45.1(2)(d) or (f) applies, the amount to be included in the judgment for the claimant’s legal representative’s charges is the total of –

(i) the fixed commencement costs; and

(ii) the sum of £57.25.

(2) Where an order for possession is made in a claim to which rule 45.1(2)(e) applies, the amount allowed for the claimant’s legal representative’s charges for preparing and filing –

(a) the claim form;

(b) the documents that accompany the claim form; and

(c) the request for possession,

is £79.50.

Miscellaneous fixed costs

45.7  Table 4 shows the amount to be allowed in respect of legal representative’s charges in the circumstances mentioned.

TABLE 4

Fixed enforcement costs

45.8  Table 5 shows the amount to be allowed in respect of legal representatives’ costs in the circumstances mentioned. The amounts shown in Table 4 are to be allowed in addition, if applicable.

TABLE 5

II ROAD TRAFFIC ACCIDENTS – FIXED RECOVERABLE COSTS

Scope and interpretation

45.9

(1) Subject to paragraph (3), this Section sets out the costs which are to be allowed in –

(a) proceedings to which rule 46.14(1) applies (costs-only proceedings); or

(b) proceedings for approval of a settlement or compromise under rule 21.10(2),

in cases to which this Section applies.

(2) This Section applies where –

(a) the dispute arises from a road traffic accident occurring on or after 6 October 2003;

(b) the agreed damages include damages in respect of personal injury, damage to property, or both;

(c) the total value of the agreed damages does not exceed £10,000; and

(d) if a claim had been issued for the amount of the agreed damages, the small claims track would not have been the normal track for that claim.

(3) This Section does not apply where –

(a) the claimant is a litigant in person; or

(b) Section III or Section IIIA of this Part applies.

(4) In this Section –

‘road traffic accident’ means an accident resulting in bodily injury to any person or damage to property caused by, or arising out of, the use of a motor vehicle on a road or other public place in England and Wales;

‘motor vehicle’ means a mechanically propelled vehicle intended for use on roads; and

‘road’ means any highway and any other road to which the public has access and includes bridges over which a road passes.

Application of fixed recoverable costs

45.10  Subject to rule 45.13, the only costs which are to be allowed are –

(a) fixed recoverable costs calculated in accordance with rule 45.11; and

(b) disbursements allowed in accordance with rule 45.12.

(Rule 45.13 provides for where a party issues a claim for more than the fixed recoverable costs.)

Amount of fixed recoverable costs

45.11

(1) Subject to paragraphs (2) and (3), the amount of fixed recoverable costs is the total of –

(a) £800;

(b) 20% of the damages agreed up to £5,000; and

(c) 15% of the damages agreed between £5,000 and £10,000.

(2) Where the claimant –

(a) lives or works in an area set out in Practice Direction 45; and

(b) instructs a legal representative who practises in that area,

the fixed recoverable costs will include, in addition to the costs specified in paragraph (1), an amount equal to 12.5% of the costs allowable under that paragraph.

(3) Where appropriate, VAT may be recovered in addition to the amount of fixed recoverable costs and any reference in this Section to fixed recoverable costs is a reference to those costs net of any such VAT.

Disbursements

45.12

(1) The court –

(a) may allow a claim for a disbursement of a type mentioned in paragraph (2); but

(b) will not allow a claim for any other type of disbursement.

(2) The disbursements referred to in paragraph (1) are –

(a) the cost of obtaining –

(i) medical records;

(ii) a medical report;

(iii) a police report;

(iv) an engineer’s report; or

(v) a search of the records of the Driver Vehicle Licensing Authority;

(b) where they are necessarily incurred by reason of one or more of the claimants being a child or protected party as defined in Part 21 –

(i) fees payable for instructing counsel; or

(ii) court fees payable on an application to the court; or

(c) any other disbursement that has arisen due to a particular feature of the dispute.

Claims for an amount of costs exceeding fixed recoverable costs

45.13

(1) The court will entertain a claim for an amount of costs (excluding any success fee or disbursements) greater than the fixed recoverable costs but only if it considers that there are exceptional circumstances making it appropriate to do so.

(2) If the court considers such a claim appropriate, it may –

(a) summarily assess the costs; or

(b) make an order for the costs to be subject to detailed assessment.

(3) If the court does not consider the claim appropriate, it will make an order for fixed recoverable costs (and any permitted disbursements) only.

Failure to achieve costs greater than fixed recoverable costs

45.14

(1) This rule applies where –

(a) costs are assessed in accordance with rule 45.13(2); and

(b) the court assesses the costs (excluding any VAT) as being an amount which is less than 20% greater than the amount of the fixed recoverable costs.

(2) The court must order the defendant to pay to the claimant the lesser of –

(a) the fixed recoverable costs; and

(b) the assessed costs.

Costs of the costs-only proceedings or the detailed assessment

45.15  Where –

(a) the court makes an order for fixed recoverable costs in accordance with rule 45.13(3); or

(b) rule 45.14 applies, the court may –

(i) decide not to make an award of the payment of the claimant’s costs in bringing the proceedings under rule 46.14; and

(ii) make orders in relation to costs that may include an order that the claimant pay the defendant’s costs of defending those proceedings.

III THE PRE-ACTION PROTOCOLS FOR LOW VALUE PERSONAL INJURY CLAIMS IN ROAD TRAFFIC ACCIDENTS AND LOW VALUE PERSONAL INJURY (EMPLOYERS’ LIABILITY AND PUBLIC LIABILITY) CLAIMS

Scope and interpretation

45.16

(1) This Section applies to claims that have been or should have been started under Part 8 in accordance with Practice Direction 8B (‘the Stage 3 Procedure’).

(2) Where a party has not complied with the relevant Protocol rule 45.24 will apply.

‘The relevant Protocol’ means

(a) the Pre-Action Protocol for Personal Injury Claims in Road Traffic Accidents (“the RTA Protocol”); or

(b) the Pre-action Protocol for Low Value Personal Injury Claims (Employers’ Liability and Public Liability) Claims ('the EL/PL Protocol').

(3) A reference to ‘Claim Notification Form’ or Court Proceedings Pack is a reference to the form used in the relevant Protocol.

Application of fixed costs, and disbursements

45.17  The only costs allowed are –

(a) fixed costs in rule 45.18; and

(b) disbursements in accordance with rule 45.19; and

(c) where applicable, fixed costs in accordance with rule 45.23A or 45.23B.

Amount of fixed costs

45.18

(1) Subject to paragraph (4), the amount of fixed costs is set out in Tables 6 and 6A.

(2) In Tables 6 and 6A –

‘Type A fixed costs’ means the legal representative’s costs;

‘Type B fixed costs’ means the advocate’s costs; and

‘Type C fixed costs’ means the costs for the advice on the amount of damages where the claimant is a child.

(3) ‘Advocate’ has the same meaning as in rule 45.37(2)(a).

(4) Subject to rule 45.24(2) the court will not award more or less than the amounts shown in Tables 6 or 6A.

(5) Where the claimant –

(a) lives or works in an area set out in Practice Direction 45; and

(b) instructs a legal representative who practises in that area,

the fixed costs will include, in addition to the costs set out in Tables 6 or 6A, an amount equal to 12.5% of the Stage 1 and 2 and Stage 3 Type A fixed costs.

(6) Where appropriate, VAT may be recovered in addition to the amount of fixed costs and any reference in this Section to fixed costs is a reference to those costs net of any such VAT.

TABLE 6

TABLE 6A

Disbursements

45.19

(1) The court –

(a) may allow a claim for a disbursement of a type mentioned in paragraphs (2) or (3); but

(b) will not allow a claim for any other type of disbursement.

(2) In a claim to which either the RTA Protocol or EL/PL Protocol applies, the disbursements referred to in paragraph (1) are –

(a) the cost of obtaining –

(i) medical records;

(ii) a medical report or reports or non-medical expert reports as provided for in the relevant Protocol;

(aa) Driver Vehicle Licensing Authority;

(bb) Motor Insurance Database;

(b) court fees as a result of Part 21 being applicable;

(c) court fees payable where proceedings are started as a result of a limitation period that is about to expire;

(d) court fees in respect of the Stage 3 Procedure; and

(e) any other disbursement that has arisen due to a particular feature of the dispute.

(3) In a claim to which the RTA Protocol applies, the disbursements referred to in paragraph (1) are also the cost of—

(a) an engineer’s report; and

(b) a search of the records of the—

(i) Driver Vehicle Licensing Authority; and

(ii) Motor Insurance Database.

Where the claimant obtains judgment for an amount more than the defendant’s relevant Protocol offer

45.20

Where rule 36.21(1)(b) or (c) applies, the court will order the defendant to pay –

(a) where not already paid by the defendant, the Stage 1 and 2 fixed costs;

(b) where the claim is determined –

(i) on the papers, Stage 3 Type A fixed costs;

(ii) at a Stage 3 hearing, Stage 3 Type A and B fixed costs; or

(iii) at a Stage 3 hearing and the claimant is a child, Type A, B and C fixed costs; and

(c) disbursements allowed in accordance with rule 45.19.

Settlement at Stage 2 where the claimant is a child

45.21

(1) This rule applies where –

(a) the claimant is a child;

(b) there is a settlement at Stage 2 of the relevant Protocol; and

(c) an application is made to the court to approve the settlement.

(2) Where the court approves the settlement at a settlement hearing it will order the defendant to pay –

(a) the Stage 1 and 2 fixed costs;

(b) the Stage 3 Type A, B and C fixed costs; and

(c) disbursements allowed in accordance with rule 45.19.

(3) Where the court does not approve the settlement at a settlement hearing it will order the defendant to pay the Stage 1 and 2 fixed costs.

(4) Paragraphs (5) and (6) apply where the court does not approve the settlement at the first settlement hearing but does approve the settlement at a second settlement hearing.

(5) At the second settlement hearing the court will order the defendant to pay –

(a) the Stage 3 Type A and C fixed costs for the first settlement hearing;

(b) disbursements allowed in accordance with rule 45.19; and

(c) the Stage 3 Type B fixed costs for one of the hearings.

(6) The court in its discretion may also order –

(a) the defendant to pay an additional amount of either or both the Stage 3 –

(i) Type A fixed costs;

(ii) Type B fixed costs; or

(b) the claimant to pay an amount equivalent to either or both the Stage 3 –

(i) Type A fixed costs;

(ii) Type B fixed costs.

Settlement at Stage 3 where the claimant is a child

45.22

(1) This rule applies where –

(a) the claimant is a child;

(b) there is a settlement after proceedings are started under the Stage 3 Procedure;

(c) the settlement is more than the defendant’s relevant Protocol offer; and

(d) an application is made to the court to approve the settlement.

(2) Where the court approves the settlement at the settlement hearing it will order the defendant to pay –

(a) the Stage 1 and 2 fixed costs;

(b) the Stage 3 Type A, B and C fixed costs; and

(c) disbursements allowed in accordance with rule 45.19.

(3) Where the court does not approve the settlement at the settlement hearing it will order the defendant to pay the Stage 1 and 2 fixed costs.

(4) Paragraphs (5) and (6) apply where the court does not approve the settlement at the first settlement hearing but does approve the settlement at the Stage 3 hearing.

(5) At the Stage 3 hearing the court will order the defendant to pay –

(a) the Stage 3 Type A and C fixed costs for the settlement hearing;

(b) disbursements allowed in accordance with rule 45.19; and

(c) the Stage 3 Type B fixed costs for one of the hearings.

(6) The court in its discretion may also order –

(a) he defendant to pay an additional amount of either or both the Stage 3 –

(i) Type A fixed costs;

(ii) Type B fixed costs; or

(b) the claimant to pay an amount equivalent to either or both of the Stage 3 –

(i) Type A fixed costs;

(ii) Type B fixed costs.

(7) Where the settlement is not approved at the Stage 3 hearing the court will order the defendant to pay the Stage 3 Type A fixed costs.

Where the court orders that the claim is not suitable to be determined under the Stage 3 Procedure and the claimant is a child

45.23  Where –

(a) the claimant is a child; and

(b) at a settlement hearing or the Stage 3 hearing the court orders that the claim is not suitable to be determined under the Stage 3 Procedure,

the court will order the defendant to pay –

(i) the Stage 1 and 2 fixed costs; and

(ii) the Stage 3 Type A, B and C fixed costs.

Settlement before proceedings are issued under Stage 3

45.23A  Where—

(a) there is a settlement after the Court Proceedings Pack has been sent to the defendant but before proceedings are issued under Stage 3; and

(b) the settlement is more than the defendant’s relevant Protocol offer,

the fixed costs will include an additional amount equivalent to the Stage 3 Type A fixed costs.

Additional advice on the value of the claim

45.23B  Where—

(a) the value of the claim for damages is more than £10,000;

(b) an additional advice has been obtained from a specialist solicitor or from counsel;

(c) that advice is reasonably required to value the claim,

the fixed costs may include an additional amount equivalent to the Stage 3 Type C fixed costs.

Failure to comply or electing not to continue with the relevant Protocol – costs consequences

45.24

(1) This rule applies where the claimant –

(a) does not comply with the process set out in the relevant Protocol; or

(b) elects not to continue with that process,

and starts proceedings under Part 7.

(2) Where a judgment is given in favour of the claimant but –

(a) the court determines that the defendant did not proceed with the process set out in the relevant Protocol because the claimant provided insufficient information on the Claim Notification Form;

(b) the court considers that the claimant acted unreasonably –

(i) by discontinuing the process set out in the relevant Protocol and starting proceedings under Part 7;

(ii) by valuing the claim at more than £25,000, so that the claimant did not need to comply with the relevant Protocol; or

(iii) except for paragraph (2)(a), in any other way that caused the process in the relevant Protocol to be discontinued; or

(c) the claimant did not comply with the relevant Protocol at all despite the claim falling within the scope of the relevant Protocol,

the court may order the defendant to pay no more than the fixed costs in rule 45.18 together with the disbursements allowed in accordance with rule 45.19.

(3) Where the claimant starts proceedings under paragraph 7.28 of the RTA Protocol or paragraph 7.26 of the EL/PL Protocol and the court orders the defendant to make an interim payment of no more than the interim payment made under paragraph 7.14(2) or (3) of the RTA Protocol or paragraph 7.17(2) or (3) of the EL/PL Protocol the court will, on the final determination of the proceedings, order the defendant to pay no more than –

(a) the Stage 1 and 2 fixed costs; and

(b) the disbursements allowed in accordance with rule 45.19.

Where the parties have settled after proceedings have started

45.25

(1) This rule applies where an application is made under rule 45.29 (costs-only application after a claim is started under Part 8 in accordance with Practice Direction 8B).

(2) Where the settlement is more than the defendant’s relevant Protocol offer the court will order the defendant to pay –

(a) the Stage 1 and 2 fixed costs where not already paid by the defendant;

(b) the Stage 3 Type A fixed costs; and

(c) disbursements allowed in accordance with rule 45.19.

(3) Where the settlement is less than or equal to the defendant’s relevant Protocol offer the court will order the defendant to pay –

(a) the Stage 1 and 2 fixed costs where not already paid by the defendant; and

(b) disbursements allowed in accordance with rule 45.19.

(4) The court may, in its discretion, order either party to pay the costs of the application.

Where the claimant obtains judgment for an amount equal to or less than the defendant’s relevant Protocol offer

45.26  Where rule 36.21(1)(a) applies, the court will order the claimant to pay –

(a) where the claim is determined –

(i) on the papers, Stage 3 Type A fixed costs; or

(ii) at a hearing, Stage 3 Type A and B fixed costs;

(b) any Stage 3 disbursements allowed in accordance with rule 45.19.

Adjournment

45.27  Where the court adjourns a settlement hearing or a Stage 3 hearing it may, in its discretion, order a party to pay –

(a) an additional amount of the Stage 3 Type B fixed costs; and

(b) any court fee for that adjournment.

Account of payment of Stage 1 and Stage 2 fixed costs

45.28  Where a claim no longer continues under the relevant Protocol the court will, when making any order as to costs including an order for fixed recoverable costs under Section II or Section IIIA of this Part, take into account the Stage 1 and Stage 2 fixed costs that have been paid by the defendant.

Costs-only application after a claim is started under Part 8 in accordance with Practice Direction 8B

45.29

(1) This rule sets out the procedure where –

(a) the parties to a dispute have reached an agreement on all issues (including which party is to pay the costs) which is made or confirmed in writing; but

(b) they have failed to agree the amount of those costs; and

(c) proceedings have been started under Part 8 in accordance with Practice Direction 8B.

(2) Either party may make an application for the court to determine the costs.

(3) Where an application is made under this rule the court will assess the costs in accordance with rule 45.22 or rule 45.25.

(4) Rule 44.5 (amount of costs where costs are payable pursuant to a contract) does not apply to an application under this rule.

SECTION IIIA CLAIMS WHICH NO LONGER CONTINUE UNDER THE RTA OR EL/PL PRE-ACTION PROTOCOLS – FIXED RECOVERABLE COSTS

Scope and interpretation

45.29A

(1) Subject to paragraph (3), this section applies where a claim is started under—

(a) the Pre-Action Protocol for Low Value Personal Injury Claims in Road Traffic Accidents ('the RTA Protocol'); or

(b)the Pre-Action Protocol for Low Value Personal Injury (Employers’ Liability and Public Liability) Claims ('the EL/PL Protocol'),

but no longer continues under the relevant Protocol or the Stage 3 Procedure in Practice Direction 8B.

(2) This section does not apply to a disease claim which is started under the EL/PL Protocol.

(3) Nothing in this section shall prevent the court making an order under rule 45.24.

Application of fixed costs and disbursements – RTA Protocol

45.29B

Subject to rules 45.29F, 45.29G, 45.29H and 45.29J, if, in a claim started under the RTA Protocol, the Claim Notification Form is submitted on or after 31st July 2013, the only costs allowed are—

(a) the fixed costs in rule 45.29C;

(b) disbursements in accordance with rule 45.29I.

Amount of fixed costs – RTA Protocol

45.29C

(1) Subject to paragraph (2), the amount of fixed costs is set out in Table 6B.

(2) Where the claimant—

(a) lives or works in an area set out in Practice Direction 45; and

(b) instructs a legal representative who practises in that area,
the fixed costs will include, in addition to the costs set out in Table 6B, an amount equal to 12.5% of the costs allowable under paragraph (1) and set out in Table 6B.

(3) Where appropriate, VAT may be recovered in addition to the amount of fixed recoverable costs and any reference in this Section to fixed costs is a reference to those costs net of VAT.

(4) In Table 6B—

(a) in Part B, 'on or after' means the period beginning on the date on which the court respectively—

(i) issues the claim;

(ii) allocates the claim under Part 26; or

(iii) lists the claim for trial; and

(b) unless stated otherwise, a reference to 'damages' means agreed damages; and

(c) a reference to 'trial' is a reference to the final contested hearing.

TABLE 6B

Application of fixed costs and disbursements – EL/PL Protocol

45.29D  Subject to rules 45.29F, 45.29H and 45.29J, in a claim started under the EL/PL Protocol the only costs allowed are—

(a) fixed costs in rule 45.29E; and

(b) disbursements in accordance with rule 45.29I.

Amount of fixed costs – EL/PL Protocol

45.29E

(1) Subject to paragraph (2), the amount of fixed costs is set out—

(a) in respect of employers’ liability claims, in Table 6C; and

(b) in respect of public liability claims, in Table 6D.

(2) Where the claimant—

(a) lives or works in an area set out in Practice Direction 45; and

(b) instructs a legal representative who practises in that area,

the fixed costs will include, in addition to the costs set out in Tables 6C and 6D, an amount equal to 12.5% of the costs allowable under paragraph (1) and set out in table 6C and 6D.

(3) Where appropriate, VAT may be recovered in addition to the amount of fixed recoverable costs and any reference in this Section to fixed costs is a reference to those costs net of VAT.

(4) In Tables 6C and 6D—

(a) in Part B, 'on or after' means the period beginning on the date on which the court respectively—

(i) issues the claim;

(ii) allocates the claim under Part 26; or

(iii) lists the claim for trial; and

(b) unless stated otherwise, a reference to 'damages' means agreed damages; and

(c) a reference to 'trial' is a reference to the final contested hearing.

TABLE 6C

TABLE 6D

Defendants’ costs

45.29F

(1) In this rule—

(a) paragraphs (8) and (9) apply to assessments of defendants’ costs under Part 36;

(b) paragraph (10) applies to assessments to which the exclusions from qualified one way costs shifting in rules 44.15 and 44.16 apply; and

(c) paragraphs (2) to (7) apply to all other cases under this Section in which a defendant’s costs are assessed.

(2) If, in any case to which this Section applies, the court makes an order for costs in favour of the defendant—

(a) the court will have regard to; and

(b) the amount of costs order to be paid shall not exceed,

the amount which would have been payable by the defendant if an order for costs had been made in favour of the claimant at the same stage of the proceedings.

(3) For the purpose of assessing the costs payable to the defendant by reference to the fixed costs in Table 6, Table 6A, Table 6B, Table 6C and Table 6D, “value of the claim for damages” and “damages” shall be treated as references to the value of the claim.

(4) For the purposes of paragraph (3), “the value of the claim” is—

(a) the amount specified in the claim form, excluding—

(i) any amount not in dispute;

(ii) in a claim started under the RTA Protocol, any claim for vehicle related damages;

(iii) interest;

(iv) costs; and

(v) any contributory negligence;

(b) if no amount is specified in the claim form, the maximum amount which the claimant reasonably expected to recover according to the statement of value included in the claim form under rule 16.3; or

(c) £25,000, if the claim form states that the claimant cannot reasonably say how much is likely to be recovered.

(5) Where the defendant—

(a) lives, works or carries on business in an area set out in Practice Direction 45; and

(b) instructs a legal representative who practises in that area,
the costs will include, in addition to the costs allowable under paragraph (2), an amount equal to 12.5% of those costs.

(6) Where an order for costs is made pursuant to this rule, the defendant is entitled to disbursements in accordance with rule 45.29I

(7) Where appropriate, VAT may be recovered in addition to the amount of any costs allowable under this rule.

(8) Where, in a case to which this Section applies, a Part 36 offer is accepted, rule 36.10A will apply instead of this rule.

(9) Where, in a case to which this Section applies, upon judgment being entered, the claimant fails to obtain a judgment more advantageous than the claimant’s Part 36 offer, rule 36.14A will apply instead of this rule.

(10) Where, in a case to which this Section applies, any of the exceptions to qualified one way costs shifting in rules 44.15 and 44.16 is established, the court will assess the defendant’s costs without reference to this rule.

Counterclaims under the RTA Protocol

45.29G

(1) If in any case to which this Section applies—

(a) the defendant brings a counterclaim which includes a claim for personal injuries to which the RTA Protocol applies;

(b) the counterclaim succeeds; and

(c) the court makes an order for the costs of the counterclaim,

rules 45.29B, 45.29C, 45.29I, 45.29J, 45.29K and 45.29L shall apply.

(2) Where a successful counterclaim does not include a claim for personal injuries—

(a) the order for costs of the counterclaim shall be for a sum equivalent to one half of the applicable Type A and Type B costs in Table 6;

(b) where the defendant—

(i) lives, works, or carries on business in an area set out in Practice Direction 45; and

(ii) instructs a legal representative who practises in that area,

the costs will include, in addition to the costs allowable under paragraph (a), an amount equal to 12.5% of those costs;

(c) if an order for costs is made pursuant to this rule, the defendant is entitled to disbursements in accordance with rule 45.29I; and

(d)where appropriate, VAT may be recovered in addition to the amount of any costs allowable under this rule.

Interim applications

45.29H

(1) Where the court makes an order for costs of an interim application to be paid by one party in a case to which this Section applies, the order shall be for a sum equivalent to one half of the applicable Type A and Type B costs in Table 6 or 6A.

(2) Where the party in whose favour the order for costs is made—

(a) lives, works or carries on business in an area set out in Practice Direction 45; and

(b) instructs a legal representative who practises in that area,
the costs will include, in addition to the costs allowable under paragraph (1), an amount equal to 12.5% of those costs.

(3) If an order for costs is made pursuant to this rule, the party in whose favour the order is made is entitled to disbursements in accordance with rule 45.29I.

(4) Where appropriate, VAT may be recovered in addition to the amount of any costs allowable under this rule.

Disbursements

45.29I

(1) The court—

(a) may allow a claim for a disbursement of a type mentioned in paragraphs (2) or (3); but

(b) will not allow a claim for any other type of disbursement.

(2) In a claim started under either the RTA Protocol or the EL/PL Protocol, the disbursements referred to in paragraph (1) are—

(a) the cost of obtaining medical records and expert medical reports as provided for in the relevant Protocol;

(b) the cost of any non-medical expert reports as provided for in the relevant Protocol;

(c) the cost of any advice from a specialist solicitor or counsel as provided for in the relevant Protocol;

(d) court fees;

(e) any expert’s fee for attending the trial where the court has given permission for the expert to attend;

(f) expenses which a party or witness has reasonably incurred in travelling to and from a hearing or in staying away from home for the purposes of attending a hearing;

(g) a sum not exceeding the amount specified in Practice Direction 45 for any loss of earnings or loss of leave by a party or witness due to attending a hearing or to staying away from home for the purpose of attending a hearing; and

(h) any other disbursement reasonably incurred due to a particular feature of the dispute.

(3) In a claim started under the RTA Protocol only, the disbursements referred to in paragraph (1) are also the cost of—

(a) an engineer’s report; and

(b) a search of the records of the—

(i) Driver Vehicle Licensing Authority; and

(ii) Motor Insurance Database.

Claims for an amount of costs exceeding fixed recoverable costs

45.29J

(1) If it considers that there are exceptional circumstances making it appropriate to do so, the court will consider a claim for an amount of costs (excluding disbursements) which is greater than the fixed recoverable costs referred to in rules 45.29B to 45.29H.

(2) If the court considers such a claim to be appropriate, it may—

(a) summarily assess the costs; or

(b) make an order for the costs to be subject to detailed assessment.

(3) If the court does not consider the claim to be appropriate, it will make an order—

(a) if the claim is made by the claimant, for the fixed recoverable costs; or

(b) if the claim is made by the defendant, for a sum which has regard to, but which does not exceed the fixed recoverable costs,

and any permitted disbursements only.

Failure to achieve costs greater than fixed recoverable costs

45.29K

(1) This rule applies where—

(a) costs are assessed in accordance with rule 45.29J(2); and

(b) the court assesses the costs (excluding any VAT) as being an amount which is in a sum less than 20% greater than the amount of the fixed recoverable costs.

(2) The court will make an order for the party who made the claim to be paid the lesser of—

(a) the fixed recoverable costs; and

(b) the assessed costs.

Costs of the costs-only proceedings or the detailed assessment

45.29L

(1) Where—

(a) the court makes an order for costs in accordance with rule 45.29J(3); or

(b) rule 45.29K applies,

the court may—

(i) decide not to award the party making the claim the costs of the costs only proceedings or detailed assessment; and

(ii) make orders in relation to costs that may include an order that the party making the claim pay the costs of the party defending those proceedings or that assessment.

IV SCALE COSTS FOR CLAIMS IN THE INTELLECTUAL PROPERTY ENTERPRISE COURT

Scope and interpretation

45.30

(1) Subject to paragraph (2), this Section applies to proceedings in the Intellectual Property Enterprise Court.

(2) This Section does not apply where –

(a) the court considers that a party has behaved in a manner which amounts to an abuse of the court’s process; or

(b) the claim concerns the infringement or revocation of a patent or registered design the validity of which has been certified by a court or by the Comptroller-General of Patents, Designs and Trade Marks in earlier proceedings.

(3) The court will make a summary assessment of the costs of the party in whose favour any order for costs is made. Rules 44.2(8), 44.7(b) and Part 47 do not apply to this Section.

(4) ‘Scale costs’ means the costs set out in Table A and Table B of the Practice Direction supplementing this Part.

Amount of scale costs

45.31

(1) Subject to rule 45.32, the court will not order a party to pay total costs of more than –

(a) £50,000 on the final determination of a claim in relation to liability; and

(b) £25,000 on an inquiry as to damages or account of profits.

(2) The amounts in paragraph (1) apply after the court has applied the provision on set off in accordance with rule 44.12(a).

(3) The maximum amount of scale costs that the court will award for each stage of the claim is set out in Practice Direction 45.

(4) The amount of the scale costs awarded by the court in accordance with paragraph (3) will depend on the nature and complexity of the claim.

(4A) Subject to assessment where appropriate, the following may be recovered in addition to the amount of the scale costs set out in Practice Direction 45 – Fixed Costs—

(a) court fees;

(b) costs relating to the enforcement of any court
order; and

(c) wasted costs.

(5) Where appropriate, VAT may be recovered in addition to the amount of the scale costs and any reference in this Section to scale costs is a reference to those costs net of any such VAT.

Summary assessment of the costs of an application where a party has behaved unreasonably

45.32  Costs awarded to a party under rule 63.26(2) are in addition to the total costs that may be awarded to that party under rule 45.31.

V FIXED COSTS: HM REVENUE AND CUSTOMS

Scope, interpretation and application

45.33

(1) This Section sets out the amounts which, unless the court orders otherwise, are to be allowed in respect of HM Revenue and Customs charges in the cases to which this Section applies.

(2) For the purpose of this Section –

(a) ‘HMRC Officer’ means a person appointed by the Commissioners under section 2 of the Commissioners for Revenue and Customs Act 2005^3 and authorised to conduct county court proceedings for recovery of debt under section 25(1A)^4 of that Act;

(b) ‘Commissioners’ means commissioners for HMRC appointed under section 1 of the Commissioners for Revenue and Customs Act 2005;

(c) ‘debt’ means any sum payable to the Commissioners under or by virtue of an enactment or under a contract settlement; and

(d) ‘HMRC charges’ means the fixed costs set out in Tables 7 and 8 in this Section.

(3) HMRC charges must, for the purpose of this Section, be claimed as ‘legal representative’s costs’ on relevant court forms.

(4) This Section applies where the only claim is a claim conducted by an HMRC Officer in the county court for recovery of a debt and the Commissioners obtain judgment on the claim.

(5) Any appropriate court fee will be allowed in addition to the costs set out in this Section.

(6) The claim form may include a claim for fixed commencement costs.

Amount of fixed commencement costs in a county court claim for the recovery of money

45.34  The amount of fixed commencement costs in a claim to which rule 45.33 applies –

(a) will be calculated by reference to Table 7; and

(b) the amount claimed in the claim form is to be used for determining which claim band in Table 7 applies.

TABLE 7

Costs on entry of judgment in a county court claim for recovery of money

45.35  Where –

(a) an HMRC Officer has claimed fixed commencement costs under Rule 45.34; and

(b) judgment is entered in a claim to which rule 45.33 applies,

<the amount="" to="" be="" included="" in="" the="" judgment="" for="" hmrc="" charges="" is="" total="" of="" –

(i) the fixed commencement costs; and

(ii) the amount in Table 8 relevant to the value of the claim.

TABLE 8

When the defendant is only liable for fixed commencement costs

45.36  Where –

(a) the only claim is for a specified sum of money; and

(b) the defendant pays the money claimed within 14 days after service of the particulars of claim, together with the fixed commencement costs stated in the claim form,

the defendant is not liable for any further costs unless the court orders otherwise.>

VI FAST TRACK TRIAL COSTS

Scope of this Section

45.37

(1) This Section deals with the amount of costs which the court may award as the costs of an advocate for preparing for and appearing at the trial of a claim in the fast track (referred to in this rule as ‘fast track trial costs’).

(2) For the purposes of this Section –

‘advocate’ means a person exercising a right of audience as a representative of, or on behalf of, a party;

‘fast track trial costs’ means the costs of a party’s advocate for preparing for and appearing at the trial, but does not include –

(i) any other disbursements; or

(ii) any value added tax payable on the fees of a party’s advocate; and

‘trial’ includes a hearing where the court decides an amount of money or the value of goods following a judgment under Part 12 (default judgment) or Part 14 (admissions) but does not include –

(i) the hearing of an application for summary judgment under Part 24; or

(ii) the court’s approval of a settlement or other compromise under rule 21.10.

Amount of fast track trial costs

45.38

(1) Table 9 shows the amount of fast track trial costs which the court may award (whether by summary or detailed assessment).

TABLE 9

(2) The court may not award more or less than the amount shown in the table except where –

(a) it decides not to award any fast track trial costs; or

(b) rule 45.39 applies,

but the court may apportion the amount awarded between the parties to reflect their respective degrees of success on the issues at trial.

(3) Where the only claim is for the payment of money –

(a) for the purpose of quantifying fast track trial costs awarded to a claimant, the value of the claim is the total amount of the judgment excluding –

(i) interest and costs; and

(ii) any reduction made for contributory negligence; and

(b) for the purpose of quantifying fast track trial costs awarded to a defendant, the value of the claim is –

(i) the amount specified in the claim form (excluding interest and costs);

(ii) if no amount is specified, the maximum amount which the claimant reasonably expected to recover according to the statement of value included in the claim form under rule 16.3; or

(iii) more than £15,000, if the claim form states that the claimant cannot reasonably say how much is likely to be recovered.

(4) Where the claim is only for a remedy other than the payment of money, the value of the claim is deemed to be more than £3,000 but not more than £10,000, unless the court orders otherwise.

(5) Where the claim includes both a claim for the payment of money and for a remedy other than the payment of money, the value of the claim is deemed to be the higher of –

(a) the value of the money claim decided in accordance with paragraph (3); or

(b) the deemed value of the other remedy decided in accordance with paragraph (4),

unless the court orders otherwise.

(6) Where –

(a) a defendant has made a counterclaim against the claimant;

(b) the counterclaim has a higher value than the claim; and

(c) the claimant succeeds at trial both on the claim and the counterclaim,

for the purpose of quantifying fast track trial costs awarded to the claimant, the value of the claim is the value of the defendant’s counterclaim calculated in accordance with this rule.

Power to award more or less than the amount of fast track trial costs

45.39

(1) This rule sets out when a court may award –

(a) an additional amount to the amount of fast track trial costs shown in Table 9 in rule 45.38(1); or

(b) less than those amounts.

(2) If –

(a) in addition to the advocate, a party’s legal representative attends the trial;

(b) the court considers that it was necessary for a legal representative to attend to assist the advocate; and

(c) the court awards fast track trial costs to that party,

the court may award an additional £345 in respect of the legal representative’s attendance at the trial.

(3) If the court considers that it is necessary to direct a separate trial of an issue then the court may award an additional amount in respect of the separate trial but that amount is limited in accordance with paragraph (4) of this rule.

(4) The additional amount the court may award under paragraph (3) will not exceed two-thirds of the amount payable for that claim, subject to a minimum award of £485.

(5) Where the party to whom fast track trial costs are to be awarded is a litigant in person, the court will award –

(a) if the litigant in person can prove financial loss, two-thirds of the amount that would otherwise be awarded; or

(b) if the litigant in person fails to prove financial loss, an amount in respect of the time spent reasonably doing the work at the rate specified in Practice Direction 46.

(6) Where a defendant has made a counterclaim against the claimant, and –

(a) the claimant has succeeded on his claim; and

(b) the defendant has succeeded on his counterclaim,

the court will quantify the amount of the award of fast track trial costs to which –

(i) but for the counterclaim, the claimant would be entitled for succeeding on his claim; and

(ii) but for the claim, the defendant would be entitled for succeeding on his counterclaim,

and make one award of the difference, if any, to the party entitled to the higher award of costs.

(7) Where the court considers that the party to whom fast track trial costs are to be awarded has behaved unreasonably or improperly during the trial, it may award that party an amount less than would otherwise be payable for that claim, as it considers appropriate.

(8) Where the court considers that the party who is to pay the fast track trial costs has behaved improperly during the trial the court may award such additional amount to the other party as it considers appropriate.

Fast track trial costs where there is more than one claimant or defendant

45.40

(1) Where the same advocate is acting for more than one party –

(a) the court may make only one award in respect of fast track trial costs payable to that advocate; and

(b) the parties for whom the advocate is acting are jointly entitled to any fast track trial costs awarded by the court.

(2) Where –

(a) the same advocate is acting for more than one claimant; and

(b) each claimant has a separate claim against the defendant,

the value of the claim, for the purpose of quantifying the award in respect of fast track trial costs is to be ascertained in accordance with paragraph (3).

(3) The value of the claim in the circumstances mentioned in paragraph (2) or (5) is –

(a) where the only claim of each claimant is for the payment of money –

(i) if the award of fast track trial costs is in favour of the claimants, the total amount of the judgment made in favour of all the claimants jointly represented; or

(ii) if the award is in favour of the defendant, the total amount claimed by the claimants,

and in either case, quantified in accordance with rule 45.38(3);

(b) where the only claim of each claimant is for a remedy other than the payment of money, deemed to be more than £3,000 but not more than £10,000; and

(c) where claims of the claimants include both a claim for the payment of money and for a remedy other than the payment of money, deemed to be –

(i) more than £3,000 but not more than £10,000; or

(ii) if greater, the value of the money claims calculated in accordance with subparagraph (a) above.

(4) Where –

(a) there is more than one defendant; and

(b) any or all of the defendants are separately represented,

the court may award fast track trial costs to each party who is separately represented.

(5) Where –

(a) there is more than one claimant; and

(b) a single defendant,

the court may make only one award to the defendant of fast track trial costs, for which the claimants are jointly and severally liable.

(6) For the purpose of quantifying the fast track trial costs awarded to the single defendant under paragraph (5), the value of the claim is to be calculated in accordance with paragraph (3) of this rule.

VII COSTS LIMITS IN AARHUS CONVENTION CLAIMS

Scope and interpretation

45.41

(1) This Section provides for the costs which are to be recoverable between the parties in Aarhus Convention claims.

(2) In this Section, ‘Aarhus Convention claim’ means a claim for judicial review of a decision, act or omission all or part of which is subject to the provisions of the UNECE Convention on Access to Information, Public Participation in Decision-Making and Access to Justice in Environmental Matters done at Aarhus, Denmark on 25 June 1998, including a claim which proceeds on the basis that the decision, act or omission, or part of it, is so subject.

(Rule 52.9A makes provision in relation to costs of an appeal.)

Opting out

45.42  Rules 45.43 to 45.44 do not apply where the claimant –

(a) has not stated in the claim form that the claim is an Aarhus Convention claim; or

(b) has stated in the claim form that –

(i) the claim is not an Aarhus Convention claim, or

(ii) although the claim is an Aarhus Convention claim, the claimant does not wish those rules to apply.

Limit on costs recoverable from a party in an Aarhus Convention claim

45.43

(1) Subject to rule 45.44, a party to an Aarhus Convention claim may not be ordered to pay costs exceeding the amount prescribed in Practice Direction 45.

(2) Practice Direction 45 may prescribe a different amount for the purpose of paragraph (1) according to the nature of the claimant.

Challenging whether the claim is an Aarhus Convention claim

45.44

(1) If the claimant has stated in the claim form that the claim is an Aarhus Convention claim, rule 45.43 will apply unless –

(a) the defendant has in the acknowledgment of service filed in accordance with rule 54.8 –

(i) denied that the claim is an Aarhus Convention claim; and

(ii) set out the defendant’s grounds for such denial; and

(b) the court has determined that the claim is not an Aarhus Convention claim.

(2) Where the defendant argues that the claim is not an Aarhus Convention claim, the court will determine that issue at the earliest opportunity.

(3) In any proceedings to determine whether the claim is an Aarhus Convention claim –

(a) if the court holds that the claim is not an Aarhus Convention claim, it will normally make no order for costs in relation to those proceedings;

(b) if the court holds that the claim is an Aarhus Convention claim, it will normally order the defendant to pay the claimant’s costs of those proceedings on the indemnity basis, and that order may be enforced notwithstanding that this would increase the costs payable by the defendant beyond the amount prescribed in Practice Direction 45.

Footnotes

1974 c.39. Back to text
1982 c.27. Back to text
2005 c.11. Back to text
2005 c.11. Section 25(1A) was inserted by the Finance Act 2008 (c.9) section 137(1)(a). Back to text

PRACTICE DIRECTION 45 - FIXED COSTS

This Practice Direction supplements Part 45

SECTION I – FIXED COSTS

Fixed costs in small claims

1.1

Under Rule 27.14 the costs which can be awarded to a claimant in a small claim include the fixed costs payable under Part 45 attributable to issuing the claim.

1.2

Those fixed costs are the sum of –

(a) the fixed commencement costs calculated in accordance with Table 1 of Rule 45.2;

(b) the appropriate court fee or fees paid by the claimant.

Claims to which Part 45 does not apply

1.3

In a claim to which Part 45 does not apply, no amount shall be entered on the claim form for the charges of the claimant's legal representative, but the words ‘to be assessed’ shall be inserted.

SECTION II – ROAD TRAFFIC ACCIDENTS: FIXED RECOVERABLE COSTS IN COSTS-ONLY PROCEEDINGS

Scope

2.1

Section II of Part 45 (‘the Section’) provides for certain fixed costs to be recoverable between parties in respect of costs incurred in disputes which are settled prior to proceedings being issued. The Section applies to road traffic accident disputes as defined in rule 45.9(4)(a), where the accident which gave rise to the dispute occurred on or after 6th October 2003.

2.2

The Section does not apply to disputes where the total agreed value of the damages is within the small claims limit or exceeds £10,000. Rule 26.8(2) sets out how the financial value of a claim is assessed for the purposes of allocation to track.

2.3

Fixed recoverable costs are to be calculated by reference to the amount of agreed damages which are payable to the receiving party. In calculating the amount of these damages –

(a) account must be taken of both general and special damages and interest;

(a) any interim payments made must be included;

(c) where the parties have agreed an element of contributory negligence, the amount of damages attributed to that negligence must be deducted;

(d) any amount required by statute to be paid by the compensating party directly to a third party (such as sums paid by way of compensation recovery payments and National Health Service expenses) must not be included.

2.4

The Section applies to cases which fall within the scope of the Uninsured Drivers Agreement dated 13 August 1999. The section does not apply to cases which fall within the scope of the Untraced Drivers Agreement dated 14 February 2003.

Fixed recoverable costs formula

2.5

The amount of fixed costs recoverable is the sum of –

(a) £800;

(b) 20% of the agreed damages up to £5,000; and

(c) 15% of the agreed damages between £5,000 and £10,000.

For example, agreed damages of £7,523 would result in recoverable costs of £2,178.45 i.e.

£800 + (20% of £5,000) + (15% of £2,523).

Additional costs for work in specified areas

2.6

The area referred to in rules 45.11(2) and 45.18(5) consists of (within London) the county court districts of Barnet, Bow, Brentford, Central London, Clerkenwell and Shoreditch, Edmonton, Ilford, Lambeth, Mayors and City of London, Romford, Wandsworth, West London, Willesden and Woolwich and (outside London) the county court districts of Bromley, Croydon, Dartford, Gravesend and Uxbridge.

Multiple claimants

2.7

Where two or more potential claimants instruct the same legal representative, the provisions of the section apply in respect of each claimant.

Information to be included in the claim form

2.8

Costs only proceedings are commenced using the procedure set out in rule 46.14. A claim form should be issued in accordance with Part 8. Where the claimant is claiming an amount of costs which exceed the amount of the fixed recoverable costs the claim form must give details of the exceptional circumstances to justify the additional costs.

2.9

The claimant must also include on the claim form details of any disbursements. The disbursements that may be claimed are set out in rule 45.12(1). If the disbursement falls within 45.12(2)(c) (disbursements that have arisen due to a particular feature of the dispute) the claimant must give details of the particular feature of the dispute that made the disbursement necessary.

Disbursements

2.10

If the parties agree the amount of the fixed recoverable costs and the only dispute is as to the payment of, or amount of, a disbursement, then proceedings should be issued under rule 46.14.

SECTION IV – SCALE COSTS FOR PROCEEDINGS IN A PATENTS COUNTY COURT

Tables A and B

3.1

Tables A and B set out the maximum amount of scale costs which the court will award for each stage of a claim in a patents county court.

3.2

Table A sets out the scale costs for each stage of a claim up to determination of liability.

3.3

Table B sets out the scale costs for each stage of an inquiry as to damages or account of profits.

Table A

Table B

SECTION VI – FAST TRACK TRIAL COSTS

Scope

4.1

Section VI of Part 45 applies to the costs of an advocate for preparing for and appearing at the trial of a claim in the fast track.

4.2

It applies only where, at the date of the trial, the claim is allocated to the fast track. It does not apply in any other case, irrespective of the final value of the claim.

4.3

In particular it does not apply to a disposal hearing at which the amount to be paid under a judgment or order is decided by the court (see paragraph 12.4 of Practice Direction 26)).

SECTION VII – COSTS LIMITS IN AARHUS CONVENTION CLAIMS

Limit on costs recoverable from a party in an Aarhus Convention claim: Rule 45.43

5.1

Where a claimant is ordered to pay costs, the amount specified for the purpose of rule 45.43(1) is –

(a) £5,000 where the claimant is claiming only as an individual and not as, or on behalf of, a business or other legal person;

(b) in all other cases, £10,000.

5.2

Where a defendant is ordered to pay costs, the amount specified for the purpose of rule 45.43(1) is £35,000.

SECTION VIII - CLAIMS WHICH NO LONGER CONTINUE UNDER THE RTA OR EL/PL PROTOCOLS - DISBURSEMENTS

Claims for loss of earnings: Rule 45.29I(2)(g)

6.1

Where, under rule 45.29I(2)(g) (loss of earnings), the court allows a claim for any loss of earnings or leave by a party or witness due to attending a hearing or staying away from home for the purpose of attending a hearing, the specified sums, per day, for each person are-

(a) £90, where the value of the claim for damages is not more that £10,000; and

(b) £135, where the value of the claim for damages is more that £10,000.

PRACTICE DIRECTION 46 - COSTS SPECIAL CASES

This Practice Direction supplements Part 46

Contents of this Practice Direction

Awards of costs in favour of a trustee or personal representative: rule 46.3

1.1  A trustee or personal representative is entitled to an indemnity out of the relevant trust fund or estate for costs properly incurred. Whether costs were properly incurred depends on all the circumstances of the case including whether the trustee or personal representative (‘the trustee’) –

(a) obtained directions from the court before bringing or defending the proceedings;

(b) acted in the interests of the fund or estate or in substance for a benefit other than that of the estate, including the trustee's own; and

(c) acted in some way unreasonably in bringing or defending, or in the conduct of, the proceedings.

1.2  The trustee is not to be taken to have acted for a benefit other than that of the fund by reason only that the trustee has defended a claim in which relief is sought against the trustee personally.

Costs where money is payable by or to a child or protected party: rule 46.4

2.1  The circumstances in which the court need not order the assessment of costs under rule 46.4(3) are as follows –

(a) where there is no need to do so to protect the interests of the child or protected party or their estate;

(b) where another party has agreed to pay a specified sum in respect of the costs of the child or protected party and the legal representative acting for the child or protected party has waived the right to claim further costs;

(c) where the court has decided the costs payable to the child or protected party by way of summary assessment and the legal representative acting for the child or protected party has waived the right to claim further costs; and

(d) where an insurer or other person is liable to discharge the costs which the child or protected party would otherwise be liable to pay to the legal representative and the court is satisfied that the insurer or other person is financially able to discharge those costs.

Litigants in person: rule 46.5

3.1  In order to qualify as an expert for the purpose of rule 46.5(3)(c) (expert assistance in connection with assessing the claim for costs), the person in question must be a –

(a) barrister;

(b) solicitor;

(c) Fellow of the Institute of Legal Executives;

(d) Fellow of the Association of Costs Lawyers;

(e) law costs draftsman who is a member of the Academy of Experts;

(f) law costs draftsman who is a member of the Expert Witness Institute.

3.2  Where a self represented litigant wishes to prove that the litigant has suffered financial loss, the litigant should produce to the court any written evidence relied on to support that claim, and serve a copy of that evidence on any party against whom the litigant seeks costs at least 24 hours before the hearing at which the question may be decided.

3.3  A self represented litigant who commences detailed assessment proceedings under rule 47.5 should serve copies of that written evidence with the notice of commencement.

3.4  The amount, which may be allowed to a self represented litigant under rule 45.39(5)(b) and rule 46.5(4)(b), is £18 per hour.

Orders in respect of pro bono representation: rule 46.7

4.1  Where an order is sought under section 194(3) of the Legal Services Act 2007 the party who has pro bono representation must prepare, file and serve a written statement of the sum equivalent to the costs that party would have claimed for that legal representation had it not been provided free of charge.

Personal liability of legal representative for costs – wasted costs orders: rule 46.8

5.1  A wasted costs order is an order –

(a) that the legal representative pay a sum (either specified or to be assessed) in respect of costs to a party; or

(b) for costs relating to a specified sum or items of work to be disallowed.

5.2  Rule 46.8 deals with wasted costs orders against legal representatives. Such orders can be made at any stage in the proceedings up to and including the detailed assessment proceedings. In general, applications for wasted costs are best left until after the end of the trial.

5.3  The court may make a wasted costs order against a legal representative on its own initiative.

5.4  A party may apply for a wasted costs order –

(a) by filing an application notice in accordance with Part 23; or

(b) by making an application orally in the course of any hearing.

5.5  It is appropriate for the court to make a wasted costs order against a legal representative, only if –

(a) the legal representative has acted improperly, unreasonably or negligently;

(b) the legal representative's conduct has caused a party to incur unnecessary costs, or has meant that costs incurred by a party prior to the improper, unreasonable or negligent act or omission have been wasted;

(c) it is just in all the circumstances to order the legal representative to compensate that party for the whole or part of those costs.

5.6  The court will give directions about the procedure to be followed in each case in order to ensure that the issues are dealt with in a way which is fair and as simple and summary as the circumstances permit.

5.7  As a general rule the court will consider whether to make a wasted costs order in two stages –

(a) at the first stage the court must be satisfied –

(i) that it has before it evidence or other material which, if unanswered, would be likely to lead to a wasted costs order being made; and

(ii) the wasted costs proceedings are justified notwithstanding the likely costs involved;

(b) at the second stage, the court will consider, after giving the legal representative an opportunity to make representations in writing or at a hearing, whether it is appropriate to make a wasted costs order in accordance with paragraph 5.5 above.

5.8  The court may proceed to the second stage described in paragraph 5.7 without first adjourning the hearing if it is satisfied that the legal representative has already had a reasonable opportunity to make representations.

5.9  On an application for a wasted costs order under Part 23 the application notice and any evidence in support must identify –

(a) what the legal representative is alleged to have done or failed to do; and

(b) the costs that the legal representative may be ordered to pay or which are sought against the legal representative.

Assessment of solicitor and client costs: rules 46.9 and 46.10

6.1  A client and solicitor may agree whatever terms they consider appropriate about the payment of the solicitor's charges. If however, the costs are of an unusual nature, either in amount or the type of costs incurred, those costs will be presumed to have been unreasonably incurred unless the solicitor satisfies the court that the client was informed that they were unusual and that they might not be allowed on an assessment of costs between the parties. That information must have been given to the client before the costs were incurred.

6.2  Costs as between a solicitor and client are assessed on the indemnity basis. The presumptions in rule 46.9(3) are rebuttable.

6.3  If a party fails to comply with the requirements of rule 46.10 concerning the service of a breakdown of costs or points of dispute, any other party may apply to the court in which the detailed assessment hearing should take place for an order requiring compliance. If the court makes such an order, it may –

(a) make it subject to conditions including a condition to pay a sum of money into court; and

(b) specify the consequence of failure to comply with the order or a condition.

6.4  The procedure for obtaining an order under Part III of the Solicitors Act 1974 is by a Part 8 claim, as modified by rule 67.3 and Practice Direction 67. Precedent J of the Schedule of Costs Precedents is a model form of claim form. The application must be accompanied by the bill or bills in respect of which assessment is sought, and, if the claim concerns a conditional fee agreement, a copy of that agreement. If the original bill is not available a copy will suffice.

6.5  Model forms of order, which the court may make, are set out in Precedents K, L and M of the Schedule of Costs Precedents.

6.6  The breakdown of costs referred to in rule 46.10 is a document which contains the following information –

(a) details of the work done under each of the bills sent for assessment; and

(b) in applications under Section 70 of the Solicitors Act 1974, a cash account showing money received by the solicitor to the credit of the client and sums paid out of that money on behalf of the client but not payments out which were made in satisfaction of the bill or of any items which are claimed in the bill.

6.7  Precedent P of the Schedule of Costs Precedents is a model form of breakdown of costs. A party who is required to serve a breakdown of costs must also serve –

(a) copies of the fee notes of counsel and of any expert in respect of fees claimed in the breakdown, and

(b) written evidence as to any other disbursement which is claimed in the breakdown and which exceeds £250.

6.8  The provisions relating to default costs certificates (rule 47.11) do not apply to cases to which rule 46.10 applies.

6.9  The time for requesting a detailed assessment hearing is within 3 months after the date of the order for the costs to be assessed.

6.10  The form of request for a hearing date must be in Form N258C. The request must be accompanied by copies of –

(a) the order sending the bill or bills for assessment;

(b) the bill or bills sent for assessment;

(c) the solicitor's breakdown of costs and any invoices or accounts served with that breakdown;

(d) a copy of the points of dispute;

(e) a copy of any replies served;

(f) a statement signed by the party filing the request or that party's legal representative giving the names and addresses for service of all parties to the proceedings.

6.11  The request must include the estimated length of hearing.

6.12  On receipt of the request the court will fix a date for the hearing, or will give directions.

6.13  The court will give at least 14 days notice of the time and place of the detailed assessment hearing.

6.14  Unless the court gives permission, only the solicitor whose bill it is and parties who have served points of dispute may be heard and only items specified in the points of dispute may be raised.

6.15  If a party wishes to vary that party's breakdown of costs, points of dispute or reply, an amended or supplementary document must be filed with the court and copies of it must be served on all other relevant parties. Permission is not required to vary a breakdown of costs, points of dispute or a reply but the court may disallow the variation or permit it only upon conditions, including conditions as to the payment of any costs caused or wasted by the variation.

6.16  Unless the court directs otherwise the solicitor must file with the court the papers in support of the bill not less than 7 days before the date for the detailed assessment hearing and not more than 14 days before that date.

6.17  Once the detailed assessment hearing has ended it is the responsibility of the legal representative appearing for the solicitor or, as the case may be, the solicitor in person to remove the papers filed in support of the bill.

6.18  If, in the course of a detailed assessment hearing of a solicitor's bill to that solicitor's client, it appears to the court that in any event the solicitor will be liable in connection with that bill to pay money to the client, it may issue an interim certificate specifying an amount which in its opinion is payable by the solicitor to the client.

6.19  After the detailed assessment hearing is concluded the court will –

(a) complete the court copy of the bill so as to show the amount allowed;

(b) determine the result of the cash account;

(c) award the costs of the detailed assessment hearing in accordance with Section 70(8) of the Solicitors Act 1974; and

(d) issue a final costs certificate.

Costs on the small claims and fast tracks: rule 46.11

7.1

(1) Before a claim is allocated to either the small claims track or the fast track the court is not restricted by any of the special rules that apply to that track but see paragraph 8.2 below.

(2) Where a claim has been so allocated , the special rules which relate to that track will apply to work done before as well as after allocation save to the extent (if any) that an order for costs in respect of that work was made before allocation.

(3) Where a claim, issued for a sum in excess of the normal financial scope of the small claims track, is allocated to that track only because an admission of part of the claim by the defendant reduces the amount in dispute to a sum within the normal scope of that track; on entering judgment for the admitted part before allocation of the balance of the claim the court may allow costs in respect of the proceedings down to that date.

Costs following allocation, re-allocation and non-allocation: rule 46.13

8.1  Before reallocating a claim from the small claims track to another track , the court must decide whether any party is to pay costs to the date of the order to re-allocate in accordance with the rules about costs contained in Part 27 If it decides to make such an order the court will make a summary assessment of those costs in accordance with that Part.

8.2  Where a settlement is reached or a Part 36 offer accepted in a case which has not been allocated but would, if allocated, have been suitable for allocation to the small claims track, rule 46.13 enables the court to allow only small claims track costs in accordance with rule 27.14. This power is not exercisable if the costs are to be paid on the indemnity basis.

Costs-only proceedings: rule 46.14

9.1  A claim form under rule 46.14 should not be issued in the High Court unless the dispute to which the agreement relates was of such a value or type that proceedings would have been commenced in the High Court.

9.2  A claim form which is to be issued in the High Court at the Royal Courts of Justice will be issued in the Costs Office.

9.3  Attention is drawn to rule 8.2 (in particular to paragraph (b)(ii)) and to rule 46.14(3). The claim form must –

(a) identify the claim or dispute to which the agreement relates;

(b) state the date and terms of the agreement on which the claimant relies;

(c) set out or attach a draft of the order which the claimant seeks;

(d) state the amount of the costs claimed.

9.4  Unless the court orders otherwise or Section II of Part 45 applies the costs will be treated as being claimed on the standard basis.

9.5  The evidence required under rule 8.5 includes copies of the documents on which the claimant relies to prove the defendant's agreement to pay costs.

9.6  A costs judge or a district judge has jurisdiction to hear and decide any issue which may arise in a claim issued under this rule irrespective of the amount of the costs claimed or of the value of the claim to which the agreement to pay costs relates. The court may make an order by consent under paragraph 9.8, or an order dismissing a claim under paragraph 9.10 below.

9.7  When the time for filing the defendant's acknowledgement of service has expired, the claimant may request in writing that the court make an order in the terms of the claim, unless the defendant has filed an acknowledgement of service stating the intention to contest the claim or to seek a different order.

9.8  Rule 40.6 applies where an order is to be made by consent. An order may be made by consent in terms which differ from those set out in the claim form.

9.9  Where costs are ordered to be assessed, the general rule is that this should be by detailed assessment. However when an order is made under this rule following a hearing and the court is in a position to summarily assess costs it should generally do so.

9.10  If the defendant opposes the claim the defendant must file a witness statement in accordance with rule 8.5(3). The court will then give directions including, if appropriate, a direction that the claim shall continue as if it were a Part 7 claim. A claim is not treated as opposed merely because the defendant disputes the amount of the claim for costs.

9.11  A claim issued under this rule may be dealt with without being allocated to a track. Rule 8.9 does not apply to claims issued under this rule.

9.12  Where there are other issues nothing in rule 46.14 prevents a person from issuing a claim form under Part 7 or Part 8 to sue on an agreement made in settlement of a dispute where that agreement makes provision for costs, nor from claiming in that case an order for costs or a specified sum in respect of costs but the ‘costs only’ procedure in rule 46.14 must be used where the sole issue is the amount of costs.

PRACTICE DIRECTION 51A – TRANSITIONAL ARRANGEMENTS

This Practice Direction supplements CPR Part 51

Contents of this Practice Direction

Title | Number
Contents of this Practice Direction |

General scheme of transitional arrangements |

Where the previous rules will normally apply |

General principle | Para. 3
Responding to old process | Para. 4
Filing and service of pleadings where old process served | Para. 5
AUTOMATIC DIRECTIONS/DISCOVERY |

High court | Para. 6
Default judgment | Para. 7
Judgment on admission in the county court | Para. 8
Order inconsistent with CPR | Para. 9
Steps taken before 26 April 1999 | Para. 10
Where the CPR will normally apply |

General principle | Para. 11
Part 1 (overriding objective) to apply | Para. 12
Originating process | Para. 13
Application to the court | Para. 14
First time before a judge on or after 26 April 1999 | Para. 15
Where pleadings deemed to close on or after 26 April 1999 | Para. 16
Agreement to apply the CPR | Para. 17
Omitted | Para. 18
Existing proceedings after one year | Para. 19

Contents of this Practice Direction

1

(1) This Practice Direction deals with the application of the Civil Procedure Rules (‘CPR’) to proceedings issued before 26 April 1999 (‘existing proceedings’).

(2) In this Practice Direction ‘the previous rules’ means, as appropriate the Rules of the Supreme Court 1965 (‘RSC’) or County Court Rules 1981 (‘CCR’) in force immediately before 26 April 1999.

General scheme of transitional arrangements

2  The general scheme is:

(a) to apply the previous rules to undefended cases, allowing them to progress to their disposal, but

(b) to apply the CPR to defended cases so far as is practicable.

Where the previous rules will normally apply

General principle

3  Where an initiating step has been taken in a case before 26 April 1999, in particular one that uses forms or other documentation required by the previous rules, the case will proceed in the first instance under the previous rules. Any step which a party must take in response to something done by another party in accordance with the previous rules must also be in accordance with those rules.

Responding to old process

4  A party who is served with an old type of originating process (writ, summons etc.) on or after 26 April 1999 is required to respond in accordance with the previous rules and the instructions on any forms received with the originating process.

Filing and service of pleadings where old process served

5  Where a case has been begun by an old type of originating process (whether served before or after 26 April 1999), filing and service of pleadings will continue according to the previous rules.

AUTOMATIC DIRECTIONS/DISCOVERY

High court

6

(1) Where the timetable for automatic directions under RSC Order 25, rule 8 or automatic discovery under RSC Order 24 has begun to apply to proceedings before 26 April 1999, those directions will continue to have effect on or after 26 April 1999.

County Court

(2) Where automatic directions under CCR Order 17, rule 11 have begun to apply to existing proceedings before 26 April 1999 or the court has sent out notice that automatic directions under CCR Order 17, rule 11 (Form N.450) will apply (even if the timetable will not begin until 26 April 1999 or after), those directions will continue to have effect on or after 26 April 1999.

(3) However CCR Order 17, rule 11(9) will not apply and therefore proceedings will not be struck out where there has been no request for a hearing to be fixed within 15 months of the date when pleadings were deemed to close. (But see paragraph 19.)

High Court and County Court

(4) However, if the case comes before the court on or after 26 April 1999, the new rules may apply. (See paragraph 15.)

Default judgment

7

(1) If a party wishes default judgment to be entered in existing proceedings, he must do so in accordance with the previous rules.

(2) Where default judgment has been entered and there are outstanding issues to be resolved (e.g. damages to be assessed), the court officer may refer the proceedings to the judge, so that case management decisions about the proceedings and the conduct of the hearing can be made in accordance with the practice set out in paragraph 15.

(3) If a party needs to apply for permission to enter default judgment, he must make that application under CPR Part 23 (general rules about applications for court orders).

(4) An application to set aside judgment entered in default must be made under CPR Part 23 (general rules about applications for court orders) and CPR Part 13 (setting aside or varying default judgment) will apply to the proceedings as it would apply to default judgment entered under the CPR.

(5) CPR rule 15.11 (claims stayed if it is not defended or admitted) applies to these proceedings.

Judgment on admission in the county court

8

(1) If a party to existing proceedings in the county court wishes to request judgment to be entered on an admission, he must do so in accordance with the previous rules.

(2) Where judgment has been entered and there are outstanding issues to be resolved (e.g. damages to be assessed), the court officer may refer the proceedings to the judge, so that case management decisions about the proceedings and the conduct of the hearing can be made in accordance with the practice set out in paragraph 15.

(3) If a party needs to apply for permission to enter judgment, he must make that application under CPR Part 23 (general rules about applications for court orders).

Order inconsistent with CPR

9  Where a court order has been made before 26 April 1999, that order must still be complied with on or after 26 April 1999.

Steps taken before 26 April 1999

10

(1) Where a party has taken any step in the proceedings in accordance with the previous rules that step will remain valid on or after 26 April 1999.

(2) A party will not normally be required to take any action that would amount to taking that step again under the CPR. For example if discovery has been given, a party will not normally be required to provide disclosure under CPR Part 31.

Where the CPR will normally apply

General principle

11

Where a new step is to be taken in any existing proceedings on or after 26 April 1999, it is to be taken under the CPR.

Part 1 (overriding objective) to apply

12  Part 1 (overriding objective) will apply to all existing proceedings from 26 April 1999 onwards.

Originating process

13

(1) Only claim forms under the CPR will be issued by the court on or after 26 April 1999.

(2) If a request to issue an old type of originating process (writ, summons etc.) is received at the court on or after 26 April 1999 it will be returned unissued.

(3) An application made on or after 26 April 1999 to extend the validity of originating process issued before 26 April 1999 must be made in accordance with CPR Part 23 (general rules about applications for court orders), but the court will decide whether to allow the application in accordance with the previous law.

Application to the court

14

(1) Any application to the court made on or after 26 April 1999 must be made in accordance with CPR Part 23 (general rules about applications for court orders).

(2) Any other relevant CPR will apply to the substance of the application, unless this practice direction provides otherwise. (See paragraphs 13(3) (application to extend the validity of originating process) and 18(2) (costs)).

(3) For example, a party wishing to apply for summary judgment must do so having regard to the test in CPR Part 24. A party wishing to apply for an interim remedy must do so under CPR Part 25 etc.

(4) Any other CPR will apply as necessary. For example, CPR Part 4 will apply as to forms and CPR Part 6 will apply to service of documents.

(5) If the pleadings have not been filed at court, the applicant must file all pleadings served when he files his application notice.

First time before a judge on or after 26 April 1999

15

(1) When proceedings come before a judge (whether at a hearing or on paper) for the first time on or after 26 April 1999, he may direct how the CPR are to apply to the proceedings and may disapply certain provisions of the CPR. He may also give case management directions (which may include allocating the proceedings to a case management track).

(2) The general presumption will be that the CPR will apply to the proceedings from then on unless the judge directs or this practice direction provides otherwise. (See paragraphs 13(3) (application to extend the validity of originating process) and 18(2) (costs).)

(3) If an application has been issued before 26 April 1999 and the hearing of the application has been set for a date on or after 26 April 1999, the general presumption is that the application will be decided having regard to the CPR. (For example an application for summary judgment issued before 26 April 1999, with a hearing date set for 1 May 1999, will be decided having regard to the test in CPR Part 24 (summary Judgment).)

(4) When the first occasion on which existing proceedings are before a judge on or after 26 April 1999 is a trial or hearing of a substantive issue, the general presumption is that the trial or hearing will be conducted having regard to the CPR.

Where pleadings deemed to close on or after 26 April 1999

16

(1) This paragraph applies to existing proceedings where pleadings are deemed to close on or after 26 April 1999. However, this paragraph does not apply to those county court proceedings where notice that automatic directions apply (Form N.450) has been sent (in which case the automatic directions will apply – see paragraph 6).

(2) CPR Part 26 (case management – preliminary stage) applies to these proceedings.

(3) If a defence is filed at court on or after 26 April 1999, the court will serve an allocation questionnaire where CPR rule 26.3 would apply, unless it dispenses with the need for one.

(4) If pleadings have not been filed at court (this will normally be the case in the Queen’s Bench Division) the claimant must file copies of all the pleadings served within 14 days of the date that pleadings are deemed to close.

(5) Unless it dispenses with the need for one, the court will then serve an allocation questionnaire.

(6) In the previous rules pleadings are deemed to close:

(a) High court –

(i) 14 days after service of any reply, or

(ii) if there is no reply, 14 days after service of the defence to counterclaim, or

(iii) if there is no reply or defence to counterclaim, 14 days after the service of the defence.

(b) County court –

14 days after the delivery of a defence or, where a counterclaim is served with the defence, 28 days after the delivery of the defence.

(7) Where there are 2 or more defendants the court will normally wait until the claimant has filed copies of all the pleadings before serving an allocation questionnaire. However, the court may (in cases where there is a delay) serve allocation questionnaires despite the fact that pleadings have not closed in respect of any other defendant.

(8) The court will then allocate the proceedings in accordance with CPR rule 26.5.

(9) The CPR will then apply generally to the proceedings.

Agreement to apply the CPR

17

The parties may agree in writing that the CPR will apply to any proceedings from the date of the agreement. When they do so:

(a) all those who are parties at that time must agree,

(b) the CPR must apply in their entirety,

(c) the agreement is irrevocable,

(d) the claimant must file a copy of the agreement at court.

18

Omitted

Existing proceedings after one year

19

(1) If any existing proceedings have not come before a judge, at a hearing or on paper, between 26 April 1999 and 25 April 2000, those proceedings shall be stayed.

(2) Any party to those proceedings may apply for the stay to be lifted.

(3) Proceedings of the following types will not be stayed as a result of this provision:

(a) where the case has been given a fixed trial date which is after 25 April 2000,

(b) personal injury cases where there is no issue on liability but the proceedings have been adjourned by court order to determine the prognosis,

(c) where the court is dealing with the continuing administration of an estate or a trust or a receivership,

(d) applications relating to funds in court.

(4) For the purposes of this paragraph proceedings will not be ‘existing proceedings’ once final judgment has been given.

Practice Direction 52C - appeals to the court of appeal

This Practice Direction supplements CPR Part 52

Contents of this Practice Direction

Contents of this Practice Direction

This Practice Direction is divided into the following sections –

Section I – Introduction and interpretation

Section II – Starting an appeal to the Court of Appeal, Grounds of Appeal and Skeleton Arguments

Section III –Respondent’s notice and respondent's skeleton argument

Section IV – Procedure where permission to appeal is sought from the Court of Appeal

Section V –Timetable

Section VI – Management of the appeal

Section VII – Bundles, amendment and supplementary skeleton arguments

SECTION I – INTRODUCTION AND INTERPRETATION

1.  In this Practice Direction –

‘appeal notice’ means either an appellant’s notice in form N161 or a respondent’s notice in form N162 ;

‘appellant’s notice’ means an appeal notice filed by an appellant and a ‘respondent’s notice’ means an appeal notice filed by a respondent;

‘hearing date’ means the date on which the appeal is listed to be heard, including a‘floating’ date over two or more days;

‘listing window notification’ means the letter sent by the Civil Appeals Office in accordance with Section 5: Timetable Part 1 notifying the parties of the window within which the appeal is likely to be heard; and ‘date of the listing window notification’ means the date of such letter;

‘replacement skeleton argument’ means a skeleton argument which has been amended in order to include cross references to the appeal bundle and is lodged and served in accordance with the timetable at Section 5 Part 2.

2.  The court may make such directions as the case may require and such directions will prevail over any provision of this practice direction.

SECTION II – STARTING AN APPEAL TO THE COURT OF APPEAL

Filing the appellant’s notice and accompanying documents

3.

(1) An appellant’s notice (Form N161) must be filed and served in all cases. The appellant’s notice must be accompanied by the appropriate fee or, if appropriate, a fee remission certificate.

(2) The appellant’s notice and accompanying documents must be filed in the Civil Appeals Office Registry, Room E307, Royal Courts of Justice, Strand, London, WC2A 2LL.

(3) At the same time as filing an appellant’s notice, the appellant must provide for the use of the court three copies of the appellant’s notice and one copy of each of the following –

(a) the sealed order or tribunal determination being appealed;

(b) any order granting or refusing permission to appeal, together with a copy of the judge’s or tribunal’s reasons for granting or refusing permission to appeal;

(c) any witness statements or affidavits relied on in support of any application included in the appellant’s notice;

(d) in cases where the decision of the lower court was itself made on appeal, the first order, the reasons given by the judge who made it, and the appellant’s notice of appeal against that order;

(e) in a claim for judicial review or a statutory appeal, the original decision which was the subject of the application to the lower court;

(f) the order allocating the case to a track (if any);

(g) the appellant’s skeleton argument in support of the appeal;

(h) the approved transcript of the judgment.

(4) The appellant must also provide to the court one copy of the appellant’s notice for each respondent for sealing by the court and return to the appellant for service.

(5) Where the appellant applies for permission to appeal, additional documents are required: see Section 4 of this Practice Direction.

(5) Provisions in relation to the skeleton argument are set out in paragraph 31.

Extension of time for filing appellant’s notice

4.

(1) Where the time for filing an appellant’s notice has expired, the appellant must –

(a) file the appellant’s notice; and

(b) include in that appellant’s notice an application for an extension of time.

(2) The appellant’s notice must state the reason for the delay and the steps taken prior to the application being made.

(3) Where the appellant’s notice includes an application for an extension of time and permission to appeal has been given or is not required, the respondent has the right to oppose that application and to be heard at any hearing of that application. In respect of any application to extend time –

(a) The respondent must–

(i) be served with a copy of any evidence filed in support of the application; and

(ii) inform the court in writing of any objections to the grant of the extension of time within 7 days of being served with the appellant’s notice.

(b) A respondent who unreasonably opposes an application for an extension of time may be ordered to pay the costs of the application.

(c) An application for an extension of time will normally be determined without a hearing unless the court directs otherwise.

Grounds of appeal

5.

(1) The grounds of appeal must identify as concisely as possible the respects in which the judgment of the court below is –

(a) wrong; or

(b) unjust because of a serious procedural or other irregularity,

as required by rule 52.11(3).

(2) The reasons why the decision under appeal is wrong or unjust must not be included in the grounds of appeal and must be confined to the skeleton argument.

Second appeals

5A  An application to make a second appeal must identify in the grounds of appeal –

(1) the important point of principle or practice, or

(2) the compelling reason

which is said to justify the grant of permission to appeal.

Non-availability of documents

6.  If the appellant is unable to provide any of the necessary documents in time, the appellant must complete the appeal notice on the basis of the available documents. The notice may be amended subsequently with the permission of the court (see paragraph 30).

Service on the respondent

7.1  The Civil Appeals Office will not serve documents. Where service is required by the Rules or this Practice Direction, it must be effected by the parties.

7.1A  The appellant’s skeleton argument must be served on each respondent at the same time as service of the appellant’s notice.

7.2  The evidence in support of any application made in an appellant’s notice must be filed and served with the appellant’s notice.

7.3  An application for an order to dispense with service of the appellant’s notice under rule 6.28 must be made in the appeal notice or, thereafter, by application notice under Part 23.

SECTION III – RESPONDENT’S NOTICE (RULE 52.5) AND RESPONDENT’S SKELETON ARGUMENT

Respondent’s notice

8.

(1) A respondent who seeks to appeal against any part of the order made by the court below must file an appeal notice.

(2) A respondent who seeks a variation of the order of the lower court must file an appeal notice and must obtain permission to appeal.

(3) A respondent who seeks to contend that the order of the court below should be upheld for reasons other than those given by that court must file a respondent’s notice.

(4) The notice may be amended subsequently with the permission of the court (see paragraph 30).

Skeleton argument to be lodged with the respondent’s notice

9.  A respondent who files a respondent’s notice must, within 14 days of filing the notice, lodge a skeleton argument with the court and serve a copy of the skeleton argument on every other party to the appeal.

(Provisions in relation to the skeleton argument are set out in paragraph 31.)

Documents to be filed with respondent’s notice

10.  The respondent must file the following documents with the respondent’s notice –

(a) two additional copies of the respondent’s notice for the court; and

(b) one copy each for the appellant and any other respondents.

Applications within respondent’s notice

11.

(1) A respondent may include an application within a respondent’s notice.

(2) The parties must consider whether it would be more convenient for any application to be listed with the appeal or whether the application needs to be considered in advance.

(3) Where parties consider that the time estimate for the appeal will be affected by listing the application with the appeal, they must inform the court without delay.

Time limits: rule 52.5(4) and (5)

12.  Where an extension of time is required, the respondent must apply in the respondent’s notice and explain the delay.

Respondent’s skeleton argument (where no respondent’s notice filed)

13.

(1) In all cases where the respondent is legally represented and proposes to address the court, the respondent must lodge and serve a skeleton argument.

(2) A respondent’s skeleton argument must be lodged and served in accordance with Part 1 of the Timetable in Section 5.

(Provisions in relation to the skeleton argument are set out in paragraph 31.)

SECTION IV – PROCEDURE WHERE PERMISSION TO APPEAL IS SOUGHT FROM THE COURT OF APPEAL

Documents for use on an application for permission

14.

(1) Within 14 days of filing the appeal notice the appellant must lodge a bundle containing only those documents which are necessary for the court to determine that application.

(2) The bundle of documents must–

(a) be paginated and in chronological order;

(b) contain an index at the front.

Determination of applications for permission to appeal

15.

(1) Applications for permission to appeal will generally be considered by the court without a hearing in the first instance. The court will notify the parties of the decision and the reasons for it.

(2) If permission is refused the appellant is entitled to have the decision reconsidered at an oral hearing, except where rule 52.3(4A) (applications totally without merit) applies. The hearing may be before the same judge.

(3) A request for the decision to be reconsidered at an oral hearing must be filed within 7 days after service of the letter giving notice that permission has been refused. A copy of the request must be served by the appellant on the respondent at the same time.

Permission hearing

16.

(1) Where an appellant who is represented makes a request for a decision to be reconsidered at an oral hearing, the appellant’s advocate must at least 4 days before the hearing file a brief written statement –

(a) informing the court and the respondent of the points which are to be raised at the hearing; and

(b) setting out the reasons why permission should be granted notwithstanding the reasons given for the refusal of permission.

(2) The court will notify the respondent of the hearing but the respondent is not expected to attend unless the court so directs.

(3) If the court directs the respondent to attend the permission hearing, the appellant must supply the respondent with a copy of the skeleton argument and any documents to which the appellant intends to refer.

Appellant in receipt of services funded by the Legal Services Commission applying for permission to appeal

17.  Where the appellant is in receipt of services funded by the Legal Services Commission and permission to appeal has been refused by the court without a hearing, the appellant must send a copy of the court’s reasons for refusing permission to the Legal Services Commission as soon as it has been received. The court will require confirmation that this has been done if a hearing is requested to re-consider the application.

Limited permission: rule 52.3

18.

(1) If, under rule 52.3(7), the court grants permission to appeal on some issues only, it will –

(a) refuse permission on any remaining issues; or

(b) adjourn the application in respect of those issues to the hearing of the appeal.

(2) If the court adjourns the application under sub-paragraph (1)(b), the appellant must inform the court and the respondent in writing, within 14 days after the date of the court’s order, whether the appellant intends to pursue the application. If the appellant intends to pursue the application, the parties must include in any time estimate for the appeal hearing an allowance for the adjourned application.

(3) If the court refuses permission to appeal on the remaining issues without a hearing and the applicant wishes to have that decision reconsidered at an oral hearing, the time limit in rule 52.3(5) applies. Any application for an extension of this time should be made promptly. When hearing the appeal on the issues for which permission has been given the court will not normally grant an application to extend time in relation to the remaining issues.

Respondent need not take any action when served with an appellant’s notice

19.  Unless the court directs otherwise, a respondent need not take any action when served with an appellant’s notice until notified that permission to appeal has been granted.

Respondent’s costs of permission applications

20.

(1) In most cases an application for permission to appeal will be determined without the need for the respondent to file submissions or attend a hearing. In such circumstances an order for costs will not normally be made in favour of a respondent who voluntarily makes submissions or attends a hearing.

(2) If the court directs the respondent to file submissions or attend a hearing, it will normally award costs to the respondent if permission is refused.

SECTION V – TIMETABLE

21.  Subject to any specific directions that may be given by the court, the timetable for the conduct of an appeal after the date of the listing window notification is set out below:

Timetable Part 1 – Listing window notification to lodging bundle

Timetable Part 2 – Steps to be taken once hearing date fixed: lodging bundles, supplemental skeletons and bundles of authorities

SECTION VI – MANAGEMENT OF THE APPEAL

Listing and hear-by dates

22.  The hear-by date is the last day of the listing window.

Appeal Questionnaire

23.  The appellant must complete and file the Appeal Questionnaire and serve it on the respondent within 14 days after the date of the listing window notification.

Time estimates

24.  If the respondent disagrees with the appellant’s time estimate, the respondent must inform the court within 7 days of service of the Appeal Questionnaire. In the absence of such notification the respondent will be deemed to have accepted the appellant’s time estimate.

Multiple appeals

25.

(1) If two or more appeals are pending in the same or related proceedings, the parties must seek directions as to whether they should be heard together or consecutively by the same judges.

(2) Whether appeals are heard together or consecutively, the parties must attempt to agree a single appeal bundle or set of bundles for all the appeals and seek directions if they are unable to do so.

Expedition

26.

(1) The court may direct that the hearing of an appeal be expedited.

(2) The court will deal with requests for expedition without a hearing. Requests for expedition must be made by letter setting out succinctly the grounds on which expedition is sought. The letter (or, if time is particularly short, email) must be marked for the immediate attention of the court and copied to the other parties to the appeal.

(3) If an expedited appeal hearing is required as a matter of extreme urgency, the Civil Appeals Office must be informed as soon as possible. If necessary, parties or their legal representatives should call the Royal Courts of Justice switchboard on 020 7947 6000 and ask a member of the security staff to contact the Duty Judge.

(4) An expedited hearing will be listed at the convenience of the court and not according to the availability of counsel.

SECTION VII – BUNDLES, AMENDMENT AND SKELETON ARGUMENTS

Bundle of documents

27.

(1) The appellant must lodge an appeal bundle which must contain only those documents relevant to the appeal. The bundle must –

(a) be paginated and in chronological order;

(b) contain an index at the front.

(2) Documents relevant to the appeal: Subject to any order made by the court, the following documents must be included in the appeal bundle –

(a) a copy of the appellant’s notice;

(b) a copy of any respondent’s notice;

(c) a copy of any appellant’s or respondent’s skeleton argument;

(d) a copy of the order under appeal;

(e) a copy of the order of the lower court granting or refusing permission to appeal together with a copy of the judge's reasons, if any, for granting or refusing permission;

(f) a copy of any order allocating the case to a track;

(g) the approved transcript of the judgment of the lower court (except in appeals in cases which were allocated to the small claims track but subject to any order of the court).

(3) Documents which may be included: The following documents should also be considered for inclusion in the appeal bundle but should be included only where relevant to the appeal –

(a) statements of case;

(b) application notices;

(c) other orders made in the case;

(d) a chronology of relevant events;

(e) witness statements made in support of any application made in the appellant’s notice;

(f) other witness statements;

(g) other documents which the appellant or respondent consider relevant to the appeal.

(4) Bundles not to include originals: Unless otherwise directed, the appeal bundle should not include original material such as original documents, photographs and recorded media. Such material should be provided to the court, if necessary, at the hearing.

(5) Destruction of bundles: Bundles lodged with the court will not be returned to the parties but will be destroyed in the confidential waste system at the conclusion of the proceedings and without further notification.

Appeals from the Upper Tribunal Immigration and Asylum Chamber

28.

(1) In an appeal from the Immigration and Asylum Chamber of the Upper Tribunal (other than an appeal relating to a claim for judicial review) –

(a) the Immigration and Asylum Chamber of the Upper Tribunal, upon request, shall send to the Civil Appeals Office copies of the documents which were before the relevant Tribunal when it considered the appeal;

(b) the appellant is not required to file an appeal bundle;

(c) the appellant must file with the appellant’s notice the documents specified in paragraph 4(3)(a) to (e) and (g) of this Practice Direction.

Bundle of authorities

29.

(1) After consultation with any opposing advocate, the appellant’s advocate must file a bundle containing photocopies of the authorities upon which each party will rely at the hearing.

(2) The most authoritative report of each authority must be used in accordance with the Practice Direction on Citation of Authorities (2012) and must have the relevant passages marked by a vertical line in the margin.

(3) Photocopies of authorities should not be in landscape format and the type should not be reduced in size.

(4) The bundle should not–

(a) include authorities for propositions not in dispute; or

(b) contain more than 10 authorities unless the issues in the appeal justify more extensive citation.

(5) A bundle of authorities must bear a certificate by the advocates responsible for arguing the case that the requirements of sub-paragraphs (2) to (4) of this paragraph have been complied with in respect of each authority included.

Amendment of appeal notice: rule 52.8

30.

(1) An appeal notice may not be amended without the permission of the court.

(2) An application for permission to amend made before permission to appeal has been considered will normally be determined without a hearing.

(3) An application for permission to amend (after permission to appeal has been granted) and any submissions in opposition will normally be dealt with at the hearing unless that would cause unnecessary expense or delay, in which case a request should be made for the application to amend to be heard in advance.

(4) Legal representatives must–

(a) inform the court at the time they make the application if the existing time estimate is affected by the proposed amendment; and

(b) attempt to agree any revised time estimate no later than 7 days after service of the application.

Skeleton argument

31.

(1) Any skeleton argument must comply with the provisions of Section 5 of Practice Direction 52A and must–

(a) not normally exceed 25 pages (excluding front sheets and back sheets);

(b) be printed on A4 paper in not less than 12 point font and 1.5 line spacing.

(2) Where an appellant has filed a skeleton argument in support of an application for permission to appeal, the same skeleton argument may be relied upon in the appeal or the appellant may file an appeal skeleton argument (Timetable Section 5, Part 1).

(3) At the hearing the court may refuse to hear argument on a point not included in a skeleton argument filed within the prescribed time.

(4) The court may disallow the cost of preparing an appeal skeleton argument which does not comply with these requirements or was not filed within the prescribed time.

Supplementary skeleton arguments

32.

(1) A party may file a supplementary skeleton argument only where strictly necessary and only with the permission of the court.

(2) If a party wishes to rely on a supplementary skeleton argument, it must be lodged and served as soon as practicable. It must be accompanied by a request for permission setting out the reasons why a supplementary skeleton argument is necessary and why it could not reasonably have been lodged earlier.

(3) Only exceptionally will the court allow the use of a supplementary skeleton argument if lodged later than 7 days before the hearing.

Practice Direction 52D - statutory appeals and appeals subject to special provision

This Practice Direction supplements CPR Part 52

Contents of this Practice Direction

Contents of this Practice Direction

This Practice Direction is divided into the following sections:

Section I –Introduction

Section II – Routes of appeal

Section III – General provisions about statutory appeals

Section IV – Specific appeals

SECTION I – INTRODUCTION

1.1  This Practice Direction applies to all statutory appeals, and to other appeals which are subject to special provision, but not to appeals by way of case stated (to which Practice Direction 52E applies).

SECTION II – ROUTES OF APPEAL

2.1  In this Practice Direction, the court to which an appeal lies is prescribed by statute.

SECTION III – GENERAL PROVISIONS ABOUT STATUTORY APPEALS

3.1  This Section contains general provisions about statutory appeals (paragraphs 3.2 – 3.8). For where this Practice Direction or a statute makes additional special provision see also Section 4.

3.2  Where any of the provisions in this Section provide for documents to be filed at the appeal court, those documents are in addition to any documents required under Part 52 or Practice Direction 52B or 52C.

3.3

(1) Where the appellant wishes to appeal against a decision of the Administrative Appeals Chamber of the Upper Tribunal, the appellant's notice must be filed within 21 days of the date on which the Upper Tribunal’s decision on permission to appeal to the Court of Appeal is given.

(2) Where the appellant wishes to appeal against a decision of any other Chamber of the Upper Tribunal, the appellant’s notice must be filed within 28 days of the date on which the Upper Tribunal's decision on permission to appeal to the Court of Appeal is given.

3.3A  Where a statement of reasons for a decision is given later than the notice of that decision, the period for filing the appellant’s notice is calculated from the date on which the statement is received by the appellant.

Service of appellant’s notice: rule 52.4(3)

3.4

(1) The appellant must serve the appellant’s notice on the respondent and on the chairman of the tribunal, Minister of State, government department or other person from whose decision the appeal is brought.

(2) In the case of an appeal from the decision of a tribunal that has no chairman or member who acts as a chairman, the appellant’s notice must be served on the member (or members if more than one) of the tribunal.

Variation of time: rule 52.6

3.5  Where any statute prescribes a period within which an appeal must be filed then, unless the statute otherwise provides, the appeal court may not extend that period.

Applications by third parties (rule 52.12A)

3.6  Where all the parties consent, the court may deal with an application under rule 52.12A without a hearing.

3.7  An application for permission must be made by letter to the relevant court office, identifying the appeal, explaining who the applicant is and indicating why and in what form the applicant wants to participate in the hearing.

3.8  If the applicant is seeking a prospective order as to costs, the letter must say what kind of order and on what grounds.

SECTION IV – SPECIFIC APPEALS

Provisions about specific appeals

4.1  This Section sets out special provisions about the appeals listed in the Table below. This Section is not exhaustive and does not create, amend or remove any right of appeal.

4.2  Part 52 applies to all appeals to which this Section applies subject to any special provisions set out in this Section.

4.3  Where any of the provisions in this Section provide for documents to be filed at the appeal court, these documents are in addition to any documents required under Part 52 or Practice Direction 52B or 52C.

Certain appeals to the High Court to be heard in Chancery Division

5.1  Any appeal to the High Court, and any case stated or question referred for the opinion of that court under any of the following enactments shall be heard in the Chancery Division –

(1) section 38(3) of the Clergy Pensions Measure 1961;

(2) regulation 74 of the European Public Limited-Liability Company Regulations 2004.

(3) the Industrial and Provident Societies Act 1965;

(4) section 222(3) of the Inheritance Tax Act 1984;

(5) the Land Registration Act 2002;

(6) paragraph 16 of Schedule 15 to the Law of Property Act 1922;

(7) section 215 or 217 of the Pensions Act 2003;

(8) section 151 of the Pension Schemes Act 1993;

(9) section 13 and 13B of the Stamp Act 1891;

(10) regulation 8(3) of the Stamp Duty Reserve Tax Regulations 1986.

Table

APPEALS TO THE COURT OF APPEAL

Appeal against decree nisi of divorce or nullity of marriage or conditional dissolution or nullity order in relation to civil partnership

6.1

(1) The appellant must file the appellant’s notice at the Court of Appeal within 28 days after the date on which the decree was pronounced or conditional order made.

(2) The appellant must file the following documents with the appellant’s notice –

(a) the decree or conditional order; and

(b) a certificate of service of the appellant’s notice.

(3) The appellant’s notice must be served on the appropriate district judge (see sub-paragraph (6)) in addition to the persons to be served under rule 52.4(3) and in accordance with that rule.

(4) The lower court may not alter the time limits for filing of the appeal notices.

(5) Where an appellant intends to apply to the Court of Appeal for an extension of time for serving or filing the appellant’s notice the appellant must give notice of that intention to the appropriate district judge (see sub-paragraph 6) before the application is made.

(6) In this paragraph ‘the appropriate district judge’ means, where the lower court is –

(a) a county court, the district judge of that court;

(b) a district registry, the district judge of that registry;

(c) the Principal Registry of the Family Division, the senior district judge of that division.

Appeals relating to the application of Articles 101 and 102 of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union and Chapters I and II of Part I of the Competition Act 1998

7.1

(1) This paragraph applies to any appeal to the Court of Appeal relating to the application of –

(a) Article 101 or Article 102 of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union; or

(b) Chapter I or Chapter II of Part I of the Competition Act 1998.

(2) In this paragraph –

(a) ‘the Act’ means the Competition Act 1998;

(b) ‘the Commission’ means the European Commission;

(c) ‘the Competition Regulation’ means Council Regulation (EC) No. 1/2003 of 16 December 2002 on the implementation of the rules on competition laid down in Articles 81 and 82 of the Treaty establishing the European Community (as amended in consequence of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union);

(d) ‘national competition authority’ means –

(i) the Office of Fair Trading; and

(ii) any other person or body designated pursuant to Article 35 of the Competition Regulation as a national competition authority of the United Kingdom;

(e) ‘the Treaty’ means the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union.

(3) Any party whose appeal notice raises an issue relating to the application of Article 101 or 102 of the Treaty, or Chapter I or II of Part I of the Act, must –

(a) state that fact in the appeal notice; and

(b) serve a copy of the appeal notice on the Office of Fair Trading at the same time as it is served on the other party to the appeal (addressed to the Director of Competition Policy Co-ordination, Office of Fair Trading, Fleetbank House, 2-6 Salisbury Square, London EC4Y 8JX).

(4) Attention is drawn to the provisions of article 15.3 of the Competition Regulation, which entitles competition authorities and the Commission to submit written observations to national courts on issues relating to the application of Article 101 or 102 and, with the permission of the court in question, to submit oral observations to the court.

(5) A national competition authority may also make written observations to the Court of Appeal, or apply for permission to make oral observations, on issues relating to the application of Chapter I or II.

(6) If a national competition authority or the Commission intends to make written observations to the Court of Appeal, it must give notice of its intention to do so by letter to the Civil Appeals Office at the earliest opportunity.

(7) An application by a national competition authority or the Commission for permission to make oral representations at the hearing of an appeal must be made by letter to the Civil Appeals Office at the earliest opportunity, identifying the appeal and indicating why the applicant wishes to make oral representations.

(8) If a national competition authority or the Commission files a notice under sub-paragraph (6) or an application under sub-paragraph (7), it must at the same time serve a copy of the notice or application on every party to the appeal.

(9) Any request by a national competition authority or the Commission for the court to send it any documents relating to an appeal should be made at the same time as filing a notice under sub-paragraph (6) or an application under sub-paragraph (7).

(10) When the Court of Appeal receives a notice under sub-paragraph (6) it may give case management directions to the national competition authority or the Commission, including directions about the date by which any written observations are to be filed.

(11) The Court of Appeal will serve on every party to the appeal a copy of any directions given or order made–

(a) on an application under sub-paragraph (7); or

(b) under sub-paragraph (10).

(12) Every party to an appeal which raises an issue relating to the application of Article 101 or 102, and any national competition authority which has been served with a copy of a party’s appeal notice, is under a duty to notify the Court of Appeal at any stage of the appeal if they are aware that –

(a) the Commission has adopted, or is contemplating adopting, a decision in relation to proceedings which it has initiated; and

(b) the decision referred to in (a) above has or would have legal effects in relation to the particular agreement, decision or practice in issue before the court.

(13) Where the Court of Appeal is aware that the Commission is contemplating adopting a decision as mentioned in sub-paragraph (12)(a), it shall consider whether to stay the appeal pending the Commission’s decision.

(14) Where any judgment is given which decides on the application of Article 101 or 102, the court shall direct that a copy of the transcript of the judgment shall be sent to the Commission. Judgments may be sent to the Commission electronically to comp-amicus@cec.eu.int or by post to the European Commission DG Competition, B-1049, Brussels.

Appeal from Competition Appeal Tribunal

8.1

(1) Where the appellant applies for permission to appeal at the hearing at which the decision is delivered by the tribunal and –

(a) permission is given; or

(b) permission is refused and the appellant wishes to make an application to the Court of Appeal for permission to appeal,

the appellant’s notice must be filed at the Court of Appeal within 14 days after the date of that hearing.

(2) Where the appellant applies in writing to the Registrar of the tribunal for permission to appeal and–

(a) permission is given; or

(b) permission is refused and the appellant wishes to make an application to the Court of Appeal for permission to appeal,

the appellant’s notice must be filed at the Court of Appeal within 14 days after the date of receipt of the tribunal's decision on permission.

(3) Where the appellant does not make an application to the tribunal for permission to appeal, but wishes to make an application to the Court of Appeal for permission, the appellant's notice must be filed at the Court of Appeal within 14 days after the end of the period within which the appellant may make a written application to the Registrar of the tribunal.

Appeals in cases of contempt of court (section 13 Administration of Justice Act 1960)

9.1  In an appeal under section 13 of the Administration of Justice Act 1960 (appeals in cases of contempt of court), the appellant must serve the appellant’s notice on the court or the Upper Tribunal from whose order or decision the appeal is brought in addition to the persons to be served under rule 52.4(3) and in accordance with that rule.

Appeal from the Court of Protection

10.1

(1) In this paragraph –

(a) ‘P’ means a person who lacks, or who is alleged to lack, capacity within the meaning of the Mental Capacity Act 2005 to make a decision or decisions in relation to any matter that is subject to an order of the Court of Protection;

(b) ‘the person effecting notification’ means –

(i) the appellant;

(ii) an agent duly appointed by the appellant; or

(iii) such other person as the Court of Protection may direct, who is required to notify P in accordance with this paragraph; and

(c) ‘final order’ means a decision of the Court of Appeal that finally determines the appeal proceedings before it.

(2) Where P is not a party to the proceedings, unless the Court of Appeal directs otherwise, the person effecting notification must notify P –

(a) that an appellant’s notice has been filed with the Court of Appeal and –

(i) who the appellant is;

(ii) what final order the appellant is seeking;

(iii) what will happen if the Court of Appeal makes the final order sought by the appellant; and

(iv) that P may apply under rule 52.12A (Statutory appeals: court's power to hear any person) by letter for permission to file evidence or make representations at the appeal hearing;

(b) of the final order, the effect of the final order and what steps P can take in relation to it; and

(c) of such other events and documents as the Court of Appeal may direct.

(Paragraphs 3.6 to 3.8 of this Practice Direction 52D contain provisions on how a third party can apply for permission to file evidence or make representations at an appeal hearing.)

(3) The person effecting notification must provide P with the information specified in sub-paragraph (2)–

(a) within 14 days of the date on which the appellant’s notice was filed with the Court of Appeal;

(b) within 14 days of the date on which the final order was made; or

(c) within such time as the Court of Appeal may direct,

as the case may be.

(4) The person effecting notification must provide P in person with the information specified in sub-paragraph (2) in a way that is appropriate to P’s circumstances (for example, using simple language, visual aids or any other appropriate means).

(5) Where P is to be notified as to –

(a) the existence or effect of a document other than the appellant's notice or final order; or

(b) the taking place of an event,

the person effecting notification must explain to P –

(i) in the case of a document, what the document is and what effect, if any, it has; or

(ii) in the case of an event, what the event is and its relevance to P.

(6) The person effecting notification must, within 7 days of notifying P, file a certificate of notification (form N165) which certifies –

(a) the date on which P was notified; and

(b) that P was notified in accordance with this paragraph.

(7) Where the person effecting notification has not notified P in accordance with this paragraph, a certificate of non-notification (form N165) must be filed with the Court of Appeal stating the reason why notification has not been effected.

(8) Where the person effecting notification must file a certificate of non-notification with the Court of Appeal, the certificate must be filed within the following time limits–

(a) where P is to be notified in accordance with sub-paragraph (2)(a) (appellant’s notice), within 21 days of the appellant’s notice being filed with the Court of Appeal;

(b) where P is to be notified in accordance with sub-paragraph (2)(b) (final order), within 21 days of the final order being made by the Court of Appeal; or

(c) where P is to be notified of such other events and documents as may be directed by the Court of Appeal, within such time as the Court of Appeal directs.

(9) The appellant or such other person as the Court of Appeal may direct may apply to the Court of Appeal seeking an order –

(a) dispensing with the requirement to comply with the provisions of this paragraph; or

(b) requiring some other person to comply with the provisions of this paragraph.

(10) An application made under sub-paragraph (9) may be made in the appellant's notice or by Part 23 application notice.

(Paragraphs 6.1 to 6.3 of Practice Direction 52A contain provisions about the dismissal of applications or appeals by consent. Paragraph 6.5 of Practice Direction 52A contains provisions about allowing unopposed appeals or applications involving a child or protected party.)

Appeal from Employment Appeal Tribunal

11.1

(1) This paragraph applies to an appeal to the Court of Appeal from the Employment Appeal Tribunal (EAT) under section 37 of the Employment Tribunals Act 1996.

(2) If an application for permission to appeal to the Court of Appeal is refused by the EAT or is not made, then such an application must be made to the Court of Appeal within 21 days of the date of the sealed order of the EAT.

(3) An application for extension of time for filing an appellant’s notice may be entertained by the EAT but such applications should normally be made to the Court of Appeal.

Immigration and Asylum Appeals

12.1  The provisions of paragraph 28 of Practice Direction 52C (bundle of documents in immigration appeals and asylum appeals) apply to appeals from the Upper Tribunal Immigration and Asylum Chamber.

Appeal from Patents Court on appeal from Comptroller

13.1  Where the appeal is from a decision of the Patents Court which was itself made on an appeal from a decision of the Comptroller-General of Patents, Designs and Trade Marks, the appellant must serve the appellant’s notice on the Comptroller in addition to the persons to be served under rule 52.4(3) and in accordance with that rule.

Appeal against order for revocation of patent

14.1

(1) This paragraph applies where an appeal lies to the Court of Appeal from an order for the revocation of a patent.

(2) The appellant must serve the appellant’s notice on the Comptroller-General of Patents, Designs and Trade Marks (the ‘Comptroller’) in addition to the persons to be served under rule 52.4(3) and in accordance with that rule.

(3) Where, before the appeal hearing, the respondent decides not to oppose the appeal or not to attend the appeal hearing, the respondent must immediately serve notice of that decision on –

(a) the Comptroller; and

(b) the appellant.

(4) Where the respondent serves a notice in accordance with sub-paragraph (3), copies of the following documents must also be served on the Comptroller with that notice –

(a) the petition;

(b) any statements of claim;

(c) any written evidence filed in the claim.

(5) Within 14 days after receiving the notice in accordance with sub-paragraph (3), the Comptroller must serve on the appellant a notice stating an intention to attend the appeal hearing or otherwise.

(6) The Comptroller may attend the appeal hearing and oppose the appeal –

(a) in any case where notice has been given under paragraph (5) of the intention to attend; and

(b) in any other case (including, in particular, a case where the respondent withdraws his opposition to the appeal during the hearing) if the Court of Appeal so directs or permits.

Appeal from Proscribed Organisations Appeal Commission

15.1  The appellant’s notice must be filed at the Court of Appeal within 14 days after the date when the Proscribed Organisations Appeal Commission –

(a) granted; or

(b) where section 6(2)(b) of the Terrorism Act 2000 applies, refused permission to appeal.

Appeals in relation to serious crime prevention orders

16.1

(1) This paragraph applies to an appeal under section 23(1) of the Serious Crime Act 2007 or section 16 of the Senior Courts Act 1981 in relation to a serious crime prevention order and is made.

(2) The appellant must serve the appellant’s notice on any person who made representations in the proceedings by virtue of section 9(1), (2) or (3) of the Serious Crime Act 2007 in addition to the persons to be served under rule 52.4(3) and in accordance with that rule.

Appeal from Special Immigration Appeals Commission

17.1

(1) An application for permission to appeal to the Court of Appeal must first be made to the Special Immigration Appeals Commission pursuant section 7(2) of the Special Immigration Appeals Commission Act 1997 and paragraph 27 of the SIAC (Procedure) Rules 2003 (as amended).

(2) The appellant’s notice must be filed at the Court of Appeal within 21 days of the date on which the Special Immigration Appeals Commission’s decision granting or refusing permission to appeal to the Court of Appeal is given.

APPEALS TO THE HIGH COURT

Reference of question of law by Agricultural Land Tribunal

18.1

(1) A question of law referred to the High Court by an Agricultural Land Tribunal under section 6 of the Agriculture (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 1954 shall be referred by way of case stated by the Tribunal.

(2) Where the proceedings before the tribunal arose on an application under section 11 of the Agricultural Holdings Act 1986, an –

(a) application notice for an order under section 6 that the tribunal refers a question of law to the court; and

(b) appellant's notice by which an appellant seeks the court’s determination on a question of law,

must be served on the authority having power to enforce the statutory requirement specified in the notice in addition to every other party to those proceedings and on the secretary of the tribunal.

(3) Where, in accordance with sub-paragraph (2), a notice is served on the authority mentioned in that paragraph, that authority may attend the appeal hearing and make representations to the court.

Appeals against decisions affecting the registration of architects and health care professionals

19.1

(1) This paragraph applies to an appeal to the High Court under –

(a) section 22 of the Architects Act 1997;

(b) section 31 of the Chiropractors Act 1994;

(c) section 29 or section 44 of the Dentists Act 1984;

(d) article 38 of the Health Professions Order 2001;

(e) section 40 of the Medical Act 1983;

(f) section 82(3) and 83(2) of the Medicines Act 1968;

(g) section 12 of the Nurses, Midwives and Health Visitors Act 1997;

(h) article 38 of the Nursing and Midwifery Order 2001;

(i) section 23 of the Opticians Act 1989;

(j) section 31 of the Osteopaths Act 1993;

(k) section 10 of the Pharmacy Act 1954;

(l) article 58 of the Pharmacy Order 2010.

(2) Every appeal to which this paragraph applies must be supported by written evidence and, if the court so orders, oral evidence and will be by way of re-hearing.

(3) The appellant must file the appellant’s notice within 28 days after the decision that the appellant wishes to appeal.

(4) In the case of an appeal under an enactment specified in column 1 of the following table, the persons to be made respondents are the persons specified in relation to that enactment in column 2 of the table and the person to be served with the appellant's notice is the Registrar of the relevant Council.

Appeals under regulation 74 of the European Public Limited-Liability Company Regulations 2004

20.1

(1) In this paragraph –

(a) ‘the 2004 Regulations’ means the European Public Limited-Liability Company Regulations 2004;

(b) ‘the EC Regulation’means Council Regulation (EC) No 2157/2001 of 8 October 2001 on the Statute for a European company (SE);

(c) ‘SE’ means a European public limited-liability company (Societas Europaea) within the meaning of Article 1 of the EC Regulation.

(2) This paragraph applies to appeals under regulation 74 of the 2004 Regulations against the opposition–

(a) of the Secretary of State or national financial supervisory authority to the transfer of the registered office of an SE under Article 8(14) of the EC Regulation; and

(b) of the Secretary of State to the participation by a company in the formation of an SE by merger under Article 19 of the EC Regulation.

(3) Where an SE seeks to appeal against the opposition of the national financial supervisory authority to the transfer of its registered office under Article 8(14) of the EC Regulation, it must serve the appellant’s notice on both the national financial supervisory authority and the Secretary of State.

(4) The appellant’s notice must contain an application for permission to appeal.

(5) The appeal will be a review of the decision of the Secretary of State and not a re-hearing. The grounds of review are set out in regulation 74(2) of the 2004 Regulations.

(6) The appeal will be heard by a High Court judge.

Appeals under the Extradition Act 2003

21.1

(1) In this paragraph, ‘the Act’ means the Extradition Act 2003.

(2) Appeals to the High Court under the Act must be started in the Administrative Court of the Queen’s Bench Division at the Royal Courts of Justice in London.

(3) Where an appeal is brought under section 26 or 28 of the Act –

(a) the appellant’s notice must be filed and served before the expiry of 7 days, starting with the day on which the order is made;

(b) the appellant must endorse the appellant’s notice with the date of the person’s arrest;

(c) the High Court must begin to hear the substantive appeal within 40 days of the person's arrest; and

(d) the appellant must serve a copy of the appellant’s notice on the Crown Prosecution Service, if they are not a party to the appeal, in addition to the persons to be served under rule 52.4(3) and in accordance with that rule.

(4) The High Court may extend the period of 40 days under sub-paragraph (3)(c) if it believes it to be in the interests of justice to do so.

(5) Where an appeal is brought under section 103 of the Act, the appellant's notice must be filed and served before the expiry of 14 days, starting with the day on which the Secretary of State informs the person under section 100(1) or (4) of the Act that an order has made in respect of the person.

(6) Where an appeal is brought under section 105 of the Act, the appellant's notice must be filed and served before the expiry of 14 days, starting with the day on which the order for discharge is made.

(7) Where an appeal is brought under section 108 of the Act the appellant's notice must be filed and served before the expiry of 14 days, starting with the day on which the Secretary of State informs the person that an order for extradition has been made.

(8) Where an appeal is brought under section 110 of the Act the appellant's notice must be filed and served before the expiry of 14 days, starting with the day on which the Secretary of State informs the person acting on behalf of a category 2 territory, as defined in section 69 of the Act, of the order for discharge.

(Section 69 of the Act provides that a category 2 territory is that designated for the purposes of Part 2 of the Act.)

(9) Subject to sub-paragraph (10), where an appeal is brought under section 103, 105, 108 or 110 of the Act, the High Court must begin to hear the substantive appeal within 76 days of the appellant's notice being filed.

(10) Where an appeal is brought under section 103 of the Act before the Secretary of State has decided whether the person is to be extradited –

(a) the period of 76 days does not start until the day on which the Secretary of State informs the person of the decision; and

(b) the Secretary of State must, as soon as practicable after the person has been informed of the decision, inform the High Court –

(i) of the decision; and

(ii) of the date on which the person was informed of the decision.

(11) The High Court may extend the period of 76 days if it believes it to be in the interests of justice to do so.

(12) Where an appeal is brought under section 103, 105, 108 or 110 of the Act, the appellant must serve a copy of the appellant’s notice on –

(a) the Crown Prosecution Service; and

(b) the Home Office,

if they are not a party to the appeal, in addition to the persons to be served under rule 52.4(3) and in accordance with that rule.

Appeals affecting industrial and provident societies etc.

22.1

(1) This paragraph applies to all appeals under –

(a) the Friendly Societies Act 1974;

(b) the Friendly Societies Act 1992 and;

(c) the Industrial and Provident Societies Act 1965.

(2) At any stage on an appeal, the court may –

(a) direct that the appellant’s notice be served on any person;

(b) direct that notice be given by advertisement or otherwise of –

(i) the bringing of the appeal;

(ii) the nature of the appeal; and

(iii) the time when the appeal will or is likely to be heard; or

(c) give such other directions as it thinks proper to enable any person interested in –

(i) the society, trade union, alleged trade union or industrial assurance company; or

(ii) the subject matter of the appeal,

to appear and be heard at the appeal hearing.

Appeals under section 222 of the Inheritance Tax Act 1984 and regulation 8(3) of the Stamp Duty Reserve Tax Regulations 1986

23.1

(1) This paragraph applies to appeals to the High Court under section 222(3) of the Inheritance Tax Act 1984 (the ‘1984 Act’) and regulation 8(3) of the Stamp Duty Reserve Tax Regulations 1986 (the ‘1986 Regulations’).

(2) The appellant’s notice must –

(a) state the date on which the Commissioners for Her Majesty’s Revenue and Customs (the ‘Board’) gave notice to the appellant under section 221 of the 1984 Act or regulation 6 of the 1986 Regulations of the determination that is the subject of the appeal;

(b) state the date on which the appellant gave to the Board notice of appeal under section 222(1) of the 1984 Act or regulation 8(1) of the 1986 Regulations and, if notice was not given within the time permitted, whether Her Majesty’s Revenue and Customs (HMRC) have given their consent or the tribunal has given permission for notice to be given after the time permitted, and where applicable, the date of such consent or permission; and

(c) either state that the appellant and the Board have agreed that the appeal may be to the High Court or contain an application for permission to appeal to the High Court.

(3) The appellant must file the following documents with the appellant’s notice –

(a) 2 copies of the notice referred to in sub-paragraph 2(a);

(b) 2 copies of the notice of appeal (under section 222(1) of the 1984 Act or regulation 8(1) of the 1986 Regulations) referred to in paragraph 2(b); and

(c) where the appellant’s notice contains an application for permission to appeal, written evidence setting out the grounds on which it is alleged that the matters to be decided on the appeal are likely to be substantially confined to questions of law.

(4) The appellant must –

(a) file the appellant’s notice at the court; and

(b) serve the appellant's notice on the Board,

within 30 days of the date on which the appellant gave to the Board notice of appeal under section 222(1) of the 1984 Act or regulation 8(1) of the 1986 Regulations or, if HMRC have given consent or the tribunal has given permission for notice to be given after the time permitted, within 30 days of the date on which such consent or permission was given.

(5) The court will set a date for the hearing of not less than 40 days from the date that the appellant’s notice was filed.

(6) Where the appellant’s notice contains an application for permission to appeal –

(a) a copy of the written evidence filed in accordance with sub-paragraph (3)(c) must be served on the Board with the appellant’s notice; and

(b) the Board –

(i) may file written evidence; and

(ii) if it does so, must serve a copy of that evidence on the appellant, within 30 days after service of the written evidence under sub-paragraph (6)(a).

(7) The appellant may not rely on any grounds of appeal not specified in the notice referred to in sub-paragraph (2)(b) on the hearing of the appeal without the permission of the court.

Appeal against a decision of the adjudicator under section 111 of the Land Registration Act 2002

24.1

(1) A person who is aggrieved by a decision of the adjudicator and who wishes to appeal that decision must obtain permission to appeal.

(2) The appellant must serve on the adjudicator a copy of the appeal court's decision on a request for permission to appeal as soon as reasonably practicable and in any event within 14 days of receipt by the appellant of the decision on permission.

(3) The appellant must serve on the adjudicator and the Chief Land Registrar a copy of any order by the appeal court to stay a decision of the adjudicator pending the outcome of the appeal as soon as reasonably practicable and in any event within 14 days of receipt by the appellant of the appeal court's order to stay.

(4) The appellant must serve on the adjudicator and the Chief Land Registrar a copy of the appeal court's decision on the appeal as soon as reasonably practicable and in any event within 14 days of receipt by the appellant of the appeal court’s decision.

Appeals under the Merchant Shipping Act 1995

25.1

(1) his paragraph applies to appeals under the Merchant Shipping Act 1995 and for this purpose a re-hearing and an application under section 61 of the Merchant Shipping Act 1995 are treated as appeals.

(2) The appellant must file any report to the Secretary of State containing the decision from which the appeal is brought with the appellant’s notice.

(3) Where a re-hearing by the High Court is ordered under sections 64 or 269 of the Merchant Shipping Act 1995, the Secretary of State must give reasonable notice to the parties whom he considers to be affected by the re-hearing.

Appeals under s 289(6) of the Town and Country Planning Act 1990 and s 65(5) of the Planning (Listed Buildings and Conservation Areas) Act 1990 26.1

26.1

(1) An application for permission to appeal to the High Court under section 289 of the Town and Country Planning Act 1990 (‘the TCP Act’) or section 65 of the Planning (Listed Buildings and Conservation Areas) Act 1990 (‘the PLBCA Act’) must be made within 28 days after notice of the decision is given to the applicant.

(2) The application –

(a) must be in writing and must set out the reasons why permission should be granted; and

(b) if the time for applying has expired, must include an application to extend the time for applying, and must set out the reasons why the application was not made within that time.

(3) The applicant must, before filing the application, serve a copy of it on the persons referred to in sub-paragraph (12) with the draft appellant’s notice and a copy of the witness statement or affidavit to be filed with the application.

(4) The applicant must file the application in the Administrative Court Office with –

(a) a copy of the decision being appealed;

(b) a draft appellant’s notice;

(c) a witness statement or affidavit verifying any facts relied on; and

(d) a witness statement or affidavit giving the name and address of, and the place and date of service on, each person who has been served with the application. If any person who ought to be served has not been served, the witness statement or affidavit must state that fact and the reason why the person was not served.

(5) An application will be heard–

(a) by a single judge; and

(b) unless the court otherwise orders, not less than 21 days after it was filed at the Administrative Court Office.

(6) Practice direction 54D applies to applications and appeals under this paragraph.

(7) Any person served with the application is entitled to appear and be heard.

(8) Any respondent who intends to use a witness statement or affidavit at the hearing –

(a) must file it in the Administrative Court Office; and

(b) must serve a copy on the applicant as soon as is practicable and in any event, unless the court otherwise allows, at least 2 days before the hearing.

(9) The court may allow the applicant to use a further witness statement or affidavit.

(10) Where on the hearing of an application the court is of the opinion that a person who ought to have been served has not been served, the court may adjourn the hearing, on such terms as it directs, in order that the application may be served on that person.

(11) Where the court grants permission –

(a) it may impose terms as to costs and as to giving security;

(b) it may give directions; and

(c) the relevant appellant’s notice must be served and filed within 7 days of the grant.

(12) The persons to be served with the appellant’s notice are –

(a) the Secretary of State;

(b) the local planning authority who served the notice or gave the decision, as the case may be, or, where the appeal is brought by that authority, the appellant or applicant in the proceedings in which the decision appealed against was given;

(c) in the case of an appeal brought by virtue of section 289(1) of the TCP Act or section 65(1) of the PLBCA Act, any other person having an interest in the land to which the notice relates; and

(d) in the case of an appeal brought by virtue of section 289(2) of the TCP Act, any other person on whom the notice to which those proceedings related was served.

(13) The appeal will be heard and determined by a single judge unless the court directs that the matter be heard and determined by a Divisional Court.

(14) The court may remit the matter to the Secretary of State to the extent necessary to enable the Secretary of State to provide the court with such further information in connection with the matter as the court may direct.

(15) Where the court is of the opinion that the decision appealed against was erroneous in point of law, it will not set aside or vary that decision but will remit the matter to the Secretary of State for re-hearing and determination in accordance with the opinion of the court.

(16) The court may give directions as to the exercise, until an appeal brought by virtue of section 289(1) of the TCP Act is finally concluded and any re-hearing and determination by the Secretary of State has taken place, of the power to serve, and institute proceedings (including criminal proceedings) concerning –

(a) a stop notice under section 183 of that Act; and

(b) a breach of condition notice under section 187A of that Act.

Appeals from decisions of the Law Society or the Solicitors Disciplinary Tribunal to the High Court

27.1

(1) This paragraph applies to appeals from the Law Society or the Solicitors Disciplinary Tribunal (‘the Tribunal’) to the High Court under the Solicitors Act 1974, Administration of Justice Act 1985, the Courts and Legal Services Act 1990, the European Communities (Lawyer’s Practice) Regulations 2000 or the European Communities (Recognition of Professional Qualifications) Regulations 2007.

(2) The appellant must file the appellant’s notice in the Administrative Court.

(3) Unless the court otherwise orders the appellant must serve the appellant’s notice on –

(a) every party to the proceedings before the Tribunal; and

(b) the Law Society.

Appeals from decisions of the Bar Standards Board or Disciplinary Tribunals to the High Court

27.1A

(1) This paragraph applies to appeals from decisions of the Bar Standards Board on review under the bar Training Rules or of Disciplinary Tribunals of the Council of the Inns of Court to the High Court under Section 24 of the Crime and Courts Act 2013.

(2) The appellant must file the appellant’s notice in the Administrative Court.

(3) Unless the court otherwise orders, the appellant must serve the appellant’s notice on—

(a) every party to the proceedings before the Bar Standards Board or the Disciplinary Tribunal as appropriate; and

(b) the Council of the Inns of Court in the case of appeals from decisions of the Disciplinary Tribunal.

APPEALS TO THE COUNTY COURT

Appeals under sections 204 and 204A of the Housing Act 1996

28.1

(1) An appellant should include appeals under section 204 and section 204A of the Housing Act 1996 in one appellant’s notice.

(2) If it is not possible to do so (for example because an urgent application under section 204A is required) the appeals may be included in separate appellant’s notices.

(3) An appeal under section 204A may include an application for an order under section 204A(4)(a) requiring the authority to secure that accommodation is available for the applicant’s occupation.

(4) If, exceptionally, the court makes an order under section 204A(4)(a) without notice, the appellant’s notice must be served on the authority together with the order. Such an order will normally require the authority to secure that accommodation is available until a hearing date when the authority can make representations as to whether the order under section 204A(4)(a) should be continued.

(5) Unless the court orders otherwise –

(a) the appellant shall file and serve its proposed case management directions for the appeal together with the appellant’s notice;

(b) the respondent shall within 14 days thereafter either agree those directions or file and serve alternative proposed directions;

(c) within 14 days after service of the appellant’s notice the respondent must disclose any documents relevant to the decision under appeal, in so far as not previously disclosed;

(d) within 14 days after receipt of any documents disclosed under sub-paragraph (c) the appellant may make any amendments to its grounds of appeal which arise out of those documents.

Appeal under Part II of the Immigration and Asylum Act 1999 (carriers’ liability)

29.1

(1) A person appealing to a county court under section 35A or section 40B of the Immigration and Asylum Act 1999 (‘the Act’) against a decision by the Secretary of State to impose a penalty under section 32 or a charge under section 40 of the Act must, subject to sub-paragraph (2), file the appellant's notice within 28 days after receiving the penalty notice or charge notice.

(2) Where the appellant has given notice of objection to the Secretary of State under section 35(4) or section 40A(3) of the Act within the time prescribed for doing so, the appellant must file the appellant’s notice within 28 days after receiving notice of the Secretary of State’s decision in response to the notice of objection.

(3) Sections 35A and 40B of the Act provide that any appeal under those sections shall be a re-hearing of the Secretary of State’s decision to impose a penalty or charge, and therefore rule 52.11(1) does not apply.

Local Government (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 1976

30.1  Where one of the grounds upon which an appeal against a notice under sections 21, 23 or 35 of the Local Government (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 1976 is brought is that –

(a) it would have been fairer to serve the notice on another person; or

(b) that it would be reasonable for the whole or part of the expenses to which the appeal relates to be paid by some other person,

that person must be made a respondent to the appeal, unless the court, on application of the appellant made without notice, otherwise directs.

Representation of the People Act 1983 – appeals against decisions of registration officers

31.1

(1) This paragraph applies in relation to an appeal against a decision of a registration officer, being a decision referred to in section 56(1) of the Representation of the People Act 1983 (‘the Act’).

(2) Where a person (‘the appellant’) has given notice of such an appeal in accordance with the relevant requirements of section 56, and of the regulations made under section 53 (‘the Regulations’), of the Act, the registration officer must, within 7 days after the appellant receives the notice, forward –

(a) the notice; and

(b) the statement required by the Regulations,

by post to the county court.

(3) The respondents to the appeal will be –

(a) the registration officer; and

(b) if the decision of the registration officer was given in favour of any other person than the appellant, that other person.

(4) On the hearing of the appeal–

(a) the statement forwarded to the court by the registration officer, and any document containing information submitted to the court by the registration officer pursuant to the Regulations, are admissible as evidence of the facts stated in them; and

(b) the court –

(i) may draw any inference of fact that the registration officer might have drawn; and

(ii) may give any decision and make any order that the registration officer ought to have given or made.

(5) A respondent to an appeal (other than the registration officer) is not liable for nor entitled to costs, unless he appears before the court in support of the registration officer’s decision.

(6) Rule 52.4 (appellant’s notice) does not apply to an appeal to which this paragraph applies.

Representation of the People Act 1983 – special provision in relation to anonymous entries in the register

31.2

(1) In this paragraph –

(a) ‘anonymous entry’has the meaning given by section 9B(4) of the Representation of the People Act 1983;

(b) ‘appeal notice’means the notice required by regulation 32 of the Representation of the People (England and Wales) Regulations 2001.

(2) This paragraph applies to an appeal to a county court to which paragraph 31.1 (Representation of the People Act 1983 – appeals against decisions of registration officers) applies if a party to the appeal is a person –

(a) whose entry in the register is an anonymous entry; or

(b) who has applied for such an entry.

(3) This paragraph also applies to an appeal to the Court of Appeal from a decision of a county court in an appeal to which paragraph 31.1 applies.

(4) The appellant may indicate in the appeal notice that an application for an anonymous entry has been applied for, or that the entry in the register is an anonymous entry.

(5) The respondent or any other person who applies to become a party to the proceedings may indicate in a respondent's notice or an application to join the proceedings that the entry in the register is an anonymous entry, or that an application has been made for an anonymous entry.

(6) Where the appellant gives such an indication in the appeal notice, the court will refer the matter to a district judge for directions about the further conduct of the proceedings, and, in particular, directions about how the matter should be listed in the court list.

(7) Where the court otherwise becomes aware that a party to the appeal is a person referred to in sub-paragraph (2), the court will give notice to the parties that no further step is to be taken until the court has given any necessary directions for the further conduct of the matter.

Representation of the People Act 1983 - appeals selected as test cases

31.3

(1) Where two or more appeals to which paragraph 31.1 (Representation of the People Act 1983 – appeals against decisions of registration officers) applies involve the same point of law, the court may direct that one appeal (‘the test-case appeal’) is to be heard first as a test case.

(2) The court will send a notice of the direction to each party to all of those appeals.

(3) Where a notice under sub-paragraph (2) is served on any party to an appeal (other than the test-case appeal), that party may (within 7 days after the notice is served on that party) give notice to the court requesting the appeal to be heard and–

(a) the court will hear that appeal after the test-case appeal is disposed of;

(b) the court will give the parties to that appeal notice of the day on which it will be heard; and

(c) the party who gave the notice is not entitled to receive any costs of the separate hearing of that appeal unless the judge otherwise orders.

(4) Where no notice is given under sub-paragraph (3) within the period limited by that paragraph –

(a) the decision on the test-case appeal binds the parties to each of the other appeals;

(b) without further hearing, the court will make, in each other appeal, an order similar to the order in the test-case appeal; and

(c) the party to each other appeal who is in the same interest as the unsuccessful party to the selected appeal is liable for the costs of the test-case appeal in the same manner and to the same extent as the unsuccessful party to that appeal and an order directing the party to pay such costs may be made and enforced accordingly.

(5) Sub-paragraph (4)(a) does not affect the right to appeal to the Court of Appeal of any party to an appeal other than the test-case appeal.

Appeals under section 11 of the UK Borders Act 2007

32.1

(1) A person appealing to a county court under section 11 of the UK Borders Act 2007 (‘the Act’) against a decision by the Secretary of State to impose a penalty under section 9(1) of the Act, must, subject to sub-paragraph (2), file the appellant’s notice within 28 days after receiving the penalty notice.

(2) Where the appellant has given notice of objection to the Secretary of State under section 10 of the Act within the time prescribed for doing so, the appellant’s notice must be filed within 28 days after receiving notice of the Secretary of State’s decision in response to the notice of objection.

PRACTICE DIRECTION 53 - DEFAMATION CLAIMS

This practice direction supplements Part 53

Contents of this Practice Direction

Title | Number
General |

Statements of case
Court’s powers in connection with an offer of amends |

Ruling on meaning |

SUMMARY DISPOSAL | Para. 5.1
Statements in open court |

General

1  This practice direction applies to defamation claims.

Statements of case

2.1  Statements of case should be confined to the information necessary to inform the other party of the nature of the case he has to meet. Such information should be set out concisely and in a manner proportionate to the subject matter of the claim.

2.2

(1) In a claim for libel the publication the subject of the claim must be identified in the claim form.

(2) In a claim for slander the claim form must so far as possible contain the words complained of, and identify the person to whom they were spoken and when.

2.3

(1) The claimant must specify in the particulars of claim the defamatory meaning which he alleges that the words or matters complained of conveyed, both

(a) as to their natural and ordinary meaning; and

(b) as to any innuendo meaning (that is a meaning alleged to be conveyed to some person by reason of knowing facts extraneous to the words complained of).

(2) In the case of an innuendo meaning, the claimant must also identify the relevant extraneous facts.

2.4  In a claim for slander the precise words used and the names of the persons to whom they were spoken and when must, so far as possible, be set out in the particulars of claim, if not already contained in the claim form.

2.5  Where a defendant alleges that the words complained of are true he must –

(1) specify the defamatory meanings he seeks to justify; and

(2) give details of the matters on which he relies in support of that allegation.

2.6  Where a defendant alleges that the words complained of are honest opinion he must –

(1) specify the defamatory meaning he seeks to defend as honest opinion; and

(2) give details of the matters on which he relies in support of that allegation.

2.7  Where a defendant alleges that the words complained of were published on a privileged occasion he must specify the circumstances he relies on in support of that contention.

2.8  Where a defendant alleges that the words complained of are true, or are honest opinion, the claimant must serve a reply specifically admitting or denying the allegation and giving the facts on which he relies.

2.9  If the defendant contends that any of the words or matters are honest opinion, or were published on a privileged occasion, and the claimant intends to allege that the defendant acted with malice, the claimant must serve a reply giving details of the facts or matters relied on.

2.10

(1) A claimant must give full details of the facts and matters on which he relies in support of his claim for damages.

(2) Where a claimant seeks aggravated or exemplary damages he must provide the information specified in rule 16.4(1)(c).

2.11  A defendant who relies on an offer to make amends under section 2 of the Defamation Act 1996, as his defence must –

(1) state in his defence –

(a) that he is relying on the offer in accordance with section 4 (2) of the Defamation Act 1996; and

(b) that it has not been withdrawn by him or been accepted, and

(2) attach a copy of the offer he made with his defence.

Court’s powers in connection with an offer of amends

3.1  Sections 2 to 4 of the Defamation Act 1996 make provision for a person who has made a statement which is alleged to be defamatory to make an offer to make amends. Section 3 provides for the court to assist in the process of making amends.

3.2  A claim under section 3 of the Defamation Act 1996 made other than in existing proceedings may be made under CPR Part 8 –

(1) where the parties agree on the steps to make amends, and the sole purpose of the claim is for the court to make an order under section 3(3) for an order that the offer be fulfilled; or

(2) where the parties do not agree –

(a) on the steps to be taken by way of correction, apology and publication (see section 3(4));

(b) on the amount to be paid by way of compensation (see section 3(5)); or

(c) on the amount to be paid by way of costs (see section 3(6)).

(Applications in existing proceedings made under section 3 of the Defamation Act 1996 must be made in accordance with CPR Part 23)

3.3

(1) A claim or application under section 3 of the Defamation Act 1996 must be supported by written evidence.

(2) The evidence referred to in paragraph (1) must include –

(a) a copy of the offer of amends;

(b) details of the steps taken to fulfil the offer of amends;

(c) a copy of the text of any correction and apology;

(d) details of the publication of the correction and apology;

(e) a statement of the amount of any sum paid as compensation;

(f) a statement of the amount of any sum paid for costs;

(g) why the offer is unsatisfactory.

(3) Where any step specified in section 2(4) of the Defamation Act 1996 has not been taken, then the evidence referred to in paragraph (2)(c) to (f) must state what steps are proposed by the party to fulfil the offer of amends and the date or dates on which each step will be fulfilled and, if none, that no proposal has been made to take that step.

Ruling on meaning

4.1  At any time the court may decide –

(1) whether a statement complained of is capable of having any meaning attributed to it in a statement of case;

(2) whether the statement is capable of being defamatory of the claimant;

(3) whether the statement is capable of bearing any other meaning defamatory of the claimant.

4.2  An application for a ruling on meaning may be made at any time after the service of particulars of claim. Such an application should be made promptly.

(This provision disapplies for these applications the usual time restriction on making applications in rule 24.4.1).

4.3  Where an application is made for a ruling on meaning, the application notice must state that it is an application for a ruling on meaning made in accordance with this practice direction.

4.4  The application notice or the evidence contained or referred to in it, or served with it, must identify precisely the statement, and the meaning attributed to it, that the court is being asked to consider.

(Rule 3.3 applies where the court exercises its powers on its own initiative)

(Following a ruling on meaning the court may exercise its power under rule 3.4)

(Section 7 of the Defamation Act 1996 applies to rulings on meaning)

SUMMARY DISPOSAL

5.1  Where an application is made for summary disposal, the application notice must state –

(1) that it is an application for summary disposal made in accordance with section 8 of the Defamation Act 1996.

(2) the matters set out in paragraph 2(3) of Practice Direction 24; and

(3) whether or not the defendant has made an offer to make amends under section 2 of the Act and whether or not it has been withdrawn.

5.2  An application for summary disposal may be made at any time after the service of particulars of claim.

(This provision disapplies for these applications the usual time restriction on making applications in rule 24.4.1).

5.3

(1) This paragraph applies where –

(a) the court has ordered the defendant in defamation proceedings to agree and publish a correction and apology as summary relief under section 8(2) of the Defamation Act 1996; and

(b) the parties are unable to agree its content within the time specified in the order.

(2) Where the court grants this type of summary relief under the Act, the order will specify the date by which the parties should reach agreement about the content, time, manner, form and place of publication of the correction and apology.

(3) Where the parties cannot agree the content of the correction and apology by the date specified in the order, then the claimant must prepare a summary of the judgment given by the court and serve it on all the other parties within 3 days following the date specified in the order.

(4) Where the parties cannot agree the summary of the judgment prepared by the claimant they must within 3 days of receiving the summary –

(a) file with the court and serve on all the other parties a copy of the summary showing the revisions they wish to make to it; and

(b) apply to the court for the court to settle the summary.

(5) The court will then itself settle the summary and the judge who delivered the judgment being summarised will normally do this.

Statements in open court

6.1  This paragraph only applies where a party wishes to accept a Part 36 offer or other offer of settlement in relation to a claim for –

(1) libel;

(2) slander;

(3) malicious falsehood;

(4) misuse of private or confidential information.

6.2  A party may apply for permission to make a statement in open court before or after he accepts the Part 36 offer in accordance with rule 36.9(1) or other offer to settle the claim.

6.3  The statement that the applicant wishes to make must be submitted for the approval of the court and must accompany the notice of application.

6.4  The court may postpone the time for making the statement if other claims relating to the subject matter of the statement are still proceeding.

(Applications must be made in accordance with Part 23)

PART 54 - JUDICIAL REVIEW AND STATUTORY REVIEW

Contents of this Part

Title
| Number
I JUDICIAL REVIEW
|

Scope and interpretation | Rule 54.1
Who may exercise the powers of the High Court | Rule 54.1A
When this Section must be used | Rule 54.2
When this Section may be used | Rule 54.3
Permission required | Rule 54.4
Time limit for filing claim form | Rule 54.5
Claim form | Rule 54.6
Service of claim form | Rule 54.7
Judicial review of decisions of the Upper Tribunal | Rule 54.7A
Acknowledgment of service | Rule 54.8
Failure to file acknowledgment of service | Rule 54.9
Permission given | Rule 54.10
Service of order giving or refusing permission | Rule 54.11
Permission decision without a hearing | Rule 54.12
Defendant etc. may not apply to set aside | Rule 54.13
Response | Rule 54.14
Where claimant seeks to rely on additional grounds | Rule 54.15
Evidence | Rule 54.16
Court's powers to hear any person | Rule 54.17
Judicial review may be decided without a hearing | Rule 54.18
Court's powers in respect of quashing orders | Rule 54.19
Transfer Rule | Rule 54.20

I JUDICIAL REVIEW

Scope and interpretation

54.1

(1) This Section of this Part contains rules about judicial review.

(2) In this Section –

(a) a ‘claim for judicial review’ means a claim to review the lawfulness of –

(i) an enactment; or

(ii) a decision, action or failure to act in relation to the exercise of a public function.

(b) revoked

(c) revoked

(d) revoked

(e) ‘the judicial review procedure’ means the Part 8 procedure as modified by this Section;

(f) ‘interested party’ means any person (other than the claimant and defendant) who is directly affected by the claim; and

(g) ‘court’ means the High Court, unless otherwise stated.

(Rule 8.1(6)(b) provides that a rule or practice direction may, in relation to a specified type of proceedings, disapply or modify any of the rules set out in Part 8 as they apply to those proceedings)

Who may exercise the powers of the High Court

54.1A

(1) A court officer assigned to the Administrative Court office who is –

(a) a barrister; or

(b) a solicitor,

may exercise the jurisdiction of the High Court with regard to the matters set out in paragraph (2) with the consent of the President of the Queen's Bench Division.

(2) The matters referred to in paragraph (1) are –

(a) any matter incidental to any proceedings in the High Court;

(b) any other matter where there is no substantial dispute between the parties; and

(c) the dismissal of an appeal or application where a party has failed to comply with any order, rule or practice direction.

(3) A court officer may not decide an application for –

(a) permission to bring judicial review proceedings;

(b) an injunction;

(c) a stay of any proceedings, other than a temporary stay of any order or decision of the lower court over a period when the High Court is not sitting or cannot conveniently be convened, unless the parties seek a stay by consent.

(4) Decisions of a court officer may be made without a hearing.

(5) A party may request any decision of a court officer to be reviewed by a judge of the High Court.

(6) At the request of a party, a hearing will be held to reconsider a decision of a court officer, made without a hearing.

(7) A request under paragraph (5) or (6) must be filed within 7 days after the party is served with notice of the decision.

When this Section must be used

54.2

The judicial review procedure must be used in a claim for judicial review where the claimant is seeking –

(a) a mandatory order;

(b) a prohibiting order;

(c) a quashing order; or

(d) an injunction under section 30 of the Supreme Court Act 1981^1 (restraining a person from acting in any office in which he is not entitled to act).

When this Section may be used

54.3

(1) The judicial review procedure may be used in a claim for judicial review where the claimant is seeking –

(a) a declaration; or

(b) an injunction(GL).

(Section 31(2) of the Supreme Court Act 1981 sets out the circumstances in which the court may grant a declaration or injunction in a claim for judicial review)

(Where the claimant is seeking a declaration or injunction in addition to one of the remedies listed in rule 54.2, the judicial review procedure must be used)

(2) A claim for judicial review may include a claim for damages, restitution or the recovery of a sum due but may not seek such a remedy alone.

(Section 31(4) of the Supreme Court Act sets out the circumstances in which the court may award damages, restitution or the recovery of a sum due on a claim for judicial review)

Permission required

54.4

The court’s permission to proceed is required in a claim for judicial review whether started under this Section or transferred to the Administrative Court.

Time limit for filing claim form

54.5

(A1) In this rule —

'the planning acts' has the same meaning as in section 336 of the Town and Country Planning Act 19902;

'decision governed by the Public Contracts Regulations 20063' means any decision the legality of which is or may be affected by a duty owed to an economic operator by virtue of regulation 47A of those Regulations (and for this purpose it does not matter that the claimant is not an economic operator); and

'economic operator' has the same meaning as in regulation 4 of the Public Contracts Regulations 2006.

(1) The claim form must be filed –

(a) promptly; and

(b) in any event not later than 3 months after the grounds to make the claim first arose.

(2) The time limits in this rule may not be extended by agreement between the parties.

(3) This rule does not apply when any other enactment specifies a shorter time limit for making the claim for judicial review.

(4) Paragraph (1) does not apply in the cases specified in paragraphs (5) and (6).

(5) Where the application for judicial review relates to a decision made by the Secretary of State or local planning authority under the planning acts, the claim form must be filed not later than six weeks after the grounds to make the claim first arose.

(6) Where the application for judicial review relates to a decision governed by the Public Contracts Regulations 2006, the claim form must be filed within the time within which an economic operator would have been required by regulation 47D(2) of those Regulations (and disregarding the rest of that regulation) to start any proceedings under those Regulations in respect of that decision.

Claim form

54.6

(1) In addition to the matters set out in rule 8.2 (contents of the claim form) the claimant must also state –

(a) the name and address of any person he considers to be an interested party;

(b) that he is requesting permission to proceed with a claim for judicial review; and

(c) any remedy (including any interim remedy) he is claiming; and

(d) where appropriate, the grounds on which it is contended that the claim is an Aarhus Convention claim.

(Rules 45.41 to 45.44 make provision about costs in Aarhus Convention claims.)

(Part 25 sets out how to apply for an interim remedy)

(2) The claim form must be accompanied by the documents required by Practice Direction 54A.

Service of claim form

54.7

The claim form must be served on –

(a) the defendant; and

(b) unless the court otherwise directs, any person the claimant considers to be an interested party,

within 7 days after the date of issue.

Judicial review of decisions of the Upper Tribunal

54.7A

(1) This rule applies where an application is made, following refusal by the Upper Tribunal of permission to appeal against a decision of the First Tier Tribunal, for judicial review –

(a) of the decision of the Upper Tribunal refusing permission to appeal; or

(b) which relates to the decision of the First Tier Tribunal which was the subject of the application for permission to appeal.

(2) Where this rule applies –

(a) the application may not include any other claim, whether against the Upper Tribunal or not; and

(b) any such other claim must be the subject of a separate application.

(3) The claim form and the supporting documents required by paragraph (4) must be filed no later than 16 days after the date on which notice of the Upper Tribunal's decision was sent to the applicant.

(4) The supporting documents are –

(a) the decision of the Upper Tribunal to which the application relates, and any document giving reasons for the decision;

(b) the grounds of appeal to the Upper Tribunal and any documents which were sent with them;

(c) the decision of the First Tier Tribunal, the application to that Tribunal for permission to appeal and its reasons for refusing permission; and

(d) any other documents essential to the claim.

(5) The claim form and supporting documents must be served on the Upper Tribunal and any other interested party no later than 7 days after the date of issue.

(6) The Upper Tribunal and any person served with the claim form who wishes to take part in the proceedings for judicial review must, no later than 21 days after service of the claim form, file and serve on the applicant and any other party an acknowledgment of service in the relevant practice form.

(7) The court will give permission to proceed only if it considers –

(a) that there is an arguable case, which has a reasonable prospect of success, that both the decision of the Upper Tribunal refusing permission to appeal and the decision of the First Tier Tribunal against which permission to appeal was sought are wrong in law; and

(b) that either –

(i) the claim raises an important point of principle or practice; or

(ii) there is some other compelling reason to hear it.

(8) If the application for permission is refused on paper without an oral hearing, rule 54.12(3) (request for reconsideration at a hearing) does not apply.

(9) If permission to apply for judicial review is granted –

(a) if the Upper Tribunal or any interested party wishes there to be a hearing of the substantive application, it must make its request for such a hearing no later than 14 days after service of the order granting permission; and

(b) if no request for a hearing is made within that period, the court will make a final order quashing the refusal of permission without a further hearing.

(10) The power to make a final order under paragraph (9)(b) may be exercised by the Master of the Crown Office or a Master of the Administrative Court.

Acknowledgment of service

54.8

(1) Any person served with the claim form who wishes to take part in the judicial review must file an acknowledgment of service in the relevant practice form in accordance with the following provisions of this rule.

(2) Any acknowledgment of service must be –

(a) filed not more than 21 days after service of the claim form; and

(b) served on –

(i) the claimant; and

(ii) subject to any direction under rule 54.7(b), any other person named in the claim form,

as soon as practicable and, in any event, not later than 7 days after it is filed.

(3) The time limits under this rule may not be extended by agreement between the parties.

(4) The acknowledgment of service –

(a) must –

(i) where the person filing it intends to contest the claim, set out a summary of his grounds for doing so; and

(ii) state the name and address of any person the person filing it considers to be an interested party; and

(b) may include or be accompanied by an application for directions.

(5) Rule 10.3(2) does not apply.

Failure to file acknowledgment of service

54.9

(1) Where a person served with the claim form has failed to file an acknowledgment of service in accordance with rule 54.8, he –

(a) may not take part in a hearing to decide whether permission should be given unless the court allows him to do so; but

(b) provided he complies with rule 54.14 or any other direction of the court regarding the filing and service of –

(i) detailed grounds for contesting the claim or supporting it on additional grounds; and

(ii) any written evidence,

may take part in the hearing of the judicial review.

(2) Where that person takes part in the hearing of the judicial review, the court may take his failure to file an acknowledgment of service into account when deciding what order to make about costs.

(3) Rule 8.4 does not apply.

Permission given

54.10

(1) Where permission to proceed is given the court may also give directions.

(2) Directions under paragraph (1) may include –

(a) a stay(GL) of proceedings to which the claim relates;

(b) directions requiring the proceedings to be heard by a Divisional Court.

Service of order giving or refusing permission

54.11

The court will serve –

(a) the order giving or refusing permission; and

(b) any directions,

on –

(i) the claimant;

(ii) the defendant; and

(iii) any other person who filed an acknowledgment of service.

Permission decision without a hearing

54.12

(1) This rule applies where the court, without a hearing –

(a) refuses permission to proceed; or

(b) gives permission to proceed –

(i) subject to conditions; or

(ii) on certain grounds only.

(2) The court will serve its reasons for making the decision when it serves the order giving or refusing permission in accordance with rule 54.11.

(3) Subject to paragraph (7), the claimant may not appeal but may request the decision to be reconsidered at a hearing.

(4) A request under paragraph (3) must be filed within 7 days after service of the reasons under paragraph (2).

(5) The claimant, defendant and any other person who has filed an acknowledgment of service will be given at least 2 days’ notice of the hearing date.

(6) The court may give directions requiring the proceedings to be heard by a Divisional Court.

(7) Where the court refuses permission to proceed and records the fact that the application is totally without merit in accordance with rule 23.12, the claimant may not request that decision to be reconsidered at a hearing.

Defendant etc. may not apply to set aside(GL)

54.13

Neither the defendant nor any other person served with the claim form may apply to set aside(GL) an order giving permission to proceed.

Response

54.14

(1) A defendant and any other person served with the claim form who wishes to contest the claim or support it on additional grounds must file and serve –

(a) detailed grounds for contesting the claim or supporting it on additional grounds; and

(b) any written evidence,

within 35 days after service of the order giving permission.

(2) The following rules do not apply –

(a) rule 8.5 (3) and 8.5 (4)(defendant to file and serve written evidence at the same time as acknowledgment of service); and

(b) rule 8.5 (5) and 8.5(6) (claimant to file and serve any reply within 14 days).

Where claimant seeks to rely on additional grounds

54.15

The court’s permission is required if a claimant seeks to rely on grounds other than those for which he has been given permission to proceed.

Evidence

54.16

(1) Rule 8.6 (1) does not apply.

(2) No written evidence may be relied on unless –

(a) it has been served in accordance with any –

(i) rule under this Section; or

(ii) direction of the court; or

(b) the court gives permission.

Court's powers to hear any person

54.17

(1) Any person may apply for permission –

(a) to file evidence; or

(b) make representations at the hearing of the judicial review.

(2) An application under paragraph (1) should be made promptly.

Judicial review may be decided without a hearing

54.18

The court may decide the claim for judicial review without a hearing where all the parties agree.

Court's powers in respect of quashing orders

54.19

(1) This rule applies where the court makes a quashing order in respect of the decision to which the claim relates.

(2) The court may –

(a)

(i) remit the matter to the decision-maker; and

(ii) direct it to reconsider the matter and reach a decision in accordance with the judgment of the court; or

(b) in so far as any enactment permits, substitute its own decision for the decision to which the claim relates.

(Section 31 of the Supreme Court Act 1981^4 enables the High Court, subject to certain conditions, to substitute its own decision for the decision in question.)

Transfer

54.20

The court may

(a) order a claim to continue as if it had not been started under this Section; and

(b) where it does so, give directions about the future management of the claim.

(Part 30 (transfer) applies to transfers to and from the Administrative Court)

Footnotes

1981 c.54. Back to text
1990 c. 8. Back to text
S.I. 2006/5, as amended in particular by S.I. 2009/2992 and S.I. 2011/2053. Back to text

1981 c.54. Section 31 is amended by section 141 of the Tribunals, Courts and Enforcement Act 2007 (c. 15). Back to text

PRACTICE DIRECTION 54D – ADMINISTRATIVE COURT (VENUE)

This Practice Direction supplements Part 54

Contents of this Practice Direction

Title
Scope and purpose
Venue – general provisions
Excepted classes of claim
Urgent applications
Assignment to another venue

Scope and purpose

1.1

This Practice Direction concerns the place in which a claim before the Administrative Court should be started and administered and the venue at which it will be determined.

1.2

This Practice Direction is intended to facilitate access to justice by enabling cases to be administered and determined in the most appropriate location. To achieve this purpose it provides flexibility in relation to where claims are to be administered and enables claims to be transferred to different venues.

Venue – general provisions

2.1

The claim form in proceedings in the Administrative Court may be issued at the Administrative Court Office of the High Court at –

(1) the Royal Courts of Justice in London; or

(2) at the District Registry of the High Court at Birmingham, Cardiff, Leeds, or Manchester unless the claim is one of the excepted classes of claim set out in paragraph 3 of this Practice Direction which may only be started and determined at the Royal Courts of Justice in London.

2.2

Any claim started in Birmingham will normally be determined at a court in the Midland region (geographically covering the area of the Midland Circuit); in Cardiff in Wales; in Leeds in the North-Eastern Region (geographically covering the area of the North Eastern Circuit); in London at the Royal Courts of Justice; and in Manchester, in the North-Western Region (geographically covering the Northern Circuit).

Excepted classes of claim

3.1

The excepted classes of claim referred to in paragraph 2.1(2) are –

(1) proceedings to which Part 76 or Part 79 applies, and for the avoidance of doubt –

(a) proceedings relating to control orders (within the meaning of Part 76);

(b) financial restrictions proceedings (within the meaning of Part 79);

(c) proceedings relating to terrorism or alleged terrorists (where that is a relevant feature of the claim); and

(d) proceedings in which a special advocate is or is to be instructed;

(2) proceedings to which RSC Order 115 applies;

(3) proceedings under the Proceeds of Crime Act 2002;

(4) appeals to the Administrative Court under the Extradition Act 2003;

(5) proceedings which must be heard by a Divisional Court; and

(6) proceedings relating to the discipline of solicitors.

3.2

If a claim form is issued at an Administrative Court office other than in London and includes one of the excepted classes of claim, the proceedings will be transferred to London.

Urgent applications

4.1

During the hours when the court is open, where an urgent application needs to be made to the Administrative Court outside London, the application must be made to the judge designated to deal with such applications in the relevant District Registry.

4.2

Any urgent application to the Administrative Court during the hours when the court is closed, must be made to the duty out of hours High Court judge by telephoning 020 7947 6000.

Assignment to another venue

5.1

The proceedings may be transferred from the office at which the claim form was issued to another office. Such transfer is a judicial act.

5.2

The general expectation is that proceedings will be administered and determined in the region with which the claimant has the closest connection, subject to the following considerations as applicable –

(1) any reason expressed by any party for preferring a particular venue;

(2) the region in which the defendant, or any relevant office or department of the defendant, is based;

(3) the region in which the claimant’s legal representatives are based;

(4) the ease and cost of travel to a hearing;

(5) the availability and suitability of alternative means of attending a hearing (for example, by videolink);

(6) the extent and nature of media interest in the proceedings in any particular locality;

(7) the time within which it is appropriate for the proceedings to be determined;

(8) whether it is desirable to administer or determine the claim in another region in the light of the volume of claims issued at, and the capacity, resources and workload of, the court at which it is issued;

(9) whether the claim raises issues sufficiently similar to those in another outstanding claim to make it desirable that it should be determined together with, or immediately following, that other claim; and

(10) whether the claim raises devolution issues and for that reason whether it should more appropriately be determined in London or Cardiff.

5.3

(1) When an urgent application is made under paragraph 4.1 or 4.2, this will not by itself decide the venue for the further administration or determination of the claim.

(2) The court dealing with the urgent application may direct that the case be assigned to a particular venue.

(3) When an urgent application is made under paragraph 4.2, and the court does not make a direction under sub-paragraph (2), the claim will be assigned in the first place to London but may be reassigned to another venue at a later date.

5.4

The court may on an application by a party or of its own initiative direct that the claim be determined in a region other than that of the venue in which the claim is currently assigned. The considerations in paragraph 5.2 apply.

5.5

Once assigned to a venue, the proceedings will be both administered from that venue and determined by a judge of the Administrative Court at a suitable court within that region, or, if the venue is in London, at the Royal Courts of Justice. The choice of which court (of those within the region which are identified by the Presiding Judge of the circuit suitable for such hearing) will be decided, subject to availability, by the considerations in paragraph 5.2.

5.6

When giving directions under rule 54.10, the court may direct that proceedings be reassigned to another region for hearing (applying the considerations in paragraph 5.2). If no such direction is given, the claim will be heard in the same region as that in which the permission application was determined (whether on paper or at a hearing).

PRACTICE DIRECTION 57 – PROBATE

This Practice Direction supplements Part 57

Contents of this Practice Direction

Title | Number
I   PROBATE CLAIMS |
General | Para. 1.1
How to start a probate claim | Para. 2.1
Testamentary documents and evidence about testamentary documents | Para. 3.1
Case management | Para. 4
Summary judgment | Para. 5.1
Settlement of a probate claim | Para. 6.1
Application for an order to bring in a will, etc. | Para. 7.1
Administration pending the determination of a probate claim | Para. 8.1
II   RECTIFICATION OF WILLS |
Scope of this Section | Para. 9.
Lodging the grant | Para. 10.1
Orders | Para. 11.
III   SUBSTITUTION AND REMOVAL OF PERSONAL REPRESENTATIVES |
Scope of this Section | Para. 12.
Starting the claim | Para. 13.1
Production of the grant | Para. 14.1
IV   CLAIMS UNDER THE INHERITANCE (PROVISION FOR FAMILY AND DEPENDANTS) ACT 1975 |
Acknowledgment of service by personal representative – rule 57.16(4) | Para. 15.
Written evidence of personal representative – rule 57.16(5) | Para. 16.
Separate representation of claimants | Para. 17.
Production of the grant | Para. 18.1
ANNEX |

I   PROBATE CLAIMS

General

1.1

This Section of this practice direction applies to contentious probate claims.

1.2

The rules and procedure relating to non-contentious probate proceedings (also known as ‘common form’) are the Non-Contentious Probate Rules 1987 as amended.

How to start a probate claim

2.1

A claim form and all subsequent court documents relating to a probate claim must be marked at the top ‘In the estate of [name] deceased (Probate)’.

2.2

The claim form must be issued out of –

(1) Chancery Chambers at the Royal Courts of Justice; or

(2) one of the Chancery district registries; or

(3) if the claim is suitable to be heard in the county court –

(a) a county court in a place where there is also a Chancery district registry; or

(b) the Central London County Court.

There are Chancery district registries at Birmingham, Bristol, Caernarfon, Cardiff, Leeds, Liverpool, Manchester, Mold, Newcastle upon Tyne and Preston.

(Section 32 of the County Courts Act 1984 identifies which probate claims may be heard in a county court.)

2.3

When the claim form is issued, the relevant office will send a notice to Leeds District Probate Registry, Coronet House, Queen Street, Leeds, LS1 2BA, DX 26451 Leeds (Park Square), telephone 0113 243 1505, requesting that all testamentary documents, grants of representation and other relevant documents currently held at any probate registry are sent to the relevant office.

2.4

The commencement of a probate claim will, unless a court otherwise directs, prevent any grant of probate or letters of administration being made until the probate claim has been disposed of.

(Rule 45 of the Non-Contentious Probate Rules 1987 makes provision for notice of the probate claim to be given, and section 117 of the Senior Courts Act 1981 for the grant of letters of administration pending the determination of a probate claim. Paragraph 8 of this practice direction makes provision about an application for such a grant.)

Testamentary documents and evidence about testamentary documents

3.1

Unless the court orders otherwise, if a testamentary document is held by the court (whether it was lodged by a party or it was previously held at a probate registry) when the claim has been disposed of the court will send it to the Leeds District Probate Registry.

3.2

The written evidence about testamentary documents required by this Part –

(1) should be in the form annexed to this practice direction; and

(2) must be signed by the party personally and not by his solicitor or other representative (except that if the party is a child or protected party the written evidence must be signed by his litigation friend).

3.3

In a case in which there is urgent need to commence a probate claim (for example, in order to be able to apply immediately for the appointment of an administrator pending the determination of the claim) and it is not possible for the claimant to lodge the testamentary documents or to file the evidence about testamentary documents in the relevant office at the same time as the claim form is to be issued, the court may direct that the claimant shall be allowed to issue the claim form upon his giving an undertaking to the court to lodge the documents and file the evidence within such time as the court shall specify.

Case management

4

In giving case management directions in a probate claim the court will give consideration to the questions –

(1) whether any person who may be affected by the claim and who is not joined as a party should be joined as a party or given notice of the claim, whether under rule 19.8A or otherwise; and

(2) whether to make a representation order under rule 19.6 or rule 19.7.

Summary judgment

5.1

If an order pronouncing for a will in solemn form is sought on an application for summary judgment, the evidence in support of the application must include written evidence proving due execution of the will.

5.2

If a defendant has given notice in his defence under rule 57.7(5) that he raises no positive case but –

(1) he insists that the will be proved in solemn form; and

(2) for that purpose he will cross-examine the witnesses who attested the will;

any application by the claimant for summary judgment is subject to the right of that defendant to require those witnesses to attend court for cross-examination.

Settlement of a probate claim

6.1

If at any time the parties agree to settle a probate claim, the court may –

(1) order the trial of the claim on written evidence, which will lead to a grant in solemn form;

(2) order that the claim be discontinued or dismissed under rule 57.11, which will lead to a grant in common form; or

(3) pronounce for or against the validity of one or more wills under section 49 of the Administration of Justice Act 1985.

(For a form of order which is also applicable to discontinuance and which may be adapted as appropriate, see Practice Form No. CH38)

(Section 49 of the Administration of Justice Act 1985 permits a probate claim to be compromised without a trial if every ‘relevant beneficiary’, as defined in that section, has consented to the proposed order. It is only available in the High Court.)

6.2

Applications under section 49 of the Administration of Justice Act 1985 may be heard by a master or district judge and must be supported by written evidence identifying the relevant beneficiaries and exhibiting the written consent of each of them. The written evidence of testamentary documents required by rule 57.5 will still be necessary.

Application for an order to bring in a will, etc.

7.1

Any party applying for an order under section 122 of the Senior Courts Act 1981 (‘the 1981 Act’) must serve the application notice on the person against whom the order is sought.

(Section 122 of the 1981 Act empowers the court to order a person to attend court for examination, and to answer questions and bring in documents, if there are reasonable grounds for believing that such person has knowledge of a testamentary document. Rule 50(1) of the Non-Contentious Probate Rules 1987 makes similar provision where a probate claim has not been commenced.)

7.2

An application for the issue of a witness summons under section 123 of the 1981 Act –

(1) may be made without notice; and

(2) must be supported by written evidence setting out the grounds of the application.

(Section 123 of the 1981 Act empowers the court, where it appears that any person has in his possession, custody or power a testamentary document, to issue a witness summons ordering such person to bring in that document. Rule 50(2) of the Non-Contentious Probate Rules makes similar provision where a probate claim has not been commenced.)

7.3

An application under section 122 or 123 of the 1981 Act should be made to a master or district judge.

7.4

A person against whom a witness summons is issued under section 123 of the 1981 Act who denies that the testamentary document referred to in the witness summons is in his possession or under his control may file written evidence to that effect.

Administration pending the determination of a probate claim

8.1

An application under section 117 of the Senior Courts Act 1981 for an order for the grant of administration pending the determination of a probate claim should be made by application notice in the probate claim.

8.2

If an order for a grant of administration is made under section 117 of the 1981 Act –

(1) Rules 69.4 to 69.7 shall apply as if the administrator were a receiver appointed by the court;

(2) if the court allows the administrator remuneration under rule 69.7, it may make an order under section 117(3) of the 1981 Act assigning the remuneration out of the estate of the deceased; and

(3) every application relating to the conduct of the administration shall be made by application notice in the probate claim.

8.3

An order under section 117 may be made by a master or district judge.

8.4

If an order is made under section 117 an application for the grant of letters of administration should be made to the Principal Registry of the Family Division, First Avenue House, 42–49 High Holborn, London WC1V 6NP.

8.5

The appointment of an administrator to whom letters of administration are granted following an order under section 117 will cease automatically when a final order in the probate claim is made but will continue pending any appeal.

II   RECTIFICATION OF WILLS

Scope of this Section

9.

This Section of this practice direction applies to claims for the rectification of a will.

Lodging the grant

10.1

If the claimant is the person to whom the grant was made in respect of the will of which rectification is sought, he must, unless the court orders otherwise, lodge the probate or letters of administration with the will annexed with the court when the claim form is issued.

10.2

If a defendant has the probate or letters of administration in his possession or under his control, he must, unless the court orders otherwise, lodge it in the relevant office within 14 days after the service of the claim form on him.

Orders

11.

A copy of every order made for the rectification of a will shall be sent to the Principal Registry of the Family Division for filing, and a memorandum of the order shall be endorsed on, or permanently annexed to, the grant under which the estate is administered.

III   SUBSTITUTION AND REMOVAL OF PERSONAL REPRESENTATIVES

Scope of this Section

12.

This Section of this practice direction applies to claims and applications for substitution or removal of a personal representative. If substitution or removal of a personal representative is sought by application in existing proceedings, this Section shall apply with references to the claim, claim form and claimant being read as if they referred to the application, application notice and applicant respectively.

Starting the claim

13.1

The claim form must be accompanied by –

(1) either –

(a) a sealed or certified copy of the grant of probate or letters of administration, or

(b) where the claim is to substitute or remove an executor and is made before a grant of probate has been issued, the original or, if the original is not available, a copy of the will; and

(2) written evidence containing the grounds of the claim and the following information so far as it is known to the claimant –

(a) brief details of the property comprised in the estate, with an approximate estimate of its capital value and any income that is received from it;

(b) brief details of the liabilities of the estate;

(c) the names and addresses of the persons who are in possession of the documents relating to the estate;

(d) the names of the beneficiaries and their respective interests in the estate; and

(e) the name, address and occupation of any proposed substituted personal representative.

13.2

If the claim is for the appointment of a substituted personal representative, the claim form must be accompanied by –

(1) a signed or (in the case of the Public Trustee or a corporation) sealed consent to act; and

(2) written evidence as to the fitness of the proposed substituted personal representative, if an individual, to act.

Production of the grant

14.1

On the hearing of the claim the personal representative must produce to the Court the grant of representation to the deceased's estate.

14.2

If an order is made substituting or removing the personal representative, the grant (together with a sealed copy of the order) must be sent to and remain in the custody of the Principal Registry of the Family Division until a memorandum of the order has been endorsed on or permanently annexed to the grant.

14.3

Where the claim is to substitute or remove an executor and the claim is made before a grant of probate has been issued, paragraphs 14.1 and 14.2 do not apply. Where in such a case an order is made substituting or removing an executor a sealed copy of the order must be sent to the Principal Registry of the Family Division where it will be recorded and retained pending any application for a grant. An order sent to the Principal Registry in accordance with this paragraph must be accompanied by a note of the full name and date of death of the deceased, if it is not apparent on the face of the order.

IV   CLAIMS UNDER THE INHERITANCE (PROVISION FOR FAMILY AND DEPENDANTS) ACT 1975

Acknowledgment of service by personal representative – rule 57.16(4)

15.

Where a defendant who is a personal representative wishes to remain neutral in relation to the claim, and agrees to abide by any decision which the court may make, he should state this in Section A of the acknowledgment of service form.

Written evidence of personal representative – rule 57.16(5)

16.

The written evidence filed by a defendant who is a personal representative must state to the best of that person's ability –

(1) full details of the value of the deceased’s net estate, as defined in section 25(1) of the Act;

(2) the person or classes of persons beneficially interested in the estate, and –

(a) the names and (unless they are parties to the claim) addresses of all living beneficiaries; and

(b) the value of their interests in the estate so far as they are known.

(3) whether any living beneficiary (and if so, naming him) is a child or a person who lacks capacity (within the meaning of the Mental Capacity Act 2005); and

(4) any facts which might affect the exercise of the court''s powers under the Act.

Separate representation of claimants

17.

If a claim is made jointly by two or more claimants, and it later appears that any of the claimants have a conflict of interests –

(1) any claimant may choose to be represented at any hearing by separate solicitors or counsel, or may appear in person; and

(2) if the court considers that claimants who are represented by the same solicitors or counsel ought to be separately represented, it may adjourn the application until they are.

Production of the grant

18.1

On the hearing of a claim the personal representative must produce to the court the original grant of representation to the deceased's estate.

18.2

If the court makes an order under the Act, the original grant (together with a sealed copy of the order) must be sent to the Principal Registry of the Family Division for a memorandum of the order to be endorsed on or permanently annexed to the grant in accordance with section 19(3) of the Act.

18.3

Every final order embodying terms of compromise made in proceedings under the Act, whether made with or without a hearing, must contain a direction that a memorandum of the order shall be endorsed on or permanently annexed to the probate or letters of administration and a copy of the order shall be sent to the Principal Registry of the Family Division with the relevant grant of probate or letters of administration for endorsement.

ANNEX

A form of witness statement or affidavit about testamentary documents

(CPR rule 57.5)

(Title of the claim)

I [name and address] the claimant/defendant in this claim state [on oath] that I have no knowledge of any document –

(i) being or purported to be or having the form or effect of a will or codicil of [name of deceased] whose estate is the subject of this claim;

(ii) being or purporting to be a draft or written instructions for any such will or codicil made by or at the request of or under the instructions of the deceased;

(iii) being or purporting to be evidence of the contents or a copy of any such will or codicil which is alleged to have been lost or destroyed,

except ... [describe any testamentary document of the deceased, and if any such document is not in your control, give the name and address of the person who you believe has possession or control of it, or state that you do not know the name and address of that person] ...

[I believe that the facts stated in this witness statement are true] [or jurat for affidavit]

(NOTE: ‘testamentary document’ is defined in CPR rule 57.1)

PRACTICE DIRECTION 58 – COMMERCIAL COURT

This practice direction supplements Part 58

Contents of this Practice Direction

Title
General
Starting proceedings in the Commercial Court
Applications before proceedings are issued
Transferring proceedings to or from the Commercial Court
Acknowledgment of service
Default judgment and admissions
Variation of time limits
Amendments
Service of documents
Case management
Pre-trial review
Case management where there is a Part 20 claim
Evidence for applications
Judgments and orders
APPENDIX A

General

1.1

This practice direction applies to commercial claims proceeding in the commercial list of the Queen's Bench Division. It supersedes all previous practice directions and practice statements in the Commercial Court.

1.2

All proceedings in the commercial list, including any appeal from a judgment, order or decision of a master or district judge before the proceedings were transferred to the Commercial Court, will be heard or determined by a Commercial Court judge, except that –

(1) another judge of the Queen's Bench Division or Chancery Division may hear urgent applications if no Commercial Court judge is available; and

(2) unless the court otherwise orders, any application relating to the enforcement of a Commercial Court judgment or order for the payment of money will be dealt with by a master of the Queen's Bench Division or a district judge.

1.3

Provisions in other practice directions which refer to a master or district judge are to be read, in relation to claims in the commercial list, as if they referred to a Commercial Court judge.

1.4

The Admiralty and Commercial Registry in the Royal Courts of Justice is the administrative office of the court for all proceedings in the commercial list.

Starting proceedings in the Commercial Court

2.1

Claims in the Commercial Court must be issued in the Admiralty and Commercial Registry.

2.2

When the Registry is closed, a request to issue a claim form may be made by fax, using the procedure set out in Appendix A to this practice direction. If a request is made which complies with that procedure, the claim form is issued when the fax is received by the Registry.

2.3

The claim form must be marked in the top right hand corner ‘Queen's Bench Division, Commercial Court’.

2.4

A claimant starting proceedings in the commercial list, other than an arbitration claim, must use practice form N1(CC) for Part 7 claims or practice form N208(CC) for Part 8 claims.

Applications before proceedings are issued

3.1

A party who intends to bring a claim in the commercial list must make any application before the claim form is issued to a Commercial Court judge.

3.2

The written evidence in support of such an application must state that the claimant intends to bring proceedings in the commercial list.

3.3

If the Commercial Court judge hearing the application considers that the proceedings should not be brought in the commercial list, he may adjourn the application to be heard by a master or by a judge who is not a Commercial Court judge.

Transferring proceedings to or from the Commercial Court

4.1

If an application is made to a court other than the Commercial Court to transfer proceedings to the commercial list, the other court may –

(1) adjourn the application to be heard by a Commercial Court judge; or

(2) dismiss the application.

4.2

If the Commercial Court orders proceedings to be transferred to the commercial list –

(1) it will order them to be transferred to the Royal Courts of Justice; and

(2) it may give case management directions.

4.3

An application by a defendant, including a Part 20 defendant, for an order transferring proceedings from the commercial list should be made promptly and normally not later than the first case management conference.

4.4

A party applying to the Commercial Court to transfer a claim to the commercial list must give notice of the application to the court in which the claim is proceeding, and the Commercial Court will not make an order for transfer until it is satisfied that such notice has been given.

Acknowledgment of service

5.1

For Part 7 claims, a defendant must file an acknowledgment of service using practice form N9 (CC).

5.2

For Part 8 claims, a defendant must file an acknowledgment of service using practice form N210 (CC).

Default judgment and admissions

6.

The practice directions supplementing Parts 12 and 14 apply with the following modifications –

(1) paragraph 4.1(1) of Practice Direction 12 is to be read as referring to the service of the claim form; and

(2) the references to ‘particulars of claim’ in paragraphs 2.1, 3.1 and 3.2 of Practice Direction 14 are to be read as referring to the claim form.

Variation of time limits

7.1

If the parties, in accordance with rule 2.11, agree in writing to vary a time limit, the claimant must notify the court in writing, giving brief written reasons for the agreed variation.

7.2

The court may make an order overriding an agreement by the parties varying a time limit.

Amendments

8.

Paragraph 2.2 of Practice Direction 17 is modified so that amendments to a statement of case must show the original text, unless the court orders otherwise.

Service of documents

9.

Unless the court orders otherwise, the Commercial Court will not serve documents or orders and service must be effected by the parties.

Case management

10.1

The following parts only of Practice Direction 29 apply –

(1) paragraph 5 (case management conferences), excluding paragraph 5.9 and modified so far as is made necessary by other specific provisions of this practice direction; and

(2) paragraph 7 (failure to comply with case management directions).

10.2

If the proceedings are started in the commercial list, the claimant must apply for a case management conference –

(a) for a Part 7 claim, within 14 days of the date when all defendants who intend to file and serve a defence have done so; and

(b) for a Part 8 claim, within 14 days of the date when all defendants who intend to serve evidence have done so.

10.3

If the proceedings are transferred to the commercial list, the claimant must apply for a case management conference within 14 days of the date of the order transferring them, unless the judge held, or gave directions for, a case management conference when he made the order transferring the proceedings.

10.4

Any party may, at a time earlier than that provided in paragraphs 10.2 or 10.3, apply in writing to the court to fix a case management conference.

10.5

If the claimant does not make an application in accordance with paragraphs 10.2 or 10.3, any other party may apply for a case management conference.

10.6

The court may fix a case management conference at any time on its own initiative. If it does so, the court will give at least 7 days notice to the parties, unless there are compelling reasons for a shorter period of notice.

10.7

Not less than 7 days before a case management conference, each party must file and serve –

(1) a completed case management information sheet; and

(2) an application notice for any order which that party intends to seek at the case management conference, other than directions referred to in the case management information sheet.

10.8

Unless the court orders otherwise, the claimant, in consultation with the other parties, must prepare –

(1) a case memorandum, containing a short and uncontroversial summary of what the case is about and of its material case history;

(2) a list of issues, with a section listing important matters which are not in dispute; and

(3) a case management bundle containing –

(a) the claim form;

(b) all statements of case (excluding schedules), except that, if a summary of a statement of case has been filed, the bundle should contain the summary, and not the full statement of case;

(c) the case memorandum;

(d) the list of issues;

(e) the case management information sheets and, if a pre-trial timetable has been agreed or ordered, that timetable;

(f) the principal orders of the court; and

(g) any agreement in writing made by the parties as to disclosure,

and provide copies of the case management bundle for the court and the other parties at least 7 days before the first case management conference or any earlier hearing at which the court may give case management directions.

10.9

The claimant, in consultation with the other parties, must revise and update the documents referred to in paragraph 10.8 appropriately as the case proceeds. This must include making all necessary revisions and additions at least 7 days before any subsequent hearing at which the court may give case management directions.

Pre-trial review

11.1

At any pre-trial review or case management hearing, the court will ensure that case management directions have been complied with and give any further directions for the trial that are necessary.

11.2

Advocates who are to represent the parties at the trial should represent them at the pre-trial review and any case management hearing at which arrangements for the trial are to be discussed.

11.3

Before the pre-trial review, the parties must discuss and, if possible, agree a draft written timetable for the trial.

11.4

The claimant must file a copy of the draft timetable for the trial at least two days before the hearing of the pre-trial review. Any parts of the timetable which are not agreed must be identified and short explanations of the disagreement must be given.

11.5

At the pre-trial review, the court will set a timetable for the trial, unless a timetable has already been fixed or the court considers that it would be inappropriate to do so or appropriate to do so at a later time.

Case management where there is a Part 20 claim

12.

Paragraph 5 of Practice Direction 20 applies, except that, unless the court otherwise orders, the court will give case management directions for Part 20 claims at the same case management conferences as it gives directions for the main claim.

Evidence for applications

13.1

The general requirement is that, unless the court orders otherwise –

(1) evidence in support of an application must be filed and served with the application (see rule 23.7(3));

(2) evidence in answer must be filed and served within 14 days after the application is served; and

(3) evidence in reply must be filed and served within 7 days of the service of evidence in answer.

13.2

In any case in which the application is likely to require an oral hearing of more than half a day the periods set out in paragraphs 13.1(2) and (3) will be 28 days and 14 days respectively.

13.3

If the date fixed for the hearing of an application means that the times in paragraphs 13.1(2) and (3) cannot both be achieved, the evidence must be filed and served –

(1) as soon as possible; and

(2) in sufficient time to ensure that the application may fairly proceed on the date fixed.

13.4

The parties may, in accordance with rule 2.11, agree different periods from those in paragraphs 13.1(2) and (3) provided that the agreement does not affect the date fixed for the hearing of the application.

Judgments and orders

14.1

An application for a consent order must include a draft of the proposed order signed on behalf of all parties to whom it relates (see paragraph 10.4 of Practice Direction 23A).

14.2

Judgments and orders are generally drawn up by the parties (see rule 58.15). The parties are not therefore required to supply draft orders on disk (see paragraph 12.1 of Practice Direction 23A).

APPENDIX A : Procedure for issue of claim form when Registry is closed – paragraph 2.2

1.

A request to issue a claim form may be made by fax when the Registry is closed, provided that –

(a) the claim form is signed by a solicitor acting on behalf of the claimant; and

(b) it does not require the permission of the court for its issue (unless such permission has already been given).

2.

The solicitor requesting the issue of the claim form (‘the issuing solicitor’) must –

(a) endorse on the claim form and sign the endorsement set out below;

(b) send a copy of the claim form so endorsed to the Registry by fax for issue under paragraph 2.2 of this practice direction; and

(c) complete and sign a certificate in the form set out below, certifying that he has received a transmission report confirming that the fax has been transmitted in full, and stating the time and date of transmission.

3.

When the Registry is next open to the public after the issue of a claim form in accordance with this procedure, the issuing solicitor or his agent must attend and deliver to the Registry –

(a) the original of the claim form which was sent by fax (including the endorsement and the certificate) or, if the claim form has been served, a true and certified copy of it;

(b) as many copies of the claim form as the Registry requires; and

(c) the transmission report.

4.

When a court officer at the Registry has checked that –

(a) the claim form delivered under paragraph 3 matches the claim form received by fax; and

(b) the correct issue fee has been paid,

he will allocate a number to the case, and seal, mark as ‘original’ and date the claim form with the date of issue (being the date when the fax is recorded at the Registry as having been received).

5.

If the issuing solicitor has served the unsealed claim form on any person, that solicitor must as soon as practicable –

(a) inform that person of the case number; and

(b) if requested, serve that person with a copy of the sealed and dated claim form at any address in the United Kingdom, unless the court orders otherwise.

6.

Any person served with a claim form issued under this procedure may, without paying a fee, inspect and take copies of the documents lodged at the Registry under paragraphs 2 and 3 above.

7.

The issue of a claim form in accordance with this procedure takes place when the fax is recorded at the Registry as having been received, and the claim form has the same effect for all purposes as a claim form issued under Part 7 or 8. Unless the court otherwise orders, the sealed version of the claim form retained by the Registry is conclusive proof that the claim form was issued at the time and on the date stated.

8.

If the procedure set out in this Appendix is not complied with, the court may declare that a claim form shall be treated as not having been issued.

Endorsement

A claim form issued pursuant to a request by fax must be endorsed as follows:

(1) This claim form is issued under paragraph 2.2 of Practice Direction 58 and may be served notwithstanding that it does not bear the seal of the Court.

(2) A true copy of this claim form and endorsement has been sent to the Admiralty and Commercial Registry, Royal Courts of Justice, Strand, London WC2A 2LL, at the time and date certified below by the solicitor whose name appears below (‘the issuing solicitor’).

(3) It is the duty of the issuing solicitor or his agent to attend at the Registry when it is next open to the public for the claim form to be sealed.

(4) Any person served with this unsealed claim form –

(a) will be notified by the issuing solicitor of the case number;

(b) may require the issuing solicitor to serve that person with a copy of the sealed claim form at an address in the United Kingdom, unless the court orders otherwise; and

(c) may inspect without charge the documents lodged at the Registry by the issuing solicitor.

(5) I, the issuing solicitor, undertake [to the Court, to the defendants named in this claim form, and to any other person served with this claim form] –

(a) that the statement in paragraph 2 above is correct;

(b) that the time and date given in the certificate with this endorsement are correct;

(c) that this claim form is a claim form which may be issued under paragraph 2.2 and Appendix A of Practice Direction 58;

(d) that I will comply in all respects with the requirements of Appendix A of Practice Direction 58; and

(e) that I will indemnify any person served with the claim form before it is sealed against any loss suffered as a result of the claim form being or becoming invalid as a result of any failure to comply with Appendix A of Practice Direction 58.

(Signed)

Solicitor for the claimant

[Note: the endorsement may be signed in the name of the firm of solicitors rather than an individual solicitor, or by solicitors' agents in their capacity as agents acting on behalf of their professional clients.]

Certificate

The issuing solicitor must sign a certificate in the following form –

I certify that I have received a transmission report confirming that the transmission of a copy of this claim form to the Registry by fax was fully completed and that the time and date of transmission to the Registry were [enter the time and date shown on the transmission report].

Dated

(Signed)

Solicitor for the claimant

[Note: the certificate must be signed in the name of the firm of solicitors rather than an individual solicitor, or by solicitors' agents in their capacity as agents acting on behalf of their professional clients.]

Commercial Court

N1(CC) Claim Form

Available on the forms page.

N1C(CC) Notes for defendant

Available on the forms page.

N9(CC) Acknowledgement of service

Available on the forms page.

N208(CC) Claim form (Part 8)

Available on the forms page.

N208C(CC) Notes for defendant (Part 8)

Available on the forms page.

N210(CC) Acknowledgement of service (Part 8)

Available on the forms page.

N211(CC) Claim form (Part 20)

Available on the forms page.

N211C(CC) Notes for Part 20 defendant

Available on the forms page.

N213(CC) Acknowledgement of service (Part 20)

Available on the forms page.

PRACTICE DIRECTION 60 – TECHNOLOGY AND CONSTRUCTION COURT CLAIMS

This practice direction supplements Part 60

Contents of this Practice Direction

Title | Number
General | Para. 1.
TCC claims | Para. 2.1
How to start a TCC claim | Para. 3.1
Applications before proceedings are issued | Para. 4.1
Transfer of proceedings | Para. 5.1
Assignment of claim to a TCC judge | Para. 6.1
Applications | Para. 7.1
Case management conference | Para. 8.1
Pre-trial review | Para. 9.1
Listing | Para. 10.
Trial | Para. 11.1
Appendix A |
Appendix B |
Appendix C |

General

1.

This practice direction applies to Technology and Construction Court claims (‘TCC claims’).

TCC claims

2.1

The following are examples of the types of claim which it may be appropriate to bring as TCC claims –

(a) building or other construction disputes, including claims for the enforcement of the decisions of adjudicators under the Housing Grants, Construction and Regeneration Act 1996;

(b) engineering disputes;

(c) claims by and against engineers, architects, surveyors, accountants and other specialised advisers relating to the services they provide;

(d) claims by and against local authorities relating to their statutory duties concerning the development of land or the construction of buildings;

(e) claims relating to the design, supply and installation of computers, computer software and related network systems;

(f) claims relating to the quality of goods sold or hired, and work done, materials supplied or services rendered;

(g) claims between landlord and tenant for breach of a repairing covenant;

(h) claims between neighbours, owners and occupiers of land in trespass, nuisance etc;

(i) claims relating to the environment (for example, pollution cases);

(j) claims arising out of fires;

(k) claims involving taking of accounts where these are complicated; and

(l) challenges to decisions of arbitrators in construction and engineering disputes including applications for permission to appeal and appeals.

2.2

A claim given as an example in paragraph 2.1 will not be suitable for this specialist list unless it demonstrates the characteristics in rule 60.1(3). Similarly, the examples are not exhaustive and other types of claim may be appropriate to this specialist list.

How to start a TCC claim

3.1

TCC claims must be issued in the High Court or in a county court specified in this practice direction.

3.2

The claim form must be marked in the top right hand corner ‘Technology and Construction Court’ below the words ‘The High Court, Queen's Bench Division’ or ‘The _____ County Court’.

3.3

TCC claims brought in the High Court outside London may be issued in any district registry, but it is preferable that wherever possible they should be issued in one of the following district registries, in which a TCC judge will usually be available –

Birmingham, Bristol, Cardiff, Chester, Exeter, Leeds, Liverpool, Manchester, Mold, Newcastle upon Tyne and Nottingham.

3.4

The county courts in which a TCC claim may be issued are the following –

Birmingham, Bristol, Cardiff, Central London, Chester, Exeter, Leeds, Liverpool, Manchester, Mold, Newcastle upon Tyne and Nottingham.

Applications before proceedings are issued

4.1

A party who intends to issue a TCC claim must make any application before the claim form is issued to a TCC judge.

4.2

The written evidence in support of such an application must state that the proposed claim is a TCC claim.

Transfer of proceedings

5.1

Where no TCC judge is available to deal with a claim which has been issued in a High Court District Registry or one of the county courts listed in paragraph 3.4 above, the claim may be transferred –

(1) if it has been issued in a District Registry, to another District Registry or to the High Court in London; or

(2) if it has been issued in a county court, to another county court where a TCC judge would be available.

5.2

Paragraph 5.1 is without prejudice to the court's general powers to transfer proceedings under Part 30.

(Rule 30.5(3) provides that an application for the transfer of proceedings to or from a specialist list must be made to a judge dealing with claims in that list.)

5.3

A party applying to a TCC judge to transfer a claim to the TCC specialist list must give notice of the application to the court in which the claim is proceeding, and a TCC judge will not make an order for transfer until he is satisfied that such notice has been given.

Assignment of claim to a TCC judge

6.1

When a TCC claim is issued or an order is made transferring a claim to the TCC specialist list, the court will assign the claim to a named TCC judge (‘the assigned TCC judge’) who will have the primary responsibility for the case management of that claim.

6.2

All documents relating to the claim must be marked in similar manner to the claim form with the words ‘Technology and Construction Court’ and the name of the assigned TCC judge.

Applications

7.1

An application should normally be made to the assigned TCC judge. If the assigned TCC judge is not available, or the court gives permission, the application may be made to another TCC judge.

7.2

If an application is urgent and there is no TCC judge available to deal with it, the application may be made to any judge who, if the claim were not a TCC claim, would be authorised to deal with the application.

Case management conference

8.1

The court will fix a case management conference within 14 days of the earliest of these events –

(1) the filing of an acknowledgment of service;

(2) the filing of a defence; or

(3) the date of an order transferring the claim to a TCC.

8.2

When the court notifies the parties of the date and time of the case management conference, it will at the same time send each party a case management information sheet and a case management directions form.

(The case management information sheet and the case management directions form are in the form set out in Appendixes A and B to this practice direction.)

8.3

Not less than two days before the case management conference, each party must file and serve on all other parties –

(1) completed copies of the case management information sheet and case management directions form; and

(2) an application notice for any order which that party intends to seek at the case management conference, other than directions referred to in the case management directions form.

8.4

The parties are encouraged to agree directions to propose to the court by reference to the case management directions form.

8.5

If any party fails to file or serve the case management information sheet and the case management directions form by the date specified, the court may –

(1) impose such sanction as it sees fit; and

(2) either proceed with or adjourn the case management conference.

8.6

The directions given at the case management conference will normally include the fixing of dates for –

(1) any further case management conferences;

(2) a pre-trial review;

(3) the trial of any preliminary issues that it orders to be tried; and

(4) the trial.

Pre-trial review

9.1

When the court fixes the date for a pre-trial review it will send each party a pre-trial review questionnaire.

(The pre-trial review questionnaire is in the form set out in Appendix C to this practice direction).

9.2

Each party must file and serve on all other parties completed copies of the questionnaire not less than two days before the date fixed for the pre-trial review.

9.3

The parties are encouraged to agree directions to propose to the court.

9.4

If any party fails to return or exchange the questionnaire by the date specified the court may –

(1) impose such sanction as it sees fit; and

(2) either proceed with or adjourn the pre-trial review.

9.5

At the pre-trial review, the court will give such directions for the conduct of the trial as it sees fit.

Listing

10.

The provisions about listing questionnaires and listing in Part 29 and Practice Direction 29 do not apply to TCC claims.

Trial

11.1

Whenever possible the trial of a claim will be heard by the assigned TCC judge.

11.2

A TCC claim may be tried at any place where there is a TCC judge available to try the claim.

Appendix A

Technology and Construction Court Claims

TCC/CM1 Case management information sheet (Appendix A)

Available on the forms page.

Appendix B

Technology and Construction Court Claims

TCC/CMD Case management directions form (Appendix B)

Available on the forms page.

Appendix C

Technology and Construction Court Claims

TCC/PTR1 Pre-trial review questionnaire (Appendix C)

Available on the forms page.

PART 62 - ARBITRATION CLAIMS

Contents of this Part

Title
| Number
Scope of this Part and interpretation | Rule 62.1
I CLAIMS UNDER THE 1996 ACT |

Interpretation | Rule 62.2
Starting the claim | Rule 62.3
Arbitration claim form | Rule 62.4
Service out of the jurisdiction | Rule 62.5
Notice | Rule 62.6
Case management | Rule 62.7
Stay of legal proceedings | Rule 62.8
Variation of time | Rule 62.9
Hearings | Rule 62.10
II OTHER ARBITRATION CLAIMS |

Scope of this Section | Rule 62.11
Applications to Judge | Rule 62.12
Starting the claim | Rule 62.13
Claims in District Registries | Rule 62.14
Time limits and other special provisions about arbitration claims | Rule 62.15
Service out of the jurisdiction | Rule 62.16
III ENFORCEMENT |

Scope of this Section | Rule 62.17
Enforcement of awards | Rule 62.18
Interest on awards | Rule 62.19
Registration in High Court of foreign awards | Rule 62.20
Registration of awards under the Arbitration (International Investment Disputes) Act 1966 | Rule 62.21

Scope of this Part and interpretation

62.1

(1) This Part contains rules about arbitration claims.

(2) In this Part –

(a) ‘the 1950 Act’ means the Arbitration Act 1950^1;

(b) ‘the 1975 Act’ means the Arbitration Act 1975^2;

(c) ‘the 1979 Act’ means the Arbitration Act 1979[3];

(d) ‘the 1996 Act’ means the Arbitration Act 1996[4];

(e) references to –

(i) the 1996 Act; or

(ii) any particular section of that Act

include references to that Act or to the particular section of that Act as applied with modifications by the ACAS Arbitration Scheme (England and Wales) Order 2001^5; and

(f) ‘arbitration claim form’ means a claim form in the form set out in Practice Direction 62.

(3) Part 58 (Commercial Court) applies to arbitration claims in the Commercial Court, Part 59 (Mercantile Court) applies to arbitration claims in the Mercantile Court and Part 60 (Technology and Construction Court claims) applies to arbitration claims in the Technology and Construction Court, except where this Part provides otherwise.

I CLAIMS UNDER THE 1996 ACT

Interpretation

62.2

(1) In this Section of this Part ‘arbitration claim’ means –

(a) any application to the court under the 1996 Act;

(b) a claim to determine –

(i) whether there is a valid arbitration agreement;

(ii) whether an arbitration tribunal is properly constituted; or

what matters have been submitted to arbitration in accordance with an arbitration agreement;

(c) a claim to declare that an award by an arbitral tribunal is not binding on a party; and

(d) any other application affecting –

(i) arbitration proceedings (whether started or not); or

(ii) an arbitration agreement.

(2) This Section of this Part does not apply to an arbitration claim to which Sections II or III of this Part apply.

Starting the claim

62.3

(1) Except where paragraph (2) applies an arbitration claim must be started by the issue of an arbitration claim form in accordance with the Part 8 procedure.

(2) An application under section 9 of the 1996 Act to stay legal proceedings must be made by application notice to the court dealing with those proceedings.

(3) The courts in which an arbitration claim may be started are set out in Practice Direction 62.

(4) Rule 30.5 applies with the modification that a judge of the Technology and Construction Court may transfer the claim to any other court or specialist list.

Arbitration claim form

62.4

(1) An arbitration claim form must –

(a) include a concise statement of –

(i) the remedy claimed; and

(ii) any questions on which the claimant seeks the decision of the court;

(b) give details of any arbitration award challenged by the claimant, identifying which part or parts of the award are challenged and specifying the grounds for the challenge;

(c) show that any statutory requirements have been met;

(d) specify under which section of the 1996 Act the claim is made;

(e) identify against which (if any) defendants a costs order is sought; and

(f) specify either –

(i) the persons on whom the arbitration claim form is to be served, stating their role in the arbitration and whether they are defendants; or

(ii) that the claim is made without notice under section 44(3) of the 1996 Act and the grounds relied on.

(2) Unless the court orders otherwise an arbitration claim form must be served on the defendant within 1 month from the date of issue and rules 7.5 and 7.6 are modified accordingly.

(3) Where the claimant applies for an order under section 12 of the 1996 Act (extension of time for beginning arbitral proceedings or other dispute resolution procedures), he may include in his arbitration claim form an alternative application for a declaration that such an order is not needed.

Service out of the jurisdiction

62.5

(1) The court may give permission to serve an arbitration claim form out of the jurisdiction if –

(a) the claimant seeks to –

(i) challenge; or

(ii) appeal on a question of law arising out of,

an arbitration award made within the jurisdiction;

(The place where an award is treated as made is determined by section 53 of the 1996 Act.)

(b) the claim is for an order under section 44 of the 1996 Act; or

(c) the claimant –

(i) seeks some other remedy or requires a question to be decided by the court affecting an arbitration (whether started or not), an arbitration agreement or an arbitration award; and

(ii) the seat of the arbitration is or will be within the jurisdiction or the conditions in section 2(4) of the 1996 Act are satisfied.

(2) An application for permission under paragraph (1) must be supported by written evidence –

(a) stating the grounds on which the application is made; and

(b) showing in what place or country the person to be served is, or probably may be found.

(3) Rules 6.40 to 6.46 apply to the service of an arbitration claim form under paragraph (1).

(4) An order giving permission to serve an arbitration claim form out of the jurisdiction must specify the period within which the defendant may file an acknowledgment of service.

Notice

62.6

(1) Where an arbitration claim is made under section 24, 28 or 56 of the 1996 Act, each arbitrator must be a defendant.

(2) Where notice must be given to an arbitrator or any other person it may be given by sending him a copy of –

(a) the arbitration claim form; and

(b) any written evidence in support.

(3) Where the 1996 Act requires an application to the court to be made on notice to any other party to the arbitration, that notice must be given by making that party a defendant.

Case management

62.7

(1) Part 26 and any other rule that requires a party to file a directions questionnaire does not apply.

(2) Arbitration claims are allocated to the multi-track.

(3) Part 29 does not apply.

(4) The automatic directions set out in Practice Direction 62 apply unless the court orders otherwise.

Stay of legal proceedings

62.8

(1) An application notice seeking a stay of legal proceedings under section 9 of the 1996 Act^6 must be served on all parties to those proceedings who have given an address for service.

(2) A copy of an application notice under paragraph (1) must be served on any other party to the legal proceedings (whether or not he is within the jurisdiction) who has not given an address for service, at –

(a) his last known address; or

(b) a place where it is likely to come to his attention.

(3) Where a question arises as to whether –

(a) an arbitration agreement has been concluded; or

(b) the dispute which is the subject-matter of the proceedings falls within the terms of such an agreement,

the court may decide that question or give directions to enable it to be decided and may order the proceedings to be stayed pending its decision.

Variation of time

62.9

(1) The court may vary the period of 28 days fixed by section 70(3) of the 1996 Act for –

(a) challenging the award under section 67 or 68 of the Act; and

(b) appealing against an award under section 69 of the Act.

(2) An application for an order under paragraph (1) may be made without notice being served on any other party before the period of 28 days expires.

(3) After the period of 28 days has expired –

(a) an application for an order extending time under paragraph (1) must –

(i) be made in the arbitration claim form; and

(ii) state the grounds on which the application is made;

(b) any defendant may file written evidence opposing the extension of time within 7 days after service of the arbitration claim form; and

(c) if the court extends the period of 28 days, each defendant's time for acknowledging service and serving evidence shall start to run as if the arbitration claim form had been served on the date when the court's order is served on that defendant.

Hearings

62.10

(1) The court may order that an arbitration claim be heard either in public or in private.

(2) Rule 39.2 does not apply.

(3) Subject to any order made under paragraph (1) –

(a) the determination of –

(i) a preliminary point of law under section 45 of the 1996 Act; or

(ii) an appeal under section 69 of the 1996 Act on a question of law arising out of an award,

will be heard in public; and

(b) all other arbitration claims will be heard in private.

(4) Paragraph (3)(a) does not apply to –

(a) the preliminary question of whether the court is satisfied of the matters set out in section 45(2)(b); or

(b) an application for permission to appeal under section 69(2)(b).

II OTHER ARBITRATION CLAIMS

Scope of this Section

62.11

(1) This Section of this Part contains rules about arbitration claims to which the old law applies.

(2) In this Section

(a) ‘the old law’ means the enactments specified in Schedules 3 and 4 of the 1996 Act as they were in force before their amendment or repeal by that Act; and

(b) ‘arbitration claim’ means any application to the court under the old law and includes an appeal (or application for permission to appeal) to the High Court under section 1(2) of the 1979 Act^7.

(3) This Section does not apply to –

(a) a claim to which Section III of this Part applies; or

(b) a claim on the award.

Applications to Judge

62.12  A claim –

(a) seeking permission to appeal under section 1(2) of the 1979 Act;

(b) under section 1(5) of that Act (including any claim seeking permission); or

(c) under section 5 of that Act,

must be made in the High Court and will be heard by a judge of the Commercial Court unless any such judge directs otherwise.

Starting the claim

62.13

(1) Except where paragraph (2) applies an arbitration claim must be started by the issue of an arbitration claim form in accordance with the Part 8 procedure.

(2) Where an arbitration claim is to be made in existing proceedings –

(a) it must be made by way of application notice; and

(b) any reference in this Section of this Part to an arbitration claim form includes a reference to an application notice.

(3) The arbitration claim form in an arbitration claim under section 1(5) of the 1979 Act (including any claim seeking permission) must be served on –

(a) the arbitrator or umpire; and

(b) any other party to the reference.

Claims in District Registries

62.14

If –

(a) a claim is to be made under section 12(4) of the 1950 Act^8 for an order for the issue of a witness summons to compel the attendance of the witness before an arbitrator or umpire; and

(b) the attendance of the witness is required within the district of a District Registry,

the claim may be started in that Registry.

Time limits and other special provisions about arbitration claims

62.15

(1) An arbitration claim to

(a) remit an award under section 22 of the 1950 Act^9;

(b) set aside an award under section 23(2) of that Act[10] or otherwise; or

(c) direct an arbitrator or umpire to state the reasons for an award under section 1(5) of the 1979 Act,

must be made, and the arbitration claim form served, within 21 days after the award has been made and published to the parties.

(2) An arbitration claim to determine any question of law arising in the course of a reference under section 2(1) of the Arbitration Act 1979 must be made, and the arbitration claim form served, within 14 days after –

(a) the arbitrator or umpire gave his consent in writing to the claim being made; or

(b) the other parties so consented.

(3) An appeal under section 1(2) of the 1979 Act must be filed, and the arbitration claim form served, within 21 days after the award has been made and published to the parties.

(4) Where reasons material to an appeal under section 1(2) of the 1979 Act are given on a date subsequent to the publication of the award, the period of 21 days referred to in paragraph (3) will run from the date on which reasons are given.

(5) In every arbitration claim to which this rule applies –

(a) the arbitration claim form must state the grounds of the claim or appeal;

(b) where the claim or appeal is based on written evidence, a copy of that evidence must be served with the arbitration claim form; and

(c) where the claim or appeal is made with the consent of the arbitrator, the umpire or the other parties, a copy of every written consent must be served with the arbitration claim form.

(6) In an appeal under section 1(2) of the 1979 Act –

(a) a statement of the grounds for the appeal specifying the relevant parts of the award and reasons; and

(b) where permission is required, any written evidence in support of the contention that the question of law concerns –

(i) a term of a contract; or

(ii) an event,

which is not a ‘one-off’ term or event,

must be filed and served with the arbitration claim form.

(7) Any written evidence in reply to written evidence under paragraph (6)(b) must be filed and served on the claimant not less than 2 days before the hearing.

(8) A party to a claim seeking permission to appeal under section 1(2) of the 1979 Act who wishes to contend that the award should be upheld for reasons not expressed or fully expressed in the award and reasons must file and serve on the claimant, a notice specifying the grounds of his contention not less than 2 days before the hearing.

Service out of the jurisdiction

62.16

(1) Subject to paragraph (2) –

(a) any arbitration claim form in an arbitration claim under the 1950 Act or the 1979 Act; or

(b) any order made in such a claim,

may be served out of the jurisdiction with the permission of the court if the arbitration to which the claim relates –

(i) is governed by the law of England and Wales; or

(ii) has been, is being, or will be, held within the jurisdiction.

(2) An arbitration claim form seeking permission to enforce an award may be served out of the jurisdiction with the permission of the court whether or not the arbitration is governed by the law of England and Wales.

(3) An application for permission to serve an arbitration claim form out of the jurisdiction must be supported by written evidence –

(a) stating the grounds on which the application is made; and

(b) showing in what place or country the person to be served is, or probably may be found.

Rules 6.40 to 6.46 apply to the service of an arbitration claim form under paragraph (1).

(4) Omitted

(5) An order giving permission to serve an arbitration claim form out of the jurisdiction must specify the period within which the defendant may file an acknowledgment of service.

III ENFORCEMENT

Scope of this Section

62.17

This Section of this Part applies to all arbitration enforcement proceedings other than by a claim on the award.

Enforcement of awards

62.18

(1) An application for permission under –

(a) section 66 of the 1996 Act[11];

(b) section 101 of the 1996 Act;

(c) section 26 of the 1950 Act[12]; or

(d) section 3(1)(a) of the 1975 Act^13,

to enforce an award in the same manner as a judgment or order may be made without notice in an arbitration claim form.

(2) The court may specify parties to the arbitration on whom the arbitration claim form must be served.

(3) The parties on whom the arbitration claim form is served must acknowledge service and the enforcement proceedings will continue as if they were an arbitration claim under Section I of this Part.

(4) With the permission of the court the arbitration claim form may be served out of the jurisdiction irrespective of where the award is, or is treated as, made.

(5) Where the applicant applies to enforce an agreed award within the meaning of section 51(2) of the 1996 Act –

(a) the arbitration claim form must state that the award is an agreed award; and

(b) any order made by the court must also contain such a statement.

(6) An application for permission must be supported by written evidence –

(a) exhibiting –

(i) where the application is made under section 66 of the 1996 Act or under section 26 of the 1950 Act, the arbitration agreement and the original award (or copies);

(ii) where the application is under section 101 of the 1996 Act, the documents required to be produced by section 102 of that Act; or

(iii) where the application is under section 3(1)(a) of the 1975 Act, the documents required to be produced by section 4 of that Act;

(b) stating the name and the usual or last known place of residence or business of the claimant and of the person against whom it is sought to enforce the award; and

(c) stating either –

(i) that the award has not been complied with; or

(ii) the extent to which it has not been complied with at the date of the application.

(7) An order giving permission must –

(a) be drawn up by the claimant; and

(b) be served on the defendant by –

(i) delivering a copy to him personally; or

(ii) sending a copy to him at his usual or last known place of residence or business.

(8) An order giving permission may be served out of the jurisdiction –

(a) without permission; and

(b) in accordance with rules 6.40 to 6.46 as if the order were an arbitration claim form.

(9) Within 14 days after service of the order or, if the order is to be served out of the jurisdiction, within such other period as the court may set –

(a) the defendant may apply to set aside the order; and

(b) the award must not be enforced until after –

(i) the end of that period; or

(ii) any application made by the defendant within that period has been finally disposed of.

(10) The order must contain a statement of –

(a) the right to make an application to set the order aside; and

(b) the restrictions on enforcement under rule 62.18(9)(b).

(11) Where a body corporate is a party any reference in this rule to place of residence or business shall have effect as if the reference were to the registered or principal address of the body corporate.

Interest on awards

62.19

(1) Where an applicant seeks to enforce an award of interest the whole or any part of which relates to a period after the date of the award, he must file a statement giving the following particulars –

(a) whether simple or compound interest was awarded;

(b) the date from which interest was awarded;

(c) where rests were provided for, specifying them;

(d) the rate of interest awarded; and

(e) a calculation showing –

(i) the total amount claimed up to the date of the statement; and

(ii) any sum which will become due on a daily basis.

(2) A statement under paragraph (1) must be filed whenever the amount of interest has to be quantified for the purpose of –

(a) obtaining a judgment or order under section 66 of the 1996 Act (enforcement of the award); or

(b) enforcing such a judgment or order.

Registration in High Court of foreign awards

62.20

(1) Where –

(a) an award is made in proceedings on an arbitration in any part of a British overseas territory or other territory to which Part I of the Foreign Judgments (Reciprocal Enforcement) Act 1933^14 (‘the 1933 Act’) extends;

(b) Part II of the Administration of Justice Act 1920[15] extended to that part immediately before Part I of the 1933 Act was extended to that part; and

(c) an award has, under the law in force in the place where it was made, become enforceable in the same manner as a judgment given by a court in that place,

rules 74.1 to 74.7 and 74.9 apply in relation to the award as they apply in relation to a judgment given by the court subject to the modifications in paragraph (2).

(2) The modifications referred to in paragraph (1) are as follows –

(a) for references to the State of origin are substituted references to the place where the award was made; and

(b) the written evidence required by rule 74.4 must state (in addition to the matters required by that rule) that to the best of the information or belief of the maker of the statement the award has, under the law in force in the place where it was made, become enforceable in the same manner as a judgment given by a court in that place.

Registration of awards under the Arbitration (International Investment Disputes) Act 1966

62.21

(1) In this rule –

(a) ‘the 1966 Act’ means the Arbitration (International Investment Disputes) Act 1966^16;

(b) ‘award’ means an award under the Convention;

(c) ‘the Convention’ means the Convention on the settlement of investment disputes between States and nationals of other States which was opened for signature in Washington on 18th March 1965^17;

(d) ‘judgment creditor’ means the person seeking recognition or enforcement of an award; and

(e) ‘judgment debtor’ means the other party to the award.

(2) Subject to the provisions of this rule, the following provisions of Part 74 apply with such modifications as may be necessary in relation to an award as they apply in relation to a judgment to which Part I of the Foreign Judgments (Reciprocal Enforcement) Act 1933[18] applies –

(a) rule 74.1;

(b) rule 74.3;

(c) rule 74.4(1), (2)(a) to (d), and (4);

(d) rule 74.6 (except paragraph (3)(c) to (e)); and

(e) rule 74.9(2).

(3) An application to have an award registered in the High Court under section 1 of the 1966 Act^19 must be made in accordance with the Part 8 procedure.

(4) The written evidence required by rule 74.4 in support of an application for registration must –

(a) exhibit the award certified under the Convention instead of the judgment (or a copy of it); and

(b) in addition to stating the matters referred to in rule 74.4(2)(a) to (d) state whether –

(i) at the date of the application the enforcement of the award has been stayed (provisionally or otherwise) under the Convention; and

(ii) any, and if so what, application has been made under the Convention, which, if granted, might result in a stay of the enforcement of the award.

(5) Where, on granting permission to register an award or an application made by the judgment debtor after an award has been registered, the court considers –

(a) that the enforcement of the award has been stayed (whether provisionally or otherwise) under the Convention; or

(b) that an application has been made under the Convention which, if granted, might result in a stay of the enforcement of the award,

the court may stay the enforcement of the award for such time as it considers appropriate.

Footnotes

1950 c. 27. Back to text
1975 c.3; repealed by the Arbitration Act 1996 (c. 23), section 107(2) and Schedule 4 but continues to apply to claims commenced before 31st January 1997 by virtue of the Arbitration Act 1996 (Commencement No. 1) Order 1996 (S.I. 1996/3146), article 4 and Schedule 2. Back to text
1979 c. 42; repealed by the Arbitration Act 1996 (c. 23), section 107(2) and Schedule 4 but continues to apply to claims commenced before 31st January 1997 by virtue of the Arbitration Act 1996 (Commencement No. 1) Order 1996 (S.I. 1996/3146), article 4 and Schedule 2. Back to text
1996 c. 23. Back to text
S.I. 2001/1185. Back to text
1996 c. 23. Back to text
1979 c. 42; repealed by the Arbitration Act 1996 (c. 23), section 107(2) and Schedule 4 but continues to apply to claims commenced before 31st January 1997 by virtue of the Arbitration Act 1996 (Commencement No. 1) Order 1996 (S.I. 1996/3146), article 4 and Schedule 2. Back to text
1950 c. 27; section 12(4) was repealed by the Arbitration Act 1996 (c. 23), section 107(2) and Schedule 4 but continues to apply to claims commenced before 31st January 1997 by virtue of the Arbitration Act 1996 (Commencement No. 1) Order 1996 (S.I. 1996/3146), article 4 and Schedule 2. Back to text
1950 c. 27; section 22 was repealed by the Arbitration Act 1996 (c. 23), section 107(2) and Schedule 4 but continues to apply to claims commenced before 31st January 1997 by virtue of the Arbitration Act 1996 (Commencement No. 1) Order 1996 (S.I. 1996/3146), article 4 and Schedule 2. Back to text
1950 c. 27; section 23(2) was repealed by the Arbitration Act 1996 (c. 23), section 107(2) and Schedule 4 but continues to apply to claims commenced before 31st January 1997 by virtue of the Arbitration Act 1996 (Commencement No. 1) Order 1996 (S.I. 1996/3146), article 4 and Schedule 2. Back to text
1996 c. 23. Back to text
1950 c. 27; section 26 was repealed by the Arbitration Act 1996 (c. 23), section 107(2) and Schedule 4 but continues to apply to claims commenced before 31st January 1997 by virtue of the Arbitration Act 1996 (Commencement No. 1) Order 1996 (S.I. 1996/3146), article 4 and Schedule 2. Back to text
1975 c. 3; repealed by the Arbitration Act 1996 (c. 23), section 107(2) and Schedule 4 but continues to apply to claims commenced before 31st January 1997 by virtue of the Arbitration Act 1996 (Commencement No. 1) Order 1996 (S.I. 1996/3146), article 4 and Schedule 2. Back to text
1933 c. 13 (23 & 24 Geo. 5). Back to text
1920 c. 81 (10 & 11 Geo. 5); section 10 of Part II was substituted by the Civil Jurisdiction and Judgments Act 1982 (c. 27), section 35(2) and section 14 of Part II was amended by the Civil Jurisdiction and Judgments Act 1982 (c. 27), section 35(3). Back to text
1966 c. 41. Back to text
The text of the Convention is set out in the Schedule to the Arbitration (International Investment Disputes) Act 1966 (c. 41). Back to text
23 & 24 Geo 5 c.13. Back to text
1966 c. 41; section 1 was amended by the Administration of Justice Act 1977 (c. 38), sections 4 and 32(4) and Schedule 5, Part I and by the Supreme Court Act 1981 (c. 54), section 152(1) and Schedule 5. Back to text

PART 63 - INTELLECTUAL PROPERTY CLAIMS

Contents of this Part

Title | Number
Scope of this Part and interpretation | Rule 63.1
I PATENTS AND REGISTERED DESIGNS |

Scope of Section I and allocation | Rule 63.2
Specialist list | Rule 63.3
Omitted | Rule 63.4
Starting the claim | Rule 63.5
Claim for infringement or challenge to validity of a patent or registered design | Rule 63.6
Defence and reply | Rule 63.7
Case management
| Rule 63.8

Disclosure and inspection | Rule 63.9
Application to amend a patent specification in existing proceedings | Rule 63.10
Court’s determination of question or application | Rule 63.11
Application by employee for compensation | Rule 63.12
II REGISTERED TRADE MARKS AND OTHER INTELLECTUAL PROPERTY RIGHTS |

Allocation | Rule 63.13
III SERVICE OF DOCUMENTS AND PARTICIPATION BY THE COMPTROLLER |

Service of documents | Rule 63.14
Participation by the Comptroller | Rule 63.15
IV APPEALS |

Appeals from decisions of the Comptroller or the registrar | Rule 63.16
V INTELLECTUAL PROPERTY ENTERPRISE COURT |

Scope of this Section | Rule 63.17
Transfer of proceedings | Rule 63.18
Enterprise judges and district judges
judge | Rule 63.19
Statements of case | Rule 63.20
Statement of truth | Rule 63.21
Defence and reply | Rule 63.22
Case management | Rule 63.23
Disclosure and inspection | Rule 63.24
Applications | Rule 63.25
Costs | Rule 63.26
Allocation to the small claims track | Rule 63.27
Extent to which rules in this Part apply to small claims | Rule 63.28

Scope of this Part and interpretation

63.1

(1) This Part applies to all intellectual property claims including –

(a) registered intellectual property rights such as –

(i) patents;

(ii) registered designs; and

(iii) registered trade marks; and

(b) unregistered intellectual property rights such as –

(i) copyright;

(ii) design right;

(iii) the right to prevent passing off; and

(iv) the other rights set out in Practice Direction 63.

(2) In this Part –

(a) ‘the 1977 Act’ means the Patents Act 1977[1];

(b) ‘the 1988 Act’ means the Copyright, Designs and Patents Act 1988^2;

(c) ‘the 1994 Act’ means the Trade Marks Act 1994^3;

(d) ‘the Comptroller’ means the Comptroller General of Patents, Designs and Trade Marks;

(e) ‘patent’ means a patent under the 1977 Act or a supplementary protection certificate granted by the Patent Office under Article 10(1) of Council Regulation (EEC) No. 1768/92^4 or of Regulation (EC) No. 1610/96 of the European Parliament and the Council^5 and includes any application for a patent or supplementary protection certificate;

(f) ‘Patents Court’ means the Patents Court of the High Court constituted as part of the Chancery Division by section 6(1) of the Senior Courts Act 1981[6];

(g) ‘Intellectual Property Enterprise Court’ means a specialist list established within the Chancery Division of the High Court;

(h) ‘enterprise judge’ means a judge authorised by the Chancellor of the High Court to sit in the Intellectual Property Enterprise Court;

(i) omitted

(j) ‘the register’ means whichever of the following registers is appropriate –

(i) patents maintained by the Comptroller under section 32 of the 1977 Act;

(ii) designs maintained by the registrar under section 17 of the Registered Designs Act 1949^7;

(iii) trade marks maintained by the registrar under section 63 of the 1994 Act;

(iv) Community trade marks maintained by the Office for Harmonisation in the Internal Market under Article 83 of Council Regulation (EC) No. 207/2009^8;

(v) Community designs maintained by the Office for Harmonisation in the Internal Market under Article 72 of Council Regulation (EC) No. 6/2002^9;

(vi) plant varieties maintained by the Controller under regulation 12 of the Plant Breeders' Rights Regulations 1998[10]; and

(vii) Community plant variety rights maintained by the Community Plant Variety Right Office under Article 87 of Council Regulation (EC) No. 2100/94; and

(k) ‘the registrar’ means–

(i) the registrar of trade marks; or

(ii) the registrar of registered designs,

whichever is appropriate.

(3) Save as provided in rule 63.27, claims to which this Part applies are allocated to the multi-track. Rule 26.3(1) applies save for the modification that the court will send the parties a notice requiring the parties to file proposed directions by the date specified in the notice. For a claim which is allocated to the multi-track by this rule, rule 26.3(1B) and rules 26.4 to 26.10 do not apply.

I PATENTS AND REGISTERED DESIGNS

Scope of Section I and allocation

63.2

(1) This Section applies to –

(a) any claim under –

(i) the 1977 Act;

(ii) the Registered Designs Act 1949;

(iii) the Defence Contracts Act 1958[11]; and

(b) any claim relating to–

(i) Community registered designs;

(ii) semiconductor topography rights; or

(iii) plant varieties.

(2) Claims to which this Section applies must be started in –

(a) the Patents Court; or

(b) the Intellectual Property Enterprise Court.

Specialist list

63.3  Claims in the Patents Court form a specialist list for the purpose of rule 30.5.

Omitted

63.4

Starting the claim

63.5  Claims to which this Section applies must be started-

(a) by a Part 7 claim form; or

(b) in existing proceedings under Part 20.

Claim for infringement or challenge to validity of a patent or registered design

63.6  A statement of case in a claim for infringement or a claim in which the validity of a patent or registered design is challenged must contain particulars as set out in Practice Direction 63.

Defence and reply

63.7  Part 15 applies with the modification –

(a) to rule 15.4(1)(b) that in a claim for infringement under rule 63.6, the period for filing a defence where the defendant files an acknowledgment of service under Part 10 is 42 days after service of the particulars of claim;

(b) that where rule 15.4(2) provides for a longer period to file a defence than in rule 63.7(a), then the period of time in rule 15.4(2) will apply; and

(c) to rule 15.8 that the claimant must –

(i) file any reply to a defence; and

(ii) serve it on all other parties,

within 21 days of service of the defence.

Case management

63.8

(1) Parties do not need to file a directions questionnaire.

(2) The following provisions only of Part 29 apply –

(a) rule 29.3(2) (legal representatives to attend case management conferences);

(b) rule 29.4 (the parties must endeavour to agree case management directions); and

(c) rule 29.5 (variation of case management timetable) with the exception of paragraph (1)(b) and (c).

(3) As soon as practicable the court will hold a case management conference which must be fixed in accordance with Practice Direction 63.

Disclosure and inspection

63.9  Part 31 is modified to the extent set out in Practice Direction 63.

Application to amend a patent specification in existing proceedings

63.10

(1) An application under section 75 of the 1977 Act for permission to amend the specification of a patent by the proprietor of the patent must be made by application notice.

(2) The application notice must–

(a) give particulars of–

(i) the proposed amendment sought; and

(ii) the grounds upon which the amendment is sought;

(b) state whether the applicant will contend that the claims prior to the amendment are valid; and

(c) be served by the applicant on all parties and the Comptroller within 7 days of it being filed.

(3) The application notice must, if it is reasonably possible, be served on the Comptroller electronically.

(4) Unless the court otherwise orders, the Comptroller will, as soon as practicable, advertise the application to amend in the journal.

(5) The advertisement will state that any person may apply to the Comptroller for a copy of the application notice.

(6) Within 14 days of the first appearance of the advertisement any person who wishes to oppose the application must file and serve on all parties and the Comptroller a notice opposing the application which must include the grounds relied on.

(7) Within 28 days of the first appearance of the advertisement the applicant must apply to the court for directions.

(8) Unless the court otherwise orders, the applicant must within 7 days serve on the Comptroller any order of the court on the application.

(9) In this rule ‘the journal’ means the journal published pursuant to rules under section 123(6) of the 1977 Act.

Court’s determination of question or application

63.11

(1) This rule applies where the Comptroller –

(a) declines to deal with a question under section 8(7), 12(2), 37(8) or 61(5) of the 1977 Act;

(b) declines to deal with an application under section 40(5) of the 1977 Act; or

(c) certifies under section 72(7)(b) of the 1977 Act that the court should determine the question whether a patent should be revoked.

(2) Any person seeking the court’s determination of that question or application must start a claim for that purpose within 14 days of receiving notification of the Comptroller's decision.

(3) A person who fails to start a claim within the time prescribed by rule 63.11(2) will be deemed to have abandoned the reference or application.

(4) A party may apply to the Comptroller or the court to extend the period for starting a claim prescribed by rule 63.11(2) even where the application is made after expiration of that period.

Application by employee for compensation

63.12

(1) An application by an employee for compensation under section 40(1) or (2) of the 1977 Act must be made –

(a) in a claim form; and

(b) within the period prescribed by paragraphs (2), (3) and (4).

(2) The prescribed period begins on the date of the grant of the patent and ends 1 year after the patent has ceased to have effect.

(3) Where the patent has ceased to have effect as a result of failure to pay renewal fees, the prescribed period continues as if the patent has remained continuously in effect provided that–

(a) the renewal fee and any additional fee are paid in accordance with section 25(4) of the 1977 Act; or

(b) restoration is ordered by the Comptroller following an application under section 28 of the 1977 Act.

(4) Where restoration is refused by the Comptroller following an application under section 28 of the 1977 Act, the prescribed period will end 1 year after the patent has ceased to have effect or 6 months after the date of refusal, whichever is the later.

II REGISTERED TRADE MARKS AND OTHER INTELLECTUAL PROPERTY RIGHTS

Allocation

63.13  Claims relating to matters arising out of the 1994 Act and other intellectual property rights set out in Practice Direction 63 must be started in–

(a) the Chancery Division;

(b) the Intellectual Property Enterprise Court; or

(c) save as set out in Practice Direction 63, a county court where there is also a Chancery District Registry.

III SERVICE OF DOCUMENTS AND PARTICIPATION BY THE COMPTROLLER

Service of documents

63.14

(1) Subject to paragraph (2), Part 6 applies to service of a claim form and any document in any proceedings under this Part.

(2) A claim form relating to a registered right may be served –

(a) on a party who has registered the right at the address for service given for that right in the United Kingdom Patent Office register, provided the address is within the United Kingdom; or

(b) in accordance with rule 6.32(1), 6.33(1) or 6.33(2) on a party who has registered the right at the address for service given for that right in the appropriate register at–

(i) the United Kingdom Patent Office; or

(ii) the Office for Harmonisation in the Internal Market.

(3) Where a party seeks any remedy (whether by claim form, counterclaim or application notice), which would if granted affect an entry in any United Kingdom Patent Office register, that party must serve on the Comptroller or registrar –

(a) the claim form, counterclaim or application notice;

(b) any other statement of case where relevant (including any amended statement of case); and

(c) any accompanying documents.

Participation by the Comptroller

63.15  Where the documents set out in rule 63.14(3) are served, the Comptroller or registrar –

(a) may take part in proceedings; and

(b) need not serve a defence or other statement of case unless the court orders otherwise.

IV APPEALS

Appeals from decisions of the Comptroller or the registrar

63.16

(1) Part 52 applies to appeals from decisions of the Comptroller and the registrar.

(2) Appeals about patents must be made to the Patents Court, and other appeals to the Chancery Division.

(3) Where Part 52 requires a document to be served, it must also be served on the Comptroller or registrar, as appropriate.

V INTELLECTUAL PROPERTY ENTERPRISE COURT

Scope of this Section

63.17  This Part, as modified by this Section, applies to claims started in or transferred to the Intellectual Property Enterprise Court.

63.17A

(1) In proceedings in the Intellectual Property Enterprise Court in which a claim is made for damages or an account of profits, the amount or value of that claim shall not exceed £500,000.

(2) In determining the amount or value of a claim for the purpose of paragraph (1), a claim for—

(a) interest, other than interest payable under an agreement; or

(b) costs,

shall be disregarded.

(3) Paragraph (1) shall not apply if the parties agree that the Intellectual Property Enterprise Court shall have jurisdiction to award damages or profits in excess of £500,000.

Transfer of proceedings

63.18

(1) Rule 30.5 applies save for the modifications—

(a) a judge sitting in the County Court or the general Chancery Division may order proceedings to be transferred to the Intellectual Property Enterprise Court; and

(b) an application for the transfer of proceedings from the County Court or the general Chancery Division to the Intellectual Property Enterprise Court may be made to a judge sitting in the County Court or the general Chancery Division respectively.

(2) When considering whether to transfer proceedings to or from the Intellectual Property Enterprise Court, the court will have regard to the provisions of Practice Direction 30.

Enterprise judges and district judges

63.19

(1) Subject to paragraph (2), proceedings in the Intellectual Property Enterprise Court will be dealt with by an enterprise judge.

(1A) For the purposes of the Practice Direction 52A – Appeals: General Provisions, a decision of the enterprise judge shall be treated as a decision by a circuit judge hearing a specialist claim in the County Court.

(2) Unless the court otherwise orders, the following matters will be dealt with by a district judge—

(a) allocation of claims to the small claims track or multi-track in accordance with rule 63.27(3);

(b) claims allocated to the small claims track; and

(c) all proceedings for the enforcement of any financial element of an Intellectual Property Enterprise Court judgment.

(3) For the purposes of the Practice Direction 52A – Appeals: General Provisions, a decision of a district judge shall be treated as a decision by a district judge hearing a specialist claim in the County Court. An appeal from such a decision shall be heard by an enterprise judge.

Statements of case

63.20

(1) Part 16 applies with the modification that a statement of case must set out concisely all the facts and arguments upon which the party serving it relies.

(2) The particulars of claim must state whether the claimant has complied with paragraph 7.1(1) and Annex A (paragraph 2) of the Practice Direction (Pre-Action Conduct).

Statement of truth

63.21  Part 22 applies with the modification that the statement of truth verifying a statement of case must be signed by a person with knowledge of the facts alleged, or if no one person has knowledge of all the facts, by persons who between them have knowledge of all the facts alleged.

Defence and reply

63.22

(1) Rule 63.7 does not apply and Part 15 applies with the following modifications.

(2) Where the particulars of claim contain a confirmation in accordance with rule 63.20(2), the period for filing a defence where the defendant files an acknowledgment of service under Part 10 is 42 days after service of the particulars of claim unless rule 15.4(2) provides for a longer period to do so.

(3) Where the particulars of claim do not contain a confirmation in accordance with rule 63.20(2), the period for filing a defence where the defendant files an acknowledgment of service under Part 10 is 70 days after service of the particulars of claim.

(4) Where the claimant files a reply to a defence it must be filed and served on all other parties within 28 days of service of the defence.

(5) Where the defendant files a reply to a defence to a counterclaim it must be filed and served on all other parties within 14 days of service of the defence to the counterclaim.

(6) The periods in this rule may only be extended by order of the court and for good reason.

Case management

63.23

(1) At the first case management conference after those defendants who intend to file and serve a defence have done so, the court will identify the issues and decide whether to make an order in accordance with paragraph 29.1 of Practice Direction 63.

(2) Save in exceptional circumstances the court will not permit a party to submit material in addition to that ordered under paragraph (1).

(3) The court may determine the claim on the papers where all parties consent.

Disclosure and inspection

63.24

(1) Rule 63.9 does not apply.

(2) Part 31 applies save that the provisions on standard disclosure do not apply.

Applications

63.25

(1) Part 23 applies with the modifications set out in this rule.

(2) Except at the case management conference provided for in rule 63.23(1), a respondent to an application must file and serve on all relevant parties a response within 5 days of the service of the application notice.

(3) The court will deal with an application without a hearing unless the court considers it necessary to hold a hearing.

(4) An application to transfer the claim to the Patents Court or general Chancery Division or to stay proceedings must be made before or at the case management conference provided for in rule 63.23(1).

(5) The court will consider an application to transfer the claim later in the proceedings only where there are exceptional circumstances.

Costs

63.26

(1) Subject to paragraph (2), the court will reserve the costs of an application to the conclusion of the trial when they will be subject to summary assessment.

(2) Where a party has behaved unreasonably the court may make an order for costs at the conclusion of the hearing.

(3) Where the court makes a summary assessment of costs, it will do so in accordance with Section IV of Part 45.

Allocation to the small claims track

63.27

(1) A claim started in or transferred to the Intellectual Property Enterprise Court will be allocated to the small claims track if–

(a) rule 63.13, but not rule 63.2, applies to the claim;

(b) the value of the claim is not more than £10,000;

(c) it is stated in the particulars of claim that the claimant wishes the claim to be allocated to the small claims track; and

(d) no objection to the claim being allocated to the small claims track is raised by the defendant in the defence.

(2) Omitted.

(3) If either –

(a) the requirements of rule 63.27(1)(a), (b) and (c) are satisfied, but in the defence the defendant objects to the claim being allocated to the small claims track; or

(b) the requirements of rule 63.27(1)(a) and (b) are satisfied, but not (c), and in the defence the defendant requests that the claim be allocated to the small claims track,

the court will allocate the claim to the small claims track or the multi-track in accordance with Part 26 (case management – preliminary stage). For that purpose the court will send the parties a directions questionnaire and require them to file completed directions questionnaires and to serve them on all other parties within 14 days.

(4) Part 27 (small claims track) shall apply to claims allocated to the small claims track in the Intellectual Property Enterprise Court with the modification to rule 27.2(1)(a) that Part 25 (interim remedies) shall not apply to such claims at all. Section IV of Part 45 (scale costs for claims in the Intellectual Property Enterprise Court) shall not apply to claims allocated to the small claims track in the Intellectual Property Enterprise Court.

Extent to which rules in this Part apply to small claims

63.28

(1) To the extent provided by this rule, this Part shall apply to a claim allocated to, or requested to be allocated to, the small claims track in the Intellectual Property Enterprise Court.

(2) Rules 63.1, 63.13, 63.18, 63.20, 63.21, 63.22, 63.25, 63.26(1) and (2), and 63.27 shall apply to the claim.

(3) No other rules in this Part shall apply.

Footnotes

1977 c. 37. Back to text
1988 c. 48. Back to text
1994 c. 26. Back to text
OJ No L182, 2.7.1992, p.1. Back to text
OJ No L198, 8.8.1996, p.30. Back to text
1981 c. 54. Back to text
1949 c. 88. Back to text
OJ No L11, 14.1.1994, p.1. Back to text
OJ No L3, 5.1.2002, p.1. Back to text
S.I. 1998/1027. Back to text
1958 c. 38. Back to text

PRACTICE DIRECTION 64A – ESTATES, TRUSTS AND CHARITIES

This Practice Direction supplements Part 64

Contents of this Practice Direction

Title | Number
I CLAIMS RELATING TO THE ADMINISTRATION OF ESTATES AND TRUSTS |

Examples of claims under rule 64.2(a) | Para. 1
Determining certain claims under rule 64.2(a) without a hearing | Para. 1A.1
Applications by trustees for directions | Para. 2
Administration orders – rule 64.2(b) | Para. 3.1
Applications under the Variation of Trusts Act 1958 – rule 64.2(c) | Para. 4.1
Applications under section 48 of the Administration of Justice Act 1985 – rule 64.2(d) | Para. 5
Prospective costs orders | Para. 6.1
II CHARITY PROCEEDINGS |

Role of Attorney-General | Para. 7
Service on Charity Commissioners or Attorney-General | Para. 8
Applications for permission to take charity proceedings – rule 64.6 | Para. 9.1
Appeals against orders of the Charity Commissioners | Para. 10
Appendix |

I CLAIMS RELATING TO THE ADMINISTRATION OF ESTATES AND TRUSTS

Examples of claims under rule 64.2(a)

1  The following are examples of the types of claims which may be made under rule 64.2(a) –

(1) a claim for the determination of any of the following questions –

(a) any question as to who is included in any class of persons having –

(i) a claim against the estate of a deceased person;

(ii) a beneficial interest in the estate of such a person; or

(iii) a beneficial interest in any property subject to a trust;

(b) any question as to the rights or interests of any person claiming –

(i) to be a creditor of the estate of a deceased person;

(ii) to be entitled under a will or on the intestacy of a deceased person; or

(iii) to be beneficially entitled under a trust;

(2) a claim for any of the following remedies –

(a) an order requiring a trustee –

(i) to provide and, if necessary, verify accounts;

(ii) to pay into court money which he holds in that capacity; or

(iii) to do or not to do any particular act;

(b) an order approving any sale, purchase, compromise or other transaction by a trustee (whether administrative or dispositive); or

(c) an order directing any act to be done which the court could order to be done if the estate or trust in question were being administered or executed under the direction of the court.

Determining certain claims under rule 64.2(a) without a hearing

1A.1  Where a claim is made by a trustee for a remedy within paragraph 1(2)(b) (including a case where the remedy sought is approval of a transaction affected by conflict of interests or duties), the court may be requested to determine the claim without a hearing.

1A.2  The claim form in such a case may be issued in accordance with rule 8.2A (Issue of claim form without naming defendants), and no separate application for permission under rule 8.2A need be made.

1A.3  The claim form must be accompanied by –

(a) a witness statement setting out the material facts justifying determination without a hearing and in particular –

(i) identifying those affected by the remedy sought and

(ii) detailing any consultation of those so affected and the result of that consultation;

(b) the advice of a lawyer having a 10-year High Court qualification within the meaning of section 71 of the Courts and Legal Services Act 1990 on the merits of the claim;

(c) a draft order for the remedy sought;

(d) a statement of costs.

1A.4  If the court considers that the case does not require an oral hearing, it will proceed to consider the claim on the papers.

1A.5  If the court considers that an oral hearing is required, it will give appropriate directions.

1A.6  If the court considers it appropriate, it will make the order sought and may direct that the claimant must –

(a) serve notice of the order on the interested parties in accordance with rule 19.8A, and

(b) file a certificate of service within 7 days of doing so.

Applications by trustees for directions

2  A separate practice direction contains guidance about applications by trustees for directions.

Administration orders – rule 64.2(b)

3.1  The court will only make an administration order if it considers that the issues between the parties cannot properly be resolved in any other way.

3.2  If, in a claim for an administration order, the claimant alleges that the trustees have not provided proper accounts, the court may –

(1) stay the proceedings for a specified period, and order them to file and serve proper accounts within that period; or

(2) if necessary to prevent proceedings by other creditors or persons claiming to be entitled to the estate or fund, make an administration order and include in it an order that no such proceedings are to be taken without the court's permission.

3.3  Where an administration order has been made in relation to the estate of a deceased person, and a claim is made against the estate by any person who is not a party to the proceedings –

(1) no party other than the executors or administrators of the estate may take part in any proceedings relating to the claim without the permission of the court; and

(2) the court may direct or permit any other party to take part in the proceedings, on such terms as to costs or otherwise as it thinks fit.

3.4  Where an order is made for the sale of any property vested in trustees, those persons shall have the conduct of the sale unless the court directs otherwise.

Applications under the Variation of Trusts Act 1958 – rule 64.2(c)

4.1  Where children or unborn beneficiaries will be affected by a proposed arrangement under the Act, the evidence filed in support of the application must –

(1) show that their litigation friends or the trustees support the arrangements as being in the interests of the children or unborn beneficiaries; and

(2) unless paragraph 4.3 applies or the court orders otherwise, be accompanied by a written opinion to this effect by the advocate who will appear on the hearing of the application.

4.2  A written opinion filed under paragraph 4.1(2) must –

(1) if it is given on formal instructions, be accompanied by a copy of those instructions; or

(2) otherwise, state fully the basis on which it is given.

4.3  No written opinion needs to be filed in support of an application to approve an arrangement under section 1(1)(d) of the Act (discretionary interests under protective trusts).

4.4  Where the interests of two or more children, or two or more of the children and unborn beneficiaries, are similar, only a single written opinion needs to be filed.

Applications under section 48 of the Administration of Justice Act 1985 – rule 64.2(d)

5  A Part 8 claim form for an application by trustees under section 48 of the Administration of Justice Act 1985 (power of High Court to authorise action to be taken in reliance on legal opinion) may be issued without naming a defendant, under rule 8.2A. No separate application for permission under rule 8.2A need be made.

Prospective costs orders

6.1  These paragraphs are about the costs of applications under rule 64.2(a).

6.2  Where trustees have power to agree to pay the costs of a party to such an application, and exercise such a power, rule 44.5 applies. In such a case, an order is not required and the trustees are entitled to recover out of the trust fund any costs which they pay pursuant to the agreement made in the exercise of such power.

6.3  Where the trustees do not have, or decide not to exercise, a power to make such an agreement, the trustees or the party concerned may apply to the court at any stage of proceedings for an order that the costs of any party (including the costs of the trustees) shall be paid out of the fund (a ‘prospective costs order’).

6.4  The court, on an application for a prospective costs order, may –

(a) in the case of the trustees' costs, authorise the trustees to raise and meet such costs out of the fund;

(b) in the case of the costs of any other party, authorise or direct the trustees to pay such costs (or any part of them, or the costs incurred up to a particular time) out of the trust fund to be assessed, if not agreed by the trustees, on the indemnity basis or, if the court directs, on the standard basis, and to make payments from time to time on account of such costs. A model form of order is annexed to this Practice Direction.

6.5  The court will always consider whether it is possible to deal with the application for a prospective costs order on paper without a hearing and in an ordinary case would expect to be able to do so. The trustees must consider whether a hearing is needed for any reason. If they consider that it is they should say so and explain why in their evidence. If any party to the application referred to in paragraph 6.1 above (or any other person interested in the trust fund) considers that a hearing is necessary (for instance because he wishes to oppose the making of a prospective costs order) this should be stated, and the reasons explained, in his evidence, if any, or otherwise in a letter to the court.

6.6  If the court would be minded to refuse the application on a consideration of the papers alone, the parties will be notified and given the opportunity, within a stated time, to ask for a hearing.

6.7  The evidence in support of an application for a prospective costs order should be given by witness statement. The trustees and the applicant (if different) must ensure full disclosure of the relevant matters to show that the case is one which falls within the category of case where a prospective costs order can properly be made.

6.8  The model form of order is designed for use in the more straightforward cases, where a question needs to be determined which has arisen in the administration of the trust, whether the claimants are the trustees or a beneficiary. The form may be adapted for use in less straightforward cases, in particular where the proceedings are hostile, but special factors may also have to be reflected in the terms of the order in such a case.

II CHARITY PROCEEDINGS

Role of Attorney-General

7  The Attorney-General is a necessary party to all charity proceedings, other than any commenced by the Charity Commissioners, and must be joined as a defendant if he is not a claimant.

Service on Charity Commissioners or Attorney-General

8  Any document required or authorised to be served on the Commissioners or the Attorney-General must be served on the Treasury Solicitor in accordance with paragraph 2.1 of Practice Direction 66.

Applications for permission to take charity proceedings – rule 64.6

9.1  The claim form for an application under section 33(5) of the Act must state –

(1) the name, address and description of the applicant;

(2) details of the proceedings which he wishes to take;

(3) the date of the Commissioners' refusal to grant an order authorising the taking of proceedings;

(4) the grounds on which the applicant alleges that it is a proper case for taking proceedings; and

(5) if the application is made with the consent of any other party to the proposed proceedings, that fact.

9.2  If the Commissioners have given reasons for refusing to grant an order, a copy of their reasons must be filed with the claim form.

Appeals against orders of the Charity Commissioners

10  Part 52 applies to any appeal against an order of the Charity Commissioners. Section III of Practice Direction 52 contains special provisions about such appeals.

Appendix

Model form of prospective costs order (PDF - opens in new window)

PRACTICE DIRECTION 64B – APPLICATIONS TO THE COURT FOR DIRECTIONS BY TRUSTEES IN RELATION TO THE ADMINISTRATION OF THE TRUST

This Practice Direction supplements Section I of Part 64

Contents of this Practice Direction

Title | Number
Contents of the claim form | Para. 2
Proceedings in private | Para. 3
Joining defendants or giving notice to those interested | Para. 4.1
Case management directions | Para. 5.1
Proceeding without a hearing | Para. 6.1
Evidence | Para. 7.1
Consultation with beneficiaries | Para. 7.7

1

This Practice Direction is about applications to the court for directions by trustees in relation to the administration of the trust.

Contents of the claim form

2

If confidentiality of the directions sought is important (for example, where the directions relate to actual or proposed litigation with a third party who could find out what directions the trustees are seeking through access to the claim form under CPR rule 5.4) the statement of the remedy sought, for the purposes of CPR rule 8.2(b), may be expressed in general terms. The trustees must, in that case, state specifically in the evidence what it is that they seek to be allowed to do.

Proceedings in private

3

The proceedings will in the first instance be listed in private (see paragraph 1.5 of Practice Direction 39A and rule 39.2(3)(f)). Accordingly the order made, as well as the other documents among the court records (apart from a claim form which has been served), will not be open to inspection by third parties without the court's permission (rule 5.4(2)). If the matter is disposed of without a hearing, the order made will be expressed to have been made in private.

Joining defendants or giving notice to those interested

4.1

Rule 64.4(1)(c) deals with the joining of beneficiaries as defendants. Often, especially in the case of a private trust, it will be clear that some, and which, beneficiaries need to be joined as defendants. Sometimes, if there are only two views of the appropriate course, and one is advocated by one beneficiary who will be joined, it may not be necessary for other beneficiaries to be joined since the trustees may be able to present the other arguments. Equally, in the case of pension trust, it may not be necessary for a member of every possible different class of beneficiaries to be joined.

4.2

In some cases the court may be able to assess whether or not to give the directions sought, or what directions to give, without hearing from any party other than the trustees. If the trustees consider that their case is in that category they may apply to the court to issue the claim form without naming any defendants under rule 8.2A. They must apply to the court before the claim form is issued (rule 8.2A(2)) and include a copy of the claim form that they propose to issue (rule 8.2A(3)(b)).

4.3

In other cases the trustees may know that beneficiaries need to be joined as defendants, or to be given notice, but may be in doubt as to which. Examples could include a case concerning a pension scheme with many beneficiaries and a number of different categories of interest, especially if they may be differently affected by the action for which directions are sought, or a private trust with a large class of discretionary beneficiaries. In those cases the trustees may apply to issue the claim form without naming any defendants under rule 8.2A. The application may be combined with an application to the court for directions as to which persons to join as parties or to give notice to under rule 19.8A.

4.4

In the case of a charitable trust the Attorney-General is always the appropriate defendant, and almost always the only one.

Case management directions

5.1

The claim will be referred to the master or district judge once a defendant has acknowledged service, or otherwise on expiry of the period for acknowledgment of service, (or, if no defendant is named, as soon as the claimants' evidence has been filed) to consider directions for the management of the case. Such directions may be given without a hearing in some cases; these might include directions as to parties or as to notice of proceedings, as mentioned in paragraph 4 above.

Proceeding without a hearing

6.1

(1) The court will dispose of the application without a hearing if it considers that to do so will save time or expense, and that a hearing is not necessary. The trustees must therefore consider whether a hearing is necessary and, if so, explain why in their evidence.

(2) When considering whether to hold a hearing, the court will take into account any dispute between the parties as to directions, but will not necessarily direct a hearing for that reason alone.

(3) If a defendant considers that a hearing is needed, and that the need is not sufficiently explained in the trustees’ evidence, that defendant should so state in evidence, giving reasons why.

6.2

Where the court deals with an application without a hearing, it will in any order give the parties an opportunity, within a stated time, to apply to vary or discharge the order at an oral hearing.

6.3

In charity cases, the master or district judge may deal with the case without a hearing on the basis of a letter by or on behalf of the Attorney-General that sets out his attitude to the application.

Evidence

7.1

The trustees' evidence should be given by witness statement. In order to ensure that, if directions are given, the trustees are properly protected by the order, they must ensure full disclosure of relevant matters, even if the case is to proceed with the participation of beneficiaries as defendants.

7.2

Applications for directions whether or not to take or defend or pursue litigation should be supported by evidence of the following matters –

(1) the advice of an appropriately qualified lawyer as to the prospects of success;

(2) an estimate in summary form of –

(a) the value or other significance to the trust estate of the issues in the proceedings;

(b) the costs likely to be incurred by the trustees in the proceedings, by reference to the principal stages in the proceedings; and

(c) the costs of other parties to the proceedings for which, if unsuccessful, the trustees may be exposed to liability;

(3) any known facts concerning the means of other parties to the proceedings; and

(4) any other factors relevant to the court’s decision whether to give the directions sought.

7.3

References in this practice direction to an appropriately qualified lawyer mean one whose qualifications and experience are appropriate to the circumstances of the case. The qualifications should be stated. If the advice is given on formal instructions, the instructions should always be put in evidence as well, so that the court can see the basis on which the advice was given. If it is not, the advice must state fully the basis on which it is given.

7.4

All applications for directions should be supported by evidence showing the value of the trust assets, the significance of the proposed litigation or other course of action for the trust, and why the court's directions are needed.In the case of a pension trust the evidence should include the latest actuarial valuation, and should describe the membership profile and, if a deficit on winding up is likely, the priority provisions and their likely effect.

7.5

On an application for directions about actual or possible litigation the evidence should also state whether (i) the Practice Direction (Pre-Action Conduct) or any relevant Pre-Action Protocol has been complied with; and (ii) the trustees have proposed or undertaken, or intend to propose, mediation by ADR, and (in each case) if not why not.

7.6

If a beneficiary of the trust is a party to the litigation about which directions are sought, with an interest opposed to that of the trustees, that beneficiary should be a defendant to the trustees' application, but any material which would be privileged as regards that beneficiary in the litigation should be put in evidence as exhibits to the trustees' witness statement, and should not be served on the beneficiary. However if the trustees' representatives consider that no harm would be done by the disclosure of all or some part of the material, then that material should be served on that defendant. That defendant may also be excluded from part of the hearing, including that which is devoted to discussion of the material withheld.

Consultation with beneficiaries

7.7

The evidence must explain what, if any, consultation there has been with beneficiaries, and with what result. In preparation for an application for directions in respect of litigation, the following guidance is to be followed:

(1) If the trust is a private trust where the beneficiaries principally concerned are not numerous and are all or mainly adult, identified and traceable, the trustees will be expected to have canvassed with all the adult beneficiaries the proposed or possible courses of action before applying for directions.

(2) If it is a private trust with a larger number of beneficiaries, including those not yet born or identified, or children, it is likely that there will nevertheless be some adult beneficiaries principally concerned, with whom the trustees must consult.

(3) In relation to a charitable trust the trustees must have consulted the Attorney-General, through the Treasury Solicitor, as well as the Charity Commissioners whose consent to the application will have been needed under section 33 of the Charities Act 1993.

(4) In relation to a pension trust, unless the members are very few in number, no particular steps by way of consultation with beneficiaries (including, where relevant, employers) or their representatives are required in preparation for the application, though the trustees' evidence should describe any consultation that has in fact taken place. If no consultation has taken place, the court could in some cases direct that meetings of one or more classes of beneficiaries be held to consider the subject matter of the application, possibly as a preliminary to deciding whether a member of a particular class ought to be joined as a defendant, though in a case concerning actual or proposed litigation, steps would need to be considered to protect privileged material from too wide disclosure.

7.8

(1) If the court gives directions allowing the trustees to take, defend or pursue litigation it may do so up to a particular stage in the litigation, requiring the trustees, before they carry on beyond that point, to renew their application to the court. What stage that should be will depend on the likely management of the litigation under the CPR. If the application is to be renewed after disclosure of documents, and disclosed documents need to be shown to the court, it may be necessary to obtain permission to do this from the court in which the other litigation is proceeding.

(2) In such a case the court will if possible deal with the matter without a hearing, and in deciding whether to do so will take into account the advice of an appropriately qualified lawyer supporting the continuation by the trustees of the pursuit or defence (as the case may be) of the proceedings.

7.9

In a case of urgency, such as where a limitation period or period for service of proceedings is about to expire, the court may be able to give directions on a summary consideration of the evidence to cover the steps which need to be taken urgently, but limiting those directions so that the application needs to be renewed on fuller consideration at an early stage.

7.10

In any application for directions where a child is a defendant, the court will expect to have put before it the instructions to and advice of an appropriately qualified lawyer as to the benefits and disadvantages of the proposed, and any other relevant, course of action from the point of view of the child beneficiary.

7.11

The master or district judge may give the directions sought though, if the directions relate to actual or proposed litigation, only if it is a plain case, and therefore the master or district judge may think it appropriate to give the directions without a hearing: see Practice Direction 2B, para 4.1 and para. 5.1(e), and see also paragraph 6 above. Otherwise the case will be referred to the judge.

7.12

Where a hearing takes place, if the advice of a lawyer has been put in evidence in accordance with paragraph 7.2 or 7.10, that lawyer should if possible appear on the hearing.

PART 65 - PROCEEDINGS RELATING TO ANTI-SOCIAL BEHAVIOUR AND HARASSMENT

Scope of this Part

65.1

This Part contains rules –

(a) in Section I, about injunctions under the Housing Act 1996[1];

(b) in Section II, about applications by local authorities under section 91(3) of the Anti-social Behaviour Act 2003[2] for a power of arrest to be attached to an injunction;

(c) in Section III, about claims for demotion orders under the Housing Act 1985[3] and Housing Act 1988[4] and proceedings relating to demoted tenancies;

(d) in Section IV, about anti-social behaviour orders under the Crime and Disorder Act 1998[5];

(e) in Section V, about claims under section 3 of the Protection from Harassment Act 1997[6];

(f) in Section VI, about applications for drinking banning orders and interim drinking banning orders under sections 4 and 9 of the Violent Crime Reduction Act 2006;

(g) in Section VII, about parenting orders under sections 26A and 26B of the Anti-social Behaviour Act 2003[7]; and

(h) in Section VIII, about injunctions under the Policing and Crime Act 2009.

I HOUSING ACT 1996 INJUNCTIONS

Scope of this Section and interpretation

65.2

(1) This Section applies to applications for an injunction and other related proceedings under Chapter III of Part V of the Housing Act 1996 (injunctions against anti-social behaviour).

(2) In this Section ‘the 1996 Act’means the Housing Act 1996.

Applications for an injunction

65.3

(1) An application for an injunction under Chapter III of Part V of the 1996 Act shall be subject to the Part 8 procedure as modified by this rule and Practice Direction 65.

(2) The application must be –

(a) made by a claim form in accordance with Practice Direction 65;

(b) commenced in the court for the district in which the defendant resides or the conduct complained of occurred; and

(c) supported by a witness statement which must be filed with the claim form.

(3) The claim form must state–

(a) the matters required by rule 8.2; and

(b) the terms of the injunction applied for.

(4) An application under this rule may be made without notice and where such an application without notice is made–

(a) the witness statement in support of the application must state the reasons why notice has not been given; and

(b) the following rules do not apply –

(i) 8.3;

(ii) 8.4;

(iii) 8.5(2) to (6);

(iv) 8.6(1);

(v) 8.7; and

(vi) 8.8.

(5) In every application made on notice, the application notice must be served, together with a copy of the witness statement, by the claimant on the defendant personally.

(6) An application made on notice may be listed for hearing before the expiry of the time for the defendant to file an acknowledgement of service under rule 8.3, and in such a case –

(a) the claimant must serve the application notice and witness statement on the defendant not less than two days before the hearing; and

(b) the defendant may take part in the hearing whether or not he has filed an acknowledgment of service.

Injunction containing provisions to which a power of arrest is attached

65.4

(1) In this rule ‘relevant provision’ means a provision of an injunction to which a power of arrest is attached.

(Sections 153C(3) and 153D(4) of the 1996 Act[8] confer powers to attach a power of arrest to an injunction)

(2) Where an injunction contains one or more relevant provisions –

(a) each relevant provision must be set out in a separate paragraph of the injunction; and

(b) subject to paragraph (3), the claimant must deliver a copy of the relevant provisions to any police station for the area where the conduct occurred.

(3) Where the injunction has been granted without notice, the claimant must not deliver a copy of the relevant provisions to any police station for the area where the conduct occurred before the defendant has been served with the injunction containing the relevant provisions.

(4) Where an order is made varying or discharging any relevant provision, the claimant must –

(a) immediately inform the police station to which a copy of the relevant provisions was delivered under paragraph (2)(b); and

(b) deliver a copy of the order to any police station so informed.

Application for warrant of arrest under section 155(3) of the 1996 Act[9]

65.5

(1) An application for a warrant of arrest under section 155(3) of the 1996 Act must be made in accordance with Part 23 and may be made without notice.

(2) An applicant for a warrant of arrest under section 155(3) of the 1996 Act must –

(a) file an affidavit setting out grounds for the application with the application notice; or

(b) give oral evidence as to the grounds for the application at the hearing.

Proceedings following arrest

65.6

(1) This rule applies where a person is arrested pursuant to –

(a) a power of arrest attached to a provision of an injunction; or

(b) a warrant of arrest.

(2) The judge before whom a person is brought following his arrest may –

(a) deal with the matter; or

(b) adjourn the proceedings.

(3) Where the proceedings are adjourned the judge may remand the arrested person in accordance with section 155(2)(b) or (5) of the 1996 Act.

(4) Where the proceedings are adjourned and the arrested person is released –

(a) the matter must be dealt with (whether by the same or another judge) within 28 days of the date on which the arrested person appears in court; and

(b) the arrested person must be given not less than 2 days' notice of the hearing.

(5) An application notice seeking the committal for contempt of court of the arrested person may be issued even if the arrested person is not dealt with within the period mentioned in paragraph (4)(a).

(6) Sections 2 and 8 of Part 81 apply where an application is made in a county court to commit a person for breach of an injunction, as if references in those Sections to the judge included references to a district judge.

(For applications for the discharge of a person committed to prison for contempt of court see rules 81.31 and 81.32.)

Recognizance

65.7

(1) Where, in accordance with paragraph 2(2)(b) of Schedule 15 to the 1996 Act, the court fixes the amount of any recognizance with a view to it being taken subsequently, the recognizance may be taken by –

(a) a judge;

(b) a justice of the peace;

(c) a justices' clerk;

(d) a police officer of the rank of inspector or above or in charge of a police station; or

(e) where the arrested person is in his custody, the governor or keeper of a prison,

with the same consequences as if it had been entered into before the court.

(2) The person having custody of an applicant for bail must release him if satisfied that the required recognizances have been taken.

II APPLICATIONS BY LOCAL AUTHORITIES FOR POWER OF ARREST TO BE ATTACHED TO AN INJUNCTION

Scope of this Section and interpretation

65.8

(1) This Section applies to applications by local authorities under section 91(3) of the Anti-social Behaviour Act 2003[10] or under section 27(3) of the Police and Justice Act 2006[11] for a power of arrest to be attached to an injunction.

(Section 91 of the 2003 Act and section 27 of the 2006 Act apply to proceedings in which a local authority is a party by virtue of section 222 of the Local Government Act 1972[12] (power of local authority to bring, defend or appear in proceedings for the promotion or protection of the interests of inhabitants in their area)

(2) In this Section ‘the 2003 Act’means the Anti-social Behaviour Act 2003.

(3) In this Section ‘the 2006 Act’means the Police and Justice Act 2006.

Applications under section 91(3) of the 2003 Act or section 27(3) of the 2006 Act for a power of arrest to be attached to any provision of an injunction

65.9

(1) An application under section 91(3) of the 2003 Act or section 27(3) of the 2006 Act for a power of arrest to be attached to any provision of an injunction must be made in the proceedings seeking the injunction by –

(a) the claim form;

(b) the acknowledgment of service;

(c) the defence or counterclaim in a Part 7 claim; or

(d) application under Part 23.

(2) Every application must be supported by written evidence.

(3) Every application made on notice must be served personally, together with a copy of the written evidence, by the local authority on the person against whom the injunction is sought not less than 2 days before the hearing.

(Attention is drawn to rule 25.3(3) – applications without notice)

Injunction containing provisions to which a power of arrest is attached

65.10

(1) Where a power of arrest is attached to a provision of an injunction on the application of a local authority under section 91(3) of the 2003 Act, the following rules in Section I of this Part shall apply –

(a) rule 65.4; and

(b) paragraphs (1), (2), (4) and (5) of rule 65.6.

(1A) Where a power of arrest is attached to a provision of an injunction on the application of a local authority under section 27(3) of the 2006 Act, the following rules in Section I of this Part apply –

(a) rule 65.4;

(b) paragraphs (1), (2), (4) and (5) of rule 65.6;

(c) paragraph (1) of rule 65.7, as if the reference to paragraph 2(2)(b) of Schedule 15 to the Housing Act 1996[13] was a reference to paragraph 2(2)(b) of Schedule 10 to the 2006 Act; and

(d) paragraph (2) of rule 65.7.

(2) CCR Order 29, rule 1 shall apply where an application is made in a county court to commit a person for breach of an injunction.

III DEMOTION CLAIMS, PROCEEDINGS RELATED TO DEMOTED TENANCIES AND APPLICATIONS TO SUSPEND THE RIGHT TO BUY

Scope of this Section and interpretation

65.11

(1) This Section applies to –

(a) claims by a landlord for an order under section 82A of the Housing Act 1985[14] or under section 6A of the Housing Act 1988[15] (‘a demotion order’);

(aa) claims by a landlord for an order under section 121A of the Housing Act 1985 (‘a suspension order’); and

(b) proceedings relating to a tenancy created by virtue of a demotion order.

(2) In this Section –

(a) ‘a demotion claim’ means a claim made by a landlord for a demotion order;

(b) ‘a demoted tenancy’ means a tenancy created by virtue of a demotion order;

(c) ‘suspension claim’ means a claim made by a landlord for a suspension order; and

(d) ‘suspension period’ means the period during which the suspension order suspends the right to buy in relation to the dwelling house.

Demotion claims or suspension claims made in the alternative to possession claims

65.12

Where a demotion order or suspension order (or both) is claimed in the alternative to a possession order, the claimant must use the Part 55 procedure and Section I of Part 55 applies, except that the claim must be made in the county court for the district in which the property to which the claim relates is situated.

Other demotion or suspension claims

65.13

Where a demotion claim or suspension claim (or both) is made other than in a possession claim, rules 65.14 to 65.19 apply.

Starting a demotion or suspension claim

65.14

(1) The claim must be made in the county court for the district in which the property to which the claim relates is situated.

(2) The claim form and form of defence sent with it must be in the forms set out in Practice Direction 65.

(Part 16 and Practice Direction 65 provide details about the contents of the particulars of claim)

Particulars of claim

65.15

The particulars of claim must be filed and served with the claim form.

Hearing date

65.16

(1) The court will fix a date for the hearing when it issues the claim form.

(2) The hearing date will be not less than 28 days from the date of issue of the claim form.

(3) The standard period between the issue of the claim form and the hearing will be not more than 8 weeks.

(4) The defendant must be served with the claim form and the particulars of claim not less than 21 days before the hearing date.

(Rule 3.1(2)(a) provides that the court may extend or shorten the time for compliance with any rule and rule 3.1(2)(b) provides that the court may adjourn or bring forward a hearing)

Defendant's response

65.17

(1) An acknowledgement of service is not required and Part 10 does not apply.

(2) Where the defendant does not file a defence within the time specified in rule 15.4 he may take part in any hearing but the court may take his failure to do so into account when deciding what order to make about costs.

(3) Part 12 (default judgment) does not apply.

The hearing

65.18

(1) At the hearing fixed in accordance with rule 65.16(1) or at any adjournment of that hearing the court may–

(a) decide the claim; or

(b) give case management directions.

(2) Where the claim is genuinely disputed on grounds which appear to be substantial, case management directions given under paragraph (1)(b) will include the allocation of the claim to a track or directions to enable it to be allocated.

(3) Except where –

(a) the claim is allocated to the fast track or the multi-track; or

(b) the court directs otherwise,

any fact that needs to be proved by the evidence of witnesses at a hearing referred to in paragraph (1) may be proved by evidence in writing.

(Rule 32.2(1) sets out the general rule about evidence. Rule 32.2(2) provides that rule 32.2(1) is subject to any provision to the contrary)

(4) All witness statements must be filed and served at least two days before the hearing.

(5) Where the claimant serves the claim form and particulars of claim, the claimant must produce at the hearing a certificate of service of those documents and rule 6.17(2)(a) does not apply.

Allocation

65.19

When the court decides the track for the claim, the matters to which it shall have regard include –

(a) the matters set out in rule 26.8; and

(b) the nature and extent of the conduct alleged.

Proceedings relating to demoted tenancies

65.20

A practice direction may make provision about proceedings relating to demoted tenancies.

IV ANTI-SOCIAL BEHAVIOUR ORDERS UNDER THE CRIME AND DISORDER ACT 1998

Scope of this Section and interpretation

65.21

(1) This Section applies to applications in proceedings in a county court under sub-sections (2), (3) or (3B) of section 1B of the Crime and Disorder Act 1998[16] by a relevant authority, and to applications for interim orders under section 1D of that Act.

(2) In this Section –

(a) ‘the 1998 Act’ means the Crime and Disorder Act 1998;

(b) ‘relevant authority’ has the same meaning as in section 1(1A) of the 1998 Act; and

(c) ‘the principal proceedings’ means any proceedings in a county court.

Application where the relevant authority is a party in principal proceedings

65.22

(1) Subject to paragraph (2) –

(a) where the relevant authority is the claimant in the principal proceedings, an application under section 1B(2) of the 1998 Act for an order under section 1B(4) of the 1998 Act must be made in the claim form; and

(b) where the relevant authority is a defendant in the principal proceedings, an application for an order must be made by application notice which must be filed with the defence.

(2) Where the relevant authority becomes aware of the circumstances that lead it to apply for an order after its claim is issued or its defence filed, the application must be made by application notice as soon as possible thereafter.

(3) Where the application is made by application notice, it should normally be made on notice to the person against whom the order is sought.

Application by a relevant authority to join a person to the principal proceedings

65.23

(1) An application under section 1B(3B) of the 1998 Act by a relevant authority which is a party to the principal proceedings to join a person to the principal proceedings must be made–

(a) in accordance with Section I of Part 19;

(b) in the same application notice as the application for an order under section 1B(4) of the 1998 Act against the person; and

(c) as soon as possible after the relevant authority considers that the criteria in section 1B(3A) of the 1998 Act are met.

(2) The application notice must contain–

(a) the relevant authority's reasons for claiming that the person's anti-social acts are material in relation to the principal proceedings; and

(b) details of the anti-social acts alleged.

(3) The application should normally be made on notice to the person against whom the order is sought.

Application where the relevant authority is not party in principal proceedings

65.24

(1) Where the relevant authority is not a party to the principal proceedings –

(a) an application under section 1B(3) of the 1998 Act to be made a party must be made in accordance with Section I of Part 19; and

(b) the application to be made a party and the application for an order under section 1B(4) of the 1998 Act must be made in the same application notice.

(2) The applications –

(a) must be made as soon as possible after the authority becomes aware of the principal proceedings; and

(b) should normally be made on notice to the person against whom the order is sought.

Evidence

65.25

An application for an order under section 1B(4) of the 1998 Act must be accompanied by written evidence, which must include evidence that section 1E of the 1998 Act has been complied with.

Application for an interim order

65.26

(1) An application for an interim order under section 1D of the 1998 Act must be made in accordance with Part 25.

(2) The application should normally be made –

(a) in the claim form or application notice seeking the order; and

(b) on notice to the person against whom the order is sought.

V PROCEEDINGS UNDER THE PROTECTION FROM HARASSMENT ACT 1997

Scope of this Section

65.27

This Section applies to proceedings under section 3 of the Protection from Harassment Act 1997[17] (‘the 1997 Act’).

Claims under section 3 of the 1997 Act

65.28

A claim under section 3 of the 1997 Act –

(a) shall be subject to the Part 8 procedure; and

(b) must be commenced –

(i) if in the High Court, in the Queen's Bench Division;

(ii) if in the county court, in the court for the district in which the defendant resides or carries on business or the court for the district in which the claimant resides or carries on business.

Applications for issue of a warrant of arrest under section 3(3) of the 1997 Act

65.29

(1) An application for a warrant of arrest under section 3(3) of the 1997 Act –

(a) must be made in accordance with Part 23; and

(a) may be made without notice.

(2) The application notice must be supported by affidavit evidence which must –

(a) set out the grounds for the application;

(b) state whether the claimant has informed the police of the conduct of the defendant as described in the affidavit; and

(c) state whether, to the claimant's knowledge, criminal proceedings are being pursued.

Proceedings following arrest

65.30

(1) The judge before whom a person is brought following his arrest may –

(a) deal with the matter; or

(b) adjourn the proceedings.

(2) Where the proceedings are adjourned and the arrested person is released –

(a) the matter must be dealt with (whether by the same or another judge) within 28 days of the date on which the arrested person appears in court; and

(b) the arrested person must be given not less than 2 days' notice of the hearing.

VI DRINKING BANNING ORDERS UNDER THE VIOLENT CRIME REDUCTION ACT 2006[18]

Scope of this Section and interpretation

65.31

(1) This Section applies to applications in proceedings in a county court under sub-sections (2), (3) or (5) of section 4 of the Violent Crime Reduction Act 2006 by a relevant authority, and to applications for interim orders under section 9 of that Act.

(2) In this Section –

(a) ‘the 2006 Act’ means the Violent Crime Reduction Act 2006;

(b) ‘relevant authority’ has the same meaning as in section 14(1) of the 2006 Act; and

(c) ‘the principal proceedings’ means any proceedings in a county court.

Application where the relevant authority is a party in principal proceedings

65.32

(1) Subject to paragraph (2) –

(a) where the relevant authority is the claimant in the principal proceedings, an application under section 4(2) of the 2006 Act for an order under section 4(7) of the 2006 Act must be made in the claim form; and

(b) where the relevant authority is a defendant in the principal proceedings, an application for an order must be made by application notice which must be filed with the defence.

(2) Where the relevant authority becomes aware of the circumstances that lead it to apply for an order after its claim is issued or its defence filed, the application must be made by application notice as soon as possible thereafter.

(3) Where the application is made by application notice, it should normally be made on notice to the person against whom the order is sought.

Application where the relevant authority is not a party in principal proceedings

65.33

(1) Where the relevant authority is not a party to the principal proceedings –

(a) an application under section 4(3) of the 2006 Act to be made a party must be made in accordance with Section I of Part 19; and

(b) the application to be made a party and the application for an order under section 4(7) of the 2006 Act must be made in the same application notice.

(2) The applications –

(a) must be made as soon as possible after the relevant authority becomes aware of the principal proceedings; and

(b) should normally be made on notice to the person against whom the order is sought.

Application by a relevant authority to join a person to the principal proceedings

65.34

(1) An application under section 4(5) of the 2006 Act by a relevant authority which is a party to the principal proceedings to join a person to the principal proceedings must be made–

(a) in accordance with Section I of Part 19;

(b) in the same application notice as the application for an order under section 4(7) of the 2006 Act against the person; and

(c) as soon as possible after the relevant authority considers that the criteria in section 4(4) of the 2006 Act are met.

(2) The application notice must contain–

(a) the relevant authority’s reasons for claiming that the person's conduct is material in relation to the principal proceedings; and

(b) details of the conduct alleged.

(3) The application should normally be made on notice to the person against whom the order is sought.

Evidence

65.35

An application for an order under section 4(7) of the 2006 Act must be accompanied by written evidence, which must include evidence that section 4(6) of the 2006 Act has been complied with.

Application for an interim order

65.36

(1) An application for an interim order under section 9 of the 2006 Act must be made in accordance with Part 25.

(2) The application should normally be made –

(a) in the claim form or application notice seeking the order; and

(b) on notice to the person against whom the order is sought.

(3) An application for an interim order may be –

(a) made without a copy of the application notice being served on the person against whom the order is sought;

(b) heard in the absence of the person against whom the order is sought,

with the permission of the court.

VII PARENTING ORDERS UNDER THE ANTI-SOCIAL BEHAVIOUR ACT 2003

Scope of this Section and interpretation

65.37

(1) This Section of this Part applies in relation to applications for parenting orders under sections 26A and 26B of the Anti-social Behaviour Act 2003 by a relevant authority.

(2) In this Section –

(a) ‘the 2003 Act’ means the Anti-social Behaviour Act 2003; and

(b) ‘relevant authority’ has the same meaning as in section 26C of the 2003 Act.

Applications for parenting orders

65.38

(1) Subject to paragraph (2) –

(a) where the relevant authority is the claimant in the proceedings, an application for an order under section 26A or 26B of the 2003 Act must be made in the claim form; and

(b) where the relevant authority is a defendant in the proceedings, an application for such an order must be made by application notice which must be filed with the defence.

(2) Where the relevant authority becomes aware of the circumstances that lead it to apply for an order after its claim is issued or its defence filed, the application must be made by application notice as soon as possible thereafter.

(3) Where the application is made by application notice, it must normally be made on notice to the person against whom the order is sought.

Applications by the relevant authority to be joined to proceedings

65.39

(1) Where the relevant authority is not a party to the proceedings –

(a) an application under section 26C(2) of the 2003 Act to be made a party must be made in accordance with Section I of Part 19; and

(b) the application to be made a party and the application for an order under section 26A or 26B of the 2003 Act must be made in the same application notice.

(2) The applications –

(a) must be made as soon as possible after the relevant authority becomes aware of the proceedings; and

(b) must normally be made on notice to the person against whom the order is sought.

Applications by the relevant authority to join a parent to proceedings

65.40

(1) An application under section 26C(3) of the 2003 Act by a relevant authority which is a party to the proceedings to join a parent to those proceedings must be made –

(a) in the same application notice as the application for an order under section 26A or 26B of the 2003 Act; and

(b) as soon as possible after the relevant authority considers that the grounds for the application are met.

(2) Rule 19.2 does not apply in relation to an application made by a relevant authority under section 26C(3) of the 2003 Act to join a parent to the proceedings.

(3) The application notice must contain–

(a) the relevant authority’s reasons for claiming the anti-social behaviour of the child or young person is material in relation to the proceedings; and

(b) details of the behaviour alleged.

(4) The application must normally be made on notice to the person against whom the order is sought.

Evidence

65.41

An application under section 26A, 26B or 26C of the 2003 Act must be accompanied by written evidence.

VIII INJUNCTIONS UNDER THE POLICING AND CRIME ACT 2009

Scope of this Section and interpretation

65.42

(1) This Section applies to applications for an injunction and other related proceedings under Part 4 of the Policing and Crime Act 2009[19] (Injunctions: gang-related violence).

(2) In this Section ‘the 2009 Act’means the Policing and Crime Act 2009.

Applications for an injunction

65.43

(1) An application for an injunction under Part 4 of the 2009 Act is subject to the Part 8 procedure as modified by this rule and Practice Direction 65.

(2) The application must be –

(a) made by a claim form in accordance with Practice Direction 65;

(b) commenced in the court for the district in which the defendant resides or the conduct complained of occurred; and

(c) supported by a witness statement which must be filed with the claim form.

(3) The claim form must state–

(a) the matters required by rule 8.2; and

(b) the terms of the injunction applied for.

(4) An application under this rule may be made without notice and where such an application without notice is made–

(a) the witness statement in support of the application must state the reasons why notice has not been given; and

(b) the following rules do not apply –

(i) 8.3;

(ii) 8.4;

(iii) 8.5(2) to (6);

(iv) 8.6(1);

(v) 8.7; and

(vi) 8.8.

(5) In every application made on notice, the application notice must be served, together with a copy of the witness statement, by the claimant on the defendant personally.

(6) An application made on notice may be listed for hearing before the expiry of the time for the defendant to file an acknowledgement of service under rule 8.3, and in such a case –

(a) the claimant must serve the application notice and witness statement on the defendant not less than 2 days before the hearing; and

(b) the defendant may take part in the hearing whether or not the defendant has filed an acknowledgment of service.

Injunction containing provisions to which a power of arrest is attached

65.44

(1) In this rule ‘relevant provision’ means a provision of an injunction to which a power of arrest is attached.

(Section 36(6) and (7) and section 40(3) and 41(4) of the 2009 Act confer powers to attach a power of arrest to an injunction.)

(2) Where an injunction contains one or more relevant provisions –

(a) each relevant provision must be set out in a separate paragraph of the injunction; and

(b) subject to paragraph (3), the claimant must deliver a copy of the relevant provisions to any police station for the area where the conduct occurred.

(3) Where the injunction has been granted without notice, the claimant must not deliver a copy of the relevant provisions to any police station for the area where the conduct occurred before the defendant has been served with the injunction containing the relevant provisions.

(4) Where an order is made varying or discharging any relevant provision, the claimant must –

(a) immediately inform the police station to which a copy of the relevant provisions was delivered under paragraph (2)(b); and

(b) deliver a copy of the order to any police station so informed.

Application to vary or discharge an injunction

65.45

(1) An application to vary or discharge an injunction under section 42(1)(b) of the 2009 Act must be made in accordance with Part 23.

(2) An application by the claimant to vary or discharge the injunction under section 42(1)(b) of the 2009 Act may be made without notice.

(3) If an application under this rule is made without giving notice, the application notice must state the reasons why notice has not been given.

Application for warrant of arrest under section 44(2) of the 2009 Act

65.46

(1) An application for a warrant of arrest under section 44(2) of the 2009 Act must be made in accordance with Part 23 and may be made without notice.

(2) An applicant for a warrant of arrest under section 44(2) of the 2009 Act must –

(a) file an affidavit setting out grounds for the application with the application notice; or

(b) give oral evidence of the grounds for the application at the hearing.

(3) Where in accordance with sub-paragraph (2)(b), oral evidence is given, the applicant must produce a written record of that evidence which must be served on the person arrested at the time of the arrest.

Proceedings following arrest under the 2009 Act

65.47

(1) This rule applies where a person is arrested pursuant to –

(a) a power of arrest attached to a provision of an injunction; or

(b) a warrant of arrest.

(2) The judge before whom a person is brought following his arrest may –

(a) deal with the matter; or

(b) adjourn the proceedings.

(3) If proceedings under section 43 or 44 of the 2009 Act are adjourned and the arrested person is released –

(a) the matter must be dealt with (whether by the same or another judge) within 28 days of the date on which the arrested person appears in court; and

(b) the arrested person must be given not less than 2 days’ notice of the hearing.

(4) An application notice seeking the committal for contempt of court of the arrested person may be issued even if the arrested person is not dealt with within the period in subparagraph (3)(a).

(5) Sections 2 and 8 of Part 81 apply where an application is made in a county court to commit a person for breach of an injunction as if references in those Sections to the judge include references to a district judge.

(For applications for the discharge of a person committed to prison for contempt of court see rules 81.31 and 81.32.)

Recognizance

65.48

(1) Where, in accordance with paragraph 2(2)(b) of Schedule 5 to the 2009 Act, the court fixes the amount of any recognizance with a view to it being taken subsequently, the recognizance may be taken by –

(a) a judge;

(b) a justice of the peace;

(c) a justices’clerk;

(d) a police officer of the rank of inspector or above, or in charge of a police station; or

(e) where the arrested person is in custody, the governor or keeper of a prison,

with the same consequences as if it had been entered into before the court.

(2) The person having custody of an applicant for bail must release that person if satisfied that the required recognizances have been taken.

Applications for a power of arrest to be attached to any provision of an injunction

65.49

(1) An application under section 34 or 39 of the 2009 Act which includes an application for a power of arrest to be attached to any provision of an injunction must be made in the proceedings seeking the injunction by –

(a) the claim form; or

(b) an application under Part 23.

(2) Every application must be supported by written evidence.

(3) Every application made on notice must be served personally, together with a copy of the written evidence, by the applicant on the person against whom the injunction is sought not less than 2 days before the hearing.

(Attention is drawn to rule 25.3(3) – applications without notice.)

Footnotes

1. 1996 c.52. Return to footnote 1

2. 2003 c.38. Return to footnote 2

3. 1985 c.68. Return to footnote 3

4. 1988 c.50. Return to footnote 4

5. 1998 c.37. Return to footnote 5

6. 1997 c.40. Return to footnote 6

7. 2003 c. 38. Section 24 of the Police and Justice Act 2006 (c. 48) inserts sections 26A, 26B and 26C into the Anti-social Behaviour Act 2003. Return to footnote 7

8. 1996 c.52. These sections were inserted by section 13 of the Anti-social Behaviour Act 2003. Return to footnote 8

9. 1996 c.52. This section was amended by section 13 of the Anti-social Behaviour Act 2003. Return to footnote 9

10. 2003 c.38. Return to footnote 10

11. 2006 c. 48. Return to footnote 11

12. 1972 c.70. Return to footnote 12

13. 1996 c. 52. Return to footnote 13

14. 1985 c.68. This section was inserted by section 14 of the Anti-social Behaviour Act 2003. Return to footnote 14

15. 1988 c.50. This section was inserted by section 14 of the Anti-social Behaviour Act 2003. Return to footnote 15

16. 1998 c.37. Sections 1(1A) and 1B were amended by section 85 of the Anti-social Behaviour Act 2003 (c.38). Return to footnote 16

17. 1997 c.40. Return to footnote 17

18. 2006 c. 38. Return to footnote 18

19. 2009 c. 26. Return to footnote 19

PRACTICE DIRECTION 66 – CROWN PROCEEDINGS

This Practice Direction supplements CPR Part 66

Contents of this Practice Direction

Title | Number
Transfer |
Service of Documents |
ANNEX 1 |
ANNEX 2 |

Transfer

1.1

Rule 30.3(2) sets out the circumstances to which the court must have regard when considering whether to make an order under section 40(2), 41(1) or 42(2) of the County Courts Act 1984 (transfer between the High Court and County Court), rule 30.2(1) (transfer between county courts) or rule 30.2(4) (transfer between the Royal Courts of Justice and the district registries).

1.2

From time to time the Attorney General will publish a note concerning the organisation of the Government Legal Service and matters relevant to the venue of Crown proceedings, for the assistance of practitioners and judges. When considering questions of venue under rule 30.3(2), the court should have regard to the Attorney General's note in addition to all the other circumstances of the case.

Service of Documents

2.1

In civil proceedings by or against the Crown, documents required to be served on the Crown must be served in accordance with rule 6.10 or 6.23(7).

(The list published under section 17 of the Crown Proceedings Act 1947 of the solicitors acting for the different government departments on whom service is to be effected, and of their addresses is annexed to this Practice Direction).

ANNEX 1Disputes as to Venue – Factors to be taken into Consideration

Attorney General’s Note to Supplement the Practice Direction

Introduction

Until the recent rule changes, the Crown was entitled in High Court matters to insist that venue was the Royal Courts of Justice in London (RCJ) (RSC O77, rule 2). This rule has now been revoked. A new rule 30.3(2)(h) provides that in cases involving civil proceedings by or against the Crown, when considering whether to order a transfer of those proceedings, the court must have regard to, ‘the location of the relevant government department or officers of the Crown and, where appropriate, any relevant public interest that the matter should be tried in London.’

The Practice Direction to Part 66, at paragraph 2, provides that the Attorney-General will publish a note concerning the organisation of the Government Legal Service and matters relevant to the venue of Crown Proceedings, for the assistance of practitioners and judges. When considering questions of venue under rule 30.3(2), the court should have regard to the Attorney-General’s note in addition to all the other circumstances of the case.

This note sets out the further factors to be taken into consideration where there is a dispute as to venue between a claimant and a government department. Where there is such a dispute, it should be dealt with at a case management conference.

Organisation of the Government Legal Service

The Government Legal Service (GLS) has the responsibility for advising the Government about its legal affairs and has the conduct of civil litigation on its behalf. The Treasury Solicitor conducts this litigation for the majority of Government Departments but lawyers in HM Revenue and Customs, the Department for the Environment, Food and Rural Affairs and the Department for Work and Pensions (which also acts for the Department of Health and the Food Standards Agency) have the conduct of litigation for their Departments. All Government litigation lawyers are based in the London with the exception of HM Revenue and Customs, whose personal injury lawyers are in Manchester. A full list of addresses for service is annexed to the Practice Direction accompanying Part 66 of the CPR.

Factors be taken into account generally

Location

Whilst a number of government departments have offices outside London, central government bodies are based in London and the GLS is geared towards processing claims in the RCJ (see above). Where there is a High Court claim, many witnesses as well as lawyers and officials are London based and there may be a disproportionate cost in transferring them to a venue outside London. That is not to say, bearing in mind the overriding objective, that the Crown would oppose transfer away from the RCJ where it was appropriate, for example in personal injury disputes.

Precedent value

Some cases have important precedent value or are of general importance to the public, which may make them more suitable for being heard in the RCJ.

Special Considerations in relation to HM Revenue and Customs

HM Revenue and Customs has no lawyers outside London, except for those personal injury lawyers based in Manchester.

The work of HM Revenue and Customs is very specialised, needing in many cases to be dealt with by specialist judges in the Chancery Division familiar, for example, with tax work.

There is also the public interest to consider. All revenue cases (including those of HM Revenue and Customs) have important precedent value that applies across the entire tax system, with implications for the Exchequer.

ANNEX 2

List of Authorised Government Departments (PDF - opens in new window)

PART 70 - GENERAL RULES ABOUT ENFORCEMENT OF JUDGMENTS AND ORDERS

Contents of this Part

Title | Number
Scope of this Part and interpretation | Rule 70.1
Methods of enforcing judgments or orders | Rule 70.2
Transfer of proceedings for enforcement | Rule 70.3
Enforcement of judgment or order by or against non-party | Rule 70.4
Enforcement of decisions of bodies other than the High Court and county courts and compromises enforceable by enactment | Rule 70.5
Effect of setting aside judgment or order | Rule 70.6

Scope of this Part and interpretation

70.1

(1) This Part contains general rules about enforcement of judgments and orders.

(Rules about specific methods of enforcement are contained in Parts 71 to 73, Schedule 1 RSC Orders 45 to 47 and 52 and Schedule 2 CCR Orders 25 to 29)

(2) In this Part and in Parts 71 to 73 –

(a) ‘judgment creditor’ means a person who has obtained or is entitled to enforce a judgment or order;

(b) ‘judgment debtor’ means a person against whom a judgment or order was given or made;

(c) ‘judgment or order’ includes an award which the court has –

(i) registered for enforcement;

(ii) ordered to be enforced; or

(iii) given permission to enforce

as if it were a judgment or order of the court, and in relation to such an award, ‘the court which made the judgment or order’ means the court which registered the award or made such an order; and

(d) ‘judgment or order for the payment of money’ includes a judgment or order for the payment of costs, but does not include a judgment or order for the payment of money into court.

Methods of enforcing judgments or orders

70.2

(1) Practice Direction 70 sets out methods of enforcing judgments or orders for the payment of money.

(2) A judgment creditor may, except where an enactment, rule or practice direction provides otherwise –

(a) use any method of enforcement which is available; and

(b) use more than one method of enforcement, either at the same time or one after another.

Transfer of proceedings for enforcement

70.3

(1) A judgment creditor wishing to enforce a High Court judgment or order in a county court must apply to the High Court for an order transferring the proceedings to that county court.

(2) A practice direction may make provisions about the transfer of proceedings for enforcement.

(CCR Order 25 rule 13 contains provisions about the transfer of county court proceedings to the High Court for enforcement.)

Enforcement of judgment or order by or against non-party

70.4

If a judgment or order is given or made in favour of or against a person who is not a party to proceedings, it may be enforced by or against that person by the same methods as if he were a party.

Enforcement of decisions of bodies other than the High Court and county courts and compromises enforceable by enactment

70.5

(1) This rule applies, subject to paragraph (2), where an enactment provides that –

(a) a decision of a court, tribunal, body or person other than the High Court or a county court; or

(b) a compromise,

may be enforced as if it were a court order or that any sum of money payable under that decision or compromise may be recoverable as if payable under a court order.

(2) This rule does not apply to –

(a) any judgment to which Part 74 applies;

(b) arbitration awards;

(c) any order to which RSC Order 115 applies; or

(d) proceedings to which Part 75 (traffic enforcement) applies.

(2A) Unless paragraph (3) applies, a party may enforce the decision or compromise by applying for a specific method of enforcement under Parts 71 to 73, Schedule 1 RSC Orders 45 to 47 and 52 and Schedule 2 CCR Orders 25 to 29 and must –

(a) file with the court a copy of the decision or compromise being enforced; and

(b) provide the court with the information required by Practice Direction 70.

(3) If an enactment provides that a decision or compromise is enforceable or a sum of money is recoverable if a court so orders, an application for such an order must be made in accordance with paragraphs (4) to (7A) of this rule.

(4) The application –

(a) may, unless paragraph (4A) applies, be made without notice; and

(b) must be made to the court for the district where the person against whom the order is sought, resides or carries on business, unless the court otherwise orders.

(4A) Where a compromise requires a person to whom a sum of money is payable under the compromise to do anything in addition to discontinuing or not starting proceedings (‘a conditional compromise’), an application under paragraph (4) must be made on notice.

(5) The application notice must –

(a) be in the form; and

(b) contain the information

required by Practice Direction 70.

(6) A copy of the decision or compromise must be filed with the application notice.

(7) An application other than in relation to a conditional compromise may be dealt with by a court officer without a hearing.

(7A) Where an application relates to a conditional compromise, the respondent may oppose it by filing a response within 14 days of service of the application notice and if the respondent –

(a) does not file a response within the time allowed, the court will make the order; or

(b) files a response within the time allowed, the court will make such order as appears appropriate.

(8) If an enactment provides that a decision or compromise may be enforced in the same manner as an order of the High Court if it is registered, any application to the High Court for registration must be made in accordance with Practice Direction 70.

Effect of setting aside judgment or order

70.6

If a judgment or order is set aside, any enforcement of the judgment or order shall cease to have effect unless the court otherwise orders.

PART 71 - ORDERS TO OBTAIN INFORMATION FROM JUDGMENT DEBTORS

Scope of this Part

71.1

This Part contains rules which provide for a judgment debtor to be required to attend court to provide information, for the purpose of enabling a judgment creditor to enforce a judgment or order against him.

Order to attend court

71.2

(1) A judgment creditor may apply for an order requiring –

(a) a judgment debtor; or

(b) if a judgment debtor is a company or other corporation, an officer of that body,

to attend court to provide information about –

(i) the judgment debtor's means; or

(ii) any other matter about which information is needed to enforce a judgment or order.

(2) An application under paragraph (1) –

(a) may be made without notice; and

(b) must be issued in the court which made the judgment or order which it is sought to enforce, except that –

(i) if the proceedings have since been transferred to a different court, it must be issued in that court; or

(ii) subject to subparagraph (b)(i), if it is to enforce a judgment made in Northampton County Court in respect of a designated money claim, it must be issued in accordance with section 2 of Practice Direction 70.

(3) The application notice must –

(a) be in the form; and

(b) contain the information

required by Practice Direction 71.

(4) An application under paragraph (1) may be dealt with by a court officer without a hearing.

(5) If the application notice complies with paragraph (3), an order to attend court will be issued in the terms of paragraph (6).

(6) A person served with an order issued under this rule must –

(a) attend court at the time and place specified in the order;

(b) when he does so, produce at court documents in his control which are described in the order; and

(c) answer on oath such questions as the court may require.

(7) An order under this rule will contain a notice in the following terms, or in terms to substantially the same effect –

“If you the within-named [    ] do not comply with this order you may be held to be in contempt of court and imprisoned or fined, or your assets may be seized.”

Service of order

71.3

(1) An order to attend court must, unless the court otherwise orders, be served personally on the person ordered to attend court not less than 14 days before the hearing.

(2) If the order is to be served by the judgment creditor, he must inform the court not less than 7 days before the date of the hearing if he has been unable to serve it.

Travelling expenses

71.4

(1) A person ordered to attend court may, within 7 days of being served with the order, ask the judgment creditor to pay him a sum reasonably sufficient to cover his travelling expenses to and from court.

(2) The judgment creditor must pay such a sum if requested.

Judgment creditor's affidavit

71.5

(1) The judgment creditor must file an affidavit[GL] or affidavits –

(a) by the person who served the order (unless it was served by the court) giving details of how and when it was served;

(b) stating either that –

(i) the person ordered to attend court has not requested payment of his travelling expenses; or

(ii) the judgment creditor has paid a sum in accordance with such a request; and

(c) stating how much of the judgment debt remains unpaid.

(2) The judgment creditor must either –

(a) file the affidavit[GL] or affidavits not less than 2 days before the hearing; or

(b) produce it or them at the hearing.

Conduct of the hearing

71.6

(1) The person ordered to attend court will be questioned on oath.

(2) The questioning will be carried out by a court officer unless the court has ordered that the hearing shall be before a judge.

(3) The judgment creditor or his representative –

(a) may attend and ask questions where the questioning takes place before a court officer; and

(b) must attend and conduct the questioning if the hearing is before a judge.

Adjournment of the hearing

71.7

If the hearing is adjourned, the court will give directions as to the manner in which notice of the new hearing is to be served on the judgment debtor.

Failure to comply with order

71.8

(1) If a person against whom an order has been made under rule 71.2 –

(a) fails to attend court;

(b) refuses at the hearing to take the oath or to answer any question; or

(c) otherwise fails to comply with the order,

the court will refer the matter to a High Court judge or circuit judge.

(2) That judge may, subject to paragraphs (3) and (4), make a committal order against the person.

(3) A committal order for failing to attend court may not be made unless the judgment creditor has complied with rules 71.4 and 71.5.

(4) If a committal order is made, the judge will direct that –

(a) the order shall be suspended provided that the person –

(i) attends court at a time and place specified in the order; and

(ii) complies with all the terms of that order and the original order; and

(b) if the person fails to comply with any term on which the committal order is suspended, he shall be brought before a judge to consider whether the committal order should be discharged.

(Part 81 contains provisions in relation to committal.)

PRACTICE DIRECTION 74B – EUROPEAN ENFORCEMENT ORDERS

This Practice Direction supplements Section V of Part 74

Contents of this Practice Direction

Title | Number
Council Regulation |
Rule 74.28 – Certification of Judgments of the Courts of England and Wales | Para. 2.1
Rule 74.29 – Applications for a certificate of lack of enforceability | Para. 3.1
Rule 74.30 – Application for rectification or withdrawal | Para. 4.1
Rule 74.31 – Enforcement of European Enforcement Orders in England and Wales | Para. 5.1
Rule 74.32 – An application for refusal of enforcement | Para. 6.1
Rule 74.33 – Stay or limitation of enforcement | Para. 7.1
Annex |

Council Regulation

1.1

Certification and enforcement of European Enforcement Orders is governed by Council Regulation (EC) No 805/2004 creating a European Enforcement Order for uncontested claims.

1.2

The EEO Regulation is annexed to this practice direction and can be found at http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2005:300:0006:0018:EN:pdf It was originally published in the official languages of the European Community in the Official Journal of the European Communities by the Office for Official Publications of the European Communities.

1.3

Section V of Part 74 sets out the procedure for enforcement under the EEO Regulation. A claim that does not meet the requirements of the EEO Regulation, or which the judgment creditor does not wish to enforce using the EEO Regulation, may be enforceable using another method of enforcement.

Rule 74.28 – Certification of Judgments of the Courts of England and Wales

2.1

An application under rule 74.28 for a certificate of a High Court or county court judgment for enforcement in another Regulation State must be made using Form N219 or Form N219A –

(1) in the case of a judgment given in the Chancery or Queen's Bench Division of the High Court, or in a district registry, to a Master, Registrar or district judge; or

(2) in the case of a county court judgment, to a district judge.

2.2

Where the application is granted, the court will send the EEO certificate and a sealed copy of the judgment to the person making the application. Where the court refuses the application, the court will give reasons for the refusal and may give further directions.

Rule 74.29 – Applications for a certificate of lack of enforceability

3.1

An application must be supported by written evidence in support of the grounds on which the judgment has ceased to be enforceable or its enforceability has been suspended or limited.

Rule 74.30 – Application for rectification or withdrawal

4.1

An application must be supported by written evidence in support of the grounds on which it is contended that the EEO should be rectified or withdrawn.

Rule 74.31 – Enforcement of European Enforcement Orders in England and Wales

5.1

When an EEO is lodged at the court in which enforcement proceedings are to be brought, it will be assigned a case number.

5.2

A copy of a document will satisfy the conditions necessary to establish its authenticity if it is an official copy of the court of origin.

5.3

If judgment is set aside in the court of origin, the judgment creditor must notify all courts in which enforcement proceedings are pending in England and Wales under the EEO as soon as reasonably practicable after the order is served on the judgment creditor. Notification may be by any means available including fax, e-mail, post or telephone.

Rule 74.32 – An application for refusal of enforcement

6.1

An application must be accompanied by an official copy of the earlier judgment, any other documents relied upon and any translations required by the EEO Regulation and supported by written evidence showing –

(1) why the earlier judgment is irreconcilable with the judgment which the judgment creditor is seeking to enforce; and

(2) why the irreconcilability was not, and could not have been, raised as an objection in the proceedings in the court of origin.

Rule 74.33 – Stay or limitation of enforcement

7.1

Unless the court orders otherwise, an application must be accompanied by evidence of the application in the court of origin, including –

(1) the application (or equivalent foreign process) or a copy of the application (or equivalent foreign process) certified by an appropriate officer of the court of origin; and

(2) where that document is not in English, a translation of it into English –

(a) certified by a notary public or person qualified to certify a translation in the Member State of the court of origin under Article 20(2)(c) of the EEO Regulation; or

(b) accompanied by written evidence confirming that the translation is accurate.

7.2

The written evidence in support of the application must state –

(1) that an application has been brought in the member state of origin;

(2) the nature of that application; and

(3) the date on which the application was filed, the state of the proceedings and the date by which it is believed that the application will be determined.

Annex

European Enforcement Order Regulation (PDF - opens in new window)

PRACTICE DIRECTION 78 – EUROPEAN PROCEDURES

This Practice Direction supplements CPR Part 78

EOP Regulation and application of the Civil Procedure Rules

1.1

EOP applications are primarily governed by the EOP Regulation. Where the EOP Regulation is silent, the Civil Procedure Rules apply with necessary modifications.

Rule 78.3 – Application for a European order for payment

2.1

An EOP application form A must be –

(1) completed in English or accompanied by a translation into English; and

(2) filed at court in person or by post.

2.2

An EOP application made to the High Court will be assigned to the Queen's Bench Division, but that will not prevent the application being transferred where appropriate.

Filing documents at court other than the EOP application form A

3

Documents other than the EOP application form A that are filed at or sent to the court in the EOP proceedings, including statements of opposition, may be filed, in addition to by post or in person, by –

(1) fax; or

(2) other electronic means where the facilities are available.

Service

4

Where the EOP Regulation is silent on service, the Service Regulation and the Civil Procedure Rules apply as appropriate.

Article 9 of the EOP Regulation – completion or rectification of the EOP application form A

5.1

Article 9 of the EOP Regulation makes provision for the completion or rectification of the EOP application form A within a specified time.

5.2

The time specified for the purposes of article 9 will normally be within 30 days of the date of the request by the court to complete or rectify the EOP application form A (using form B annexed to the EOP Regulation).

Applications under Part 23

6.1

Where an application is made under Section I of Part 78, there will not normally be an oral hearing.

6.2

Where an oral hearing is to be held, it will normally take place by telephone or video conference.

Rule 78.9 – Enforcement of European orders for payment

7.1

When an EOP is filed at the High Court or county court in which enforcement proceedings are to be brought, it will be assigned a case number.

7.2

A copy of a document will satisfy the conditions necessary to establish its authenticity if it is an official copy of the court of origin.

7.3

If judgment is set aside in the court of origin, the judgment creditor must notify all courts in which enforcement proceedings are pending in England and Wales under the EOP as soon as reasonably practicable after the order is served on the judgment creditor. Notification may be by any means available including fax, e-mail, post or telephone.

Rule 78.10 – An application for refusal of enforcement

8.1

An application must be accompanied by an official copy of the earlier judgment, any other documents relied upon and any translations required by the EOP Regulation.

8.2

Where the applicant relies on article 22(1) of the EOP Regulation, the application must be supported by written evidence showing –

(1) why the earlier judgment is irreconcilable with the judgment which the claimant is seeking to enforce; and

(2) why the irreconcilability was not, and could not have been, raised as an objection in the proceedings in the court of origin.

8.3

Where the applicant relies on article 22(2), the application must be supported by written evidence of the extent to which the defendant has paid the claimant the amount awarded in the EOP.

Rule 78.11 – Stay of or limitation on enforcement

9.1

Unless the court orders otherwise, an application must be accompanied by evidence of the review application in the court of origin, including –

(1) the review application or a copy of the review application certified by an appropriate officer of the court of origin; and

(2) where that document is not in English, a translation of it into English.

9.2

The written evidence in support of the application must state –

(1) that a review application has been brought in the Member State of origin;

(2) the nature of that review application; and

(3) the date on which the review application was filed, the stage the application has reached and the date by which it is believed that the application will be determined.

ESCP Regulation and application of the Civil Procedure Rules

10

Claims under the ESCP are primarily governed by the ESCP Regulation. Where the ESCP Regulation is silent, the Civil Procedure Rules apply with necessary modifications. In particular, Part 52 applies to any appeals.

Rule 78.13 – Filing an ESCP claim form

11

An ESCP claim form must be filed at court in person or by post.

Article 4(4) of the ESCP Regulation - inadequate or insufficient information

12.1

Article 4(4) of the ESCP Regulation makes provision for –

(1) the completion or rectification of the claim form;

(2) the supply of supplementary information or documents; or

(3) the withdrawal of the claim,

within a specified time.

12.2

The time specified for the purposes of article 4(4) is within 30 days of the date of the request by the court to complete or rectify the claim form (using Form B annexed to the ESCP Regulation).

Rule 78.14 – Allocation of ESCP claims

13.1

Rule 78.14(1) provides that ESCP claims are treated as if they were allocated to the small claims track. However, rule 78.14(2) disapplies rule 27.14 on costs because recital 29 to the ESCP Regulation contains different provisions on costs.

13.2

Rule 26.6(1) (scope of the small claims track) is also disapplied because article 2(1) of the ESCP Regulation has a different financial limit.

Filing documents at court other than the ESCP claim form

14

Documents other than the ESCP claim form that are filed at or sent to the court in the ESCP proceedings, including the defendant's response, may be filed, in addition to by post or in person, by –

(1) fax; or

(2) other electronic means where the facilities are available.

Service

15

Where the ESCP Regulation is silent on service, the Service Regulation and the Civil Procedure Rules apply as appropriate.

Rule 78.17 – Transfer of proceedings where the defendant claims that the non-monetary claim exceeds the limit set in article 2(1) of the ESCP Regulation – article 5(5) of the ESCP Regulation

16.1

Rule 78.17(7) applies to counterclaims as if the counterclaim were an ESCP claim because the second paragraph of article 5(7) of the ESCP Regulation applies certain provisions about claims in the ESCP Regulation, including article 5(5), to ESCP counterclaims.

16.2

Attention is also drawn to the first paragraph of article 5(7) of the ESCP Regulation (transfer of claim and counterclaim in certain circumstances).

Oral hearing under article 8 of the ESCP Regulation

17.1

Attention is drawn to article 5(1) of the ESCP Regulation, which sets out limitations on when oral hearings may be held.

17.2

Where an oral hearing is to be held, it will normally take place by telephone or video conference.

Applications under Part 23

18.1

Where an application is made under Section II of Part 78 there will not normally be an oral hearing.

18.2

Where an oral hearing is to be held, it will normally take place by telephone or video conference.

Rule 78.20 – Enforcement of an ESCP judgment

19.1

When an ESCP judgment is filed at the High Court or county court in which enforcement proceedings are to be brought, it will be assigned a case number.

19.2

A copy of a document will satisfy the conditions necessary to establish its authenticity if it is an official copy of the courts of the Member State of judgment.

19.3

If judgment is set aside in the Member State of judgment, the judgment creditor must notify all courts in which proceedings are pending in England and Wales to enforce the ESCP judgment as soon as reasonably practicable after the order is served on the judgment creditor. Notification may be by any means available including fax, e-mail, post or telephone.

Rule 78.21 – Application for refusal of enforcement

20.1

An application must be accompanied by an official copy of the earlier judgment, any other documents relied upon and any translations required by the ESCP Regulation.

20.2

The application must be supported by written evidence showing –

(1) why the earlier judgment is irreconcilable with the judgment which the claimant is seeking to enforce; and

(2) why the irreconcilability was not, and could not have been, raised as an objection in the proceedings in the Member State of judgment.

Rule 78.22 – Stay of or limitation on enforcement – application following application for review or where the judgment has been challenged

21.1

This paragraph applies where a defendant makes an application under article 23 of the ESCP Regulation in circumstances where –

(1) an application for review has been made under article 18 (‘review application’); or

(2) the defendant has challenged the judgment.

21.2

Unless the court orders otherwise, the application under article 23 must be accompanied by evidence of the review application or challenge in the Member State of judgment. This must include a copy of the document initiating the review application or challenge or a copy of the review application or challenge, certified by an appropriate officer of the court in the Member State of judgment.

21.3

Where a document is not in English, it must be accompanied by a translation of it into English.

21.4

The written evidence in support of the application must state –

(1) that a review application or challenge has been brought in the Member State of judgment;

(2) the nature of that review application or challenge; and

(3) the date on which the review application or challenge was filed, the state of the proceedings and the date by which it is believed that the application or challenge will be determined.

Rule 78.24 Making a mediation settlement enforceable (mediation settlement enforcement orders)

22.1

Where an application for a mediation settlement enforcement order is made under rule 78.24(1)(a) in accordance with Part 23, a copy of the application notice, mediation settlement agreement and evidence of explicit consent must be served on all parties to the mediation settlement agreement who are not also parties to the application.

22.2

Where an application for a mediation settlement enforcement order is made under rule 78.24(1)(b) by the Part 8 procedure –

(1) the claim form may be issued without naming a defendant; and

(2) a copy of the claim form, mediation settlement agreement and evidence of explicit consent must be served on all parties to the mediation settlement agreement who are not also parties to the application.

22.3

No document relating to an application for a mediation settlement enforcement order may be inspected by a person who is not a party to the proceedings under rule 5.4C without the permission of the court.

22.4

Where the application is supported by evidence of explicit consent to the application by a party to the mediation settlement agreement, the evidence must be in English or accompanied by a translation into English.

22.5

Where a party to the mediation settlement agreement writes to the court consenting to the making of the mediation settlement enforcement order, the correspondence must be in English or accompanied by a translation into English.

22.6

Where the parties to pending proceedings agree to apply for a mediation settlement enforcement order, they must inform the court immediately.

Annex 1

The EOP Regulation (PDF - opens in new window)

Annex 2

The ESCP Regulation (PDF - opens in new window)

Annex 3

EU Directive on Mediation (PDF - opens in new window)

PRACTICE DIRECTION – PRE-ACTION CONDUCT

PRACTICE DIRECTION – PRE-ACTION CONDUCT

Contents of this Practice Direction

SECTION I – INTRODUCTION

1. Aims

1.1  The aims of this Practice Direction are to –

(1) enable parties to settle the issue between them without the need to start proceedings (that is, a court claim); and

(2) support the efficient management by the court and the parties of proceedings that cannot be avoided.

1.2  These aims are to be achieved by encouraging the parties to –

(1) exchange information about the issue, and

(2) consider using a form of Alternative Dispute Resolution (‘ADR’).

2. Scope

2.1  This Practice Direction describes the conduct the court will normally expect of the prospective parties prior to the start of proceedings.

2.2  There are some types of application where the principles in this Practice Direction clearly cannot or should not apply. These include, but are not limited to, for example –

(1) applications for an order where the parties have agreed between them the terms of the court order to be sought (‘consent orders’);

(2) applications for an order where there is no other party for the applicant to engage with;

(3) most applications for directions by a trustee or other fiduciary;

(4) applications where telling the other potential party in advance would defeat the purpose of the application (for example, an application for an order to freeze assets).

2.3  Section II deals with the approach of the court in exercising its powers in relation to pre-action conduct. Subject to paragraph 2.2, it applies in relation to all types of proceedings including those governed by the pre-action protocols that have been approved by the Head of Civil Justice and which are listed in paragraph 5.2 of this Practice Direction.

2.4  Section III deals with principles governing the conduct of the parties in cases which are not subject to a pre-action protocol.

2.5  Section III of this Practice Direction is supplemented by two annexes aimed at different types of claimant.

(1) Annex A sets out detailed guidance on a pre-action procedure that is likely to satisfy the court in most circumstances where no pre-action protocol or other formal pre-action procedure applies. It is intended as a guide for parties, particularly those without legal representation, in straightforward claims that are likely to be disputed. It is not intended to apply to debt claims where it is not disputed that the money is owed and where the claimant follows a statutory or other formal pre-action procedure.

(2) Annex B sets out some specific requirements that apply where the claimant is a business and the defendant is an individual. The requirements may be complied with at any time between the claimant first intimating the possibility of court proceedings and the claimant’s letter before claim.

2.6  Section IV contains requirements that apply to all cases including those subject to the pre-action protocols (unless a relevant pre-action protocol contains a different provision). It is supplemented by Annex C, which sets out guidance on instructing experts.

3. Definitions

3.1  In this Practice Direction together with the Annexes –

(1) ‘proceedings’ means any proceedings started under Part 7 or Part 8 of the Civil Procedure Rules 1998 (‘CPR’);

(2) ‘claimant’ and ‘defendant’ refer to the respective parties to potential proceedings;

(3) ‘ADR’ means alternative dispute resolution, and is the collective description of methods of resolving disputes otherwise than through the normal trial process; (see paragraph 8.2 for further information); and

(4) ‘compliance’ means acting in accordance with, as applicable, the principles set out in Section III of this Practice Direction, the requirements in Section IV and a relevant pre-action protocol. The words ‘comply’ and ‘complied’ should be construed accordingly.

SECTION II – THE APPROACH OF THE COURTS

4. Compliance

4.1  The CPR enable the court to take into account the extent of the parties’ compliance with this Practice Direction or a relevant pre-action protocol (see paragraph 5.2) when giving directions for the management of claims (see CPR rule 3.1(4) and (5)) and when making orders about who should pay costs (see CPR rule 44.2(5)(a)).

4.2  The court will expect the parties to have complied with this Practice Direction or any relevant pre-action protocol. The court may ask the parties to explain what steps were taken to comply prior to the start of the claim. Where there has been a failure of compliance by a party the court may ask that party to provide an explanation.

Assessment of compliance

4.3  When considering compliance the court will –

(1) be concerned about whether the parties have complied in substance with the relevant principles and requirements and is not likely to be concerned with minor or technical shortcomings;

(2) consider the proportionality of the steps taken compared to the size and importance of the matter;

(3) take account of the urgency of the matter. Where a matter is urgent (for example, an application for an injunction) the court will expect the parties to comply only to the extent that it is reasonable to do so. (Paragraph 9.5 and 9.6 of this Practice Direction concern urgency caused by limitation periods.)

Examples of non-compliance

4.4  The court may decide that there has been a failure of compliance by a party because, for example, that party has –

(1) not provided sufficient information to enable the other party to understand the issues;

(2) not acted within a time limit set out in a relevant pre-action protocol, or, where no specific time limit applies, within a reasonable period;

(3) unreasonably refused to consider ADR (paragraph 8 in Part III of this Practice Direction and the pre-action protocols all contain similar provisions about ADR); or

(4) without good reason, not disclosed documents requested to be disclosed.

Sanctions for non-compliance

4.5  The court will look at the overall effect of non-compliance on the other party when deciding whether to impose sanctions.

4.6  If, in the opinion of the court, there has been non-compliance, the sanctions which the court may impose include –

(1) staying (that is suspending) the proceedings until steps which ought to have been taken have been taken;

(2) an order that the party at fault pays the costs, or part of the costs, of the other party or parties (this may include an order under rule 27.14(2)(g) in cases allocated to the small claims track);

(3) an order that the party at fault pays those costs on an indemnity basis (rule 44.3(3) sets out the definition of the assessment of costs on an indemnity basis);

(4) if the party at fault is the claimant in whose favour an order for the payment of a sum of money is subsequently made, an order that the claimant is deprived of interest on all or part of that sum, and/or that interest is awarded at a lower rate than would otherwise have been awarded;

(5) if the party at fault is a defendant, and an order for the payment of a sum of money is subsequently made in favour of the claimant, an order that the defendant pay interest on all or part of that sum at a higher rate, not exceeding 10% above base rate, than would otherwise have been awarded.

5. Commencement of pre-action protocols

5.1  When considering compliance, the court will take account of a relevant pre-action protocol if the proceedings were started after the relevant pre-action protocol came into force.

5.2  The following table sets out the pre-action protocols currently in force and the dates that they came into force –

SECTION III – THE PRINCIPLES GOVERNING THE CONDUCT OF THE PARTIES IN CASES NOT SUBJECT TO A PRE-ACTION PROTOCOL

6. Overview of principles

6.1  The principles that should govern the conduct of the parties are that, unless the circumstances make it inappropriate, before starting proceedings the parties should –

(1) exchange sufficient information about the matter to allow them to understand each other's position and make informed decisions about settlement and how to proceed;

(2) make appropriate attempts to resolve the matter without starting proceedings, and in particular consider the use of an appropriate form of ADR in order to do so.

6.2  The parties should act in a reasonable and proportionate manner in all dealings with one another. In particular, the costs incurred in complying should be proportionate to the complexity of the matter and any money at stake. The parties must not use this Practice Direction as a tactical device to secure an unfair advantage for one party or to generate unnecessary costs.

7. Exchanging information before starting proceedings

7.1  Before starting proceedings –

(1) the claimant should set out the details of the matter in writing by sending a letter before claim to the defendant. This letter before claim is not the start of proceedings; and

(2) the defendant should give a full written response within a reasonable period, preceded, if appropriate, by a written acknowledgment of the letter before claim.

7.2  A ‘reasonable period of time’ will vary depending on the matter. As a general guide –

(1) the defendant should send a letter of acknowledgment within 14 days of receipt of the letter before claim (if a full response has not been sent within that period);

(2) where the matter is straightforward, for example an undisputed debt, then a full response should normally be provided within 14 days;

(3) where a matter requires the involvement of an insurer or other third party or where there are issues about evidence, then a full response should normally be provided within 30 days;

(4) where the matter is particularly complex, for example requiring specialist advice, then a period of longer than 30 days may be appropriate;

(5) a period of longer than 90 days in which to provide a full response will only be considered reasonable in exceptional circumstances.

7.3  Annex A sets out detailed guidance on a pre-action procedure that is likely to satisfy the court in most circumstances where no pre-action protocol applies and where the claimant does not follow any statutory or other formal pre-action procedure.

7.4  Annex B sets out the specific information that should be provided in a debt claim by a claimant who is a business against a defendant who is an individual.

8. Alternative Dispute Resolution

8.1  Starting proceedings should usually be a step of last resort, and proceedings should not normally be started when a settlement is still actively being explored. Although ADR is not compulsory, the parties should consider whether some form of ADR procedure might enable them to settle the matter without starting proceedings. The court may require evidence that the parties considered some form of ADR (see paragraph 4.4(3)).

8.2  It is not practicable in this Practice Direction to address in detail how the parties might decide to resolve a matter. However, some of the options for resolving a matter without starting proceedings are –

(1) discussion and negotiation;

(2) mediation (a form of negotiation with the help of an independent person or body);

(3) early neutral evaluation (where an independent person or body, for example a lawyer or an expert in the subject, gives an opinion on the merits of a dispute); or

(4) arbitration (where an independent person or body makes a binding decision), many types of business are members of arbitration schemes for resolving disputes with consumers.

8.3  The Legal Services Commission has published a booklet on ‘Alternatives to Court’, CLS Direct Information Leaflet 23 (www.clsdirect.org.uk) which lists a number of organisations that provide alternative dispute resolution services. The National Mediation Helpline on 0845 603 0809 or at www.nationalmediationhelpline.com can provide information about mediation.

8.4  The parties should continue to consider the possibility of reaching a settlement at all times. This still applies after proceedings have been started, up to and during any trial or final hearing.

SECTION IV – REQUIREMENTS THAT APPLY IN ALL CASES

9. Specific provisions

9.1  The following requirements (including Annex C) apply in all cases except where a relevant pre-action protocol contains its own provisions about the topic.

Disclosure

9.2  Documents provided by one party to another in the course of complying with this Practice Direction or any relevant pre-action protocol must not be used for any purpose other than resolving the matter, unless the disclosing party agrees in writing.

Experts

9.4  Where the evidence of an expert is necessary the parties should consider how best to minimise expense. Guidance on instructing experts can be found in Annex C.

Limitation periods

9.5  There are statutory time limits for starting proceedings (‘the limitation period’). If a claimant starts a claim after the limitation period applicable to that type of claim has expired the defendant will be entitled to use that as a defence to the claim.

9.6  In certain instances compliance may not be possible before the expiry of the limitation period. If, for any reason, proceedings are started before the parties have complied, they should seek to agree to apply to the court for an order to stay (i.e. suspend) the proceedings while the parties take steps to comply.

Notifying the court

9.7  Where proceedings are started the claimant should state in the claim form or the particulars of claim whether they have complied with Sections III and IV of this Practice Direction or any relevant protocol.

Transitional provision

9.8  The amendments to paragraph 9.3 do not apply to a funding arrangement entered into before the 1st October 2009 and paragraph 9.3 in force immediately before that date will continue to apply to that funding arrangement as if paragraph 9.3 had not been amended.

ANNEX A

Guidance on pre-action procedure where no pre-action protocol or other formal pre-action procedure applies

1. General

1.1  This Annex sets out detailed guidance on a pre-action procedure that is likely to satisfy the court in most circumstances where no pre-action protocol or other formal pre-action procedure applies. It is intended as a guide for parties, particularly those without legal representation, in straightforward claims that are likely to be disputed. It is not intended to apply to debt claims where it is not disputed that the money is owed and where the claimant follows a statutory or other formal pre-action procedure.

2. Claimant’s letter before claim

2.1  The claimant’s letter should give concise details about the matter. This should enable the defendant to understand and investigate the issues without needing to request further information. The letter should include –

(1) the claimant’s full name and address;

(2) the basis on which the claim is made (i.e. why the claimant says the defendant is liable);

(3) a clear summary of the facts on which the claim is based;

(4) what the claimant wants from the defendant; and

(5) if financial loss is claimed, an explanation of how the amount has been calculated.

2.2  The letter should also –

(1) list the essential documents on which the claimant intends to rely;

(2) set out the form of ADR (if any) that the claimant considers the most suitable and invite the defendant to agree to this;

(3) state the date by which the claimant considers it reasonable for a full response to be provided by the defendant; and

(4) identify and ask for copies of any relevant documents not in the claimant's possession and which the claimant wishes to see.

2.3  Unless the defendant is known to be legally represented the letter should –

(1) refer the defendant to this Practice Direction and in particular draw attention to paragraph 4 concerning the court's powers to impose sanctions for failure to comply with the Practice Direction; and

(2) inform the defendant that ignoring the letter before claim may lead to the claimant starting proceedings and may increase the defendant's liability for costs.

3. Defendant’s acknowledgment of the letter before claim

3.1  Where the defendant is unable to provide a full written response within 14 days of receipt of the letter before claim the defendant should, instead, provide a written acknowledgment within 14 days.

3.2  The acknowledgment –

(1) should state whether an insurer is or may be involved;

(2) should state the date by which the defendant (or insurer) will provide a full written response; and

(3) may request further information to enable the defendant to provide a full response.

3.3  If the date stated under paragraph 3.2(2) of this Annex is longer than the period stated in the letter before claim, the defendant should give reasons why a longer period is needed.

3.4  If the defendant (or insurer) does not provide either a letter of acknowledgment or full response within 14 days, and proceedings are subsequently started, then the court is likely to consider that the claimant has complied.

3.5  Where the defendant is unable to provide a full response within 14 days of receipt of the letter before claim because the defendant intends to seek advice then the written acknowledgment should state –

(1) that the defendant is seeking advice;

(2) from whom the defendant is seeking advice; and

(3) when the defendant expects to have received that advice and be in a position to provide a full response.

3.6  A claimant should allow a reasonable period of time of up to 14 days for a defendant to obtain advice.

4. Defendant’s full response

4.1  The defendant’s full written response should –

(1) accept the claim in whole or in part; or

(2) state that the claim is not accepted.

4.2  Unless the defendant accepts the whole of the claim, the response should –

(1) give reasons why the claim is not accepted, identifying which facts and which parts of the claim (if any) are accepted and which are disputed, and the basis of that dispute;

(2) state whether the defendant intends to make a counterclaim against the claimant (and, if so, provide information equivalent to a claimant’s letter before claim);

(3) state whether the defendant alleges that the claimant was wholly or partly to blame for the problem that led to the dispute and, if so, summarise the facts relied on;

(4) state whether the defendant agrees to the claimant’s proposals for ADR and if not, state why not and suggest an alternative form of ADR (or state why none is considered appropriate);

(5) list the essential documents on which the defendant intends to rely;

(6) enclose copies of documents requested by the claimant, or explain why they will not be provided; and

(7) identify and ask for copies of any further relevant documents, not in the defendant's possession and which the defendant wishes to see.

4.3  If the defendant (or insurer) does not provide a full response within the period stated in the claimant’s letter before claim (or any longer period stated in the defendant’s letter of acknowledgment), and a claim is subsequently started, then the court is likely to consider that the claimant has complied.

4.4  If the claimant starts proceedings before any longer period stated in the defendant’s letter of acknowledgment, the court will consider whether or not the longer period requested by the defendant was reasonable.

5. Claimant’s reply

5.1  The claimant should provide the documents requested by the defendant within as short a period of time as is practicable or explain in writing why the documents will not be provided.

5.2  If the defendant has made a counterclaim the claimant should provide information equivalent to the defendant's full response (see paragraphs 4.1 to 4.3 above).

6. Taking Stock

6.1  In following the above procedure, the parties will have a genuine opportunity to resolve the matter without needing to start proceedings. At the very least, it should be possible to establish what issues remain outstanding so as to narrow the scope of the proceedings and therefore limit potential costs.

6.2  If having completed the procedure the matter has not been resolved then the parties should undertake a further review of their respective positions to see if proceedings can still be avoided.

ANNEX B

Information to be provided in a debt claim where the claimant is a business and the defendant is an individual

1.  Where paragraph 7.4 of the Practice Direction applies the claimant should –

(1) provide details of how the money can be paid (for example the method of payment and the address to which it can be sent);

(2) state that the defendant can contact the claimant to discuss possible repayment options, and provide the relevant contact details; and

(3) inform the defendant that free independent advice and assistance can be obtained from organisations including those listed in the table below.

2.  The information set out in paragraph 1 of this Annex may be provided at any time between the claimant first intimating the possibility of court proceedings and the claimant’s letter before claim.

3.  Where the defendant is unable to provide a full response within the time specified in the letter before claim because the defendant intends to seek debt advice then the written acknowledgment should state –

(1) that the defendant is seeking debt advice;

(2) who the defendant is seeking advice from; and

(3) when the defendant expects to have received that advice and be in a position to provide a full response.

4.  A claimant should allow a reasonable period of time of up to 14 days for a defendant to obtain debt advice.

5.  But the claimant need not allow the defendant time to seek debt advice if the claimant knows that –

(1) the defendant has already received relevant debt advice and the defendant's circumstances have not significantly changed; or

(2) the defendant has previously asked for time to seek debt advice but has not done so.

ANNEX C

Guidance on instructing experts

1.  The CPR contain extensive provisions which strictly control the use of experts both before and after proceedings are started. These provisions are contained in –

(1) CPR Part 35;

(2) Practice Direction 35; and

(3) the Protocol for the ‘Instruction of Experts to give Evidence in Civil Claims’ which is annexed to that Practice Direction.

2.  Parties should be aware that once proceedings have been started –

(1) expert evidence may not be used in court without the permission of the court;

(2) a party who instructs an expert will not necessarily be able to recover the cost from another party; and

(3) (it is the duty of an expert to help the court on the matters within the expert’s scope of expertise and this duty overrides any obligation to the person instructing or paying the expert.

3.  Many matters can and should be resolved without the need for advice or evidence from an expert. If an expert is needed, the parties should consider how best to minimise the expense for example by agreeing to instruct –

(1) a single joint expert (i.e. engaged and paid jointly by the parties whether instructed jointly or separately); or

(2) an agreed expert (i.e. the parties agree the identity of the expert but only one party instructs the expert and pays the expert’s costs).

4.  If the parties do not agree that the nomination of a single joint expert is appropriate, then the party seeking the expert evidence (the first party) should give the other party (the second party) a list of one or more experts in the relevant field of expertise whom the first party would like to instruct.

5.  Within 14 days of receipt of the list of experts, the second party may indicate in writing an objection to one or more of the experts listed. If there remains on the list one or more experts who are acceptable, then the first party should instruct an expert from the list.

6.  If the second party objects to all the listed experts, the first party may then instruct an expert of the first party’s own choice. Both parties should bear in mind that if proceedings are started the court will consider whether a party has acted reasonably when instructing (or rejecting) an expert.

PRACTICE DIRECTION RELATING TO THE USE OF THE WELSH LANGUAGE IN CASES IN THE CIVIL COURTS IN WALES

PRACTICE DIRECTION RELATING TO THE USE OF THE WELSH LANGUAGE IN CASES IN THE CIVIL COURTS IN WALES The Purpose of this Practice Direction is to reflect the principle of the Welsh Language Act 1993 that in the administration of justice in Wales, the English and Welsh languages should be treated on the basis of equality.

1. GENERAL

1.1

This practice direction applies to civil proceedings in courts in Wales.

1.2

The existing practice of conducting a hearing entirely in the Welsh language on an ad hoc basis and without notice will continue to apply when all parties and witnesses directly involved at the time consent to the proceedings being so conducted.

1.3

In every case in which it is possible that the Welsh language may be used by any party or witness [or in any document which may be placed before the court], the parties or their legal representatives must inform the court of that fact so that appropriate arrangements can be made for the management and listing of the case.

1.4

If costs are incurred as a result of a party failing to comply with this direction, a costs Order may be made against him or his legal representative.

1.5

Where a case is tried with a jury, the law does not permit the selection of jurors in a manner which enables the court to discover whether a juror does or does not speak Welsh or to secure a jury whose members are bilingual to try a case in which the Welsh language may be used.

2. THE ALLOCATION QUESTIONNAIRE

2.1

In any proceedings in which a party is required to complete an allocation questionnaire, he must include details relating to the possible use of Welsh i.e. details of any person wishing to give oral evidence in Welsh and of any documents in Welsh (e.g. documents to be disclosed under Part 31 or witness statements) which that party expects to use.

2.2

A party must include the details mentioned in paragraph (2.1) in the allocation questionnaire even if he has already informed the court of the possible use of Welsh in accordance with the provisions of section 1 above.

3. CASE MANAGEMENT

3.1

At any interlocutory hearing, the court will take the opportunity to consider whether it should give case management directions. To assist the court, a party or his legal representative should draw the court’s attention to the possibility of Welsh being used in the proceedings, even where he has already done so in compliance with other provisions of this direction.

3.2

In any case where a party is required to complete a pre-trial check list (listing questionnaire) and has already intimated the intention to use Welsh, he should confirm the intended use of Welsh in the pre-trial check list and provide any details which have not been set out in the allocation questionnaire.

4. LISTING BY THE COURT

4.1

The diary manager, in consultation with the Designated Civil Judge, will ensure that a case in which the Welsh language is to be used is listed:

(a) wherever practicable before a Welsh speaking judge; and

(b) where translation facilities are needed, at a court with simultaneous translation facilities.

5. INTERPRETERS

5.1

Whenever an interpreter is needed to translate evidence from English to Welsh or from Welsh to English, the Court Manager in whose court the case is to be heard will take steps to secure the attendance of an interpreter whose name is included in the list of approved court interpreters.

6. WITNESSES AND JURORS

6.1

When each witness is called, the court officer administering the oath or affirmation will inform the witness that he or she may be sworn or may affirm in Welsh or English as he or she wishes.

6.2

Where a case is tried with a jury, the court officer swearing in the jury will inform the jurors in open court that each juror may take the oath or may affirm in Welsh or English as he or she wishes.

7. ROLE OF THE LIAISON JUDGE

7.1

If any question or difficulty arises concerning the implementation of this practice direction, contact should in the first place be made with the Liaison Judge for the Welsh language.

CYFARWYDDIADAU YMARFER AR DDEFNYDDIO’R IAITH GYMRAEG MEWN ACHOSION YN Y LLYSOEDD SIFIL YNG NGHYMRU Diben y Cyfarwyddiadau Ymarfer hyn yw adlewyrchu egwyddor Deddf yr Iaith Gymraeg 1993 sef y dylid trin y Gymraeg a’r Saesneg yn gyfartal wrth weinyddu cyfiawnder yng Nghymru.

1. CYFFREDINOL

1.1

Mae’r cyfarwyddiadau ymarfer hyn yn berthnasol i achosion sifil mewn llysoedd yng Nghymru.

1.2

Bydd yr ymarfer presennol o gynnal gwrandawiad yn gyfan gwbl yn y Gymraeg ar sail ad hoc a heb rybudd yn parhau’n ddilys pan fo pob parti a phob tyst sy’n ymwneud yn uniongyrchol â’r achos ar y pryd yn cytuno iddo gael ei gynnal felly.

1.3

Ym mhob achos lle y bydd tyst neu barti o bosibl am ddefnyddio’r Gymraeg [neu lle o bosibl y defnyddir y Gymraeg mewn unrhyw ddogfen a gyflwynir gerbron y llys], cyfrifoldeb y parti neu ei gynrychiolwyr cyfreithiol yw hysbysu’r llys o hyn fel y gellir gwneud trefniadau priodol ar gyfer trin a rhestru’r achos.

1.4

Os achosir costau yn sgil methu â chydymffurfio â’r Cyfarwyddiadau hyn, gellir codi gorchymyn costau yn erbyn y parti neu ei gynrychiolydd cyfreithiol.

1.5

Pan fydd achos yn cael ei brofi gyda rheithgor, nid yw’r gyfraith yn caniatáu dethol rheithgor mewn modd sy’n galluogi’r Llys i ganfod a yw Rheithiwr yn siarad Cymraeg ai peidio nac i sicrhau Rheithgor y mae ei aelodau yn ddwyieithog i wrando achos lle o bosibl y defnyddir y Gymraeg.

2. YR HOLIADUR DYRANNU

2.1

Mewn unrhyw achos lle y mae gofyn i barti lenwi holiadur dyrannu, rhaid iddo gynnwys manylion ynghylch defnydd posibl o’r Gymraeg, h.y. manylion unrhyw berson a ddymunai roi tystiolaeth lafar yn y Gymraeg ac unrhyw ddogfennau yn y Gymraeg (e.e. dogfennau i’w datgelu o dan Ran 31 neu ddatganiadau tystion) y mae’r parti hwnnw’n disgwyl eu defnyddio.

2.2

Rhaid i barti gynnwys y manylion a nodir ym mharagraff (2.1) yn yr holiadur dyrannu, hyd yn oed os yw ef eisoes wedi hysbysu’r llys am ddefnydd posibl o’r Gymraeg yn unol â gofynion adran 1 uchod.

3. RHEOLI ACHOSION

3.1

Mewn unrhyw wrandawiad yng nghwrs achos bydd y llys yn manteisio ar y cyfle i ystyried a ddylai roi cyfarwyddiadau rheoli achos. I gynorthwyo’r llys, dylai parti neu ei gynrychiolydd cyfreithiol dynnu sylw’r llys at y posibilrwydd y gallai’r Gymraeg gael ei defnyddio yn yr achos, hyd yn oed os yw ef eisoes wedi gwneud hynny wrth gydymffurfio â gofynion eraill y cyfarwyddiadau hyn.

3.2

Mewn unrhyw achos pan fydd gofyn i barti lenwi rhestr wirio cyn-treial (holiadur rhestru) a’r parti hwnnw eisoes wedi nodi ei fwriad i ddefnyddio’r Gymraeg, dylai gadarnhau ei fwriad i ddefnyddio’r Gymraeg yn yr rhestr wirio cyn-treial, a rhoi unrhyw fanylion na chafodd eu nodi yn yr holiadur dyrannu.

4. RHESTRU GAN Y LLYS

4.1

Bydd rheolwr y dyddiadur, mewn ymgynghoriad â’r Barnwr Sifil Dynodedig, yn sicrhau y bydd achos lle y defnyddir y Gymraeg yn cael ei restru:

(a) pryd bynnag y bydd hynny’n ymarferol bosib, gerbron barnwr Cymraeg ei iaith; a

(b) lle y bo angen cyfleusterau cyfieithu, mewn llys gyda chyfleusterau cyfieithu ar y pryd.

5. CYFIEITHWYR

5.1

Pryd bynnag y bydd angen cyfieithydd i gyfieithu tysiolaeth o’r Saesneg i’r Gymraeg neu o’r Gymraeg i’r Saesneg, bydd Rheolwr y Llys lle y cynhelir yr achos yn sicrhau y trefnir i gyfieithydd, y mae ei enw ar restr y llys o gyfieithwyr cymeradwy, fod yn bresennol.

6. TYSTION A RHEITHWYR

6.1

Wrth i bob tyst gael ei alw, bydd y swyddog llys sy’n gweinyddu’r llw neu’r cadarnhad yn hysbysu’r tyst y gall ef dyngu llw neu gadarnhau yn y Gymraeg neu yn y Saesneg yn ôl ei ddymuniad.

6.2

Pan gaiff achos ei brofi gan reithgor, bydd y swyddog llys sy’n gweinyddu llwon y rheithwyr yn hysbysu’r rheithwyr mewn llys agored y caiff pob rheithiwr dyngu llw neu gadarnhau yn y Gymraeg neu yn y Saesneg yn ôl ei ddymuniad.

7. RÔL Y BARNWR CYSWLLT

7.1

Os cyfyd unrhyw gwestiwn neu broblem ynghylch gweithredu’r cyfarwyddiadau uchod, dylid yn y lle cyntaf gysylltu â’r Barnwr Cyswllt dros faterion y Gymraeg ar y Gylchdaith.

CYFARWYDDYD YMARFER

Contents of this Practice Direction

Title
RHAN I CYFLWYNIAD
Diffiniadau
Ystod
Deddfwriaeth datganoli
RHAN II CYFARWYDDIADAU PERTHNASOL I BOB ACHOS
Ystod
Codi cwestiwn a yw mater datganoli’n codi
Penderfyniad gan lys a yw mater datganoli’n codi
Rhybudd o fater datganoli i’r Twrnai Cyffredinol ac i’r Cynulliad
Ychwanegu’r Twrnai Cyffredinol neu’r Cynulliad at yr achos a’u hawl i fynnu cyfeirio mater datganoli i’r Pwyllgor Barnwrol
Penderfyniad gan y llys ar gyfeirio mater datganoli ai peidio os nad yw’r Twrnai Cyffredinol neu’r Cynulliad yn mynnu cyfeirio
Ffurflen a threfn cyfeirio
P?er llys i ddelio ag achos yn yr arfaeth os gwneir cyfeirio (naill ai gan y Twrnai Cyffredinol, y Cynulliad neu’r llys)
Yr iaith Gymraeg
Deddf Achosion y Goron 1947 (Adran 19)
Rhan III CYFARWYDDIADAU PERTHNASOL I ACHOSION PENODOL
Achosion adolygiad barnwrol
Achosion teulu mewn llysoedd ynadon, y llysoedd sirol a’r Uchel Lys
Achosion sifil yn y llysoedd sirol a’r Uchel Lys
Achosion troseddol yn Llys y Goron
Achosion troseddol a sifil yn llysoedd yr ynadon
RHAN IV APELIADAU
Apeliadau i’r Llys Apêl (Adran Sifil a Throseddol)
Apeliadau i Lys y Goron
ATODIAD 1
ATODIAD 2

RHAN I CYFLWYNIAD

Diffiniadau

1

Yn y Cyfarwyddyd Ymarfer hwn –

golyga ‘y Cynulliad’ Gynulliad Cenedlaethol Cymru

golyga ‘DLlC’ Ddeddf Llywodraeth Cymru 1998

golyga ‘DGI’ Ddeddf Gogledd Iwerddon 1998

golyga ‘DA’ Ddeddf yr Alban 1998

golyga ‘y Deddfau’ DLlC, DGI a DA

golyga ‘y Pwyllgor Barnwrol’ Bwyllgor Barnwrol y Cyfrin-Gyngor

golyga ‘RhTS’ Reolau Trefn Sifil 1998

golyga ‘RhAT’ Reolau Achosion Teulu 1991

golyga ‘LlAT’ Reolau Llysoedd Achosion Teulu (Deddf Plant 1989) 1991

mae gan ‘mater datganoli’ yr un ystyr ag ym mharagraff 1, atodlen 8 DLlC; paragraff 1, atodlen 10 DGI; a pharagraff 1, atodlen 6 DA

golyga ‘rhybudd mater datganoli’ rybudd bod mater datganoli wedi codi mewn achos

Ystod

2.1

Mae’r Cyfarwyddyd Ymarfer hwn yn ategu’r darpariaethau sy’n delio â materion datganoli yn y Deddfau. Mae’n delio’n benodol â’r sefyllfa os yw mater datganoli’n codi o dan DLlC. Os yw mater datganoli’n codi o dan DGI neu DA dylid addasu’r drefn a osodir yn y Cyfarwyddyd Ymarfer hwn fel y bo’r angen.

Deddfwriaeth datganoli

3.1

Mae atodlen 8 DLlC yn cynnwys darpariaethau’n delio â materion datganoli sy’n deillio o DLlC; mae atodlen 10 DGI yn cynnwys darpariaethau’n delio â materion datganoli’n deillio o DGI; ac mae atodlen 6 DA yn cynnwys darpariaethau’n delio â materion datganoli’n deillio o DA.

3.2

Yn gyffredinol bydd mater datganoli’n ymwneud ag a yw corff datganoledig wedi gweithredu neu’n bwriadu gweithredu o fewn ei bwerau (sy’n cynnwys peidio â gweithredu’n anghydnaws â hawliau Confensiwn[1] a deddf Cymuned[2]) neu wedi methu â chydymffurfio â dyletswydd a osodwyd arno. Dylid cyfeirio at y Deddfau lle caiff ‘mater datganoli’ ei ddiffinio.

3.3

(1) Os yw mater datganoli o dan DLlC yn codi mewn achos, rhaid i’r llys orchymyn bod rhybudd ohono yn cael ei roi i’r Twrnai Cyffredinol ac i’r Cynulliad os nad ydynt eisoes yn barti. Mae ganddynt hawl i gymryd rhan fel parti yn yr achos i’r graddau y maent yn berthnasol i fater datganoli, os nad ydynt eisoes yn barti (paragraff 5, atodlen 8 i DLlC). Os ydynt yn cymryd rhan, gallant fynnu bod y llys yn cyfeirio’r mater datganoli i’r Pwyllgor Barnwrol (paragraff 30, atodlen 8 DLlC)[3].

(2) Ceir darpariaethau tebyg yn DGI a DA er bod y personau i’w hysbysu’n wahanol (paragraffau 13, 14, a 33, atodlen 10 DGI; paragraffau 16, 17 a 33, atodlen 6 DA).

3.4

O dan yr holl Ddeddfau gall y llys gyfeirio mater datganoli i lys arall fel a ganlyn:

(1) Gall llys ynadon gyfeirio mater datganoli’n codi o achos sifil neu ddiannod i’r Uchel Lys (paragraffau 6 a 9, atodlen 8 DLlC; paragraffau 15 ac 18, atodlen 10 DGI; a pharagraffau 18 a 21, atodlen 6 DA).

(2) Gall Llys y Goron gyfeirio mater datganoli’n codi mewn achos diannod i’r Uchel Lys a mater datganoli’n codi mewn achosion ar dditiad i’r Llys Apêl (paragraff 9, atodlen 8 DLlC; paragraff 18, atodlen 10 DGI, paragraff 21, atodlen 6 DA).

(3) Gall llys sirol, yr Uchel Lys (oni bai bod y mater datganoli wedi ei gyfeirio i’r Uchel Lys)[4], a Llys y Goron[5] gyfeirio mater datganoli’n codi o achos sifil i’r Llys Apêl (paragraff 7, atodlen 8 DLlC; paragraff 16, atodlen 10 DGI, paragraff 19, atodlen 6 DA).

(4) Rhaid i dribiwnlys lle nad oes apêl, a gall unrhyw dribiwnlys arall, gyfeirio mater datganoli i’r Llys Apêl (paragraff 8, atodlen 8 DLlC; paragraff 17, atodlen 10 DGI; paragraff 20, atodlen 6 DA).

(5) Gall y Llys Apêl gyfeirio mater datganoli i’r Pwyllgor Barnwrol, oni bai bod y mater datganoli wedi ei gyfeirio iddo gan lys arall (paragraff 10, atodlen 8 DLlC; paragraff 19, atodlen 10 DGI; paragraff 22, atodlen 6 DA).

(6) Y Pwyllgor Barnwrol sydd i ddelio ag apêl yn erbyn cyfeirio penderfyniad ar fater datganoli i’r Uchel Lys neu Lys Apêl, gyda chaniatâd y llys perthnasol, neu o fethu â chael caniatâd o’r fath, gyda chaniatâd arbennig y Pwyllgor Barnwrol (paragraff 11, atodlen 8 DLlC; paragraff 20, atodlen 10 DGI; paragraff 23, atodlen 6 DA).

3.5

Gall llys gymryd i ystyriaeth dreuliau ychwanegol y mae’r llys yn tybio bod parti wedi eu talu wrth i’r Twrnai Cyffredinol neu’r Cynulliad gymryd rhan wrth benderfynu unrhyw gwestiwn ar gostau (paragraff 35, atodlen 8 DLlC).

RHAN II CYFARWYDDIADAU PERTHNASOL I BOB ACHOS

Ystod

4

Mae Paragraffau 5 i 13 yn berthnasol i achosion yng Nghymru a Lloegr mewn llysoedd ynadon, llysoedd sirol, Llys y Goron, yr Uchel Lys a’r Llys Apêl (Adran Sifil a Throseddol). Mae paragraff 10 hefyd yn berthnasol i ffurf a threfn cyfeirio i Lys Apêl gan dribiwnlys.

Codi cwestiwn a yw mater datganoli’n codi

5.1

Lle y mae parti i unrhyw ffurf o achos am godi mater a all fod yn fater datganoli, boed fel cais (neu ran o gais) i orfodi neu i sefydlu hawl gyfreithiol neu i geisio rhwymedi neu fel amddiffyniad (neu ran o amddiffyniad), bydd darpariaethau’r Cyfarwyddyd Ymarfer hwn yn berthnasol yn ogystal â’r rheolau trefn sy’n berthnasol i’r achos y cwyd y mater ohono.

5.2

Gall llys, ohono’i hun, fynnu bod ystyriaeth yn cael ei rhoi i’r cwestiwn a yw mater datganoli’n codi, os yw’r defnyddiau a osodwyd gerbron y llys yn nodi y gall mater o’r fath godi, hyd yn oed os nad yw’r partïon wedi defnyddio’r term ‘mater datganoli’.

Penderfyniad gan lys a yw mater datganoli’n codi

6.1

Gall y llys roi cyfarwyddiadau y cred eu bod yn addas i gael eglurhad neu wybodaeth ychwanegol i bennu a yw mater datganoli’n codi.

6.2

Wrth bennu a yw mater datganoli’n codi, gall y llys, beth bynnag fo haeriad parti i’r llys, benderfynu nad yw mater datganoli’n codi os yw’r haeriad yn ymddangos i’r llys yn wamal neu’n flinderus (paragraff 2 atodlen 8 DLlC).

6.3

Os yw’r llys yn penderfynu bod mater datganoli’n codi rhaid iddo ddatgan yn glir ac yn gryno beth yw’r mater datganoli.

Rhybudd o fater datganoli i’r Twrnai Cyffredinol ac i’r Cynulliad

7.1

Os yw llys yn penderfynu bod mater datganoli’n codi yn yr achos, rhaid iddo orchymyn rhybudd mater datganoli o ran sylwedd yn y ffurflen rhif ‘DI 1’ yn Atodiad 1 i’w rhoi i’r Twrnai Cyffredinol ac i’r Cynulliad oni bai eu bod eisoes yn barti i’r achos (paragraff 5(1), atodlen 8 DLlC).

7.2

Nid oes rhaid i lys sy’n derbyn y cyfeirio gyhoeddi rhybudd mater datganoli oni bai ei fod yn penderfynu fod mater datganoli wedi codi na chafodd ei nodi gan y llys sy’n gwneud y cyfeirio. Yn yr achos hwnnw rhaid i’r llys sy’n derbyn y cyfeirio gyhoeddi rhybudd mater datganoli. Rhaid i’r rhybudd hwn:

(1) nodi pa fater neu faterion datganoli sydd wedi cael ei gyfeirio neu eu cyfeirio iddo;

(2) nodi pa fater neu faterion datganoli pellach sydd wedi codi; a

(3) nodi’r llys sy’n cyfeirio.

7.3

Os yw’r mater datganoli wedi codi mewn achos troseddol, rhaid i’r rhybudd mater datganoli nodi:

(1) a yw’r achos wedi cael ei ohirio;

(2) a yw’r diffynnydd wedi ei gadw yn y ddalfa; ac

(3) os yw’r diffynnydd wedi ei gadw yn y ddalfa ac os nad yw ei brawf wedi dechrau, pryd y bydd terfyn amser cadw yn y ddalfa’n dod i ben.[6]

7.4

Os yw’r mater datganoli’n codi mewn apêl, rhaid i’r rhybudd mater datganoli:

(1) nodi bod y mater datganoli’n codi mewn apêl;

(2) nodi’r llys yr apelir yn erbyn ei benderfyniad; a

(3) nodi a godir y mater datganoli am y tro cyntaf ar apêl; neu os nad dyna’r sefyllfa, nodi bod y mater datganoli wedi ei godi yn y llys y mae apêl yn erbyn ei benderfyniad, pa benderfyniad a wnaed yn y llys hwnnw, a dyddiad y rhybudd blaenorol i’r Twrnai Cyffredinol ac i’r Cynulliad.

7.5

Bydd y rhybudd mater datganoli’n pennu dyddiad a fydd yn 14 diwrnod, neu’n gyfnod hwy yn ôl cyfarwyddyd y llys (gweler isod), ar ôl dyddiad y rhybudd mater datganoli, fel y dyddiad y bydd rhaid i’r Twrnai Cyffredinol neu’r Cynulliad roi gwybod i’r llys a ydyw am gymryd rhan fel parti i’r achos, o ran ei berthynas i fater datganoli.

7.6

Gall y llys, mewn amgylchiadau eithriadol, nodi dyddiad hwy na 14 diwrnod ar ôl dyddiad y rhybudd mater datganoli fel y dyddiad y bydd rhaid i’r Twrnai Cyffredinol neu’r Cynulliad roi gwybod i’r llys a ydyw am gymryd rhan fel parti i’r achos. Gall y llys wneud hyn cyn rhoi’r rhybudd, neu cyn neu ar ôl diwedd y cyfnod a roddir yn y rhybudd.

7.7

(1) Ar ddyddiad y rhybudd mater datganoli

(a) rhaid i’r rhybudd mater datganoli i’r Twrnai Cyffredinol gael ei ffacsio ato gan y llys[7]; a

(b) rhaid i’r rhybudd mater datganoli i’r Cynulliad gael ei ffacsio gan y llys at Gwnsel Cyffredinol y Cynulliad.

(2) Yr un diwrnod ag yr anfonir ffacs rhaid anfon copi o’r rhybudd mater datganoli gan y llys gyda phost dosbarth cyntaf at y Twrnai Cyffredinol ac at Gwnsel Cyffredinol y Cynulliad.

7.8

Gall y llys, ar delerau yr ystyria’n addas, orchymyn bod dogfennau ychwanegol yn cael eu cyflwyno (ee mewn achos sifil, y ffurflen hawlio) neu bod gwybodaeth ychwanegol yn cael ei darparu gyda’r rhybudd mater datganoli.

7.9

(1) Pan fo llys yn gorchymyn bod rhybudd mater datganoli’n cael ei roi gall y llys wneud gorchmynion pellach fel y gwêl yn dda mewn perthynas â gohirio, atal neu barhau’r achos, neu fesurau dros dro, yn ystod y cyfnod y mae rhaid i’r Twrnai Cyffredinol a’r Cynulliad roi gwybod i’r llys a ydynt yn bwriadu cymryd rhan fel parti i’r achos.

(2) Cyn gorchymyn gohiriad mewn achos troseddol, bydd y llys yn ystyried yr holl amgylchiadau perthnasol, gan gynnwys a fyddai’n golygu gohirio a allai estyn y tu hwnt i derfynau amser cadw yn y ddalfa os yw’r diffynnydd wedi ei gadw yn y ddalfa ac os nad yw ei brawf wedi dechrau.

7.10

Os nad yw’r Twrnai Cyffredinol na’r Cynulliad yn rhoi gwybod i’r llys o fewn yr amser penodedig ei fod am gymryd rhan fel parti i’r achos:

(1) dylai’r achos fynd yn ei flaen ar unwaith ar ddiwedd y cyfnod yr oedd ganddynt i roi gwybod i’r llys; a

(2) nid oes dyletswydd ar y llys i’w hysbysu o ganlyniad yr achos ac eithrio’r ddyletswydd i roi gwybod iddynt a yw’r llys yn penderfynu cyfeirio’r mater datganoli i lys arall (gweler paragraff 10.3(5)).[8]

Ychwanegu’r Twrnai Cyffredinol neu’r Cynulliad at yr achos a’u hawl i fynnu cyfeirio mater datganoli i’r Pwyllgor Barnwrol

8.1

Os yw’r Twrnai Cyffredinol neu’r Cynulliad am gymryd rhan fel parti i’r achos cyhyd ag y bo’n ymwneud â mater datganoli, rhaid iddo anfon i’r llys ac at y partïon eraill (ac at ei gilydd os un ohonynt yn unig sydd wedi dod yn barti) rybudd o ran sylwedd yn y ffurflen a rifwyd ‘DI 2’ a ddangosir yn Atodiad 1 o fewn yr amser a nodir yn y rhybudd mater datganoli.

8.2

Wrth dderbyn y ffurflen hon gall y llys roi cyfarwyddiadau dilynol fel y gwêl yn angenrheidiol.

8.3

Os yw’r Twrnai Cyffredinol neu’r Cynulliad yn barti i’r achos, ac os yw’r naill neu’r llall ohonynt am fynnu bod y llys yn cyfeirio’r mater datganoli i’r Pwyllgor Barnwrol, rhaid iddo cyn gynted ag y bo’n ymarferol anfon rhybudd o ran sylwedd yn y ffurflen a rifwyd ‘DI 3’ yn Atodiad 1 i’r llys ac at y partïon eraill (ac at ei gilydd os un ohonynt yn unig sydd wedi dod yn barti).

Penderfyniad gan y llys ar gyfeirio mater datganoli ai peidio os nad yw’r Twrnai Cyffredinol neu’r Cynulliad yn mynnu cyfeirio

9.1

Os nad oes gofyn i’r llys gyfeirio’r mater datganoli i’r Pwyllgor Barnwrol, bydd y llys yn penderfynu a ddylai gyfeirio’r mater datganoli i’r llys perthnasol fel y nodir ym mharagraff 3.4.

9.2

Cyn penderfynu a ddylid cyfeirio, gall y llys gynnal gwrandawiad cyfarwyddo neu roi cyfarwyddiadau ysgrifenedig ar wneud argymhellion ynglyn â chyfeirio neu beidio.

9.3

Gall y llys benderfynu ar sail argymhellion ysgrifenedig os yw ei drefniadaeth yn caniatáu hyn ac os yw’n dymuno gwneud hyn, neu gall y llys gynnal gwrandawiad cyn penderfynu.

9.4

Wrth ddefnyddio’i ddisgresiwn a ydyw am gyfeirio, bydd y llys yn ystyried yr holl amgylchiadau perthnasol ac yn enwedig:

(1) pwysigrwydd y mater datganoli i’r cyhoedd yn gyffredinol;

(2) pwysigrwydd y mater datganoli i bartïon gwreiddiol yr achos;

(3) a fyddai penderfyniad ar gyfeirio’r mater datganoli yn dyngedfennol yn y materion o anghydfod rhwng y partïon;

(4) a yw’r holl ganfyddiadau ffeithiol perthnasol wedi eu gwneud (ni fydd mater datganoli, oni bai bod amgylchiadau eithriadol, yn addas i’w gyfeirio os oes rhaid iddo gael ei gyfeirio ar sail ffeithiau tybiedig);

(5) y gohirio y byddai cyfeirio’n ei olygu yn enwedig mewn achosion sy’n cynnwys plant ac achosion troseddol (gan gynnwys a yw’r cyfeirio’n debyg o olygu gohirio a fyddai’n estyn y tu hwnt i ddiwedd y terfynau amser ar gadw yn y ddalfa os yw’r diffynnydd wedi ei gadw yn y ddalfa ac os nad yw ei brawf wedi dechrau); a

(6) costau ychwanegol y gallai cyfeirio eu golygu.[9]

9.5

Dylai’r llys nodi ei resymau dros wneud neu wrthod cyfeirio.

9.6

Os yw’r llys yn penderfynu peidio â chyfeirio’r achos, bydd yn rhoi cyfarwyddiadau ar gyfer trin yr achos yn y dyfodol, a fydd yn cynnwys cyfarwyddiadau ar y rhan a gymer y Twrnai Cyffredinol a’r Cynulliad os ydynt yn bartïon.

Ffurflen a threfn cyfeirio

10.1

Os yw’r Twrnai Cyffredinol neu’r Cynulliad yn mynnu bod y llys neu’r tribiwnlys (mewn perthynas ag unrhyw achos gerbron y llys y mae’n barti iddo) yn cyfeirio’r mater datganoli i’r Pwyllgor Barnwrol:

(1) bydd y llys neu’r tribiwnlys yn gwneud y cyfeirio cyn gynted ag y bo’n ymarferol ar ôl derbyn y rhybudd oddi wrth y Twrnai Cyffredinol neu’r Cynulliad o ran sylwedd yn y ffurflen a rifwyd ‘DI 3’ a ddangosir yn Atodiad 1, ac yn dilyn y drefn ar gyfer cyfeirio yng Ngorchymyn Rheolau’r Pwyllgor Barnwrol (Materion Datganoli) 1999; a

(2) gall y llys neu’r tribiwnlys orchymyn y partïon, neu unrhyw un ohonynt, i lunio’r cyfeirio.

10.2

Os yw’r Llys Apêl yn penderfynu cyfeirio’r mater datganoli i’r Pwyllgor Barnwrol:

(1) bydd yn dilyn y drefn yng Ngorchymyn Rheolau’r Pwyllgor Barnwrol (Materion Datganoli) 1999; a

(2) gall y llys orchymyn y partïon, neu unrhyw un ohonynt, i lunio’r cyfeirio.

10.3

Os yw unrhyw lys neu dribiwnlys arall yn penderfynu cyfeirio’r mater datganoli i unrhyw lys arall, neu os mynnir bod tribiwnlys yn gwneud hynny:

(1) rhaid i’r cyfeirio fod o ran sylwedd yn y ffurflen a rifwyd ‘DI 4’ a ddangosir yn Atodiad 1 a rhaid iddo nodi’r canlynol:

(a) y cwestiwn a gyfeirir;

(b) cyfeiriadau’r partïon, ac eithrio mewn achosion teulu - gweler paragraffau 15.2–4;

(c) datganiad cryno o gefndir y mater gan gynnwys –

(i) ffeithiau’r achos, gan gynnwys unrhyw ganfyddiadau ffeithiol perthnasol gan y llys cyfeirio neu’r llysoedd is; a

(ii) y prif bynciau yn yr achos a haeriadau’r partïon yngln â hwy;

(ch) y gyfraith berthnasol, gan gynnwys darpariaethau perthnasol DLlC;

(d) y rhesymau pam caiff ateb i’r cwestiwn ei ystyried yn angenrheidiol er mwyn gwaredu’r achos;

(2) bydd pob dyfarniad a roddwyd eisoes yn yr achos yn cael ei atodi i’r cyfeirio;

(3) gall y llys orchymyn y partïon, neu unrhyw un ohonynt, i lunio’r cyfeirio;

(4) bydd y llys neu’r tribiwnlys yn trosglwyddo’r cyfeirio i:

(a) Cofrestrfa’r Swyddfa Apeliadau Sifil os yw’r cyfeirio i’r Llys Apêl oddi wrth lys sirol, yr Uchel Lys neu Lys y Goron mewn achos sifil, neu oddi wrth dribiwnlys;

(b) Y Cofrestrydd Apeliadau Troseddol os yw’r cyfeirio i’r Llys Apêl oddi wrth Lys y Goron mewn achos ar dditiad; a

(c) Swyddfa’r Llys Gweinyddol os yw’r cyfeirio i’r Uchel Lys o lys ynadon mewn achos sifil neu ddiannod neu oddi wrth Lys y Goron mewn achos diannod[10].

Os caiff y cyfeirio ei drosglwyddo i Gaerdydd rhaid ffeilio copi ychwanegol o’r cyfeirio fel y gellir ei gadw gan Swyddfa Caerdydd. Caiff y cyfeirio gwreiddiol ei anfon i Swyddfa’r Llys Gweinyddol yn Llundain.

(5) yr un pryd ag y caiff y cyfeirio ei drosglwyddo i’r llys sy’n derbyn y cyfeirio anfonir copi o’r cyfeirio gyda’r post dosbarth cyntaf at:

(a) y partïon;

(b) y Twrnai Cyffredinol os nad yw ef eisoes yn barti; a

(c) y Cynulliad os nad yw eisoes yn barti;

(6) rhaid i bob un y cyflwynir copi o’r cyfeirio iddo roi gwybod i’r llys y trosglwyddir y cyfeirio iddo ac i eraill y cyflwynir y cyfeirio iddynt, o fewn 21 diwrnod, a ydynt am gael eu clywed ar y cyfeirio;

(7) bydd y llys sy’n derbyn y cyfeirio (naill ai’r Llys Apêl neu’r Uchel Lys) yn rhoi cyfarwyddiadau ar sut y trafodir y cyfeirio, gan gynnwys cyflwyno argymhellion neu ddadleuon sgerbwd; a throsglwyddo copi o’r penderfyniad ar y cyfeirio i’r llys cyfeirio; a

(8) os ceir apêl i’r Pwyllgor Barnwrol yn erbyn penderfyniad yr Uchel Lys neu’r Llys Apêl ar gyfeirio, ac os oes copi o benderfyniad y Pwyllgor Barnwrol ar yr apêl honno wedi ei anfon i’r Uchel Lys neu i’r Llys Apêl (fel y bo’n briodol), bydd y llys hwnnw’n anfon copi i’r llys a gyfeiriodd y mater datganoli iddo.

10.4

Pan fo llys yn derbyn hysbysiad o benderfyniad ar gyfeirio, bydd yn penderfynu ar sut i fwrw ymlaen â gweddill yr achos.

P?er llys i ddelio ag achos yn yr arfaeth os gwneir cyfeirio (naill ai gan y Twrnai Cyffredinol, y Cynulliad neu’r llys)

11

Os gwneir cyfeirio bydd y llys yn gohirio neu’n atal yr achos lle y cododd y mater datganoli, oni bai ei fod yn gorchymyn fel arall; a bydd yn gwneud gorchmynion pellach fel y gwêl yn dda mewn perthynas ag unrhyw ohirio neu atal.

Yr iaith Gymraeg

12.1

Os yw unrhyw barti’n dymuno cynnig haeriad ynglyn â mater datganoli sy’n cynnwys cymharu testunau Cymraeg a Saesneg unrhyw ddeddfwriaeth eilradd o eiddo’r Cynulliad, rhaid i’r parti hwnnw roi rhybudd i’r llys cyn gynted ag y bo modd.

12.2

Wrth dderbyn yr hysbysiad, bydd y llys yn ystyried y dull priodol o benderfynu’r mater, gan gynnwys, os oes angen, benodi asesydd barnwrol Cymraeg i gynorthwyo’r llys.

12.3

Rhaid i bartïon i unrhyw achos lle y caiff y Gymraeg o bosib ei defnyddio hefyd gydymffurfio â Chyfarwyddyd Ymarfer 16 Hydref 1998 (yn ymwneud ag achosion yn Llys y Goron) a Chyfarwyddyd Ymarfer 26 Ebrill 1999 (yn ymwneud ag achosion sifil). Mae’r Cyfarwyddiadau Ymarfer hyn yn berthnasol, fel y bo’n briodol, i achosion yn ymwneud â mater datganoli lle y bydd y Gymraeg o bosib yn cael ei defnyddio.

Deddf Achosion y Goron 1947 (Adran 19)

13

Lle y mae llys wedi penderfynu bod achos datganoli’n codi, bydd y Twrnai Cyffredinol yn rhoi unrhyw gydsyniad angenrheidiol i:

(1) drosglwyddo’r achos i’r Llysoedd Barn, Parc Cathays, Caerdydd CF10 3PG, neu i gofrestrfa ranbarthol arall a gaiff (yn eithriadol) ei chyfarwyddo gan y llys; a

(2) gynnal yr achos yng Nghaerdydd neu mewn lleoliad prawf arall a gaiff (yn eithriadol) ei chyfarwyddo gan y llys.

Rhan III CYFARWYDDIADAU PERTHNASOL I ACHOSION PENODOL

Achosion adolygiad barnwrol

14.1

Mae’r Cyfarwyddyd Ymarfer sy’n ategu Rhan 5 (adolygiad barnwrol) yn cynnwys darpariaethau ynglyn â pha bryd y gellir dwyn achos adolygiad barnwrol yn y Llys Gweinyddol yng Nghymru.

Achosion teulu mewn llysoedd ynadon, y llysoedd sirol a’r Uchel Lys

15.1

Mewn unrhyw achos lle y mae unrhyw gwestiwn yn codi ynglyn â chodi plentyn, bydd y llys yn rhoi sylw i’r egwyddor gyffredinol fod unrhyw oedi wrth benderfynu’r mater yn debyg o niweidio lles y plentyn.[11]

15.2

Os yw’r RhAT yn berthnasol, bydd y llys yn cydymffurfio â rheol 10.21.[12]

15.3

Os yw Rhan IV RhAT yn berthnasol, bydd y llys yn cydymffurfio â rheol 4.23.[13]

15.4

Os yw’r LlAT yn berthnasol, bydd y llys yn cydymffurfio â Rheolau 23 a 33A.[14]

15.5

Os caiff yr achos ei restru yng ngholofn (i) Atodiad 3 RhAT neu Atodlen 2 LlAT, rhaid i gopi o unrhyw rybudd a roddir i’r partïon gael ei roi hefyd i’r rhai a nodir yng ngholofn (iv) Atodiad 3 neu Atodlen 2 fel y bo’n addas.

15.6

Rhaid i barti sy’n dymuno codi mater datganoli, lle y bo modd, ei godi (gan roi manylion llawn y darpariaethau y dibynnir arnynt) yn y cais neu ateb neu yn y gwrandawiad cyfarwyddiadau cyntaf lle y bo’n addas.

15.7

Os nad yw parti wedi codi mater datganoli fel uchod, rhaid i’r parti geisio caniatâd y llys i godi’r mater yn ddiweddarach.

15.8

Lle y mae llys wedi cyfeirio’r mater datganoli i lys arall ac wedi derbyn rhybudd o’r penderfyniad ar y cyfeirio, dylai’r mater cyhyd ag y bo modd gael ei roi gerbron yr un barnwr neu’r un ynadon a ddeliodd â’r achos cyn y cyfeirio.

Achosion sifil yn y llysoedd sirol a’r Uchel Lys

16.1

Rhaid i barti sydd am godi mater datganoli nodi yn y ffurflen gais, neu os ef yw’r diffynnydd, yn yr amddiffyniad (neu dystiolaeth ysgrifenedig wedi ei ffeilio gyda’r cydnabyddiad cyflwyno mewn cais Rhan 8) fod y cais yn codi mater datganoli a darpariaethau perthnasol DLlC.

16.2

Rhaid i’r manylion cais neu amddiffyniad os yw’r mater datganoli yn cael ei godi gan y diffynnydd (neu dystiolaeth ysgrifenedig a ffeiliwyd gyda’r cydnabyddiad cyflwyno mewn cais Rhan 8) gynnwys yn ddigon manwl y ffeithiau a’r amgylchiadau a’r pwyntiau cyfraith yr honnir ar eu sail bod mater datganoli’n codi i alluogi’r llys i benderfynu a yw mater datganoli’n codi yn yr achos.

16.3

Os yw’r rheolau dyrannu’n berthnasol ai peidio, os caiff cwestiwn ei godi yn ystod yr achos a allai fod yn fater datganoli, yna rhaid i wrandawiad cyfarwyddiadau gael ei gynnal a rhaid i’r mater gael ei gyfeirio i farnwr cylchdaith (mewn achosion llys sirol) neu i farnwr Uchel Lys (mewn achosion Uchel Lys) i benderfynu a oes mater datganoli’n codi ac i gael cyfarwyddiadau pellach.

16.4

Os yw parti’n methu â nodi yn y ddogfen briodol bod mater datganoli’n codi, ond os yw’r parti hwnnw wedi hynny’n dymuno codi mater datganoli, rhaid i’r parti hwnnw geisio caniatâd y llys.

16.5

Lle y bo unrhyw barti wedi nodi bod mater datganoli’n codi, ni ellir cael dyfarniad trwy ddiffyg.

Achosion troseddol yn Llys y Goron

17.

Os yw’r diffynnydd am godi mater datganoli dylai wneud hynny yn y Gwrandawiad Ple a Chyfarwyddiadau.

Achosion troseddol a sifil yn llysoedd yr ynadon

18.1

(1) Lle y bo diffynnydd, sydd wedi ei gyhuddo neu sydd wedi cael gwybodaeth wedi ei gosod yn ei erbyn ynglyn â thramgwydd droseddol ac sydd wedi nodi ple ‘Dieuog’, am godi mater datganoli, dylai, lle y bo modd, roi manylion llawn y darpariaethau y dibynnir arnynt trwy roi rhybudd ysgrifenedig.

(2) Lle y mae parti i gwyn, neu geisydd am drwydded am godi mater datganoli dylai, lle y bo modd, roi manylion llawn y darpariaethau y dibynnir arnynt trwy roi rhybudd ysgrifenedig.

(3) Dylid rhoi’r rhybudd hwn i’r erlyniad (ac i unrhyw barti arall os oes un) ac i’r llys cyn gynted ag sy’n ymarferol ar ôl cyflwyno’r ple ‘Dieuog’ neu ar ôl gwneud y gwyn neu’r cais fel y bo’n addas.

18.2

Lle y caiff achos ei draddodi neu ei drosglwyddo i Lys y Goron gan yr ynadon, Llys y Goron sydd i benderfynu a oes mater datganoli’n codi.

RHAN IV APELIADAU

Apeliadau i’r Llys Apêl (Adran Sifil a Throseddol)

19.1

Mae’r paragraff hwn yn berthnasol os yw mater datganoli’n codi mewn unrhyw apêl i Adran Sifil neu Adran Droseddol y Llys Apêl.

19.2

Mae’n bosibl bod y mater datganoli eisoes wedi codi yn y llys yr apelir yn erbyn ei benderfyniad. Gall y mater datganoli, serch hynny, godi am y tro cyntaf wrth apelio.

19.3

Lle y gwneir cais am ganiatâd i apelio, neu lle gwneir apêl pan nad oes angen caniatâd, rhaid i’r apelydd nodi yn y rhybudd cais (neu’r rhybudd apêl neu rybudd o gynnig fel y bo’n addas):

(1) fod yr apêl yn codi mater datganoli a darpariaethau perthnasol DLlC;

(2) yn ddigon manwl y ffeithiau a’r amgylchiadau a’r pwyntiau cyfraith yr honnir ar eu sail bod mater datganoli’n codi i alluogi’r llys i benderfynu a yw mater datganoli’n codi yn yr achos; a

(3) a ystyriwyd y mater datganoli yn y llys is, ac os felly, roi manylion y penderfyniad.

19.4

Ni chaiff apelydd geisio codi mater datganoli heb ganiatâd y llys ar ôl iddo ffeilio rhybudd cais; neu rybudd apêl neu rybudd o gynnig (os nad oes rhybudd cais).

19.5

Lle y ceisir caniatâd i apelio a lle y mae parti i’r apêl am godi mater datganoli na chodwyd yn y llys is, bydd y llys yn penderfynu a oes mater datganoli’n codi cyn penderfynu rhoi caniatâd i apelio.

Apeliadau i Lys y Goron

20

Rhaid i rybudd apelio o benderfyniad llys yr ynadon i Lys y Goron nodi a ystyriwyd y mater datganoli yn y llys is, ac os felly, roi manylion y penderfyniad. Os nad ystyriwyd hyn, dylai’r rhybudd nodi:

(1) fod yr apêl yn codi mater datganoli a darpariaethau perthnasol DLlC; a

(2) yn ddigon manwl y ffeithiau a’r amgylchiadau a’r pwyntiau cyfraith yr honnir ar eu sail bod mater datganoli’n codi i alluogi’r llys i benderfynu a yw mater datganoli’n codi yn yr achos.

ATODIAD 1

DI 1

MATERION DATGANOLI

Rhybudd Mater Datganoli i’r Twrnai Cyffredinol ac i Gynulliad Cenedlaethol Cymru

[ENW’R ACHOS]

Bydded hysbys fod yr achos a grybwyllir uchod wedi codi mater datganoli fel y’i diffiniwyd gan Atodlen 8 Deddf Llywodraeth Cymru 1998. Rhoddir manylion y mater datganoli yn yr atodlen a atodir.

Mae’r rhybudd hwn yn diwallu gofynion rhybuddio o dan baragraff 5(1) Atodlen 8 Deddf Llywodraeth Cymru 1998. Gellwch gymryd rhan fel parti i’r achos hwn, cyhyd ag y bo’n ymwneud â mater datganoli (paragraff 5(2) Atodlen 8). Os ydych am wneud hyn rhaid i chi roi gwybod i’r llys trwy gwblhau’r ffurflen atodedig, a’i dychwelyd i’r llys yn [cyfeiriad ] erbyn [ dyddiad ].

DYDDIAD

At:

Y Twrnai Cyffredinol Cynulliad Cenedlaethol Cymru

Partïon eraill (lle y bo’n addas)

DI 2

MATERION DATGANOLI

Rhybudd o fwriad y Twrnai Cyffredinol neu Gynulliad Cenedlaethol Cymru i ddod yn barti i achos, cyhyd ag y bo’n berthnasol i fater datganoli, o dan Baragraff 5(2) Atodlen 8 Deddf Llywodraeth Cymru 1998

Yn [enw’r llys]

[enw’r achos]

Bydded hysbys fod y [Twrnai Cyffredinol ] [ Cynulliad Cenedlaethol Cymru ] yn bwriadu cymryd rhan fel parti i’r achos, cyhyd ag y bo’n ymwneud â mater datganoli fel a ganiateir gan baragraff 5(2) Atodlen 8 Deddf Llywodraeth Cymru 1998 mewn perthynas â’r mater datganoli a godwyd gan [ ], y derbyniwyd rhybudd ohono gan y [ Twrnai Cyffredinol ] [ Cynulliad ] ar [ ].

[Mae’r [ ] hefyd yn ei gwneud yn hysbys ei fod [yn mynnu bod y mater yn cael ei gyfeirio i ] [ yn dal i ystyried a ddylai fynnu bod y mater yn cael ei gyfeirio i ] Bwyllgor Barnwrol y Cyfrin Gyngor o dan baragraff 30 Atodlen 8 Deddf Llywodraeth Cymru 1998. ]

[DYDDIAD]

Ar ran y [Twrnai Cyffredinol] [ Cynulliad Cenedlaethol Cymru]

At:

Y Twrnai Cyffredinol Cynulliad Cenedlaethol Cymru

Partïon eraill (lle y bo’n addas)

DI 3

MATERION DATGANOLI

Rhybudd gan y Twrnai Cyffredinol neu Gynulliad Cenedlaethol Cymru eu bod yn mynnu bod y mater datganoli’n cael ei gyfeirio i Bwyllgor Barnwrol y Cyfrin Gyngor

Yn y [llys]

[enw’r achos]

Mae’r [Twrnai Cyffredinol] [Cynulliad Cenedlaethol Cymru] yn ei gwneud yn hysbys fod rhaid cyfeirio’r mater datganoli, a godwyd yn yr achos uchod y mae’n barti iddo, gael ei gyfeirio i Bwyllgor Barnwrol y Cyfrin Gyngor o dan baragraff 30 Atodlen 8 Deddf Llywodraeth Cymru 1998. [DYDDIAD]

Ar ran y [Twrnai Cyffredinol] [ Cynulliad Cenedlaethol Cymru]

At:

Y Twrnai Cyffredinol Cynulliad Cenedlaethol Cymru

Partïon eraill (lle y bo’n addas)

DI 4

MATERION DATGANOLI

Cyfeirio mater datganoli gan y llys neu dribiwnlys i [Uchel Lys] [Lys Apêl] [Bwyllgor Barnwrol y Cyfrin Gyngor]

Yn y [llys]

[enw’r achos]

Gorchmynnir cyfeirio’r mater(ion) datganoli a nodir yn yr atodlen [ i’r Uchel Lys] [ i’r Llys Apêl] [i Bwyllgor Barnwrol y Cyfrin Gyngor] i’w benderfynu yn unol â pharagraff [ ] Atodlen 8 Deddf Llywodraeth Cymru 1998.

Gorchmynnir ymhellach fod yr achos yn cael ei ohirio nes bod [yr Uchel Lys] [y Llys Apêl] [Pwyllgor Barnwrol y Cyfrin Gyngor] yn penderfynu ar y mater[ion] datganoli neu nes gorchymyn pellach.

DYDDIAD

Barnwr/clerc y llys ynadon

Cadeirydd y Tribiwnlys

[Cyfeiriad]

CYFEIRIO SGERBWD I’W ATODI WRTH FFURFLEN DI 4

Yn y [llys ]

[enw’r achos]

(a) [Y cwestiwn a gyfeiriwyd.]

(b) [Cyfeiriadau’r partïon]

(c) [Datganiad cryno o gefndir y materion gan gynnwys –

(i) Ffeithiau’r achos gan gynnwys unrhyw ganfyddiadau o ffaith gan y llys cyfeirio neu lysoedd is; a

(ii) Y prif bynciau yn yr achos a haeriadau’r partïon ynglyn â hwy;]

(ch) [Y ddeddf berthnasol gan gynnwys darpariaethau perthnasol Deddf Llywodraeth Cymru 1998]

(d) [Y rhesymau pam ystyrir bod ateb i’r cwestiwn yn angenrheidiol ar gyfer dibenion gwaredu’r achos.]

[Caiff yr hol ddyfarniadau a roddwyd eisoes yn yr achos eu hatodi wrth y cyfeirio hwn.]

ATODIAD 2

CYFEIRIADAU

(1) Rhaid i hysbysiadau i Gynulliad Cenedlaethol Cymru gael eu hanfon at Gwnsel Cyffredinol Cynulliad Cenedlaethol Cymru, Adeiladau’r Goron, Parc Cathays, Caerdydd. Rhif ffacs 01222 826798.

(2) Rhaid anfon hysbysiadau at y Twrnai Cyffredinol i Siambrau’r Twrnai Cyffredinol, 9 Buckingham Gate, Llundain, SW1E 6JP. Rhif ffacs 0171 271 2433.

(3) Gellir anfon cyfeirio i Swyddfa’r Goron o dan baragraff 14.2 y Cyfarwyddyd Ymarfer i Swyddfa’r Goron, Llysoedd Barn Brenhinol, Strand, Llundain WC2A 2LL; neu i’r Llysoedd Barn, Parc Cathays, Caerdydd, CF10 3PG (2 gopi).

NODYN EGLURHAOL

(4) Y cyfeiriadau a’r rhifau ffacs uchod yw’r wybodaeth orau sydd ar gael, serch hynny y mae’n bosibl i’r rhain (yn enwedig y rhifau ffacs a’r cyfeiriad am Hysbysiadau i’r Cynulliad) newid, a byddai felly’n ddoeth cadarnhau’r rhifau cyn anfon gwybodaeth.

Footnotes

1. Yr hawliau a rhyddid sylfaenol a nodir yn – (a) Erthyglau 2 i 12 ac 14 y Confensiwn Ewropeaidd ar Hawliau Dynol ("CEHD"), (b) Erthyglau 1 i 3 o'r Protocol Cyntaf (cytunwyd ym Mharis 20 Mawrth 1952), ac (c) Erthyglau 1 a 2 y Chweched Protocol (cytunwyd yn Strasbourg 11 Mai 1994), fel y'u darllenir gydag Erthyglau 16 ac 18 CEHD (Adran 1 Deddf Hawliau Dynol 1998; a. 107(1) a (5) DLlC; adrannau 6(2); 24(1) a 98(1) DGI; adrannau 29(2); 57(2) a 126(1) DA).

2. Yr holl hawliau, pwerau, rhwymedigaethau, goblygiadau a chyfyngiadau a grëwyd neu sy'n deillio o bryd i'w gilydd gan neu o dan y Cytundebau Cymuned; a'r holl rwymedïau a threfniadaethau a ddarparwyd o bryd i'w gilydd ar gyfer, gan neu o dan y Cytundebau Cymuned (adrannau 106(7) a 155(1), DLlC; adrannau 6(2); 24(1) a 98(1), DGI; adrannau 29(2); 57(2) a 126(9) DA).

3. Pe bai'r Twrnai Cyffredinol neu'r Cynulliad wedi dod yn barti i'r achos gwreiddiol ond heb ymarfer eu hawl i fynnu bod y mater datganoli'n cael ei gyfeirio i'r Pwyllgor Barnwrol a'r llys wedi penderfynu'r achos, byddai ganddynt yr un hawl apêl â phartïon. Ni fyddai'r rhain yn caniatáu apêl iddynt ar benderfyniad a wnaed mewn achos ar dditiad, er bod gan y Twrnai Cyffredinol b?er o dan adran 36 Deddf Cyfiawnder Troseddol 1972 i gyfeirio pwynt o gyfraith i'r Llys Apêl lle bo'r diffynnydd wedi ei farnu'n ddieuog mewn prawf ar dditiad.Mae paragraff 31, atodlen 8 DLlC, yn caniatáu i'r Twrnai Cyffredinol ac i'r Cynulliad gyfeirio i'r Pwyllgor Barnwrol unrhyw fater datganoli nad yw'n destun achos. Gellid defnyddio'r p?er hwn o bosib pe bai llys yn penderfynu a hwythau heb fod yn bartïon ac felly heb hawl apêl ond ni allai cyfeirio o'r fath effeithio ar benderfyniad y llys.

4. Os yw apêl mewn ffurf achos datganedig mewn achos troseddol yn mynd i Lys Adrannol ymddengys nad oes p?er gan y Llys Adrannol i gyfeirio mater datganoli i'r Llys Apêl.

5. e.e. mewn apeliadau o lys ynadon ar fater trwyddedu.

6. Caiff terfynau amser cadw yn y ddalfa eu gosod gan Reoliadau Erlyn Troseddau (Terfynau Amser yn y Ddalfa) 1987 fel y'u diwygiwyd.

7. Gweler Atodiad 2 am wybodaeth am rifau ffacs a chyfeiriadau.

8. Os oes apêl, bydd y llys apêl yn cyflwyno rhybudd mater datganoli i'r Twrnai Cyffredinol ac i'r Cynulliad (gweler paragraff 7.4).

9. Mewn achosion troseddol nid yw adran 16 Deddf Erlyn Troseddau 1985 yn galluogi llys sy'n derbyn cyfeirio i wneud gorchymyn costau diffynnydd. Os yw'r diffynnydd wedi hyn yn cael ei farnu'n ddieuog gan y llys sydd wedi gwneud y cyfeirio, gall y llys hwnnw wneud gorchymyn costau diffynnydd. Serch hynny ni fyddai'n ymwneud â chostau'r cyfeirio gan fod "achos" fel y'i diffinnir yn adran 21 yn cynnwys achos mewn unrhyw lys llai ond nid yw'n sôn am achos ar ôl cyfeirio.

10. Gweler Atodiad 2 am y cyfeiriadau perthnasol. Dengys y Llysoedd Barn, Parc Cathays, Caerdydd CF10 3PG a'r Llysoedd Barn Brenhinol, Strand, Llundain WC2A 2LL fel cyfeiriadau eraill ar gyfer trosglwyddo dogfennau i Swyddfa'r Goron. Os caiff y gorchymyn ei drosglwyddo i Gaerdydd, caiff y copi ychwanegol ei anfon gan Swyddfa Caerdydd i Swyddfa'r Goron yn Llundain.

11. Adran 1(2), Deddf Plant 1989.

12. Noda Rheol 10.21: (1) Yn amodol ar reol 2.3 [RhAT] nid oes dim yn y rheolau hyn i gael ei ddeall mewn modd a fyddai'n mynnu bod unrhyw barti'n datgelu cyfeiriad ei drigfan breifat (neu un unrhyw blentyn) ac eithrio trwy orchymyn y llys. (2) Lle y bo parti'n gwrthod datgelu cyfeiriad wrth ddibynnu ar baragraff (1) uchod, bydd yn rhoi rhybudd o'r cyfeiriad hwnnw i'r llys yn Ffurflen C8 ac ni chaiff y cyfeiriad hwnnw ei ddatgelu i unrhyw un heblaw trwy orchymyn y llys.

13. Noda Rheol 4.23: (1) Er gwaethaf unrhyw reol llys i'r gwrthwyneb, ni chaiff unrhyw ddogfen, ac eithrio cofnod o orchymyn, a ddelir gan y llys ac sy'n ymwneud ag achos y mae [Rhan IV] yn berthnasol iddo, ei datgelu, ac eithrio i – (a) barti, (b) cynrychiolydd cyfreithiol parti (c) y gwarcheidwad ad litem, (d) y Bwrdd Cymorth Cyfreithiol, neu (e) swyddog lles, heb ganiatâd y barnwr neu'r barnwr rhanbarthol. (2) Ni fydd dim yn y rheol hon yn rhwystro rhoi rhybudd i'r awdurdod perthnasol gan y llys neu swyddog priodol o gyfarwyddyd o dan adran 37(1). (3) Ni fydd dim yn y rheol hon yn rhwystro datgelu dogfen a baratowyd gan warcheidwad ad litem ar gyfer dibenion – (a) galluogi person i gyflawni swyddogaethau a fynnir gan reoliadau a wnaed o dan adran 41(7); (b) cynorthwyo gwarcheidwad ad litem neu swyddog hysbysu (o fewn ystyr adran 65(1)(b) Deddf Mabwysiadu 1976) a benodir o dan unrhyw ddeddfiad i gyflawni ei swyddogaethau.

14. Noda Rheol 23: (1) Ni chaiff unrhyw ddogfen, ac eithrio cofnod o orchymyn, a ddelir gan y llys ac sy'n ymwneud ag achosion perthnasol ei datgelu, heblaw i – (a) parti, (b) cynrychiolydd cyfreithiol parti, (c) y gwarcheidwad ad litem, (d) y Bwrdd Cymorth Cyfreithiol, neu (e) swyddog lles, heb ganiatâd clerc yr ynadon neu'r llys. (2) Ni fydd dim yn y rheol hon yn atal y llys neu glerc yr ynadon rhag rhoi gwybod am gyfarwyddyd o dan adran 37(1) i'r awdurdod perthnasol. (3) Ni fydd dim yn y rheol hon yn rhwystro datgelu dogfen a baratowyd gan warcheidwad ad litem ar gyfer dibenion – (a) galluogi person i gyflawni swyddogaethau a fynnir gan reoliadau a wnaed o dan adran 41(7); (b) cynorthwyo gwarcheidwad ad litem neu swyddog hysbysu (o fewn ystyr adran 65(1)(b) Deddf Mabwysiadu 1976) a benodir o dan unrhyw ddeddfiad i gyflawni ei swyddogaethau.Noda Rheol 33A: (1) Nid oes dim yn y Rheolau hyn i gael ei ddeall mewn modd a fyddai'n mynnu bod unrhyw barti'n datgelu cyfeiriad ei drigfan breifat (neu un unrhyw blentyn) ac eithrio trwy orchymyn y llys. (2) Lle y bo parti'n gwrthod datgelu cyfeiriad wrth ddibynnu ar baragraff (1) uchod, bydd yn rhoi rhybudd o'r cyfeiriad hwnnw i'r llys yn Ffurflen C8 ac ni chaiff y cyfeiriad hwnnw ei ddatgelu i unrhyw un ac eithrio trwy orchymyn y llys.